<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>Fusion isn't so hard</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I saw somebody <a href="https://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/amp/news/2020/10/middle-school-student-achieved-nuclear-fusion-in-his-family-playroom-631163">post</a> about a kid achieving nuclear fusion at home,
and I was sure it was fake news. It referenced <a href="https://fusor.net/">fusor.net</a>, which
also looks fake. But the concept, at least, is real!
(<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fusor">WikiPedia</a>/<a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/energy/nuclear/fusion-on-a-budget">IEEE</a>) How cool! For a couple thousand dollars or
so, you can make a fusion reactor in your house, on a desk! I feel
like this should be more widely known.</p>
<p>You mostly hear about fusion in stars, which makes it seem... big. And
far away. Knowing you can do it as a hobbyist if you feel like makes
it seem so much more approachable! Together with the naturally
occurring fission <a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/guest-blog/natures-nuclear-reactors-the-2-billion-year-old-natural-fission-reactors-in-gabon-western-africa/">reactors</a>, there are cool non-bomb, non-star
examples of both fission and fusion. Nice!</p>
<p>Also did you know you can buy <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deuterium">deuterium</a>? I think you can probably
get it as a gas, but you can also just buy yourself some heavy water
if you want! It's just water, but with extra neutrons on the hydrogen!
How cool!</p>
<p>The good and bad of home fusion is that it's just a <em>little</em> bit of
fusion, and it takes a lot more energy to make it happen than you get
out. So it doesn't blow up, and the extra radioactivity won't kill you
very fast. As far as I can tell, these fusor devices are in a weird
zone of not being regulated, I think, because they're hard enough to
make and not quite dangerous enough to be a big risk.</p>
<p>I think it'd be a great thing to see more fusors in children's museums
(and other science museums). They don't have to turn it on; it'd just
be a cool exhibit to demonstrate that it's so possible.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20201008-fusion_isnt_so_hard/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20201008-fusion_isnt_so_hard/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Give the model epistemology</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Jaskie has a nice paper with
<a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9048765">A Modified Logistic Regression for Positive and Unlabeled Learning</a>.
I like that it extends the usual logistic function in a way that
captures the idea that labels may be incorrect. I wonder about
extending the idea to multi-class softmax, and its relationship with
label smoothing.</p>
<p>Here's the usual <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logistic_function">logistic function</a>.</p>
<p>\[ \frac{ 1 }{ 1 + e^{-x} } \tag{1} \]</p>
<p>What Jaskie does is introduce another term in the denominator:</p>
<p>\[ \frac{ 1 }{ 1 + b^2 + e^{-x} } \tag{2} \]</p>
<p>The \( b \) term is squared to be non-negative, and learned during
model fitting. The effect is that the maximum score for a positive
example is less than one.</p>
<p>This makes sense in the positive unlabeled setting because Jaskie
differentiates between whether an example <em>is</em> positive and whether an
example is <em>labeled</em> positive. We only have the labels, and we know
that some positive examples may not be positively labeled, so the
probability based on the example that it is positively labeled is less
than one.</p>
<p>It's somewhat surprising that this seems to work quite well, as
demonstrated (for example) in Jaskie's Figure 6. (SLR is Standard
Logistic Regression, MLR is Jaskie's Modified Logistic Regression.)</p>
<p><img alt="Figure 6" src="figure_6.png"></p>
<p>Let's speculate about extending this idea to the multi-class setting.
First, just moving things around, Equation 2 becomes Equation 3.</p>
<p>\[ \frac{ e^x }{ (1 + b^2) e^x + 1 } \tag{3} \]</p>
<p>That form makes it easy to see the analogy between the usual logistic
function and the multi-class <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Softmax_function">softmax</a>. Then the natural thing to
suggest is Equation 4.</p>
<p>\[ \frac{ e^{x_i} }{ \sum (1 + b_i^2) e^{x_i} } \tag{4} \]</p>
<p>The semi-supervised setting in which there's a pile of unlabeled data
in addition to the labeled data is pretty common, especially when
labeling is expensive, and if something relatively simple like this
were to give similar performance benefits to Jaskie's binary case, it
could easily become very popular. (Assume you have a "garbage" class
as well, in the <a href="https://paperswithcode.com/task/open-set-learning">open set</a> sense.)</p>
<p>There's probably a similar extension to keep the negative example
scores from going all the way to zero, if you think some of the true
negatives might have incorrectly positive labels (or otherwise wrong
labels in the multi-class setting).</p>
<p>I wonder about the relationship between these techniques and
<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.02629">label smoothing</a>... With smoothed labels you still have fixed (or
at least sort of balanced) target probabilities, whereas the above
techniques allow learning where the targets should be... But I think
you wouldn't get the limits on logit growth, with the above
techniques... It would be neat if the above techniques gave you good
calibration <em>and</em> informative logits in the distillation sense. Hmm!</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20201005-give_the_model_epistemology/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20201005-give_the_model_epistemology/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Drawbridge Up, by Enzensberger</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This <a href="https://smile.amazon.com/Drawbridge-Up-Mathematics-Cultural-Anathema/dp/156881156X">talk</a> from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_Magnus_Enzensberger">the author of The Number Devil</a> is unfortunately
hard to find at a reasonable price. It's a beautiful short version of
the not uncommon sentiment that math should be more widely
appreciated.</p>
<ul>
<li>Short: Drawbridge Up, by Enzensberger</li>
<li>Medium: <a href="/20200909-mathematicians_lament_by_lockhart/">A Mathematician's Lament, by Lockhart</a></li>
<li>Long: <a href="//20200925-how_not_to_be_wrong_by_ellenberg/">How Not to Be Wrong, by Ellenberg</a></li>
</ul>
<p>At least <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Mumford">Mumford</a>'s preface is <a href="https://www.dam.brown.edu/people/mumford/beyond/education.html">available</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"I am accustomed, as a professional mathematician, to living in a
sort of vacuum, surrounded by people who, as in the first paragraph
of Enzensberger's essay, declare with an odd sort of pride that they
are mathematically illiterate. How astonishing to come to the
International Congress and find a distinguished poet and essayist
who analyzes this problem with such a deep understanding and
sensitivity. This is a beautiful essay and great delight for a
mathematician to read. Here the strange contradictions with which we
live are laid bare with accuracy of a dissecting microscope. He is
onto our schizophrenic world in which, with one hand, we take pride
in building an elegant world utterly divorced from the demands of
reality and, with the other, claim that our ideas underlie virtually
all technological developments of significance. I was particularly
pleased to find that he believes progress is possible in teaching
mathematics, that it can be made exciting to young minds. I tried
(unsuccessfully) to get each high school in which my children were
enrolled to go outside during geometry class and find out how tall
the oak in the yard really is. Instead they buckled under to the
establishment and even removed that staple of my generation: the odd
formulaic Euclidean-style proof in which the pedigree of each step
was detailed. This old game, the one piece of high school
mathematics often mentioned warmly by people who otherwise hated
math, had been found wanting by the mathematical puritans described
in the Stewart quote, where the mathematician is unwilling to "lie a
bit, like everyone else does". I hope the right people read this
essay -- the movers and shakers of school curricula -- and that it
moves them to let a hundred flowers bloom in the classroom."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let me know if you want to borrow my copy.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Selected quotes</h3>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We know that ignorance is a cosmic force of truly insuperable
power." (page 21)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The unforeseen utility of mathematical models is somewhat
puzzling." (page 27)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The ancient debate among the Platonists, the Formalists and the
Constructivists appears to be petering out into an exhausting
stalemate. Mathematicians hardly concern themselves in their praxis
with such questions." (page 29</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It seems a pedagogical <em>id&#233;e fixe</em> that children are incapable of
abstract thinking." (page 37)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20201001-drawbridge_up_by_enzensberger/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20201001-drawbridge_up_by_enzensberger/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Definitional and Computational Sum of Squares are equal</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The definitional (or conceptual) and computational forms of the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Total_sum_of_squares">sum of squared deviations from the mean</a> are equivalent, as in
Equation 1.</p>
<p>\[ SS = \sum \left( x - \overline{x} \right)^2 =
         \sum x^2 - \frac{ \left( \sum x \right)^2 }{ N } \tag{1} \]</p>
<p>We have \( N \) numbers \( x_i \). Their mean is \( \overline{x} \).</p>
<p>\[ \overline{x} = \frac{ \sum_{i=1}^{N} x_i }{ N }  \tag{2} \]</p>
<p>The limits of every sum here are the same, and always range over the
numbers \( x_i \), so the limits and subscript \( i \) are not
shown outside of Equation 2.</p>
<p>The sum of squared deviations from the mean is defined as in Equation
1.</p>
<p>\[ \sum \left( x - \overline{x} \right)^2 \tag{3} \]</p>
<p>Distributing and rearranging, Expression 3 is the same as Expression
4.</p>
<p>\[ \sum \left( x^2 + \overline{x} \left( \overline{x} - 2x \right) \right) \tag{4} \]</p>
<p>Considering the properties of sums, Expression 4 can be re-written as
Expression 5.</p>
<p>\[ \sum x^2 + \overline{x} \left( \sum \overline{x} -2 \sum x \right) \tag{5} \]</p>
<p>The mean \( \overline{x} \) is a constant, so summing over it gives
\( N \overline{x} \). As can be seen from Equation 2, the sum over
\( x \) is also \( N \overline{x} \). Using these, Expression 5
becomes Expression 6.</p>
<p>\[ \sum x^2 - N \overline{x}^2 \tag{6} \]</p>
<p>Replacing the mean \( \overline{x} \) with its definition as in
Equation 2, we arrive at the computational form.</p>
<p>\[ \sum x^2 - \frac{ \left( \sum x \right)^2 }{ N } \tag{7} \]</p>
<p>Expression 3 and Expression 7 are therefore equal, as shown in
Equation 1. \( \blacksquare \)</p>
<hr>
<p>I thought about writing this up years ago; here's an old
<a href="old.html">draft</a>. I referred to McDowell's <a href="http://psychology.emory.edu/clinical/mcdowell/PSYCH560/Basics/var.html">derivation</a> (nominally
for variance) in writing the above. The computational form is nice
especially if you're calculating by hand, and is (has been?) sometimes
<a href="http://www.ablongman.com/graziano6e/text_site/MATERIAL/Stats/manvar.htm">taught</a> as a procedure, sort of like long division. I don't think
teaching that is really a good idea, if what you care about is
teaching statistics, but it could be a neat example in the right kind
of course on implementation of algorithms (applied math or CS,
maybe?).</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200927-definitional_and_computational_sum_of_squares_are_equal/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200927-definitional_and_computational_sum_of_squares_are_equal/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>AI Superpowers, by Lee</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>There's a lot <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kai-Fu_Lee">Kai-fu Lee</a> isn't wrong about in <a href="https://www.aisuperpowers.com/">AI Superpowers</a>.
The major break-through of deep learning has occurred, and
applications are now more engineering than invention (cf. <a href="/20200728-technological_revolutions_and_financial_capital/">Perez</a>).
China has data, entrepreneurs, engineers, and government support for
AI. Compared to the US, China has fewer ethical qualms and democratic
controls, which Lee propagandizes as advantages for China. I think
he's right that we should worry more about human society than about
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_general_intelligence">AGI</a>, but I think he exaggerates the exceptionalism of AI.</p>
<p>The boundary between AI and non-AI computing isn't clear. There have
been industrial robots for years. Does it matter whether Google search
is powered by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PageRank">PageRank</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BERT_(language_model)">BERT</a>? It's hard to pin down exactly
what's AI and what isn't. But this isn't my main objection.</p>
<p>There has <em>already been</em> a trend toward concentration of corporate
power, economic inequality, and unemployment/underemployment. The main
problem with Harari's "<a href="https://ideas.ted.com/the-rise-of-the-useless-class/">useless class</a>" idea is his use of the
future tense. The useless class is here already.</p>
<p>It might be better to discuss issues of the future of society in
connections with AI rather than not at all, but I worry that the focus
on AI can distract from trends and approaches that aren't tied to AI.
It isn't useful to make new AI a scapegoat for existing phenomena.</p>
<p>I think Lee overestimates the magnitude of AI's direct impact on jobs,
but maybe not the magnitude of the overall trend in jobs. Regardless,
he then spends the back of the book opining on public policy after his
come-to-Jesus (not literally) experience with cancer. He praises
volunteers and then proposes that we must pay people for things they
would volunteer to do if they didn't have to worry about money. I
don't oppose paying teachers (etc.) more, but I think he's
fundamentally wrong about how humans work, and I think he's way
outside his area of expertise.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Selected quotes and (rarely) commentary</h3>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In my view, that [Chinese/US] lead in AI development will translate
into productivity gains on a scale not seen since the Industrial
Revolution." (page 18)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Based on the current trends in technology advancement and adoption,
I predict that within fifteen years, artificial intelligence will
technically be able to replace around 40 to 50 percent of jobs in
the United States. Actual job losses may end up lagging those
technical capabilities by an additional decade, but I forecast that
the disruption to job markets will be very real, very large, and
coming soon." (page 19)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Published in 2018, so that's capability by 2033 and job losses by
2043.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The AI world order will combine winner-take-all economics with an
unprecedented concentration of wealth in the hands of a few
companies in China and the United States. This, I believe, is the
real underlying threat posed by artificial intelligence: tremendous
social disorder and political collapse stemming from widespread
unemployment and gaping inequality." (page 21)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Entry into the country's imperial bureaucracy depended on
word-for-word memorization of ancient texts and the ability to
construct a perfect "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eight-legged_essay">eight-legged essay</a>" following rigid
stylistic guidelines." (page 27)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"But what these critics miss is that this process
[of Chinese central government support] can be both highly
inefficient and extraordinarily effective." (page 65)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Lucky for them, these [Chinese] cities are also home to large pools
of migrant laborers who would gladly bring that service to their
door for a small fee." (page 69)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2019/05/china-migrant-workers-miserable/589423/">The Migrant Workers Behind China&#8217;s Economic Miracle Are Miserable</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>AI is "the defining technology of the twenty-first century." (page
80)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As I laid out earlier, creating an AI superpower for the
twenty-first century requires four main building blocks: abundant
data, tenacious entrepreneurs, well-trained AI scientists, and a
supportive policy environment." (page 82)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The complete AI revolution will take a little time and will
ultimately wash over us in a series of four waves: internet AI,
business AI, perception AI, and autonomous AI." (page 105)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"And judicial biases can be far less malicious than racism: a study
of Israeli judges found them far more severe in their decision
before lunch and more lenient in granting parole after having a good
meal." (page 116)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Even if this well-known judge study were replicated and broadly
believed (which it is <a href="http://nautil.us/blog/impossibly-hungry-judges">not</a>), Lee's reference is still rather
appalling excuse-making for racist algorithms.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Chinese and American internet companies have taken different
approaches to winning local markets,
[China supporting local companies, America expanding into markets directly]
and as these AI services filter out to every corner of the world,
they may engage in proxy competition in countries like India,
Indonesia, and parts of the Middle East and Africa." (page 139)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We looked at technical fixes that seek to smooth the transition to
an AI economy: retraining workers, reducing work hours, and
redistributing income through a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_basic_income">UBI</a>. While all of these
technical fixes have a role to play, I believe something more is
needed. I envision the private sector creatively fostering
human-machine symbiosis, a new wave of impact investing funding
human-centric service jobs, and the government filling the gaps with
a social investment stipend that rewards care, service, and
education." (page 224-225)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In revamping our education systems, we can learn much from South
Korea's embrace of gifted and talented education. These programs
seek to identify and realize the potential of the country's top
technical minds, an approach suited to creating the material
prosperity that can then be broadly shared across society." (page
229)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Describes <a href="https://www.smartfinancegroup.com/static/publish/en_aboutus.html">Smart Finance</a> as a technological leap-frog AI success
story (page 112-113) but many would describe it as a privacy and
fairness nightmare.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/want-a-loan-in-china-keep-your-phone-charged-1491474250">Want a Loan in China? Keep Your Phone Charged</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/12/25/business/china-online-lending-debt.html">China&#8217;s New Lenders Collect Invasive Data and Offer Billions. Beijing Is Worried.</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200926-ai_superpowers_by_lee/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200926-ai_superpowers_by_lee/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How Not to Be Wrong, by Ellenberg</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I like <a href="https://www.jordanellenberg.com/how-not-to-be-wrong/">this book</a> a lot. The five parts (Linearity, Inference,
Expectation, Regression, Existence) provide beautiful large-scale
structure, and it also shimmers on every page. Supreme Court justices
encounter the word "orthogonal." There's a beautiful proof of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffon%27s_needle_problem">Buffon's needle problem</a>. There's some philosophy of math.
Ellenberg is a delight.</p>
<p>In some ways, How Not to Be Wrong is like a long version of
<a href="/20200909-mathematicians_lament_by_lockhart/">Lockhart's exultation</a>, with examples. Lockhart extols the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Method_of_exhaustion">method of exhaustion</a>; Ellenberg teaches it. The author clearly
loves math, and shares it generously with the reader.</p>
<p>The "How Not to Be Wrong" is delivered by exposing numerous common
fallacies or errors in understanding. Not every phenomenon is linear.
"Don't talk about percentages of numbers when the numbers might be
negative." "Improbable things happen a lot," and that affects how you
should think about significance tests and related things. The book is
a joy to read, I'd also read a "handbook" version collecting just the
main ideas.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Selected quotations and (rarely) comments</h3>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Those [homework] integrals are to mathematics as weight training
and calisthenics are to soccer. If you want to play soccer&#8212;I mean,
<em>really play</em>, at a competitive level&#8212;you've got to do a lot of
boring, repetitive, apparently pointless drills." (page 2)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Math is woven into the way we reason." (page 2)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Here's an old mathematician's trick that makes the picture
perfectly clear: <em>set some variables to zero</em>." (pages 6-7)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"What assumptions are you making? And are they justified?" (page 7)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Mathematics <em>is</em> common sense." (page 10)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Mathematicians like to give names to the phenomena our common sense
describes: instead of saying &#8220;<em>This</em> thing added to <em>that</em> thing is
the <em>same</em> thing as <em>that</em> thing added to <em>this</em> thing,&#8221; we say
&#8220;Addition is commutative.&#8221;" (page 11)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Seems like a philosophy similar to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Where_Mathematics_Comes_From">Where Mathematics Comes From</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We tend to teach mathematics as a long list of rules. You learn
them in order and you have to obey them, because if you don&#8217;t obey
them you get a C-. <em>This is not mathematics.</em> Mathematics is the
study of things that come out a certain way because there is no
other way they could possibly be." (page 12)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The specialized language in which mathematicians converse with one
another is a magnificent tool for conveying complex ideas precisely
and swiftly. But its foreignness can create among outsiders the
impression of a sphere of thought totally alien to ordinary
thinking. That's exactly wrong." (page 12)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Mathematics is the extension of common sense by other means." (page
13)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"School mathematics is largely made up of a sequence of facts and
rules, facts which are certain, rules which come from a higher
authority and cannot be questioned." (page 14)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Mathematics is not settled." (page 14)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"(Aside: it's important to point out here that people with
out-of-the-mainstream ideas who compare themselves to Edison and
Galileo are <em>never actually right</em>. I get letters with this kind of
language at least once a month, usually from people who have
&#8220;proofs&#8221; of mathematical statements that have been known for
hundreds of years to be false. I can guarantee you Einstein did not
go around telling people, &#8220;Look, I know this theory of general
relativity sounds wacky, but that's what they said about Galileo!&#8221;)"
(page 27)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... the oldest false syllogism in the book:"</p>
<p>"It <em>could</em> be the case that lowering taxes will increase government
revenue;"</p>
<p>"I <em>want</em> it to be the case that lowering taxes will increase
government revenue;"</p>
<p>"Therefore, <em>it is</em> the case that lowering taxes will increase
government revenue." (page 30)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The Pythagoreans, you have to remember, were extremely weird."
(page 33)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"A basic rule of mathematical life: if the universe hands you a hard
problem, try to solve an easier one instead, and hope the simple
version is close enough to the original problem that the universe
doesn't object." (page 35)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"What's the numerical value of an infinite sum? It doesn't have
one&#8212;<em>until we give it one</em>." (page 47)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"(In mathematics, you very seldom get the clearest account of an
idea from the person who invented it.)" (page 49)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Cauchy was not interested in the needs of engineers. Cauchy was
interested in the truth. It's hard to defend Cauchy's stance on
pedagogical grounds." (page 49)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Working an integral or performing a linear regression is something
a computer can do quite effectively. Understanding whether the
result makes sense&#8212;or deciding whether the method is the right one
to use in the first place&#8212;requires a guiding human hand. When we
teach mathematics we are supposed to be explaining how to be that
guide. A math course that fails to do so is essentially training the
student to be a very slow, buggy version of Microsoft Excel." (page
56)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"there are algorithms I think we can safely discard in the modern
world. We don't need to teach students how to extract square roots
by hand, or in their head ..." (page 57)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Of course it's no better (in fact, it's substantially worse) to
pass along a population of students who've developed some wispy
sense of mathematical meaning but can't work examples swiftly and
correctly. A math teacher's least favorite thing to hear from a
student is &#8220;I get the concept, but I couldn't do the problems.&#8221;
Though the student doesn't know it, this is shorthand for &#8220;I don't
get the concept.&#8221; The ideas of mathematics can sound abstract, but
they make sense only in reference to concrete computations. William
Carlos Williams put it crisply: <em>no ideas but in things</em>." (page 58)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The situation [of school geometry] is so dire that the Fields
Medalist David Mumford has suggested that we might dispense with
plane geometry entirely and replace it with a first course in
programming." (page 58)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Mumford <a href="https://www.dam.brown.edu/people/mumford/beyond/education.html">links</a> to his <a href="https://www.dam.brown.edu/people/mumford/beyond/papers/CurtisArticleRev10-6.pdf">manuscript</a>, "What Mathematics Serves the
Majority of 21st Century American Students?"</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"If a tiny state like South Dakota experiences a rash of brain
cancer, you might presume that the spike is in large measure due to
luck, and you might estimate that the rate of brain cancer in the
future is likely to be closer to the overall national number. You
could accomplish this by taking some kind of weighted average of the
South Dakota rate with the national rate. But how to weight the two
numbers? That's a bit of an art, involving a fair amount of
technical labor I'll spare you here." (pages 70-71)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think he's referring to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multilevel_model">multi-level modeling</a>, in the Gelman
style.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<em>Don't talk about percentages of numbers when the numbers might be
negative.</em>" (page 78)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<em>Improbable things happen a lot.</em>" (page 98)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When we are scientists, or Torah scholars, or toddlers gaping at
the clouds, we are presented with <em>observations</em> and asked to build
<em>theories</em>&#8211;what went into the box to produce the world that we see?
Inference is a hard thing, maybe the hardest thing." (page 110)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Ellenberg says "inference" but I might say "abduction."</p>
<hr>
<p>Dangers of comparing very small rates:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"... <em>twice a tiny number is a tiny number</em>. How good or bad it is
to double something depends on how big that something is!" (page
120)</p>
<p>"Risk ratios are much easier for the brain to grasp than tiny
splinters of probability like 1 in 7,000. But risk ratios applied to
small probabilities can easily mislead you." (page 120)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The truth is, the null hypothesis, if we take it literally, is
probably just about always false." (page 120)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"If only we could go back in time to the dawn of statistical
nomenclature and declare that a result passing Fisher's test with a
p-value of less than 0.05 was &#8220;statistically noticeable&#8221; or
&#8220;statistically detectable&#8221; instead of &#8220;statistically significant&#8221;!
That would be truer to the meaning of the method, which merely
counsels us about the existence of an effect but is silent about its
size or importance. But it's too late for that. We have the language
we have." (page 121)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It has come to my attention that hardly anybody knows what the
logarithm is. Let me take a step toward fixing this. The logarithm
of a positive number <em>N</em>, called <em>log N</em>, is the number of digits it
has." (page 139)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He goes on to call this the "fake logarithm," of "flogarithm."</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In particular, the view that the primary concern of statistics is
making decisions is more closely associated with Neyman than with
Pearson." (page 159)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Reminds me of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cassie_Kozyrkov">Cassie Kozyrkov</a>, the Google Decision Scientist.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<em>The significance test is the detective, not the judge.</em>" (page
161)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>I have <em>tried</em> to find the origin of the Target pregnancy prediction
story before, but somehow I never tracked it down. Ellenberg has it!</p>
<p><a href="https://charlesduhigg.com/how-companies-learn-your-secrets-part-1/">How Companies Learn Your Secrets</a>, by Charles Duhigg</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The p-value is the answer to the question</p>
<p>""The chance that the observed experimental result would occur,
given that the null hypothesis is correct."</p>
<p>"But what we <em>want</em> to know is the other conditional probability:</p>
<p>""The chance that the null hypothesis is correct, given that we
observed a certain experimental result."" (page 170)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is connected to Bayesian stats as "inverse probability", and he
also notes that it's referred to as "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prosecutor%27s_fallacy">the prosecutor's fallacy</a>" and
references the book <em>Math on Trial</em>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"no scientific worker has a fixed level of significance at which
from year to year, and in all circumstances, he rejects hypotheses;
he rather gives his mind to each particular case in the light of his
evidence and his ideas" (page 180, quoting Fisher)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Saying that even Fisher thinks our prior beliefs enter our work;
Fisher just has certain ideas about when it's appropriate to invoke
probability: he insists on some actual chance process.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We tend to like simpler theories better than more complicated ones;
theories that rest on analogies to things we already know about
better than theories that posit totally novel phenomena." (page 182)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... you have to be careful about the universe of theories you
consider. Just as there may be more than one solution to a quadratic
equation, there may be multiple theories that give rise to the same
observation, and if we don't consider them all, our inferences may
lead us badly astray." (page 185)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is an old maxim of mine that when you have excluded the
impossible, whatever remains, however improbably, must be the truth,
unless the truth is a hypothesis it didn't occur to me to consider."
(page 188)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"And as much as I love Bayesian inference, I think people are
probably best off arriving at their faith, or discarding it, in a
non-quantitative way." (page 191)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Expected value is not the value you expect" (page 198)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://www.maa.org/sites/default/files/pdf/upload_library/22/Ford/Abrams2011.pdf">Finding Good Bets in the Lottery, and Why You Shouldn&#8217;t Take Them</a> is a great reference, which I connect to my <a href="/2012/06/04/expected-value-is-not-useful-for-making/">Expected value is not useful for making decisions about lottery tickets</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Any given ticket is probably worthless, but if you've got a
thousand tickets, it's essentially certain that you'll make your
money back and then some." (page 209)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This gets at what I think is important: It isn't the expected value
you care about, it's your probability of being in a state that doesn't
suck. You want P(losing money) to become negligible, and that can
happen if you have positive expected value <em>and</em> enough tickets.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When you're faced with a math problem you don't know how to do,
you've got two basic options. You can make the problem easier, or
you can make it harder." (page 218)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Mathematics as currently practiced is a delicate interplay between
monastic contemplation and blowing stuff up with dynamite." (page
223)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"If gambling is exciting, you're doing it wrong" (page 227)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The doctrine of expected utility is appealingly straightforward and
simple: presented with a set of choices, pick the one with the
highest expected utility. It is perhaps the closest thing we have to
a simple mathematical theory of individual decision making. And it
captures many features of the way humans make choices, which is why
it remains a central part of the quantitative social scientist's
tool kit. (page 248)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In the decision-theory literature, the former kind of unknown is
called <em>risk</em>, the latter <em>uncertainty</em>." (page 251)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The former is known unknowns (30% chance of drawing a black ball) and
the latter is unknown unknowns (maybe we're wrong about what the
chance is).</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As always, it can be easier to see what's going on with the math if
we make the numbers small enough that we can draw pictures." (page
258)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Mathematical elegance and practical utility are close companions,
as the history of science has shown again and again." (page 266)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The Patent Department would not release the thing until they had
patent coverage. ... I didn't believe that they could patent a bunch
of mathematical formulas. I said they couldn't. They said, "Watch
us." They were right. And since then I have known that I have a very
weak understanding of patent laws because, regularly, things that
you shouldn't be able to patent&#8211;it's outrageous&#8211;you can patent."
(page 276, quoting Hamming)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Cohn works at Microsoft Research, which is in a way a continuation
of the Bell Labs model of pure math supported by high-tech industry,
hopefully to the benefit of both." (page 281)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Apparently Galton wrote an article called "Statistical Inquiries into
the Efficacy of Prayer". (page 299)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"You have made a convert of an opponent in one sense, for I have
always maintained that excepting fools, men did not differ much in
intellect, only in zeal and hard work; and I still think this is an
eminently important difference." (page 300, quoting Charles Darwin's
letter to his cousin Francis Galton on the effect of reading
Galton's "Hereditary Genius")</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Ellenberg includes a fun table of Galton's on page 316, which has the
character of a visualization in that you can see an ellipse, sort of
like a two-dimensional stem and leaf plot...</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_anthropometry#Forensic_anthropometry">Bertillonage</a> (page 325) is kind of interesting and can be related
to modern systems that use data to track people, but it's also a lot
like a primitive "hashing" method for more quickly finding a record.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parsons_code">Parsons code</a> is pretty neat, and can be used for contour search at
<a href="https://www.musipedia.org/">Musipedia</a>. (page 329)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"A democracy cannot endure unless it be composed of able citizens;
therefore it must in self-defence withstand the free introduction of
degenerate stock." (page 335, quoting Galton)</p>
<p>"There is real danger that, by strengthening our abilities to
analyze some questions mathematically, we acquire a general
confidence in our beliefs, which extends unjustifiably to those
things we're still wrong about." (page 335)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Darwin showed that one could meaningfully talk about progress
without any need to invoke purpose. Galton showed that one could
meaningfully talk about association without any need to invoke
underlying cause." (page 336)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Mathematicians ever since Descartes have enjoyed the wonderful
freedom to flip back and forth between algebraic and geometric
descriptions of the world. The advantage of algebra is that it's
easier to formalize and to type into a computer. The advantage of
geometry is that it allows us to bring our physical intuition to
bear on the situation, particularly when you can draw a picture. I
seldom feel I <em>really</em> understand a piece of mathematics until I
know what it's about in geometric language." (page 336)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This relates to "The Rule of Three" in the McCallum et al. <em>Multivariable Calculus</em>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Every topic should be presented geometrically, numerically and
algebraically." (page v)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It may sound impressive that we can do geometry in ten dimensions
(or a hundred, or a million...), but the mental pictures we keep in
our mind are two- or at most three-dimensional. That's all our
brains can handle. Fortunately, this impoverished vision is usually
enough." (page 338)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... a mathematical tool that's just right for one purpose tends to
make itself useful again and again." (page 340)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Correlation is not transitive. It's more like "blood relation"&#8211;I'm
related to my son, who's related to my wife, but my wife and I
aren't blood relatives to each other. In fact, it's not a terrible
idea to think of correlated variables as "sharing part of their
DNA."" (page 342)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Undecided voters, by and large, aren't undecided because they're
carefully weighing the merits of each candidate, unprejudiced by
political dogma. They're undecided because they're barely paying
attention." (page 346)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>A section titled "It's not always wrong to be wrong" on page 354
suggests decision-making by expected value can be appropriate even if
it turns out later that a risk isn't as previously believed.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There is no such thing as public opinion" (page 365)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The "majority rules" system is simple and elegant and feels fair,
but it's at its best when deciding between just two options. Any
more than two, and contradictions start to seep into the majority's
preferences." (page 368)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Ellenberg's immediate (and real, October 2010) example:</p>
<ul>
<li>52% oppose ACA</li>
<li>41% support ACA</li>
</ul>
<p>But:</p>
<ul>
<li>37% favor repeal of ACA</li>
<li>10% favor weakening ACA</li>
<li>15% favor maintaining ACA</li>
<li>36% favor expanding ACA</li>
</ul>
<p>This implies that some of the "oppose" people oppose it because they
want <em>more extreme</em> policy than ACA, not less.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The poll watcher who aspires not to be wrong has to test each of
the poll's options, to see whether it might break down into
different-colored pieces." (page 368)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Public opinion doesn't exist. More precisely, it exists sometimes,
concerning matters about which there's a clear majority view." (page
369)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"the inconsistency of aggregate judgments." (page 374)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Maybe individual people seem irrational because they aren't really
individuals." (page 383)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"For most people, nowadays, the appeal of democratic choice is that
it's <em>fair</em>; we speak in the language of rights and believe on moral
grounds that people should be able to choose their own rulers,
whether these choices are wise or not." (page 393)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This is a story told in mathematics again and again: we develop a
method that works for one problem, and if it is a <em>good</em> method, one
that really contains a new idea, we typically find that the same
proof works in many different contexts, which may be as different
from the original as a sphere is from a plane, or more so." (page
399)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Describes formalism as being the tradition of definition; thinking
about what "1 - 1 + 1 -1 + ..." should be <em>defined as</em>, rather that
what it <em>is</em>. This can have the effect of replacing <em>meaning</em> with
definition.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"If we're to be precise, Russell was not a formalist, like Hilbert,
who declared that the axioms were just strings of symbols with no
defined meaning; rather, he was a "logicist," whose view was that
the axioms were actually true statements about logical facts. Both
groups shared a vigorous interest in figuring out which statements
could be deduced from the axioms. The extent to which you care about
this distinction is a good measure of whether you would enjoy going
to graduate school in analytic philosophy." (page 409)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The genius cult tells students it's not worth doing mathematics
unless you're the <em>best</em> at mathematics, because those special few
are the only ones whose contributions matter." (page 412)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The cult of genius also tends to undervalue hard work." (page 413)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Sitting around waiting for inspiration leads to failure, no matter
how much of a whiz kid you are." (page 414)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Poincar&#233;'s essay <em>Mathematical Creation</em> is in his book
<a href="https://www.google.com/books/edition/_/qgkeAAAAMAAJ">The Foundations of Science</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Genius is a thing that happens, not a kind of person." (page 416)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Political logic is not a formal system in the sense that Hilbert
and the mathematical logicians meant, but mathematicians with a
formalist outlook couldn't help but approach politics with the same
kind of methodological sympathies. They were encouraged in this by
Hilbert himself, who in his 1918 lecture "<a href="/20200923-axiomatic_thinking_hilbert_1918/">Axiomatic Thought</a>"
advocated that the other sciences adopt the axiomatic approach that
had been so successful in mathematics."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There's such a thing as being too precise." (page 430)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Philosophers of a mathematical bent call this brittleness in formal
logic <em>ex falso quodlibet</em>, or, among friends, "the principle of
explosion."" (page 433)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Say we have a contradiction, both A and not A, and want to show B.</p>
<p>Consider A and not B. A is false, so A and not B is false. Then since
A and not B is false, and A is true, not B is false, so B is true.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Believe whatever you believe by day; but at night, argue against
the propositions you hold most dear." (page 434)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"[F. Scott Fitzgerald's] endorsement of holding contradictory
beliefs ["the test of a first-rate intelligence is the ability to
hold two opposed ideas in the mind at the same time, and still
retain the ability to function"] comes from "The Crack-Up," his
1936 essay about his own irreparable brokenness. The opposing ideas
he has in mind there are "the sense of futility of effort and the
sense of the necessity to struggle."" (page 434)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"All mathematical writing is creative writing." (page 436)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Logic forms a narrow channel through which intuition flows with
vastly augmented force." (page 437)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... mathematical certainty is one thing, the softer convictions we
find attached to us in everyday life another, and we should keep
track of the difference if we can." (page 437)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3>Some fun words</h3>
<p>demotic: denoting or relating to the kind of language used by ordinary
people; popular or colloquial. (page 340)</p>
<p>diverticular disease: bulges in the large intestine; diverticulosis.
(page 309)</p>
<p>physiognomy: a person's facial features or expression, especially when
regarded as indicative of character or ethnic origin. (page 328)</p>
<p>recondite: (of a subject or knowledge) little known; abstruse. (page 3)</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200925-how_not_to_be_wrong_by_ellenberg/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200925-how_not_to_be_wrong_by_ellenberg/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Trivia rewards test-time effort</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I've been a casual <a href="https://www.learnedleague.com/">LearnedLeague</a> trivia player for a while. I was
inspired by <a href="/20200716-lateral_thinking_creativity_step_by_step/">Lateral Thinking</a> (the book) to try typing out
"conversations with myself" as I thought about the questions during
season 86. I didn't study or change anything else. Directing effort
during question-answering seems to have helped me answer more
questions correctly.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#sure">Am I sure I did better?</a></li>
<li><a href="#diff">What did I do differently?</a></li>
<li><a href="#obvious">Is the benefit of effort obvious?</a></li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="SchumacherA correct answers per season" src="tca.png"></p>
<p><em>There are four LearnedLeague seasons per year, each with 25 match
days of 6 questions each. My performance has ranged from 34 to 66
correct out of 150, or 22.7% to 44.0% correct.</em></p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="sure"></a>Am I sure I did better?</h3>
<p>A change in question difficulty could also lead to me getting more
right. I've been in Rundle E for all the seasons shown, which means
I'm in with a bunch of other casual players. Since the mix of people
isn't likely to suddenly change, the performance of my opponents is a
rough control for question difficulty. Looking at the difference
between my number of correct answers and my opponents', the season 86
improvement is still clear.</p>
<p><img alt="SchumacherA correct answer differential per season" src="cadiff.png"></p>
<p>Looking at the league-wide correct answer percentage, it does seem
that this season was slightly easier than last season, but the
difference is small (50.71% vs. 49.06%). There are fancier ways to try
to control for question difficulty, but I'm satisfied that the change
in my performance isn't primarily due to changes in question
difficulty.</p>
<p>I also don't think the change is explained by a gradual process of
natural learning over time. I don't see any compelling pattern in the
first fifteen data points.</p>
<p>If you assume the earlier 15 season results were samples from the same
distribution, my season 86 result is very unlikely to arise from that
distribution by chance (p-value well under 0.01) for either view of
the data. (<a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/blob/master/20200924-trivia_rewards_effort/analyze.ipynb">calculations</a>)</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="diff"></a>What did I do differently?</h3>
<p>Previously, I'd look at the questions online, think about them, and
write in my answers. For season 86, I inserted an extra step. I copied
the questions into a text file on my computer, and I typed out my
thinking process, using lots of question marks and thinking of lots of
related things, even sometimes free-associating.</p>
<p>Here's an example <a href="https://www.learnedleague.com/question.php?86&amp;7&amp;1">question</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The decade of chaos and political upheaval in China that began in
1966, grounded in a factional conflict over the future of Chinese
socialism, and ended with Mao's death in 1976, is best known in the
west as what "Revolution"?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's not a hard question, but I didn't remember the answer at first.
In fact, I had a wrong answer that I was nearly ready to use. Here's
what I wrote in my file:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Children's? Somehow I think "Children's Revolution"... Was that
something from 3 Body Problem? Seems like a weird revolution name.
What else... Green Revolution was/is a big agriculture thing... That
other Chinese thing is "The Great Leap Forward" when lots of people
died... Mao's Revolution? People's Revolution? Socialist Revolution?
Weird Revolution? Party Revolution? Dance Dance Revolution? Red
Revolution? "It was known in the west as the ..." Decade? 10-year
Revolution? Slow revolution? Is it named after a leader? Other than
Mao? Cultural Revolution? Hmm... That sounds right somehow. Great
Leap Forward, Cultural Revolution... both of those sound like
history things.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It took me a while to finally get to the right answer. If I hadn't
been writing things out like this, I might have just written down my
first guess. There were many questions like this, when I felt like the
extra process helped me get to a correct answer.</p>
<p>The extra process also led to me getting more mentally and emotionally
involved in the season. I felt like I was doing a little bit better,
and it made me care more. A seemingly mechanical task change ended up
increasing my motivation.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="obvious"></a>Is the benefit of effort obvious?</h3>
<p>In the extreme, low effort can lead to scores of zero, so effort
certainly has some effect. But I've never "blown off" LearnedLeague;
I've always tried to answer as best I can. So the possibly surprising
thing is that I was able to improve markedly from that baseline.</p>
<p>Trivia is pretty close to a pure knowledge test: "either you know it
or you don't." It isn't surprising that performance improves with
study in advance, and it isn't surprising that performance varies by
person based on strength of memory, etc. But it might be surprising
that performance can vary for an individual, depending on approach
during the test itself.</p>
<p>If performance changes measurably on a task like this, how much more
so for process tasks like mathematics? How large must be the
contribution to a student's standardized test scores from motivation
and focus on a particular day?</p>
<p>On the other hand, the observed effect doesn't move me at all into the
ranks of the strongest competitors on LearnedLeague, who routinely get
70% of questions correct, compared to my new record of 44%.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the effect is large enough that it seems like it
matters, and it certainly matters psychologically to me. Something
like a <a href="https://www.mindsetworks.com/science/">growth mindset</a>, it motivates me a lot more to think about
LearnedLeague as something that responds to effort, rather than just a
test of what I happen to know... It's more like climbing a rope than
checking oil with a dipstick. (More like climbing a rope than
measuring a rope? I'm liking this image...)</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200924-trivia_rewards_effort/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200924-trivia_rewards_effort/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Axiomatic Thinking (Hilbert, 1918)</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I had difficulty finding this online, so I'm posting it here for
reference.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="#1" name="1">&#182;</a> Just as in the life of nations the
individual nation can only thrive when all neighbouring nations are in
good health; and just as the interest of states demands, not only that
order prevail within every individual state, but also that the
relationships of the states among themselves be in good order; so it
is in the life of the sciences. In due recognition of this fact the
most important bearers of mathematical thought have always evinced
great interest in the laws and the structure of the neighbouring
sciences; above all for the benefit of mathematics itself they have
always cultivated the relations to the neighbouring sciences,
especially to the great empires of physics and epistemology. I believe
that the essence of these relations, and the reason for their
fruitfulness, will appear most clearly if I describe for you the
general method of research which seems to be coming more and more into
its own in modern mathematics: I mean the <em>axiomatic method</em>.</p>
<p><a href="#2" name="2">&#182;</a> When we assemble the facts of a definite,
more-or-less comprehensive field of knowledge, we soon notice that
these facts are capable of being ordered. This ordering always comes
about with the help of a certain <em>framework of concepts</em>
[<em>Fachwerk von Begriffen</em>] in the following way: a concept of this
framework corresponds to each individual object of the field of
knowledge, and a logical relation between concepts corresponds to
every fact within the field of knowledge. The framework of concepts is
nothing other than the <em>theory</em> of the field of knowledge.</p>
<p><a href="#3" name="3">&#182;</a> Thus the facts of geometry order
themselves into a geometry, the facts of arithmetic into a theory of
numbers, the facts of statics, mechanics, electrodynamics into a
theory of statics, mechanics, electrodynamics, or the facts from the
physics of gases into a theory of gases. It is precisely the same with
the fields of knowledge of thermodynamics, geometrical optics,
elementary radiation-theory, the conduction of heat, or also with the
calculus of probabilities or the theory of sets. It even holds of
special fields of knowledge in pure mathematics, such as the theory of
surfaces, the theory of Galois equations, and the theory of prime
numbers, no less than for several fields of knowledge that lie far
from mathematics, such as certain parts of psychophysics or the theory
of money.</p>
<p><a href="#4" name="4">&#182;</a> If we consider a particular theory more
closely, we always see that a few distinguished propositions of the
field of knowledge underlie the construction of the framework of
concepts, and these propositions then suffice by themselves for the
construction, in accordance with logical principles, of the entire
framework.</p>
<p><a href="#5" name="5">&#182;</a> Thus in geometry the proposition of the
linearity of the equation of the plane and of the orthogonal
transformation of point-coordinates is completely adequate to produce
the whole broad science of spatial Euclidean geometry purely by means
of analysis. Moreover, the laws of calculation and the rules for
integers suffice for the construction of number theory. In statics the
same role is played by the proposition of the parallelogram of forces;
in mechanics, say, by the Lagrangian differential equations of motion;
and in electrodynamics by the Maxwell equations together with the
requirement of the rigidity and charge of the electron. Thermodynamics
can be completely built up from the concept of energy function and the
definition of temperature and pressure as derivatives of its
variables, entropy and volume. At the heart of the elementary theory
of radiation is Kirchhoff's theorem on the relationships between
emission and absorption; in the calculus of probabilities the Gaussian
law of errors is the fundamental proposition; in the theory of gases,
the proposition that entropy is the negative logarithm of the
probability of the state; in the theory of surfaces, the
representation of the element of arc by the quadratic differential
form; in the theory of equations, the proposition concerning the
existence of roots; in the theory of prime numbers, the proposition
concerning the reality and frequency of Rieman's function &#120577;(s).</p>
<p><a href="#6" name="6">&#182;</a> These fundamental propositions can be
regarded from an initial standpoint as the <em>axioms of the individual
fields of knowledge</em>: the progressive development of the individual
field of knowledge then lies solely in the further logical
construction of the already mentioned framework of concepts. This
standpoint is especially predominant in pure mathematics, and to the
corresponding manner of working we owe the mighty development of
geometry, of arithmetic, of the theory of functions, and of the whole
of analysis.</p>
<p><a href="#7" name="7">&#182;</a> Thus in the cases mentioned above the
problem of grounding the individual field of knowledge had found a
solution; but this solution was only temporary. In fact, in the
individual fields of knowledge the need arose to ground the
fundamental axiomatic propositions themselves. So one acquired
'proofs' of the linearity of the equation of the plane and the
orthogonality of the transformation expressing a movement, of the laws
of arithmetical calculation, of the parallelogram of forces, of the
Lagrangian equations of motion, of Kirchhoff's law regarding emission
and absorption, of the law of entropy, and of the proposition
concerning the existence of roots of an equation.</p>
<p><a href="#8" name="8">&#182;</a> But critical examination of these 'proofs'
shows that they are not in themselves proofs, but basically only make
it possible to trace things back to certain deeper propositions, which
in turn are now to be regarded as new axioms instead of the
propositions to be proved. The actual so-called <em>axioms</em> of geometry,
arithmetic, statics, mechanics, radiation theory, or thermodynamics
arose in this way. These axioms form a layer of axioms which lies
deeper than the axiom-layer given by the recently-mentioned
fundamental theorems of the individual field of knowledge. The
procedure of the axiomatic method, as it is expressed here, amounts to
a <em>deepening of the foundations</em> of the individual domains of
knowledge&#8212;a deepening that is necessary for every edifice that one
wishes to expand and to build higher while preserving its stability.</p>
<p><a href="#9" name="9">&#182;</a> If the theory of a field of knowledge&#8212;that
is, the framework of concepts that represents it&#8212;is to serve its
purpose of orienting and ordering, then it must satisfy two
requirements above all: <em>first</em> it should give us an overview of the
<em>independence</em> and <em>dependence</em> of the propositions of the theory;
<em>second</em>, it should give us a guarantee of the <em>consistency</em> of all
the propositions of the theory. In particular, the axioms of each
theory are to be examined from these two points of view.</p>
<p><a href="#10" name="10">&#182;</a> Let us first consider the independence
or dependence of the axioms.</p>
<p><a href="#11" name="11">&#182;</a> The <em>axiom of parallels</em> in geometry is
the classical example of the independence of an axiom. When he placed
the parallel postulate among the axioms, Euclid thereby denied that
the proposition of parallels is implied by the other axioms. Euclid's
method of investigation became the paradigm for axiomatic research,
and since Euclid geometry has been the prime example of an axiomatic
science.</p>
<p><a href="#12" name="12">&#182;</a> Classical mechanics furnishes another
example of an investigation of the independence of axioms. The
Lagrangian equations of motion were temporarily able to count as
axioms of mechanics&#8212;for mechanics can of course be entirely based on
these equations when they are generally formulated for arbitrary
forces and arbitrary side-constraints. But further investigation shows
that it is not necessary in the construction of mechanics to
presuppose arbitrary forces or arbitrary side-constraints; thus the
system of presuppositions can be reduced. This piece of knowledge
leads, on the one hand, to the axiom system of Boltzmann, who assumes
only forces (and indeed special central forces) but no
side-constraints, and the axiom system of Hertz, who discards forces
and makes do with side-constraints (and indeed special
side-constraints with rigid connections). These two axiom systems form
a deeper layer in the progressive axiomatization of mechanics.</p>
<p><a href="#13" name="13">&#182;</a> If in establishing the theory of Galois
equations we assume as an axiom the existence of roots of an equation,
then this is certainly a dependent axiom; for, as Gauss was the first
to show, that existence theorem can be proved from the axioms of
arithmetic.</p>
<p><a href="#14" name="14">&#182;</a> Something similar would happen if we
were to assume as an axiom in the theory of prime numbers the
proposition about the reality of the zeroes of the Riemann
&#120577;(s)-function: as we progress to a deeper layer of purely arithmetical
axioms the proof of this reality-proposition would become necessary,
and only this proof would guarantee the reliability of the important
conclusions which we have already achieved for the theory of prime
numbers by taking it as a postulate.</p>
<p><a href="#15" name="15">&#182;</a> A particularly interesting question for
axiomatics concerns the independence of the propositions of a field of
knowledge from the axiom of <em>continuity</em>.</p>
<p><a href="#16" name="16">&#182;</a> In the theory of real numbers it is
shown that the axiom of measurement&#8212;the so-called Archimedean axiom&#8212;is
independent of all the other arithmetical axioms. As everybody knows,
this information is of great significance for geometry; but it seems
to me to be of capital interest for physics as well, for it leads to
the following result: the fact that by adjoining terrestrial distances
to one another we can achieve the dimensions and distances of bodies
in outer space (that is, that we can measure heavenly distances with
an earthly yardstick) and the fact that the distances within an atom
can all be expressed in terms of metres&#8212;these facts are not at all a
mere logical consequence of propositions about the congruence of
triangles or about geometric configurations, but are a result of
empirical research. The validity of the Archimedean axiom in nature
stands in just as much need of confirmation by experiment as does the
familiar proposition about the sum of the angles of a triangle.</p>
<p><a href="#17" name="17">&#182;</a> In general, I should like to formulate
the axiom of continuity in physics as follows: 'If for the validity of
a proposition of physics we prescribe any degree of accuracy
whatsoever, then it is possible to indicate small regions within which
the presuppositions that have been made for the proposition may vary
freely, without the deviation of the proposition exceeding the
prescribed degree of accuracy.' This axiom basically does nothing more
than express something that already lies in the essence of experiment;
it is constantly presupposed by the physicists, although it has not
previously been formulated.</p>
<p><a href="#18" name="18">&#182;</a> For example, if one follows Planck and
derives the second law of thermodynamics from the axiom of the
impossibility of a <em>perpetuum mobile of the second sort</em>, then this
axiom of continuity must be used in the derivation.</p>
<p><a href="#19" name="19">&#182;</a> By invoking the theorem that the
continuum can be well-ordered, Hamel has shown in a most interesting
manner that, in the foundations of statics, the axiom of continuity is
necessary for the proof of the theorem concerning the <em>parallelogram
of forces</em>&#8212;at any rate, given the most obvious choice of other axioms.</p>
<p><a href="#20" name="20">&#182;</a> The axioms of classical mechanics can be
deepened if, using the axiom of continuity, one imagines continuous
motion to be decomposed into small straight-line movements caused by
discrete impulses and following one another in rapid succession. One
then applies Bertrand's maximum principle as the essential axiom of
mechanics, according to which the motion that actually occurs after
each impulse is that which maximizes the kinetic energy of the system
with respect to all motions that are compatible with the law of the
conservation of energy.</p>
<p><a href="#21" name="21">&#182;</a> The most recent ways of laying the
foundations of physics&#8212;of electrodynamics in particular&#8212;are all
theories of the continuum, and therefore raise the demand for
continuity in the most extreme fashion. But I should prefer not to
discuss them because the investigations are not yet completed.</p>
<p><a href="#22" name="22">&#182;</a> We shall now examine the second of the
two points of view mentioned above, namely, the question concerning
the <em>consistency</em> of the axioms. This question is obviously of the
greatest importance, for the presence of a contradiction in a theory
manifestly threatens the contents of the entire theory.</p>
<p><a href="#23" name="23">&#182;</a> Even for successful theories that have
long been accepted, it is difficult to know that they are internally
consistent: I remind you of the reversibility and recurrence paradox
in the kinetic theory of gases.</p>
<p><a href="#24" name="24">&#182;</a> It often happens that the internal
consistency of a theory is regarded as obvious, while in reality the
proof requires deep mathematical developments. For example, consider a
problem from the elementary theory of the <em>conduction of heat</em>&#8212;namely,
the distribution of temperatures within a homogeneous body whose
surfaces are maintained at a definite temperature that varies from
place to place: then in fact the requirement that there be an
equilibrium of temperatures involves no internal theoretical
contradiction. But to know this it is necessary to prove that the
familiar boundary-value problem of potential theory is always
solvable; for only this proof shows that a temperature distribution
satisfying the equations of the conduction of heat is at all possible.</p>
<p><a href="#25" name="25">&#182;</a> But particularly in physics it is not
sufficient that the propositions of a theory be in harmony with each
other; there remains the requirement that they not contradict the
propositions of a neighbouring field of knowledge.</p>
<p><a href="#26" name="26">&#182;</a> Thus, as I showed earlier, the axioms of
the elementary theory of radiation can be used to prove not only
<em>Kirchhoff's law</em> of emission and absorption, but also a special law
about the reflection and refraction of individual beams of light,
namely, the law: If two beams of natural light and of the same energy
each fall on the surface separating two media from different sides in
such a way that one beam after its reflection, and the other after its
passage, each have the same direction, then the beam that arises from
uniting the two is also of natural light and of the same energy. This
theorem is, as the facts show, not at all in contradiction with
optics, but can be derived as a conclusion from the electromagnetic
theory of light.</p>
<p><a href="#27" name="27">&#182;</a> As is well known, the results of the
<em>kinetic theory of gases</em> are in full harmony with thermodynamics.</p>
<p><a href="#28" name="28">&#182;</a> Similarly, <em>electrodynamic inertia</em> and
<em>Einsteinian gravitation</em> are compatible with the corresponding
concepts of the classical theories, since the classical concepts can
be conceived as limiting cases of the more general concepts in the new
theories.</p>
<p><a href="#29" name="29">&#182;</a> In contrast, <em>modern quantum theory</em> and
our developing knowledge of the internal structure of the atom have
led to laws which virtually contradict the earlier electrodynamics,
which was essentially built on the Maxwell equations; modern
electrodynamics therefore needs&#8212;as everybody acknowledges&#8212;a new
foundation and essential reformulation.</p>
<p><a href="#30" name="30">&#182;</a> As one can see from what has already
been said, the contradictions that arise in physical theories are
always eliminated by changing the selection of the axioms; the
difficulty is to make the selection so that all the observed physical
laws are logical consequences of the chosen axioms.</p>
<p><a href="#31" name="31">&#182;</a> But matters are different when
contradictions appear in purely theoretical fields of knowledge. Set
theory contains the classic example of such an occurrence, namely, in
the <em>paradox of the set of all sets</em>, which goes back to Cantor. This
paradox is so serious that distinguished mathematicians, for example,
Kronecker and Poincar&#233;, felt compelled by it to deny that set
theory&#8212;one of the most fruitful and powerful branches of knowledge
anywhere in mathematics&#8212;has any justification for existing.</p>
<p><a href="#32" name="32">&#182;</a> But in this precarious state of affairs
as well, the axiomatic method came to the rescue. By setting up
appropriate axioms which in a precise way restricted both the
arbitrariness of the definitions of sets and the admissibility of
statements about their elements, Zermelo succeeded in developing set
theory in such a way that the contradictions disappear, but the scope
and applicability of set theory remain the same.</p>
<p><a href="#33" name="33">&#182;</a> In all previous cases it was a matter of
contradictions that had emerged in the course of the development of a
theory and that needed to be eliminated by a reformulation of the
axiom system. But if we wish to restore the reputation of mathematics
as the exemplar of the most rigorous science it is not enough merely
to avoid the existing contradictions. The chief requirement of the
theory of axioms must go farther, namely, to show that within every
field of knowledge contradictions based on the underlying axiom-system
are <em>absolutely impossible</em>.</p>
<p><a href="#34" name="34">&#182;</a> In accordance with this requirement I
have proved the consistency of the axioms laid down in the <em>Grundlagen
der Geometrie</em> by showing that any contradiction in the consequences
of the geometrical axioms must necessarily apppear in the arithmetic
of the system of real numbers as well.</p>
<p><a href="#35" name="35">&#182;</a> For the fields of physical knowledge
too, it is clearly sufficient to reduce the problem of <em>internal
consistency</em> to the consistency of the arithmetical axioms. Thus I
showed the consistency of the axioms of the <em>elementary theory of
radiation</em> by constructing its axiom system out of analytically
independent pieces&#8212;presupposing in the process the consistency of
analysis.</p>
<p><a href="#36" name="36">&#182;</a> One may and should in some circumstances
proceed similarly in the construction of a mathematical theory. For
example, if in the development of the theory of Galois groups we have
taken the proposition of the <em>existence of roots</em> as an axiom, or if
in the theory of prime numbers we have taken the hypothesis concerning
the <em>reality of the zeros</em> of the Riemann &#120577;(s)-function as an axiom,
then in each case the proof of the consistency of the axiom system
comes down to a proof, using the means of analysis, of the proposition
of the existence of roots or of the Riemann hypothesis concerning
&#120577;(s)&#8212;and only then has the theory been securely completed.</p>
<p><a href="#37" name="37">&#182;</a> The problem of the consistency of the
axiom system for the <em>real numbers</em> can likewise be reduced by the use
of set-theoretic concepts to the same problem for the integers: this
is the merit of the theories of the irrational numbers developed by
Weierstrass and Dedekind.</p>
<p><a href="#38" name="38">&#182;</a> In only two cases is this method of
reduction to another special domain of knowledge clearly not
available, namely, when it is a matter of the axioms for the
<em>integers</em> themselves, and when it is a matter of the foundation of
<em>set theory</em>; for here there is no other discipline besides logic
which it would be possi-ble to invoke.</p>
<p><a href="#39" name="39">&#182;</a> But since the examination of consistency
is a task that cannot be avoided, it appears necessary to axiomatize
logic itself and to prove that number theory and set theory are only
parts of logic.</p>
<p><a href="#40" name="40">&#182;</a> This method was prepared long ago (not
least by Frege's profound investigations); it has been most
successfully explained by the acute mathematician and logician
Russell. One could regard the completion of this magnificent
Russellian enterprise of the <em>axiomatization of logic</em> as the crowning
achievement of the work of axiomatization as a whole.</p>
<p><a href="#41" name="41">&#182;</a> But this completion will require further
work. When we consider the matter more closely we soon recognize that
the question of the consistency of the integers and of sets is not one
that stands alone, but that it belongs to a vast domain of difficult
epistemological questions which have a specifically mathematical tint:
for example (to characterize this domain of questions briefly) the
problem of the <em>solvability in principle of every mathematical
question</em>, the problem of the subsequent <em>checkability</em> of the results
of a mathematical investigation, the question of a <em>criterion of
simplicity</em> for mathematical proofs, the question of the relationship
between <em>content and formalism</em> in mathematics and logic, and finally
the problem of the <em>decidability</em> of a mathematical question in a
finite number of operations.</p>
<p><a href="#42" name="42">&#182;</a> We cannot rest content with the
axiomatization of logic until all questions of this sort and their
interconnections have been understood and cleared up.</p>
<p><a href="#43" name="43">&#182;</a> Among the mentioned questions, the
last&#8212;namely, the one concerning decidability in a finite number of
operations&#8212;is the best-known and the most discussed; for it goes to
the essence of mathematical thought.</p>
<p><a href="#44" name="44">&#182;</a> I should like to increase the interest
in this question by indicating several particular mathematical
problems in which it plays a role.</p>
<p><a href="#45" name="45">&#182;</a> In the theory of <em>algebraic invariants</em>
we have the fundamental theorem that there is always a finite number
of whole rational invariants by means of which all other such
invariants can be represented. In my opinion, my first general proof
of this theorem completely satisfied our requirements of simplicity
and perspicuity; but it is impossible to reformulate this proof so
that we can obtain from it a statable bound for the number of the
finitely many invariants of the full system, let alone obtain an
actual listing of them. Instead, new principles and considerations of
a completely different sort were necessary in order to show that the
construction of the full system of invariants requires only a finite
number of operations, and that this number is less than a bound that
can be stated before the calculation.</p>
<p><a href="#46" name="46">&#182;</a> We see the same thing happening in an
example from the <em>theory of surfaces</em>. It is a fundamental question in
the geometry of surfaces of the fourth order to determine the maximum
number of separate sheets it takes to make up such a surface.</p>
<p><a href="#47" name="47">&#182;</a> The first step towards an answer to this
question is the proof that the number of sheets of a curved surface
must be finite. This can easily be shown function-theoretically as
follows. One assumes the existence of infinitely many sheets, and
selects a point inside each spatial region bounded by a sheet. A point
of accumulation for these infinitely many chosen points would then be
a point of a singularity that is excluded for an algebraic surface.</p>
<p><a href="#48" name="48">&#182;</a> This function-theoretic path does not at
all lead to an upper bound for the number of surface-sheets. For that,
we need instead certain observations on the number of cut-points,
which then show that the number of sheets certainly cannot be greater
than 12.</p>
<p><a href="#49" name="49">&#182;</a> The second method, entirely different
from the first, in turn cannot be applied or transformed to decide
whether a surface of the fourth order with twelve sheets actually
exists.</p>
<p><a href="#50" name="50">&#182;</a> Since a quaternary form of the fourth
order possesses 35 homogeneous coefficients, we can conceive of a
given surface of the fourth order as a point in 34-dimensional space.
The discriminant of the quaternary form of fourth order is of degree
108 in its coefficients; if it is set equal to zero, it accordingly
represents in 34-dimensional space a surface of order 108. Since the
coefficients of the discriminant are themselves determinate integers,
the topological character of the discriminant surface can be precisely
determined by the rules that are familiar to us from 2- and
3-dimensional space; so we can obtain precise information about the
nature and significance of the individual subdomains into which the
discriminant surface partitions the 34-dimensional space. Now, the
surfaces of fourth order represented by points of these subdomains all
certainly possess the same sheet-number; and it is accordingly
possible to establish, by a long and wearying but finite calculation,
whether we have a surface of fourth order with n &#8804; 12 sheets or not.</p>
<p><a href="#51" name="51">&#182;</a> The geometric method just described is
thus a third way of treating our question about the maximum number of
sheets of a surface of the fourth order. It proves the decidability of
this question in a finite number of opera-tions. So in principle an
important demand of our problem has been satisfied: it has been
reduced to a problem of the level of difficulty of determining the \(
10^{(10^{10})} \)th numeral in the decimal expansion for &#120587;&#8212;a task
which is clearly solvable, but which remains unsolved.</p>
<p><a href="#52" name="52">&#182;</a> Rather, it took a profound and difficult
algebraic-geometric investigation by Rohn to show that 11 sheets are
not possible in a surface of the fourth order, while 10 sheets
actually occur. Only this fourth method delivered the full solution of
the problem.</p>
<p><a href="#53" name="53">&#182;</a> These particular discussions show how a
variety of methods of proof can be applied to the same problem, and
they ought to suggest how necessary it is to study the essence of
mathematical proof itself if one wishes to answer such questions as
the one about decidability in a finite number of operations.</p>
<p><a href="#54" name="54">&#182;</a> All such questions of principle, which I
characterized above and of which the question just discussed&#8212;that is,
the question about decidability in a finite number of operations&#8212;was
only the last, seem to me to form an important new field of research
which remains to be developed. To conquer this field we must, I am
persuaded, make the concept of specifically mathematical proof itself
into an object of investigation, just as the astronomer considers the
movement of his position, the physicist studies the theory of his
apparatus, and the philosopher criticizes reason itself.</p>
<p><a href="#55" name="55">&#182;</a> To be sure, the execution of this
programme is at present still an unsolved task.</p>
<p><a href="#56" name="56">&#182;</a> In conclusion, I should like to sum up
in a few sentences my general conception of the essence of the
axiomatic method. I believe: anything at all that can be the object of
scientific thought becomes dependent on the axiomatic method, and
thereby indirectly on mathematics, as soon as it is ripe for the
for-mation of a theory. By pushing ahead to ever deeper layers of
axioms in the sense explained above we also win ever-deeper insights
into the essence of scien-tific thought itself, and we become ever
more conscious of the unity of our knowledge. In the sign of the
axiomatic method, mathematics is summoned to a leading role in
science.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="#from" name="from">From</a> Ewald's introduction to the
above, in <em>From Kant to Hilbert</em>, volume 2:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Hilbert is persistently misconstrued as a 'formalist', i.e. as
somebody who was so shaken by the paradoxes that he took up the
theory that mathematics is merely a game played with meaningless
symbols. But the intellectual background to Hilbert's proof theory
was richer than this. To be sure, the paradoxes were an important
goad; but he had more positive ambitions than the mere avoidance of
paradox. (Hilbert, in fact, in his unpublished G&#246;ttingen lectures,
repeatedly indicated that in his opinion Zermelo's work had
successfully resolved the known paradoxes.) His study of the
axiomatic foundations of geometry had yielded a rich harvest of
mathematical results&#8212;non-Archimedean geometries, a new topological
characterization of the plane, new theorems on the nature of
continuity&#8212;and there was every reason to hope that the same powerful
tool would prove equally useful in the other branches of mathematics
and physics mentioned in this article.</p>
<p>"As for the term 'formalist', it is so misleading that it should be
abandoned altogether as a label for Hilbert's philosophy of
mathematics. On the face of it, 'formalism' is not a felicitous
description for the style of reasoning one finds in <em>Anschauliche
Geometrie&#8211;'Intuitive geometry' (Hilbert and Cohn-Vossen 1932)</em>, a
work which was written at the high-point of Hilbert's work in proof
theory; nor does it accurately convey the convictions of the man
who, in his G&#246;ttingen lectures, derided those who saw mathematics as
a mere heaping-up of consequences mechanically derived from a given
stock of axioms; nor the man who ended his essay, 'On the infinite',
by saying, 'We gain a conviction that runs counter to the earlier
endeavours of Frege and Dedekind, the conviction that, if scientific
knowledge is to be possible, certain intuitive conceptions
[Vorstellungen] and insights are indispensable; logic alone does not
suffice' (<em>Hilbert 1926</em>). As the present selection makes clear,
Hilbert viewed formal axiom systems instrumentally, as a powerful
tool for mathematical research, a tool to be employed when a field
had reached a point of sufficient ripeness. But he nowhere suggests
that the whole of mathematics can simply be <em>identified</em> with the
study of formal systems; and indeed in his proof-theoretical
writings he took considerable pains to point out that the genuine
mathematics&#8211;<em>inhaltliche Mathematik</em>&#8211;takes place, not in the
formalism, but in the meta-language. For all these reasons, Hilbert
himself rejected the label 'formalist' (see, for example, <em>Hilbert
1931a</em>, &#167;35), and students of his thought would do well to follow
his example."</p>
</blockquote>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200923-axiomatic_thinking_hilbert_1918/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200923-axiomatic_thinking_hilbert_1918/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Book of Why, by Pearl and Mackenzie</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>In <a href="http://bayes.cs.ucla.edu/WHY/">The Book of Why</a>, Judea Pearl explains that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judea_Pearl">Judea Pearl</a>'s
work is very important and most statisticians are malicious, fools, or
both. The attempt to popularize his work fails to usefully communicate
his contributions. You're better off reading his <a href="https://ftp.cs.ucla.edu/pub/stat_ser/r481.pdf">Seven Tools</a>
paper, which in six pages is more complete than and as instructive as
the book.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#useful">Possibly useful ideas</a></li>
<li><a href="#no_causality">Sidestepping causality</a></li>
<li><a href="#no_ai">Wishful AI</a></li>
<li><a href="#impediments">Difficulties in reading</a></li>
<li><a href="#quotes">Selected quotes</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3><a name="useful"></a>Possibly useful ideas</h3>
<p>The book is about how to answer questions based on data, which is a
topic I'm very interested in. I tried to <a href="/20200912-what_should_be_in_your_regression/">summarize</a> some of the
simplest ideas conveyed, about what variables to control for when
estimating an effect. The book isn't a textbook, but I wish it had
better explained how to implement more sophisticated control
techniques.</p>
<p>Pearl references a <a href="https://scholar.harvard.edu/files/aglynn/files/glynnkashin-frontdoor.pdf">paper</a> whose authors used paired observational
and experimental data, finding that "front-door adjustment" with the
observational data gives a result like that from the experimental
data. That's compelling! How can I use that adjustment?</p>
<p>I also liked the material (starting pages 200 and 309) on
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simpson%27s_paradox">Simpson's Paradox</a>.</p>
<p>To be clear, I think the book is trying to offer some useful ideas. I
wish it were more successful in conveying them.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="no_causality"></a>Sidestepping causality</h3>
<p>You might think this book is about determining whether something
causes something else, based on data. It is <a href="#hill_guidelines">not</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"... causal questions can never be answered from data alone." (page
351)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Despite Pearl's finality, there is research on doing just this. It
goes by <a href="https://paperswithcode.com/task/causal-discovery">causal discovery</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exploratory_causal_analysis">exploratory causal analysis</a>. In
<a href="http://www.chalearn.org/challenges.html">experiments</a>, some machine learning <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/guyon_isabelle_causality_challenge_final_short_r02.pdf">methods</a> do much better than
chance in identifying known causal relationships. Pearl even advised a
<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1301.2312">related paper</a>. I agree there are epistemological uncertainties in
this field, but it's interesting!</p>
<p>The closest the book comes to model identification are some allusions
to independence tests that can indicate data isn't consistent with a
model (or "Fit Indices" in <a href="https://ftp.cs.ucla.edu/pub/stat_ser/r481.pdf">Seven Tools</a>). Pearl's causal models
come from the outside knowledge of humans.</p>
<p>The book also doesn't have much to say on the philosophy of causation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"... I have not attempted to define causation anywhere in this book
..." (page 48)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That isn't quite true, because he does eventually discuss
counterfactual definitions of causality. But for the most part,
causation is given an axiomatic existence and becomes a silent arrow.
<a href="https://youtu.be/36GT2zI8lVA">Feynman</a> is more fun.</p>
<p>The arrows aren't necessarily bad, but the book is so
<a href="#impediments">busy</a> begging for unrelated praise that we don't get a
clear picture of what they're good for.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="no_ai"></a>Wishful AI</h3>
<p>Distinctions between statistics, machine learning, and AI can be
murky, but this book has a mostly statistical flavor. Given a causal
model and data, it's possible to estimate (learn) parameters and make
predictions.</p>
<p>As <a href="#no_causality">above</a>, there's no developed mechanism to learn
what the causal graph should be. Systems like
<a href="https://automaticstatistician.com/">The Automatic Statistician</a> do more to discover relationships in
data. Pearl's methods require a human to provide a causal graph.</p>
<p>I quite agree with Pearl that current AI seems too <a href="/20170429-from_behaviorist_to_constructivist_ai/">behaviorist</a>.
Mental models seem important to intelligence. His approach of defining
a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symbolic_artificial_intelligence">symbolic</a> solution to a class of problems he likes is not a
compelling solution.</p>
<p>Like the proposal of Gary Marcus in The Algebraic Mind, Pearl
<a href="#brain">offers</a> that the symbolic system of his design "must be close
to the way that our brains represent" things (page 269). This is not
clear to me.</p>
<p>I agree that more advanced AI should be able to understand causality.
I'm not sure Pearl's explicit methods will play a part. I further
disagree with him on how <a href="#conversation">communication</a> works, and the
<a href="#chinese_room">Chinese Room</a>.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="impediments"></a>Difficulties in reading</h3>
<p>I have to imagine that Pearl is likable in person, but his style here
reads as extreme self-praise and even putting down others to seem
better by comparison. Knowing him only through this book, it's hard to
root for him.</p>
<p>He tilts at straw men, writing as if <a href="https://stats.stackexchange.com/questions/376920/the-book-of-why-by-judea-pearl-why-is-he-bashing-statistics">statisticians</a> and economists
have never thought about causality without his guidance. But
researchers have <a href="https://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/Digitization/141324NCJRS.pdf">not</a> been afraid to say things are "most likely a
cause, not just a correlate" even without his work.</p>
<p>To make his work seem more novel, he keeps it at a distance from
<a href="#coefficients">familiar</a> topics, even when only the interpretation is
different, preventing readers from easily connecting with prior
knowledge.</p>
<p>He writes as if he could have more quickly shown a connection between
smoking and lung cancer, but does not support this with evidence or
example of a feasible mechanism. You might disagree with Tufte about
whether data visualization could have prevented the Challenger
disaster, but at least Tufte <a href="https://blogs.stockton.edu/hist4690/files/2012/06/Edward-Tufte-Visual-and-Statistical-Thinking.pdf">shows</a> you the visualization.</p>
<p>In <a href="#interaction1">multiple</a> <a href="#interaction2">places</a>, Pearl says
linear models don't support interactions. There must be an
interpretation of this that is true, but I don't know what it is.
Interactions are commonly modeled with linear models.</p>
<p>I had hoped that with some effort I'd be able to follow the example on
page 83, but as far as I can tell it is incomplete or incorrect. (I
emailed the authors asking for clarification and will update as
appropriate.)</p>
<p>Andrew Gelman's <a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2019/01/08/book-pearl-mackenzie/">notes</a> mention some issues with the book. (And some
others are even more <a href="#asylum">glaring</a>.) But also: Sherlock Holmes is
not known for deduction or induction, but for abduction (page 93).
It's not clear why we should change multiple variables on page 279,
but freeze them on page 312.</p>
<p>This book could have been so much better.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="quotes"></a>Selected quotes</h3>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... statistics focused exclusively on how to summarize data, not on
how to interpret it." (page 6)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Another advantage causal models have that data mining and deep
learning lack is adaptability." (page 17)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In his book <em>Sapiens</em>, historial Yuval Harari posits that our
ancestors' capacity to imagine nonexistent things was the key to
everything, for it allowed them to communicate better." (page 25)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The difference is profound and lies in the absence of a model of
reality." (page 30)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a name="chinese_room"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Searle's [Chinese Room] challenge has only one flaw: cheating
[meaning having a working Chinese Room] is not easy; in fact, it is
impossible." (page 38)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Instead of predicting whether a prisoner is alive or dead, we might
want to predict how much the unemployment rate will go up if we
raise the minimum wage." (page 43)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"a philosophical school called positivism, which holds that the
universe is a product of human thought and that science is only a
description of those thoughts." (page 67)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is at best a tortured interpretation of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Positivism">positivism</a>. Wikipedia
says: "Positivism asserts that all authentic knowledge allows
verification and that all authentic knowledge assumes that the only
valid knowledge is scientific."</p>
<hr>
<p><a name="hill_guidelines"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Two people who believe in two different causal diagrams can analyze
the same data and may never come to the same conclusion, regardless
of how &#8220;big&#8221; the data are." (page 90)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's hard to see how this is an improvement over the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bradford_Hill_criteria">Hill guidelines</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Generally [sensitivity] is the same for all types of patients,
because it depends only on the technical capability of the testing
instrument to detect the abnormalities associated with the disease."
(page 104)</p>
<p>"... the sensitivity of mammograms for forty-year-old women is 73
percent." (page 105)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a name="asylum"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"(Applicants for asylum must prove that they have fifteen family
members in the Netherlands.)" (page 122)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://skeptics.stackexchange.com/questions/45502/applicants-for-asylum-must-prove-that-they-have-fifteen-family-members-in-the-n?newreg=cbb6f3f1487f4560bcb4db567af373d2">This is not true.</a> There is an update in the <a href="http://bayes.cs.ucla.edu/WHY/errata-pages-PearlMackenzie_BookofWhy_Final.pdf">errata</a>, but it's still surprising it made it to print.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... if you have identified a sufficient set of deconfounders in
your diagram, gathered data on them, and properly adjusted for them,
then you have every right to say that you have computed the causal
effect <em>X</em> &#10132; <em>Y</em> (provided, of course, that you can defend your
causal diagram on scientific grounds)." (page 139)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Statisticians have devised ingenius methods for handling this
&#8220;curse of dimensionality&#8221; problem. Most involve some sort of
extrapolation, whereby a smooth function is fitted to the data and
used to fill in the holes created by the empty strata." (page 221)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a name="coefficients"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Regression coefficients, whether adjusted or not, are only
statistical trends, conveying no causal information in themselves.
\( r_{YX.Z} \) represents the causal effect of <em>X</em> on <em>Y</em>, whereas
\( r_{YX} \) does not, exclusively because we have a diagram
showing <em>Z</em> as a confounder of <em>X</em> and <em>Y</em>." (page 223)</p>
<p>"Path coefficients are fundamentally different from regression
coefficients, although they can often be computed from the latter."
(page 223)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"If I were less modest, I would close here with Isaac Newton's
famous saying about &#8220;standing on the shoulders of giants.&#8221;" (page
244)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is at the close of a section about the work his students have
done. The generous interpretation is that he isn't saying that he's
the giant.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As argued in Chapter 1, our ability to conceive of alternative,
nonexistent worlds separated us from our protohuman ancestors and
indeed from any other creature on the planet." (page 260)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a name="brain"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Could structural models, in some shape or form, be the actual
shortcut that we use [in our physical brains]? I think it is very
likely, for two reasons. First, structural causal models are a
shortcut that works, and there aren't any competitors around with
that miraculous property. Second, they were modeled on Bayesian
networks, which in turn were modeled on David Rumelhart's
description of message passing in the brain." (page 268)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Causal diagrams, with their simple rules of following and erasing
arrows, must be close to the way that our brains represent
counterfactuals." (page 269)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a name="interaction1"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"[Linear models] also cannot represent interactions between
variables." (page 286)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Provided the assumptions of no confounding and no protection hold,
the rung-one metric of FAR [Fraction of Attributable Risk] is
promoted to rung three, where it becomes <em>PN</em>
[Probability of Necessity]." (page 292)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Using her data and path analysis, she computed the direct effect of
parental IQ on children's IQ and found that only 35 percent, or
about one-third, of IQ variation is inherited. In other words,
parents with an IQ fifteen points above average would typically have
children five points above average." (page 306)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a name="interaction2"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"... linear models do not allow interactions ..." (page 322)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This was one of the three greatest blunders of my career." (page
331)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I didn't notice if the other two were mentioned.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The questions I have just asked are all causal, and causal
questions can never be answered from data alone." (page 351)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I wish I could present the reader with successful case studies of a
complex transportability task and recovery from selection bias, but
the techniques are still too new to have penetrated into general
usage." (page 357)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a name="conversation"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"If our robots will all be as opaque as AlphaGo, we will not be able
to hold a meaningful conversation with them, and that would be quite
unfortunate." (page 361)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I think that understanding the benefits of the illusion of free
will is the key to the stubbornly enigmatic problem of reconciling
it with determinism." (page 364)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="book_of_why.jpg"></p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200917-book_of_why/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200917-book_of_why/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>What should be in your regression?</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>If you're fitting a model in the hopes of better understanding the
effect of <em>x</em> on <em>y</em>, then including another predictor variable <em>z</em>
could be necessary, or could be harmful. Deciding whether to control
for <em>z</em> depends on identifying how the variables are causally related.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#direct">Simple direct causation</a></li>
<li><a href="#mediated">Mediated causation</a>: don't control for <em>z</em></li>
<li><a href="#common_cause">Common cause (confounding)</a>: control for <em>z</em></li>
<li><a href="#common_effect">Common effect (collider)</a>: don't control for <em>z</em></li>
<li><a href="#complicated">More complicated cases</a></li>
</ul>
<p>These examples vary the data generating process (which isn't possible
in practice) in order to illustrate what happens in each case when you
do or don't control for <em>z</em>.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.r-project.org/about.html">R</a> code uses random <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Normal_distribution">normal</a> data, additive relationships,
and linear regression. With real data and processes, other modeling
methods may be more appropriate.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="direct"></a>Simple direct causation</h3>
<p><img alt="x -&gt; y" src="direct.png"></p>
<p>Say the reality is that <em>x</em> influences <em>y</em> (not the reverse) and no
other variables are involved.</p>
<!-- set.seed(99) -->

<pre><code class="language-r">x = rnorm(100)
y = x + rnorm(100)
summary(lm(y ~ x))
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  x            1.07747    0.11931   9.031 1.53e-14 ***</code></pre>

<p>The estimate of 1.077 is close to the true value of 1. The very low
p-value (with three stars) indicates confidence that there is a
non-random relationship between <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="mediated"></a>Mediated causation</h3>
<p><img alt="x -&gt; z -&gt; y" src="mediated.png"></p>
<p>Here, the reality is that <em>x</em> influences <em>z</em>, which then influences
<em>y</em>.</p>
<p>In this case, <em>x</em> really does influence <em>y</em>, so you're right to look
for the relationship. And it might be tempting to control for <em>z</em>,
perhaps because of a desire to &#8220;isolate&#8221; the effect of <em>x</em>.</p>
<p>If you include <em>z</em> in your regression, the desired estimate of the
effect of <em>x</em> will disappear.</p>
<!-- set.seed(101) -->

<pre><code class="language-r">x = rnorm(100)
z = x + rnorm(100)
y = z + rnorm(100)
summary(lm(y ~ x + z))
##               Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  x           -0.146874   0.135695  -1.082    0.282
##  z            1.127586   0.087819  12.840   &lt;2e-16 ***</code></pre>

<p>Including <em>z</em> makes it appear that <em>x</em> has no significant influence on
<em>y</em>, which is incorrect.</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">summary(lm(y ~ x))
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  x            1.11140    0.15343   7.244    1e-10 ***</code></pre>

<p>Leaving <em>z</em> out gives a good estimate of the effect of <em>x</em>.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="common_cause"></a>Common cause (confounding)</h3>
<p><img alt="x &lt;- z -&gt; y" src="common_cause.png"></p>
<p>In this case, the reality is that <em>z</em> influences both <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>,
which are otherwise unrelated.</p>
<p>This is an extreme example, in the sense that you'd be totally wrong
to look for an effect of <em>x</em> on <em>y</em> in this case. The case where
there's also a direct connection between <em>x</em> and <em>y</em> is similar, but
for simplicity this example doesn't have one.</p>
<p>If you don't include <em>z</em> in your regression, the relationship between
<em>x</em> and <em>y</em> could be misleading.</p>
<!-- set.seed(103) -->

<pre><code class="language-r">z = rnorm(100)
x = z + rnorm(100)
y = z + rnorm(100)
summary(lm(y ~ x))
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  x            0.56257    0.10365   5.428 4.14e-07 ***</code></pre>

<p>There is a relationship between <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>, but it's because of <em>z</em>,
not because of <em>x</em>. The regression result ignoring <em>z</em> could easily be
misinterpreted.</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">summary(lm(y ~ x + z))
##             Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
## x            0.03608    0.10590   0.341    0.734
## z            1.05814    0.13556   7.806 6.93e-12 ***</code></pre>

<p>With <em>z</em> in the model, the result correctly indicates that <em>z</em> is the
influencing factor.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="common_effect"></a>Common effect (collider)</h3>
<p><img alt="x -&gt; z &lt;- y" src="collider.png"></p>
<p>Here, the reality is that <em>x</em> and <em>y</em> are completely unrelated, but
they both influence <em>z</em>.</p>
<p>As with <a href="#common_cause">common cause</a>, it's more interesting when
there's also a direct connection between <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>, but the behavior
is similar and this example keeps things simpler.</p>
<p>Somewhat surprisingly, if you include <em>z</em> in your regression, you'll
see evidence that both <em>z</em> and <em>x</em> influence <em>y</em>.</p>
<!-- set.seed(105) -->

<pre><code class="language-r">x = rnorm(100)
y = rnorm(100)
z = x + y + rnorm(100)
summary(lm(y ~ x + z))
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  x           -0.46951    0.08831  -5.317 6.76e-07 ***
##  z            0.44439    0.04971   8.939 2.62e-14 ***</code></pre>

<p>This is a case of &#8220;<a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/3192123_Explaining_explaining_away%27">explaining away</a>.&#8221;</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">summary(lm(y ~ x))
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  x           -0.11308    0.10586  -1.068    0.288</code></pre>

<p>Without <em>z</em> in the regression, the result correctly indicates no
relationship between <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="complicated"></a>More complicated cases</h3>
<p>With a more complex causal graph, it may not be obvious what you need
to control for, or it may be that conventional methods of control
aren't sufficient. Methods like Judea Pearl's do-calculus might be
helpful.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thanks to Erica Blom, Ben Klemens, and Jonathan Robinson for providing
helpful feedback.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200912-what_should_be_in_your_regression/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200912-what_should_be_in_your_regression/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>GPU environment variables</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><code>CUDA_DEVICE_ORDER</code> can default to <code>FASTEST_FIRST</code>, which may not
match the order you see in <code>nvidia-smi</code> output. Use
<code>CUDA_DEVICE_ORDER=PCI_BUS_ID</code>.</p>
<p>Set <code>CUDA_VISIBLE_DEVICES=2</code> to only run on GPU 2. That GPU will then
be accessed as GPU 0, not GPU 2.</p>
<p>When using TensorFlow, you <a href="https://www.tensorflow.org/guide/gpu#limiting_gpu_memory_growth">can</a> set
<code>TF_FORCE_GPU_ALLOW_GROWTH=true</code> to keep TF from preemptively claiming
all the GPU memory. However, in my tests (with the older version 1.14)
TF still allocates way more memory than it really needs, so this
setting doesn't help much in practice.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200910-gpu_environment_variables/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200910-gpu_environment_variables/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>A Mathematician's Lament, by Lockhart</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://www.maa.org/external_archive/devlin/LockhartsLament.pdf">Lockhart&#8217;s Lament</a> (and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Mathematician%27s_Lament">Exultation</a>!) is <a href="https://smile.amazon.com/Mathematicians-Lament-School-Fascinating-Imaginative/dp/1934137170/">available</a> as a
beautiful little book. It&#8217;s in the familiar territory of balancing
doing original things versus learning what others have done, but he&#8217;s
probably right that many people don&#8217;t really know what <em>doing</em> math
is. I particularly identify with his emphasis on understanding and
good explanations.</p>
<p>Lockhart&#8217;s recommendation to do math for the pleasure of it reminds me
of McCullough&#8217;s similar thought on history:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"It should be taught for pleasure: The pleasure of history, like art
or music or literature, consists of an expansion of the experience
of being alive, which is what education is largely about."
(<a href="https://imprimis.hillsdale.edu/knowing-history-and-knowing-who-we-are/">McCullough</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is important to remember: People don&#8217;t really do things they
don&#8217;t enjoy. Pleasure can be found in most things, but it can be more
or less difficult to find. Finding it is important.</p>
<p>Lockhart correctly identifies the epistemology of math, in my opinion.
He points out that most people don&#8217;t need or use the math that&#8217;s
currently taught in schools, so losing it wouldn't be a great loss.
Carpenters don&#8217;t use trigonometry. Have you ever used the quadratic
formula?</p>
<p>I&#8217;m not sure Lockhart wrote to change anyone&#8217;s mind, and he doesn&#8217;t
include many approachable recommendations. On page 82 he says, "There
should be no standards, and no curriculum." He recommends <a href="https://www.usgo.org/news/2016/07/paul-lockhart-named-teacher-of-the-year/">games</a>,
which is something, at least. He also teaches at a K-12 school where
students interview for a chance to pay $50k <a href="https://saintannsny.org/divisions-and-offices/finance/parents/tuition-financial-aid/tuition/">tuition</a>. I like his
ideas, but is there an accessible implementation?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"By concentrating on <em>what</em>, and leaving out <em>why</em>, mathematics is
reduced to an empty shell. The art is not in the &#8220;truth&#8221; but in the
explanation, the argument. It is the argument itself that gives the
truth its context, and determines what is really being said and
meant. Mathematics is <em>the art of explanation</em>." (page 29)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Mental acuity of any kind comes from solving problems yourself, not
from being told how to solve them." (pages 53-54)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"[Accepting the standard math curriculum as being synonymous with math itself]
is intimately connected to what I call the &#8220;ladder myth&#8221;&#8212;the idea
that mathematics can be arranged as a sequence of &#8220;subjects&#8221; each
being in some way more advanced, or &#8220;higher,&#8221; than the previous. The
effect is to make school mathematics into a race&#8212;some students are
&#8220;ahead&#8221; of others, and parents worry that their child is &#8220;falling
behind.&#8221;" (page 56)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"High school students must learn to use the secant function, &#8216;sec
<em>x</em>,&#8217; as an abbreviation for the reciprocal of the cosine function,
&#8216;1 / cos <em>x</em>,&#8217; a definition with as much intellectual weight as the
decision to use &#8216;&amp;&#8217; in place of &#8220;and.&#8221; That this particular
shorthand, a holdover from fifteenth-century nautical tables, is
still with us (whereas others, such as &#8220;versine,&#8221; have died out) is
mere historical accident, and is of utterly no value in an era when
rapid and precise shipboard computation is no longer an issue. Thus
we clutter our math classes with pointless nomenclature for its own
sake." (pages 58-59)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Mathematics is about problems, and problems must be made the focus
of a student&#8217;s mathematical life." (pages 60-61)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I was made to learn by heart: &#8220;The square of the sum of two numbers
is equal to the sum of their squares increased by twice their
product.&#8221; I had not the vaguest idea what this meant and when I
could not remember the words, my tutor threw the book at my head,
which did not stimulate my intellect in any way." (quoting Bertrand
Russell, pages 61-62)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There should be no standards, and no curriculum." (page 82)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Ultimately you have to face the fact that people are different, and
that&#8217;s just fine." (page 82)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="A_Mathematician's_Lament.png"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200909-mathematicians_lament_by_lockhart/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200909-mathematicians_lament_by_lockhart/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Share a tmux session</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Multiple people can connect to the same <a href="https://github.com/tmux/tmux/wiki">tmux</a> session, with all
participants able to control the session. Combined with a voice
connection (phone, etc.) this can be used for remote pair programming
in an editor like <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/">Emacs</a>, for example.</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash"># originating:
tmux -S /tmp/party_socket new -s party_session
chgrp shared_group /tmp/party_socket
# joining:
tmux -S /tmp/party_socket attach -t party_session</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>All participants need to be logged in to the same machine, likely
using <a href="https://www.ssh.com/ssh/">ssh</a>. If everyone's logged in as the same user, you're
already done: just make a session and have everyone join it. If people
have separate user accounts, you need to think about sockets.</p>
<p>tmux uses a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix_domain_socket">socket</a> for communication. Joining will require access
to that socket.</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">tmux -S /tmp/party_socket new -s party_session</code></pre>

<p>That line names the socket and the session explicitly, which is
convenient. In an existing tmux session, you can find your current
socket with "<code>echo $TMUX</code>", and you can check your session name with
"<code>tmux display-message -p '#S'</code>".</p>
<p>Let's grant access at the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Group_identifier">group</a> level, assuming everyone is in a
group called <code>shared_group</code>. You can check using <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/coreutils/manual/html_node/groups-invocation.html#groups-invocation">groups</a> and use an
existing shared group (<code>user</code> is common) which is convenient but will
allow anyone in that group to join. Or you could create a new group
for the purpose and add only the intended participants.</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">chgrp shared_group /tmp/party_socket</code></pre>

<p>Now the group has access to the socket, and can join the tmux session.</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">tmux -S /tmp/party_socket attach -t party_session</code></pre>

<p>If people don't need to control the session, they can add "<code>-r</code>" to
that line to join read-only.</p>
<p>This is a simple way to check who's connected to the session:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">ps -eo user:16,cmd | grep party_session</code></pre>

<p>That could be made fancier (as in <a href="https://github.com/zolrath/wemux">wemux</a>, for example) but should
generally do the job.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://www.howtoforge.com/sharing-terminal-sessions-with-tmux-and-screen">HowtoForge</a>, from which I adapted the core of this.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200902-share_a_tmux_session/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200902-share_a_tmux_session/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>e: The Story of a Number (and more)</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eli_Maor">Eli Maor</a> gives a great <a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/paperback/9780691168487/e-the-story-of-a-number">history</a> of <a href="https://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/E_(mathematical_constant)"><em>e</em></a>, full of
personalities and math concepts that I found very enjoyable. I was
reminded of the difference between historical development and modern
understanding, which led me to revisit
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Where_Mathematics_Comes_From">Where Mathematics Comes From</a>, which has in its part VI perhaps a
better presentation of the latter way of knowing about <em>e</em>.</p>
<p>The historical perspective reminds me that math didn't start as formal
as it is now. Like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas_Bourbaki">Bourbaki</a> leading to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Math">New Math</a>, modern
formalism may not be the best way to teach concepts. Being able to
prove something and understanding it are not the same thing. I'm not
sure I agree completely with the idea of what math is in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Where_Mathematics_Comes_From">WMCF</a>, but
I do agree that humans do better when they understand things as
something more than just a game of symbol manipulation. In a similar
spirit to the <a href="https://tauday.com/tau-manifesto">tau movement</a>, I think mathematical notation, proof,
and especially education should focus on communicating <em>meaning</em>.</p>
<p>More broadly, I think there ought to be <a href="https://fs.blog/2012/04/feynman-technique/">Feynman explanations</a> for
more topics.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#is_e_so_natural">Is <em>e</em> so "natural?"</a></li>
<li><a href="#a_quick_trip">A quick trip to \( e^{\pi i} -1 = 0\)</a></li>
<li><a href="#a_few_quotes">A few quotes from <em>e</em>: The Story of a Number</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3><a name="is_e_so_natural"></a>Is <em>e</em> so "natural?"</h3>
<p>I think <em>e</em> is not always the best choice of base, despite being the
"natural" log base. The advantages of <em>e</em> are largely to do with
calculus, and may not help in a particular application.</p>
<p>In the math for radioactive decay, often <em>e</em> is used even though
things are mostly otherwise in terms of half-life. This <a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/science/physics/quantum-physics/in-in-nuclei/v/exponential-decay-formula-proof-can-skip-involves-calculus">introduces</a>
complexity that just isn't necessary. It would be more convenient to
use 1/2 as the base. (I wonder whether <em>e</em> is used just because that's
the button people have on their calculators.)</p>
<p>In finance, interest is usually based on some finite period, like 1/12
of a year in the case of my savings account and mortgage. I did find,
<a href="https://twitter.com/planarrowspace/status/1293999229363458051">with help</a>, <a href="https://www.myfreeholdbank.com/savings.aspx">one bank</a> that compounds continuously for some
products. But usually \( e^x \) will be an approximation, not what
is really going on, for finance.</p>
<p>When scaling data with a log, changing the base is the same as
multiplying the scaled data by some constant. Especially if you're
already going to normalize that data (with a z-score, for example) or
use scale invariant techniques on the transformed data, it doesn't
matter what log base you use.</p>
<p>For <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Softmax_function">softmax</a>, we do care about the derivative, but not really about
whether it's <em>exactly</em> equal to the function's value. When training a
neural net, the constant factor is "neutralized" by the constant
factor we introduce in the learning rate. At inference, using a
different base is the same thing as changing the softmax temperature,
which people already do for various reasons.</p>
<p>The number \( e \) is very cool, no doubt, but that doesn't mean it
has to be used for every application.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="a_quick_trip"></a>A quick trip to \( e^{\pi i} -1 = 0\)</h3>
<p>What function is always equal to its own derivative?</p>
<p>\[ f(x) = f'(x) \tag{1} \]</p>
<p>The constant function \( f(x) = 0 \) has that property, but is dull,
so leave it out.</p>
<p>The function can't ever touch the x-axis: the closer it gets, the
slower it approaches.</p>
<!-- Then the function can't ever touch the x-axis, because of
something like Zeno's paradox." -->

<p>The function can't be moved up or down, because that would break
equality with its derivative. It can be moved left or right, and it
can be flipped over the x-axis, so to pick a unique function, set the
y-intercept to be 1.</p>
<p>\[ f(0) = 1 \tag{2} \]</p>
<p>Equations (1) and (2) are enough to write out the function as a
polynomial.</p>
<p>Equation (2) says the constant term is 1. Equation (1) says the
polynomial must include a term whose derivative is 1, so the linear
term is \( \int{1} = x \). By the same reasoning, the next term is
\( \int{x} = \frac{1}{2} x^2 \), and the next is \( \frac{1}{3}
\cdot \frac{1}{2} x^3 \), and so on. This gives equation (3).</p>
<p>\[ f(x) =
    1 + x + \frac{x^2}{2} + \frac{x^3}{3!} + \dots =
    \sum_{n=0}^{\infty} \frac{x^n}{n!}
    \tag{3} \]</p>
<p>The functions with derivatives proportional to their values are the
exponential functions, \( f(x) = b^x \). Equation (2) is aligned
with \( b^0 = 1 \). Using \( b^1 = b \) identifies the base for
equation (3).</p>
<p>\[ f(1) =
    \frac{1}{0!} + \frac{1}{1!} + \frac{1}{2!} + \frac{1}{3!} + \dots =
    2.718281828
    \tag{4} \]</p>
<p>This is \( e \), and it's \( e \) not by numerical equality but
because this is the essence of \( e \): the base of the exponential
whose derivative equals its value.</p>
<p>\[ e^x = \sum_{n=0}^{\infty} \frac{x^n}{n!} \tag{5} \]</p>
<p>This relates exponentiation using arbitrary powers with using only
integer powers. It already supports complex exponents if you don't
mind doing some calculating.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">import math

def approx_exp(x, terms=20):
    return sum(x**n / math.factorial(n) for n in range(terms))

approx_exp(math.pi * 1j)
## (-1.0000000035290801-5.289182672965142e-10j)</code></pre>

<p>\[ e^{\pi i} + 1 = 0 \tag{6} \]</p>
<p>To understand why that should be, consider that exponentiation
connects addition and multiplication, as \( b^{m + n} = b^m \cdot b^n
\). Imaginary numbers add as usual, but their multiplication amounts
to rotation. The base \( e \) has the property that rotation is
given in radians, so \( \pi i \) means one half turn, taking the
result to -1.</p>
<p>This can also be seen by discovering that \( e^{xi} = \cos{x} + i
\sin{x} \), for example by checking that their values at 0 and all
their derivatives are equal.</p>
<p>Negative bases have the funny property that their even exponents give
positive results, but odd exponents give negative results. What should
the result be for an exponent like 1.2, then? Thinking of rotation, it
makes sense that results sweep through complex values to get from the
positive real axis to the negative real axis and so on. This is a fine
way to draw a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logarithmic_spiral">logarithmic spiral</a>. It can be connected to equation
(6).</p>
<p>\[ (-b)^x = b^x (-1)^x = b^x (e^{\pi i})^x = b^x e^{x \pi i} \tag{7} \]</p>
<p>The rotation comes from the negative base <em>already</em> being rotated to
begin with. In fact it's only the boring positive real numbers that
don't rotate when exponentiated.</p>
<hr>
<p>Forgive me for using \( \pi \) despite mentioning \( \tau \)
above; \( \pi \) is so familiar in this context that I didn't want
to introduce a separate new thing, even though \( \tau \) is
arguably better <em>especially</em> in this setting.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="a_few_quotes"></a>A few quotes from <em>e</em>: The Story of a Number</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>"Though [William] Oughtred held no official university position, his
contributions to mathematics were substantial. In his most
influential work, the <em>Clavis mathematicae</em> (1631), a book on
arithmetic and algebra, he introduced many new mathematical symbols,
some of which are still in use today. (Among them is the symbol &#215;
for multiplication, to which Leibniz later objected because of its
similarity to the letter <em>x</em>; two other symbols that can still be
seen occasionally are :: to denote a proportion and ~ for "the
difference between.")" (page 15)</p>
<p>"The Pythagoreans believed that numbers are the prime cause behind
everything in the world, from the laws of musical harmony to the
motion of the planets. "Number rules the universe" was their motto,
and by "number" they meant natural numbers and their ratios;
everything else&#8212;negative numbers, irrational numbers, and even
zero&#8212;was excluded." (page 51)</p>
<p>"[William Rowan] Hamilton's rigorous approach marked the beginning
of axiomatic algebra: ..." (page 167)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/wmkarney">Will Karnasiewicz</a> for pointing me to a continuously
compounding bank, and Mervin Chen for pointing me to Khan's gratuitous
calculus.</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="e: The Story of a Number" src="e_cover.jpg"></p>
<p><img alt="Where Mathematics Comes From" src="Where_Mathematics_Comes_From.jpg"></p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200816-e_the_story_of_a_number_and_more/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200816-e_the_story_of_a_number_and_more/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Green Eggs and Ham uses 50 words</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I recently heard that Dr. Seuss wrote Green Eggs and Ham using
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green_Eggs_and_Ham#Background">just 50 words</a> to win a bet. Naturally, I had to check. Counting
"Sam-I-am" as three distinct words, it is indeed exactly 50 unique
words, used 802 total times, with no use of the letters J, P, Q, V, or
Z.</p>
<hr>
<p>Dr. Seuss introduces no more than 7 new words on any one of the book's
62 pages, and indeed eight pages introduce just one new word.</p>
<p><img alt="Introduction of words by page in Green Eggs and Ham" src="new_words_by_page.png"></p>
<p>I used only the words that appear printed as text in the book, which
ignores the "I am Sam" sign carried by Sam in the illustration on page
three (and similar sign on page seven). If those are included, word
counts change slightly and the maximum new words on a page is just
five.</p>
<hr>
<p>Green Eggs and Ham doesn't seem to follow <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zipf%27s_law">Zipf's Law</a> very well. If
it did, the log-log plot here should show a straight line rather than
being concave. The repetitive nature of the text means more words
appear more often than a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_law">power law</a> would suggest.</p>
<p><img alt="Word frequencies in Green Eggs and Ham" src="frequencies_log_log.png"></p>
<p>Of course this is a small sample of text, so
<a href="https://xkcd.com/2268/">draw conclusions accordingly</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Here's a list showing numbers of occurrences and each word that
appears with that frequency (there are 25 unique frequencies):</p>
<ul>
<li>84: not</li>
<li>82: I</li>
<li>61: them</li>
<li>59: a</li>
<li>44: like</li>
<li>40: in</li>
<li>37: do</li>
<li>33: you</li>
<li>26: would</li>
<li>25: and, eat</li>
<li>21: will</li>
<li>19: with</li>
<li>16: Sam</li>
<li>14: could</li>
<li>13: am</li>
<li>11: green, eggs, ham, here, the</li>
<li>9: there, train</li>
<li>8: or, anywhere, house, mouse</li>
<li>7: box, fox, car, on, dark</li>
<li>6: tree</li>
<li>5: say, so</li>
<li>4: may, see, let, me, be, rain, goat, try</li>
<li>3: that, boat</li>
<li>2: they, are, good, thank</li>
<li>1: if</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Data and code is <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/green_eggs_and_ham">on GitHub</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200815-green_eggs_and_ham_uses_50_words/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200815-green_eggs_and_ham_uses_50_words/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Life expectancy is historically misleading</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The modern distribution of age at death is substantially novel. In
today's wealthiest countries most people die at an age near their life
expectancy, but historically a third of people died as young children
and the remainder died over a wide range of ages.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Life_expectancy">Life expectancy</a> at birth, an average of possible ages at death, is
now a measure of central tendency, but even just 100 years ago the
distribution of age at death didn't really <em>have</em> a central tendency.
Interpreting it as if it did gives a misleading impression of past
cultures.</p>
<p><img alt="Life Expectancy and Distribution of Age at Death Over Time in Sweden" src="lifetimes_in_sweden.png"></p>
<p>Inspired by <a href="/20200805-factfulness_by_rosling/">Hans Rosling</a>, I went looking for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Life_table">life tables</a>.
Appropriately enough, his native Sweden birthed the first National
Statistical Office, with 270 years of life tables <a href="https://www.mortality.org/cgi-bin/hmd/country.php?cntr=SWE&amp;level=1">available</a>.
That's enough history to show how the world used to be, and as a rich
country Sweden also shows us where the whole world is (hopefully)
heading.</p>
<p>Back when life expectancy was mid-thirties, you were more likely to
die in your seventies than in your thirties. If you interpret a life
expectancy of 36 to mean "most people died around age 36" you might
incorrectly imagine a world with very few people over 50.</p>
<p>Or, as Rosling explains it:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Back in 1800, when Swedes starved to death and British children
worked in coal mines, life expectancy was roughly 30 years
everywhere in the world. That was what it had been throughout
history. Among all babies who were ever born, roughly half died
during their childhood. Most of the other half died between the ages
of 50 and 70. So the average was around 30. It doesn't mean most
people lived to be 30. It's just an average, and with averages we
must always remember that there's a spread." (<a href="/20200805-factfulness_by_rosling/">Factfulness</a>, page
54)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This doesn't mean that life expectancy isn't a useful statistic for
tracking development! It can be both limited and useful.</p>
<p>I like the visualization I made (above) because it shows enough
information to see distributional changes over time.</p>
<p>The question of whether life expectancy will <em>continue</em> to go up is an
interesting one. I'm not sure this data has much to say. The length of
past lives has an <a href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20181002-how-long-did-ancient-people-live-life-span-versus-longevity">uncertain</a> relationship with theoretical/possible
lifespan. Are people living longer, or just not dying earlier? There's
also a possible question about quality of life at extreme ages which
might be complicating.</p>
<hr>
<p>Source for the visualization above is <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/life_expectancy">on github</a>.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200806-life_expectancy_is_historically_misleading/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200806-life_expectancy_is_historically_misleading/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Factfulness, by Rosling</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://www.gapminder.org/factfulness-book/">Factfulness</a> finds <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_Rosling">Rosling</a> realizing that facts are not enough,
because thinking is polluted by "dramatic instincts," so his
presentation of little-known optimistic trends is organized to address
not just ignorance, but systematic biases in how people think.</p>
<ol>
<li><em>The Gap Instinct</em>: Giving its name to his <a href="https://www.gapminder.org/">foundation</a>, this is
   the tendency to think groups are completely different. Usually even
   if group averages are different, the distributions significantly
   overlap.</li>
<li><em>The Negativity Instinct</em>: Bad news is reported and feels salient,
   even if trends are positive overall.</li>
<li><em>The Straight Line Instinct</em>: Trends are not always linear, but
   it's easiest to extrapolate as if they were&#8212;and be wrong.</li>
<li><em>The Fear Instinct</em>: Fear is often not calibrated to true risk.</li>
<li><em>The Size Instinct</em>: Understanding "big" requires appropriate
   comparison.</li>
<li><em>The Generalization Instinct</em>: Both categories and anecdotes can be
   misleading.</li>
<li><em>The Destiny Instinct</em>: Slow change is not the same as no change.</li>
<li><em>The Single Perspective Instinct</em>: Understanding requires more than
   one approach, view, or tool (even statistics).</li>
<li><em>The Blame Instinct</em>: Whether effects are good or bad, the reasons
   are probably more complex than just one individual or organization.</li>
<li><em>The Urgency Instinct</em>: It's better to think and act carefully
    than jump into drastic moves.</li>
</ol>
<p>Rosling wants us to realize our shared humanity, see that things have
mostly gotten better over long time scales, and work to keep improving
things. The philanthropy of <a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/books/factfulness">Bill Gates</a> is largely working to
continue the trends Rosling focuses on, for example.</p>
<p>Like his classic <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jbkSRLYSojo">presentation</a>, celebrated by data visualizers, the
book is a study in good communication. I particularly noticed that he
often found opportunities to present dialogue rather than just
narrative, and that he used cute attention-getting flourishes like
using hypothetical "chimps" to stand in for random performance on his
quizzes.</p>
<p>I agree there's risk in assuming positive trends inevitably continue.
But it isn't fair to say Rosling ignored future risks. He listed five
things that he thought we <em>should</em> worry about:</p>
<ol>
<li>Global pandemic</li>
<li>Financial collapse</li>
<li>World War III</li>
<li>Climate change</li>
<li>Extreme poverty</li>
</ol>
<p>Writing in 2017, he seems particularly prescient today.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... free access to data doesn't turn into knowledge without
effort." (page 79)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It will be helpful to you if you always assume your categories are
misleading." (page 158)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200805-factfulness_by_rosling/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200805-factfulness_by_rosling/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Man Who Solved the Market, by Zuckerman</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/557104/the-man-who-solved-the-market-by-gregory-zuckerman/">book</a> demystifies <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Simons_(mathematician)">Jim Simons</a> and makes his
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renaissance_Technologies#Monemetrics">Medallion Fund</a> seem more like grinding at a poker table than like
solving the market. I was interested to read about his connection to
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Mercer">Robert Mercer</a> and otherwise hiring "smart people" regardless of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_No_Asshole_Rule">other characteristics</a>.</p>
<p>Technical detail is light, but Zuckerman emphasizes that Renaissance
used a monolithic trading model that could accept additional signals
over time, manage <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slippage_(finance)">slippage</a> sometimes to the extent that signals
Renaissance was using could be made to disappear to outside observers
while exploited, and that frequently was basically based on reversion
to the mean. And Renaissance was not at all shy about using any
available tax dodges.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Simons was struck by the unique way talented researchers were
recruited and managed in his unit [of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institute_for_Defense_Analyses" title="the Institute for Defense Analyses">IDA</a>]. Staff members, most
of whom had doctorates, were hired for their brainpower, creativity,
and ambition, rather than for any specific expertise or background.
The assumption was that researchers would find problems to work on
and be clever enough to solve them. Lenny Baum, among the most
accomplished code-breakers, developed a saying that became the
group's credo: "Bad ideas is good, good ideas terrific, no ideas is
terrible."" (pages 24-25)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Courting accomplished candidates, Simons developed a unique
perspective on talent. He told one Stony Brook professor, Hershel
Farkas, that he valued "killers," those with a single-minded focus
who wouldn't quit on a math problem until arriving at a solution.
Simons told another colleague that some academics were "super smart"
yet weren't original thinkers worthy of a position at the
university.</p>
<p>""There are guys and there are <em>real</em> guys," he said." (pages 34-35)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Truth ... is much too complicated to allow for anything but
approximations." (page 67, epigraph quoting John von Neuman)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"No one ever made a decision because of a number. They need a
story." (page 161, epigraph quoting Daniel Kahneman)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Early one evening, his eyes blurry from staring at his computer
screen for hours on end, Magerman spotted something odd: A line of
simulation code used for Brown and Mercer&#8217;s trading system showed
the Standard &amp; Poor&#8217;s 500 at an unusually low level. This test code
appeared to use a figure from back in 1991 that was roughly half the
current number. Mercer had written it as a static figure, rather
than as a variable that updated with each move in the market.</p>
<p>"When Magerman fixed the bug and updated the number, a second
problem&#8212;an algebraic error&#8212;appeared elsewhere in the code. Magerman
spent most of the night on it but he thought he solved that one,
too. Now the simulator&#8217;s algorithms could finally recommend an ideal
portfolio for the Nova system to execute, including how much
borrowed money should be employed to expand its stock holdings. The
resulting portfolio seemed to generate big profits, at least
according to Magerman&#8217;s calculations.</p>
<p>"Overcome with excitement, he raced to tell Brown what he had
discovered. Brown flashed his breathless colleague a look of deep
skepticism but agreed to hear Magerman out. Afterward, Brown still
showed little enthusiasm. Mercer had done the coding for the system,
after all. Everyone knew Mercer rarely made errors, especially
mathematical ones. Crestfallen, Magerman slunk away. His screwup had
branded him a nuisance, not any kind of potential savior.</p>
<p>"Without much to lose, Magerman brought his work to Mercer, who also
agreed to take a look. Sitting at his desk, hunched over his
computer, Mercer patiently examined the old code, line by line,
comparing it to Magerman&#8217;s new code. Slowly, a smile formed on his
face. Mercer reached for some paper and a pencil from his desk and
began working on a formula. He was checking Magerman&#8217;s work. After
about fifteen minutes of scribbling, Mercer put his pencil down and
looked up.</p>
<p>"&#8220;You&#8217;re right,&#8221; Mercer told Magerman.</p>
<p>"Later, Mercer convinced Brown that Magerman was on to something.
But when Brown and Mercer told other staffers about the problem that
had been uncovered, as well as the fix, they were met with
incredulity, even laughter. A junior programmer fixed the problem?
The same guy who had crashed the system a few weeks after being
hired?</p>
<p>"Brown and Mercer ignored the doubts and restarted the system, with
Simons&#8217;s backing, incorporating the improvements and corrections.
Instant gains resulted, defying the skeptics. The long losing streak
was over. Magerman finally received the appreciation he longed for,
receiving a cherished pat on the back from Brown.</p>
<p>"&#8220;This is great,&#8221; Simons boomed at a weekly meeting. &#8220;Let&#8217;s keep it
going.&#8221;</p>
<p>"A new era for both Magerman and the firm seemed within reach."
(pages 194-195)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When asked to comment, Bannon said there are "errors of fact" in
this description of events surrounding the election and his
interactions with the Mercers, though he wouldn't specify the
inaccuracies. "Dude, it's not my fucking book," he said in an
email." (footnote page 280)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>&#8220;We can teach you about money,&#8221; Patterson explains. &#8220;We can&#8217;t teach
you about smart.&#8221; (page 284)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200804-man_who_solved_the_market/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200804-man_who_solved_the_market/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Technological Revolutions and Financial Capital, by Perez</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlota_Perez">Perez</a> offers a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Other_Canon_Foundation" title="The Other Canon">heterodox</a> abduction from economic history, in
the tradition of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Schumpeter">Schumpeter</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kondratiev_wave">Kondratiev</a>, suggesting
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_Revolutions_and_Financial_Capital">Technological Revolutions and Financial Capital</a> dance through
"great surges" of 40 to 60 years, like giant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hype_cycle">hype cycles</a> driving
development.</p>
<p><img alt="hype cycle overlaid with great surge pattern" src="cycle.jpg"></p>
<p>(The hype cycle analogy isn't perfect; see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_Revolutions_and_Financial_Capital">elsewhere</a> for
summarization of Perez's formulation and five surges.)</p>
<p>Taking Dosi's extension of Kuhn's scientific paradigms to
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_paradigm#Giovanni_Dosi">technological paradigms</a> and further involving economics and
societal institutions (especially as capitalism vs. regulation), the
ideas are <a href="https://www.oxfordscholarship.com/view/10.1093/0199251053.001.0001/acprof-9780199251056" title="As Time Goes By, Freeman and Lou&#231;&#227;">not wholly original</a>, but neither are they very common.</p>
<p><img alt="diagram of technological, economic, and institutional change" src="diagram.jpg"></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The justification for an exercise that claims to give order to the
historical record at the expense of its infinite complexity and
richness is its heuristic value." (page 161)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Perez doesn't seem happy that the historical approach
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methodenstreit" title="Methodenstreit">fell out of favor</a> in economics, and it's neat to see her analysis
cover hundreds of years. This is economic history that doesn't just
refer to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bretton_Woods_system">Bretton Woods</a>, but also the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peterloo_Massacre">Peterloo Massacre</a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corn_Laws">Corn Laws</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nabob">nabobs</a>, to sample a few references. You know
about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May_68">May 1968 in Europe</a>, right?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The role of the economic historian, as Gay perceived it, was to
study and comprehend these cycles and to suggest ways of restraining
their excesses." (page 158, quoting Cruikshank, extended quote
below)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This book is the closest thing I've seen to Asimov's
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychohistory_(fictional)">psychohistory</a>, as in the <a href="/20200714-foundation_trilogy/">Foundation</a> books. The time-scale
(around 50 years vs. thousands) and claimed predictive power (little
vs. godlike) are very different, but the ideas of anticipating
long-term shifts and being ready for them are analogous, and Perez
does discuss some psychosocial aspects, as in "ethical softening"
during parts of her surges.</p>
<p>The book was published in 2002. It was a theory that fit the dot-com
crash. How has the theory fit since then? The financial industry was
not much reined in, for one.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"However, this change in the rules of the game may not be easy,
because the financial collapse has not been spectacular enough to
wipe out the excess self-confidence." (page 168, on the dot-com
crash)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Maybe the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Recession">Great Recession</a> was just a late example of financial
adventurism. The theory suggests that shouldn't be happening so much
during the deployment phase of the age of information. It's easy to
feel like markets were <em>never</em> really brought back in line with the
real economy. Have we been in a "gilded age"?</p>
<p>It should be about time for the start of a new surge. What will the
next big technology be?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"It has often been suggested that biotechnology, bioelectrics and
nanotechnology might conform the next technological revolution."
(page 13)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>From where I sit, AI/ML seems like a good candidate. Should we throw
in VR/AR? Blockchain? Private space? Does the social web constitute a
separate technology?</p>
<p>The book's theory treats technologies as available resources just
waiting for capital to fund them into prominence. I think this may be
too much of a simplification. In particular, it's <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/8-lessons-from-20-years-hype-cycles-michael-mullany/">pretty hard</a> to
guess in advance which technologies will take off and which will
fizzle, and I don't think there's any guarantee that there will always
be a technology at hand substantial enough to power another surge.</p>
<p>Alternatively, what if an even longer phase is coming to an end? What
if <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Productivity_paradox">declines in productivity growth</a> are a real indication of the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigmoid_function">sigmoid</a> peak of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Great_Transformation_(book)" title="The Great Transformation">Market Society</a> overall, and extended
financial weirdness a sign of an impending larger transformation of
societal system?</p>
<p>It certainly feels, in 2020, as if the world sits on a knife-edge,
with forces pulling in multiple directions. Hopefully history will
help us to create a worthy future.</p>
<p><img alt="book cover" src="book_cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... Schumpeter's own view that aggregate figures conceal more than
they reveal." (page 61, refs Schumpeter (1939) Vol. 1, pp. 43-4, I
checked the ref and it's correct, but unfortunately Schumpeter's
language is not very quotable)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"People living through the period of paradigm transition experience
great uncertainty as to the 'right' price of things (including that
of stocks, of course)." (page 62)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"So again, and not surprisingly, nothing in the capitalist system is
clear and simple." (page 67)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Schumpeter defined capitalism as 'that form of private property
economy in which innovations are carried out by means of borrowed
money'." (page 72, refs Schumpeter (1939) p. 223)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There is a certain amount of circularity in all these observations,
because the phases have been dated taking the occurrence of crises
into account." (page 79)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Interesting reference: <a href="https://www.amazon.com/End-Finance-Inflation-Derivatives-Capitalism/dp/0415208815">The End of Finance: Capital Market Inflation, Financial Derivatives and Pension Fund Capitalism</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The full history of the readjustment of relative paper and real
values at the beginning of the twenty-first century will only be
appropriately judged with hindsight." (page 112)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As with many processes in capitalism, it is by taking a successful
behavior to its extreme that it turns into failure." (page 115)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"To begin with, knowledge, experience and information have become
capital goods." (page 144)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Without recognizable labor unions, salaries would not have been
enough to serve as solvent demand much beyond food and basics."
(page 145)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Page 146 has an interesting meta-analysis of the field of economics
viewed through the lens of the book's theory.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Technology is the fuel of the capitalist engine." (page 155)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"[E.F. Gay] developed a dynamic vision of economic history [as] a
record of swings of the pendulum between periods when social
controls dominated and periods dominated by the actions of
aggressive individuals. The former periods were static,
characterized by security and stability. The latter periods ushered
in by the introduction of new tools, weapons or other forces, were
controlled by the powerful individuals who introduced these forces.
These dynamic periods ... were crucial to economic development ...
The role of the economic historian, as Gay perceived it, was to
study and comprehend these cycles and to suggest ways of restraining
their excesses." (page 158, quoting Cruikshank, 1987, on the
founding Dean of Harvard Business School)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The <em>Methodenstreit</em> between the historical school and the
neo-classicals, which in practice expelled the state, Society and
the historical context from economic theory, occurred in the period
of installation of the third surge, which in the periodization
proposed here is parallel to the installation period of the fifth,
when the monetarists defeated the Keynesians." (page 162)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The ultimate test of usefulness of a model such as the one
presented here is in relation to policy making, be it in business,
in social organizations or in government." (page 163)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Yet if this model is a reasonable approximation to the way the
system works then it is wise to try to engage in the design of
regulations and institutions so they will be ready and in the arena
of debate when the moment comes for them to be accepted." (page 165)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"A golden age of worldwide expansion is possible." (page 171)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200728-technological_revolutions_and_financial_capital/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200728-technological_revolutions_and_financial_capital/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Art of Doing Science and Engineering, by Hamming</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>You should definitely read <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Hamming">Hamming</a>'s "You and Your Research"
<a href="https://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/YouAndYourResearch.html">talk</a>, and probably also his 1996 <a href="http://worrydream.com/refs/Hamming-TheArtOfDoingScienceAndEngineering.pdf">book</a> (both freely available).
I read the beautiful new printing from <a href="https://press.stripe.com/">Stripe Press</a>, with a
forward by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bret_Victor">Victor</a>. Hamming may not be perfect, but he has a lot of
ideas.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"We live in an age of exponential growth in knowledge, and it is
increasingly futile to teach only polished theorems and proofs. We
must abandon the guided tour through the art gallery of mathematics,
and instead teach how to create the mathematics we need. In my
opinion, there is no long-term practical alternative." (page v,
epigraph quoting Hamming)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The book is roughly Hamming's lectures from a graduate course he
taught after he could teach whatever he felt like. It is "Hamming on
Hamming" in that it's largely him expounding on whatever he liked.
It's a bit like a (very technical) grandparent telling stories and
giving advice to their grandkids.</p>
<p><img alt="book cover" src="book_cover.jpg"></p>
<p>The cover image is a visual form of the book's inspirational message:
A random walk won't take you anywhere, but if you have a vision, a
direction that you keep trying to pursue, then even if not every step
is correct, you will make progress in that direction.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"What is wanted in the long run, of course, is that the man with the
problem does the actual writing of the code with no human interface,
as we all too often have these days, between the person who knows
the problem and the person who knows the programming language. This
date is unfortunately too far off to do much good immediately, but I
would think by the year 2020 it would be fairly universal practice
for the expert in the field of application to do the actual program
preparation rather than have experts in computers (and ignorant of
the field of application) do the program preparation." (page 55;
writing around 1995)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"You read constantly about "engineering the production of software,"
both for the efficiency of production and for the reliability of the
product. But you do not expect novelists to "engineer the production
of novels." The question arises: "Is programming closer to novel
writing than it is to classical engineering?" I suggest yes! Given
the problem of getting a man into outer space, both the Russians and
the Americans did it pretty much the same way, all things
considered, and allowing for some espionage. They were both limited
by the same firm laws of physics. But give two novelists the problem
of writing on "the greatness and misery of man," and you will
probably get two very different novels (without saying just how to
measure this). Give the same complex problem to two modern
programmers and you will, I claim, get two rather different
programs. Hence my belief that current programming practice is
closer to novel writing than it is to engineering. The novelists are
bound only by their imaginations, which is somewhat as the
programmers are when they are writing software. Both activities have
a large creative component, and while you would like to make
programming resemble engineering, it will take a lot of time to get
there&#8212;and maybe you really, in the long run, do not want to do it!
Maybe it just sounds good. You will have to think about it many
times in the coming years; you might as well start now and discount
propaganda you hear, as well as all the wishful thinking which goes
on in the area! The software of the utility programs of computers
has been done often enough, and is so limited in scope, so it might
reasonably be expected to become "engineered," but the general
software preparation is not likely to be under "engineering control"
for many, many years.</p>
<p>"There are many proposals on how to improve the productivity of the
individual programmer, as well as groups of programmers. I have
already mentioned top-down and bottom-up; there are others, such as
head programmer, lead programmer, proving the program is correct in
a mathematical sense, and the waterfall model of programming, to
name but a few. While each has some merit I have faith in only one,
which is almost never mentioned&#8212;<em>think before you write the
program,</em> it might be called. Before you start, think carefully
about the whole thing, <em>including</em> what will be your acceptance test
that it is right, as well as how later field maintenance will be
done. Getting it right the first time is much better than fixing it
up later!</p>
<p>"One trouble with much of programming is simply that often there is
not a well-defined job to be done; rather, the programming process
itself will gradually discover what the problem is! The desire that
you will be given a well-defined problem before you start
programming often does not match reality, and hence a lot of the
current proposals to "solve the programming problem" will fall to
the ground if adopted rigorously." (pages 57-58)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Many studies have shown programmers differ in productivity, from
worst to best, by much more than a factor of ten. From this I long
ago concluded the best policy is to pay your good programmers very
well but regularly fire the poorer ones&#8212;if you can get away with it!
One way is, of course, to hire them on contract rather than as
regularly employed people, but that is increasingly against the law,
which seems to want to guarantee even the worst have some
employment. In practice you may actually be better off to pay the
worst to stay home and not get in the way of the more capable (and I
am serious)!" (page 59)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I made the comparison of writing software with the act of literary
writing; both seem to depend fundamentally on clear thinking. Can
good programming be taught? If we look at the corresponding teaching
of "creative writing" courses we find most students of such courses
do not become great writers, and most great writers in the past did
not take creative writing courses! Hence it is dubious that great
programmers can be trained easily.</p>
<p>"Does experience help? Do bureaucrats after years of writing reports
and instructions get better? I have no real data, but I suspect with
time they get worse! The habitual use of "governmentese" over the
years probably seeps into their writing style and makes them worse.
I suspect the same for programmers! Neither years of experience nor
the number of languages used is any reason for thinking the
programmer is getting better from these experiences. An examination
of books on programming suggests most of the authors are not good
programmers!</p>
<p>"The results I picture are not nice, but all you have to oppose it
is wishful thinking&#8212;I have evidence of years and years of
programming on my side!" (pages 60-61)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"People often make the mistake of saying, "Thinking is what Newton
and Einstein did." But by that definition most of us cannot
think&#8212;and usually we do not like that conclusion!" (page 79)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... Of course robots will displace many humans doing routine jobs.
In a very real sense, machines can best do routine jobs, thus
freeing humans for more humane jobs. Unfortunately, many humans at
present are not equipped to compete with machines&#8212;they are unable to
do much more than routine jobs. There is a widespread belief (hope?)
that humans can compete, once they are given proper training.
However, I have long publicly doubted you could take many coal
miners and make them into useful programmers. I have my reservations
on the fraction of the human population that can be made into
programmers in the classical sense; if you call getting money from
the bank dispensing "machine programming," or the dialing of a
telephone number (both of which apply the human input to an
elaborate program which is then executed, much like an interpreter
acts on your program input), then of course most people can be made
into programmers. But if you mean the more classical activity of
careful analysis of a situation and then the detailed specification
as to what is to be done, then I say there are doubts as to what
fraction of the population can <em>compete</em> with computers, even with
nice interactive prompting menus.</p>
<p>"Computers have both displaced so many people from jobs, and also
made so many new jobs, it is hopeless to try to answer which is the
larger number. But it is clear that on average it is the lower-level
jobs which are disappearing and the higher-level jobs which are
appearing. Again, one would like to believe <em>most</em> people can be
trained in the future to do the higher-level jobs&#8212;but that is a hope
without any real evidence." (pag 94)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We started to play games on computers to study the human thought
processes and not to win the game; the goal has been perverted to
win, and never mind the insight into the human mind and how it
works." (page 100)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Thus AI requires your careful thought and should not be dismissed
lightly just because many experts make obviously false claims."
(page 103)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<em>Information theory</em> was created by C.E. Shannon in the late 1940s.
The management of Bell Telephone Labs wanted him to call it
"communication theory," as that is a far more accurate name, but for
obvious publicity reasons "information theory" has a much greater
impact&#8212;this Shannon chose and so it is known to this day." (page
163)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is always wise to adopt a standard notation and framework of
thinking of diverse things&#8212;one field of application may suggest
things to do in the other. I have found it of great value to do so
whenever possible&#8212;remove the extraneous scale factors and get to the
basic expressions. (But then I was originally trained as a
mathematician.)" (page 184)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is another example of why you need to know the fundamentals very
well; the fancy parts then follow easily and you can do things that
they never told you about." (page 186)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Many people had the opportunity to discover (really rediscover) the
Gibbs phenomenon, and it was Gibbs who made the effort. It is
another example of what I maintain, that there are opportunities all
around and few people reach for them. As Pasteur said, "Luck favors
the prepared mind."" (page 201)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It must be your friends, in some sense, who make you famous by
quoting and citing you, and it pays, so I claim, to be helpful to
others as they try to do their work. They may in time give you
credit for the work, which is better than trying to claim it
yourself. Cooperation is essential in these days of complex
projects; the day of the individual worker is dying fast. Teamwork
is more and more essential, and hence learning to work on a team,
indeed possibly seeking out places where you can help others, is a
good idea. In any case the fun of working with good people on
important problems is more pleasure than the resulting fame." (page
210)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Moral: when you know something cannot be done, also remember the
essential reason why, so later, when the circumstances have changed,
you will not say, "It can't be done."" (page 218, on how he missed
the opportunity to help develop FFT)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Let us analyze carefully what we do and its implications, because
<em>what we do to a great extent controls what we can see.</em>" (page 219)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"If you will only ask yourself, "Is what I am being told really
true?," it is amazing how much you can find is, or borders on, being
false, even in a well-developed field!" (page 227)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When I went to Bell Telephone Laboratories in 1946 I soon found
myself in the early stages of the design of the earliest Nike system
of guided missiles." (page 238)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I have emphasized the necessity of having the underlying laws of
whatever field you are simulating well under control. But there are
no such laws of economics! The only law of economics that I believe
in is Hamming's law: "You cannot consume what is not produced."
There is not another single reliable law in all of economics I know
of which is not either a tautology in mathematics or else sometimes
false. Hence when you do simulations in economics you have not the
reliability you have in the hard sciences." (page 250)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Now this fact, once understood, impacts design! Good design
protects you from the need for too many highly accurate components
in the system. But such design principles are still, to this date,
ill understood and need to be researched extensively. Not that good
designers do not understand this intuitively, merely it is not
easily incorporated into the design methods you were taught in
school. Good minds are still needed in spite of all the computing
tools we have developed. But the best mind will be the one who gets
the principle into the design methods taught so it will be
automatically available for lesser minds!" (page 269)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"You also realize any dictionary must be circular; the first word
you look up must be defined in terms of other words&#8212;there can be no
first definition which does not use words." (page 307)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When stuck I often ask myself, "If I had a solution, what would it
look like?" This tends to sharpen up the approach, and may reveal
new ways of looking at the problem you had subconsciously ignored
but now see should not be excluded. What must the solution involve?
Are there conservation laws which must apply? Is there some
symmetry? How does each assumption enter into the solution, and is
each one really necessary? Have you recognized all the relevant
factors?" (page 327)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"...saturate the subconscious with the problem, try to not think
seriously about anything else for hours days, or even weeks, and
thus the subconscious ... is left with only the problem to mull
over. We simply deprive it of all else as best we can! ... In a way,
I am repeating Pasteur, "Luck favors the prepared mind." You prepare
your mind for success "by thinking on it constantly" (Newton), and
occasionally you are lucky." (page 328)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Probably the most important tool in creativity is the use of an
<em>analogy.</em> Something seems like something else which we knew in the
past. Wide acquaintance with various fields of knowledge is thus a
help&#8212;<em>provided</em> you have the knowledge filed away so it is available
when needed, rather than to be found only when led directly to it.
This flexible access to pieces of knowledge seems to come from
looking at knowledge <em>while you are acquiring it</em> from many
different angles, turning over any new idea to see its many sides
before filing it away. This implies effort on your part not to take
the easy, immediately useful "memorizing the material" path, but to
prepare your mind for the future. It is for this reason I have urged
you in many of the chapters to get down to the fundamentals of a
field, since it implies you must examine things in many ways before
you can decide what is fundamental and what is frills. In fact, for
one person they may be in one order, and for another in the opposite
order. What is fundamental partly depends on the individual and
their mental makeup. It is obvious you need many "hooks" on the
knowledge if you are to use it in new situations.</p>
<p>"... I can only advise you to do what I do&#8212;when you learn something
new, think of other applications of it, ones which have not arisen
in your past but which might in your future. How easy to say, but
how hard to do! Yet what else can I say about how to organize your
mind so useful things will be recalled readily at the right time?"
(pages 328-329)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The person who thinks they understand the problem and does not is
usually more of a curse (blockage) than the person who knows they do
not understand the problem." (page 333)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It has been my experience, as well as the experience of many others
who have looked, that data is generally much less accurate than it
is advertised to be." (page 345)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"From that experience I learned never to process any data until I
had first examined it carefully for errors. There have been
complaints that I would take too long, but almost always I found
errors, and when I showed the errors to them they had to admit I was
wise in taking the precautions I did. No matter how sacred the data
and urgent the answer, I have learned to pretest it for consistency
and outliers at a minimum." (page 348)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Second, you cannot gather a really large amount of data accurately.
It is a known fact which is constantly ignored. It is always a
matter of limited resources and limited time. The management will
usually want a 100% survey when a small one consisting of a good
deal less, say 1% or even 0.1%, will yield more accurate results! It
is known, I say, but ignored. The telephone companies, in order to
distribute the income to the various companies involved in a single
long-distance phone call, used to take a very small, carefully
selected sample, and on the basis of this sample they distributed
the money among the partners. The same is now done by the airlines.
It took them a long while before they listened, but they finally
came to realize the truth that <em>small samples carefully taken are
better than large samples poorly done</em>&#8212;better both in lower cost and
in greater accuracy." (page 355)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Of the things you can choose to measure some are hard, firm
measurements, such as height and weight, while some are soft, such
as social attitudes. There is always a tendency to grab the hard,
firm measurement, though it may be quite irrelevant as compared to
the soft one, which in the long run may be much more relevant to
your goals. <em>Accuracy</em> of measurement tends to get confused with
<em>relevance</em> of measurement, much more than most people believe. That
a measurement is accurate, reproducible, and easy to make does not
mean it should be done; instead, a much poorer one which is more
closely related to your goals may be much preferable. For example,
in school it is easy to measure training and hard to measure
education, and hence you tend to see on final exams an emphasis on
the training part and a great neglect of the education part.</p>
<p>"Let me turn to another effect of a measurement system, and
illustrate it by the definition and use of IQs. What is done is a
plausible list of questions&#8212;plausible from past experience&#8212;is made
and then tried out on a small number of people. Those questions
which show an internal correlation with others are kept and those
which do not correlate well are dropped. Next, the revised test is
calibrated by using it on a much larger sample. How? Simply by
taking the accumulated scores (the number of people's score which
are below the given amount) and plotting these revised numbers on
probability paper&#8212;meaning the cumulative probabilities of a normal
distribution are the horizontal lines. Next, the points where the
cumulative actual scores fall at a given percentage points are
related, via a calibration table, to the corresponding points on the
cumulative normal probability curve. As a result it is observed
intelligence has a normal distribution in the population! Of course
it has, it was made to be that way! Furthermore, they have defined
intelligence to be what is measured by the calibrated exam, and if
that is the definition of intelligence, then of course intelligence
is normally distributed. But if you think maybe intelligence is not
exactly what the calibrated exam measures, then you are entitled to
doubt intelligence is normally distributed in the population. Again,
you get what was measured, and the normal distribution announced is
an artifact of the method of measurement and hardly relates to
reality." (pages 374-375)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200725-art_of_doing_science_and_engineering/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200725-art_of_doing_science_and_engineering/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
