<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>Core Socialist Values of the Chinese Communist Party</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<ul>
<li>National values<ul>
<li>Prosperity</li>
<li>Democracy</li>
<li>Civility</li>
<li>Harmony</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Social values<ul>
<li>Freedom</li>
<li>Equality</li>
<li>Justice</li>
<li>Rule of law</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Individual values<ul>
<li>Patriotism</li>
<li>Dedication</li>
<li>Integrity</li>
<li>Friendship</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Sure enough, China (or the CCP, anyway) has a set of values.
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Core_Socialist_Values">Looks like</a> they were put together in 2012!</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20260107-core_socialist_values_of_the_ccp/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20260107-core_socialist_values_of_the_ccp/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Moral Code of the Builder of Communism</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<ul>
<li>Devotion to the communist cause; love of the socialist motherland
   and of the other socialist countries.</li>
<li>Conscientious labor for the good of society—he who does not work,
   neither shall he eat.</li>
<li>Concern on the part of everyone for the preservation and growth of
   public wealth.</li>
<li>A high sense of public duty; intolerance of actions harmful to the
   public interest.</li>
<li>Collectivism and comradely mutual assistance: one for all and all
   for one.</li>
<li>Humane relations and mutual respect between individuals—man is to
   man a friend, comrade and brother.</li>
<li>Honesty and truthfulness, moral purity, modesty, and
   unpretentiousness in social and private life.</li>
<li>Mutual respect in the family, and concern for the upbringing of
   children.</li>
<li>An uncompromising attitude to injustice, parasitism, dishonesty,
   careerism, and money-grubbing.</li>
<li>Friendship and brotherhood among all peoples of the USSR;
   intolerance of national and racial hatred.</li>
<li>An uncompromising attitude to the enemies of communism, peace, and
   the freedom of nations.</li>
<li>Fraternal solidarity with the working people of all countries, and
   with all peoples.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>The "Moral Code of the Builder of Communism" was part of the the 1961
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third_Program_of_the_CPSU">Third Program</a> of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The core of the new approach to building communism was an attempt to
replace Stalin's harsh administrative "pressure from above" with
socialist self-government based on the principles of communist
morality.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nick-aristov-57b924b/">Nick Aristov</a> for <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7411869918872260608?commentUrn=urn%3Ali%3Acomment%3A%28activity%3A7411869918872260608%2C7411895007353413632%29&amp;replyUrn=urn%3Ali%3Acomment%3A%28activity%3A7411869918872260608%2C7411906333794414592%29&amp;dashCommentUrn=urn%3Ali%3Afsd_comment%3A%287411895007353413632%2Curn%3Ali%3Aactivity%3A7411869918872260608%29&amp;dashReplyUrn=urn%3Ali%3Afsd_comment%3A%287411906333794414592%2Curn%3Ali%3Aactivity%3A7411869918872260608%29">pointing</a> me to this! Here's the
relevant page from the <a href="https://www.marxists.org/history/ussr/cpsu/1961/3rd-cpsu-program.pdf#page=62">long PDF</a> of the 1963 English translation,
from which I copied the Moral Code above. (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moral_Code_of_the_Builder_of_Communism">Wikipedia</a> has slightly
different text somehow.)</p>
<p><img alt="page" src="page.png"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20260106-moral_code_of_the_builder_of_communism/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20260106-moral_code_of_the_builder_of_communism/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Girl Scouts of the USA Promise and Law</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<h3>Girl Scout Promise</h3>
<p>On my honor, I will try:<br>
To serve God* and my country,<br>
To help people at all times,<br>
And to live by the Girl Scout Law.</p>
<p>*Members may substitute for the word God<br>
in accordance with their own spiritual beliefs.</p>
<h3>Girl Scout Law</h3>
<p>I will do my best to be<br>
honest and fair,<br>
friendly and helpful,<br>
considerate and caring,<br>
courageous and strong,<br>
and responsible for what I say and do,<br>
and to respect myself and others,<br>
respect authority,<br>
use resources wisely,<br>
make the world a better place,<br>
and be a sister to every Girl Scout.</p>
<hr>
<p>This is the version, down to the line breaks, current <a href="https://www.girlscouts.org/en/discover/about-us/what-girl-scouts-do/promise-and-law.html">online</a> for
the Girl Scouts of the USA. (Equivalents elsewhere are often called
"Girl Guides.")</p>
<p>The explicit flexibility for different spiritualities is not unique to
Girl Scouts of the USA. For example, UK Scouts publishes eight
versions of each of its <a href="https://www.scouts.org.uk/volunteers/running-your-section/programme-guidance/information-for-volunteers/the-scout-promise/">promises</a> covering Atheists, Buddhists,
Christians, Hindus, Humanists, Jews, Muslims, and Sikhs.</p>
<p>Juliette Gordon Low’s <a href="https://thebadgearchive.com/gsusa-evolution-of-the-promise-and-law/">original</a> Promise and Law from 1912 was very
similar to Baden-Powell’s. It included, for example, that "a Girl
Scout keeps herself pure," instead of that "a Scout is clean in
thought, word and deed."</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251231-girl_scouts_of_usa_promise_and_law/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251231-girl_scouts_of_usa_promise_and_law/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Asimov's Three Laws of Robotics</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<ol>
<li>A robot may not injure a human being or, through inaction, allow a
   human being to come to harm.</li>
<li>A robot must obey the orders given it by human beings except where
   such orders would conflict with the First Law.</li>
<li>A robot must protect its own existence as long as such protection
   does not conflict with the First or Second Law.</li>
</ol>
<p>I was reminded of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Laws_of_Robotics">Three Laws</a> while looking at Scout Laws.
They're not so different, in many ways, from a lot of these codes.
Apparently Asimov was explicit in thinking that humans should follow
the Three Laws as well.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251231-asimov_three_laws_of_robotics/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251231-asimov_three_laws_of_robotics/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Scouting America Oath and Law</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<h3>Scout Oath</h3>
<p>On my honor I will do my best to do my duty to God and my country and to obey the Scout Law; to help other people at all times; to keep myself physically strong, mentally awake, and morally straight.</p>
<h3>Scout Law</h3>
<p>A Scout is:</p>
<ul>
<li>Trustworthy</li>
<li>Loyal</li>
<li>Helpful</li>
<li>Friendly</li>
<li>Courteous</li>
<li>Kind</li>
<li>Obedient</li>
<li>Cheerful</li>
<li>Thrifty</li>
<li>Brave</li>
<li>Clean</li>
<li>Reverent</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scout_Law">Since</a> 1907 and 1908 with the writings of Seton and Baden-Powell,
there have been many forms and evolutions of Scout Laws. The version
here is <a href="https://www.scouting.org/about/faq/question10/">current</a> for Scouting America (formerly Boy Scouts of
America) and somewhat distinctive in its focus on single words.
(Explanatory sentences are also included but omitted above.)</p>
<p>Here's Baden-Powell's 1911 <a href="http://www.netpages.free-online.co.uk/sha/law.htm">version</a>:</p>
<h3>Promise</h3>
<p>On my honour I promise that I will do my best:</p>
<ol>
<li>To do my duty to God and the King.</li>
<li>To help other people at all times.</li>
<li>To obey the Scout Law.</li>
</ol>
<h3>Law</h3>
<ol>
<li>A Scout's honour is to be trusted.</li>
<li>A Scout is Loyal to the King, and to his officers, and to his
   country, and to his employers.</li>
<li>A Scout's duty is to be useful and to help others.</li>
<li>A Scout is a friend to all and a brother to every other scout no
   matter to what social class the other belongs.</li>
<li>A Scout is Courteous.</li>
<li>A Scout is a friend to animals.</li>
<li>A Scout obeys orders of his patrol leader or scoutmaster without
   question.</li>
<li>A Scout smiles and whistles under all difficulties.</li>
<li>A Scout is thrifty.</li>
<li>A Scout is clean in thought, word and deed.</li>
</ol>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251231-scouting_america_oath_and_law/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251231-scouting_america_oath_and_law/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Christian Beatitudes</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<ul>
<li>Blessed are the poor in spirit, for theirs is the kingdom of
   heaven.</li>
<li>Blessed are they who mourn, for they will be comforted.</li>
<li>Blessed are the meek, for they will inherit the land.</li>
<li>Blessed are they who hunger and thirst for righteousness, for they
   will be satisfied.</li>
<li>Blessed are the merciful, for they will be shown mercy.</li>
<li>Blessed are the clean of heart, for they will see God.</li>
<li>Blessed are the peacemakers, for they will be called children of
   God.</li>
<li>Blessed are they who are persecuted for the sake of righteousness,
   for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.</li>
</ul>
<p>These eight verses are Matthew 5:3-10 in the NABRE (New American Bible
Revised Edition) translation used in Catholic churches in the US, and
the most famous part of the Sermon on the Mount delivered by Jesus.</p>
<p>"Beatitude" is from a word meaning "blessed" and not any breakdown
like "be" followed by "attitude." Interpretations vary, with at least
<a href="https://openthebible.org/article/the-beatitudes-of-jesus-explained/">one</a> being that the Beatitudes are not just reports about who is
blessed but a step-by-step guide to becoming more blessed.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251231-christian_beatitudes/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251231-christian_beatitudes/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Buddhist Noble Eightfold Path</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<ol>
<li>Right understanding (Samma ditthi)</li>
<li>Right thought (Samma sankappa)</li>
<li>Right speech (Samma vaca)</li>
<li>Right action (Samma kammanta)</li>
<li>Right livelihood (Samma ajiva)</li>
<li>Right effort (Samma vayama)</li>
<li>Right mindfulness (Samma sati)</li>
<li>Right concentration (Samma samadhi)</li>
</ol>
<p>Buddhism has Four Noble Truths: There is suffering, suffering is
caused by desire, freedom from suffering can come from ending desire,
and the path to do this is the Noble Eightfold Path.</p>
<p>English versions vary; I like the version quoted above which comes
from <a href="https://tricycle.org/magazine/noble-eightfold-path/">Tricycle</a>. Interpretations vary somewhat as well, but one
reading is as a step-by-step guide.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251231-buddhist_noble_eightfold_path/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251231-buddhist_noble_eightfold_path/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The UK's Seven Principles of Public Life</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<ul>
<li>Selflessness</li>
<li>Integrity</li>
<li>Objectivity</li>
<li>Accountability</li>
<li>Openness</li>
<li>Honesty</li>
<li>Leadership</li>
</ul>
<p>The UK's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Committee_on_Standards_in_Public_Life">Committee on Standards in Public Life</a> was created in
response to issues of corruption in the government and published its
<a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-7-principles-of-public-life/the-7-principles-of-public-life--2">Seven Principles</a>, also known as the Nolan principles after the
committee's initial chair.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251230-uk_seven_principles_of_public_life/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251230-uk_seven_principles_of_public_life/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>U.S. Army Values</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<ul>
<li>Loyalty</li>
<li>Duty</li>
<li>Respect</li>
<li>Selfless service</li>
<li>Honor</li>
<li>Integrity</li>
<li>Personal courage</li>
</ul>
<p>The U.S. Army <a href="https://www.army.mil/values/">defines</a> "honor" as being "a matter of carrying out,
acting, and living" the other six values in the list.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251230-us_army_values/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251230-us_army_values/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>DoorDash's Values</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<ul>
<li>We are leaders.<ul>
<li>Be an owner</li>
<li>Dream big start small</li>
<li>Choose optimism and have a plan</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>We are doers.<ul>
<li>Bias for action</li>
<li>Operate at the lowest level of detail</li>
<li>And not either/or</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>We are learners.<ul>
<li>Truth seek</li>
<li>1% better every day</li>
<li>Customer-obsessed, not competitor focused</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>We are one team.<ul>
<li>Make room at the table</li>
<li>Think outside the room</li>
<li>One team, one fight</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>These are taken directly from <a href="https://careersatdoordash.com/mission-and-values/">DoorDash</a>. I don't know much about
the history of their development. It is interesting that they arrange
their 12 values into sections this way; I haven't seen that elsewhere
yet.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251230-doordash_values/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251230-doordash_values/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Quaker Testimonies</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<ul>
<li>Simplicity</li>
<li>Peace</li>
<li>Integrity (Truth)</li>
<li>Community</li>
<li>Equality</li>
<li>Stewardship</li>
</ul>
<p>Quakers are interesting. The list here is the SPICES list of
Testimonies, or values, which appears for example on the
<a href="https://www.quakersdc.org/quaker-values">DC Quakers site</a>. A list of four items (Simplicity, Truth,
Equality, Peace) is also common, for example appearing on the
<a href="https://www.quaker.org.uk/faith/read-about-quaker-faith">UK Quakers site</a>.</p>
<p>As the two versions suggest, Quakers don't have to agree on much.
Different "Yearly Meetings" put together their own books. Here's a
selection from the <a href="https://www.bym-rsf.org/file_download/inline/281d7f8f-f578-4b0a-baeb-8ab753a30320">Faith and Practice</a> of the Baltimore Yearly
Meeting:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Baltimore Yearly Meeting has no binding creed. Its principles of
belief are based on its Judeo-Christian heritage and adherence to
the Spirit of Christ (the Inward Light, the Divine Seed, That of God
in Everyone). The testimonies spring from respect for truth; for
peace, harmony, and a settled intention to practice love; for
simplicity, community, and the equal worth of all people.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>No fixed list of Testimonies, then, is official. Some Quaker Friends
even <a href="https://www.friendsjournal.org/categorically-not-the-testimonies/">object</a> to them:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Human beings need words to communicate. But when we codify, make
creeds, and canonize a few words, we limit our vision, as well as
the possibility of God’s work through us. Walking away from such
deified virtues, where might we go instead? What if we were to start
with fresh, personal experiences and then shared them in a manner
that was as mediated as little as possible by advance expectations?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's an interesting and characteristically Quaker objection.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251229-quaker_testimonies/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251229-quaker_testimonies/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Noise, by Kahneman, Sibony, and Sunstein</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="/2011/12/17/selections-from-and-thoughts-on/">Thinking, Fast and Slow</a> was about bias, and now <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noise:_A_Flaw_in_Human_Judgment">Noise</a> is about
variance. It even opens with the classic two-by-two accuracy and
precision bullseye <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bias%E2%80%93variance_tradeoff#Motivation">illustration</a>. But the book is really about how
people are systematically different from one another. The book
considers federated systems in which work items are assigned to
different people, and concludes that most of the "variance" comes from
stable differences between those people.</p>
<p><img alt="breakdown" src="breakdown.jpg"></p>
<p>(I am a fan of the <a href="/20201030-the_variance_sum_law_is_interesting/">variance sum law</a>.)</p>
<p>In the book's phrasing, "system noise" is variance in outcomes,
distinct from bias. System noise is the sum of "level noise," which is
stable differences in average outcomes per person - "strict judge vs.
lenient judge" - and "stable pattern noise," which is stable
differences in how individuals are overfit, in the ML sense, - "Bob's
generally strict but always lenient with young mothers" - and
"occasion noise," which is true repeat-performance noise based on
randomness from somewhere (conditions, etc.).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>while the existence of occasion noise is surprising and even
disturbing, there is no indication that within-person variability is
larger than between-person differences. The most important component
of system noise is the one we had initially neglected: stable
pattern noise, the variability among judges in their judgments of
particular cases.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(Note also that "level noise" can be properly thought of as just an
average over "pattern noise" - I'm not sure it's correct to treat it
separately.)</p>
<p>The challenge, not sufficiently addressed, in my opinion, is that
removing this "noise" requires not just choosing one answer to be the
right one, but convincing the people involved. This is a societal
challenge. Whatever level of strictness or leniency you choose, for
the judges, some judges will disagree.</p>
<p>I think Kahneman neglects the extent to which systems exist through
false consensus: It isn't possible to get everyone to agree on the
details, so the system has to be made vague enough that everyone can
<em>think</em> it says what they want. Then they can go on having differences
of opinion.</p>
<p>Not that this is good, exactly. It's politics.</p>
<p>And Kahneman does talk about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Na%C3%AFve_realism_(psychology)">naïve realism</a> and the illusion of
agreement, so this idea isn't totally absent from the book. But just
like hand-washing took (and takes) surprisingly much effort, there's a
big gap between <em>having</em> a Gawande-style checklist and getting it
accepted and followed, for example.</p>
<p>There were interesting bits about how groups can have opposite
effects: Averaging independent outcomes can decrease noise, but
discussion can actually amplify noise. They recommend techniques like
"estimate-talk-estimate" to try to get positive effects.</p>
<p>Kahneman also emphasizes "percent concordant" and always includes it
with correlation coefficients. This is exactly the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Probability_of_superiority">Common Language Effect Size</a> which goes by many names. I'm a fan!
Glad to have Kahneman supporting this here. It sure would be nice if
it went from zero to one though.</p>
<p>Another interesting topic is what Kahneman calls “objective ignorance”
and is very tightly related to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayes_error_rate">Bayes error rate</a> or
"irreducible error." It made me wonder, when we're talking about
variance explained, if 60% is "irreducible," then maybe explaining 20%
is quite a strong result, actually. Unclear how to be quite confident
about this kind of thing though. Bad news for <a href="/20200714-foundation_trilogy/">psychohistory</a> too.
(How much is chaos?)</p>
<p>Kahneman chastises people for feeling they're 80% confident about a
given decision if they'll only be right 60% of the time. But there's a
difference he ignores, I think: You could be 80% confident that you
made the best possible decision given your information at the time,
and still be right just 60% of the time. Those can be consistent.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/dietrich/sds/docs/dawes/the-robust-beauty-of-improper-linear-models-in-decision-making.pdf">The Robust Beauty of Improper Linear Models in Decision Making</a>
(just give everything equal weight) is interesting. I wonder whether
some big chunk of AI "success" will essentially come from this kind of
effect, just the benefit of statistical instead of clinical judgement,
but the fanciness of AI will make it more palatable.</p>
<p>There's bits on incorporating the base rate, which feels like being
Bayesian. Don't overfit, etc. And be actively open-minded.</p>
<p>What is the right way to average predictions of superforecasters? Is
it just simple arithmetic mean? Or is it some other mean that works
best?</p>
<p>Long ago I was in a start-up that didn't do annual performance
reviews. I thought it was radical and great. So it was interesting to
hear that apparently more companies are moving away from annual
performance reviews.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>And if your goal is to bring out the best in people, you can
reasonably ask whether measuring individual performance and using
that measurement to motivate people through fear and greed is the
best approach (or even an effective one).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The book finishes out with some discussion of rules vs. standards,
where rules are more mechanical and standards still allow some
discussion while being more prescriptive than just principles.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<h3>Six principles of decision hygiene</h3>
<ol>
<li>The goal of judgment is accuracy, not individual expression.</li>
<li>Think statistically, and take the outside view of the case.</li>
<li>Structure judgments into several independent tasks.</li>
<li>Resist premature intuitions.</li>
<li>Obtain independent judgments from multiple judges, then consider
aggregating those judgments.</li>
<li>Favor relative judgments and relative scales.</li>
</ol>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251229-noise_by_kahneman_sibony_and_sunstein/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251229-noise_by_kahneman_sibony_and_sunstein/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Psychology of Money, by Housel</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Housel had a <a href="https://collabfund.com/blog/the-psychology-of-money/">blog post</a> in 2018, and it was big enough that it
became a <a href="https://planetone.online/downloads/others/books/The_Psychology_of_Money.pdf">book</a> in 2020. It's wild how many books come about that
way now; it's like your proposal has to go viral before you get a book
deal.</p>
<p>The blog post and book are structured similarly <em>enough</em> that I think
it's interesting to compare them.</p>
<p>The blog post was a list of 20 items. I think 7 of them don't really
appear in the book at all, perhaps because they're too wonky or
specific:</p>
<ul>
<li>(9) Attachment to social proof in a field that demands contrarian
   thinking to achieve above-average results.</li>
<li>(10) An appeal to academia in a field that is governed not by clean
   rules but loose and unpredictable trends.</li>
<li>(12) A tendency toward action in a field where the first rule of
   compounding is to never interrupt it unnecessarily.</li>
<li>(15) An attachment to financial entertainment due to the fact that
   money is emotional, and emotions are revved up by argument, extreme
   views, flashing lights, and threats to your wellbeing.</li>
<li>(17) A preference for skills in a field where skills don’t matter
   if they aren’t matched with the right behavior.</li>
<li>(19) Political beliefs driving financial decisions, influenced by
   economics being a misbehaved cousin of politics.</li>
<li>(20) The three-month bubble: Extrapolating the recent past into the
   near future, and then overestimating the extent to which whatever
   you anticipate will happen in the near future will impact your
   future.</li>
</ul>
<p>The book, then, has 18 items: 13 from the blog post's list, and 5 that
are new (at least new as whole sections). The book has an intro, and
two other chapters in which are a summary and a breakdown of the
author's personal money choices, and then there's a postscript with
his "brief history of why the U.S. consumer thinks the way they do,"
which is something like "after WWII people got used to a little bit of
equality and a little bit of debt, and now they're using too much debt
to try to get back a little bit of equality".</p>
<p>Here are the book's chapters, with blog equivalents (original blog
post numbering in parens) and notes:</p>
<ol>
<li>No One's Crazy: Your personal experiences with money make up maybe
   0.00000001% of what's happened in the world, but maybe 80% of how
   you think the world works.<ul>
<li>(5) Anchored-to-your-own-history bias: Your personal experiences
  make up maybe 0.00000001% of what’s happened in the world but
  maybe 80% of how you think the world works.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Luck &amp; Risk: Nothing is as good or as bad as it seems.<ul>
<li>(1) Earned success and deserved failure fallacy: A tendency to
  underestimate the role of luck and risk, and a failure to
  recognize that luck and risk are different sides of the same
  coin.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Never Enough: When rich people do crazy things.<ul>
<li>This is the first new section, and it's about greed, in fairly
  extreme cases where successful people were found to have
  committed fraud even when you wouldn't think they'd need to. I
  think the section has noble intent but fails because (a) you
  have to believe that these people's <em>earlier</em> success was
  non-fraudulent, which is suspect (Madoff's earlier "success" was
  based on payment for order flow, it seems, which is illegal in
  Canada and disliked by many in the US) and (b) the general theme
  of avarice need not go so far as fraud to be worthwhile. See,
  for example, <a href="/20251123-your_money_or_your_life/">Your money or your life</a>. On the other hand,
  maybe it's easier to talk about greed with extreme cases so that
  the reader can safely revile them without finding them familiar.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Confounding Compounding: $81.5 billion of Warren Buffett's $84.5
   billion net worth came after his 65th birthday. Our minds are not
   built to handle such absurdities.<ul>
<li>(8) Underappreciating the power of compounding, driven by the
  tendency to intuitively think about exponential growth in linear
  terms.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Getting Wealthy vs. Staying Wealthy: Good investing is not
   necessarily about making good decisions. It's about consistently
   not screwing up.<ul>
<li>(16) Optimism bias in risk-taking, or “Russian Roulette should
  statistically work” syndrome: An over attachment to favorable
  odds when the downside is unacceptable in any circumstance.</li>
<li>This one is tangled up with 13, and indeed includes "the most
  important part of every plan is to plan on the plan not going
  according to plan" here too. The distinction, perhaps, is about
  not actively <em>doing</em> things that risk ruining you, as opposed to
  defensively <em>protecting yourself</em> from outside forces ruining
  you.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Tails, You Win: You can be wrong half the time and still make a
   fortune.<ul>
<li>This is a new one, about making lots of bets. Assuming no bet
  can kill you, you only need a minority of them to do really well
  in order to win.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Freedom: Controlling your time is the highest dividend money pays.<ul>
<li>This appeared in the blog post in passing ("A key use of wealth
  is using it to control your time") but it's grown into a whole
  section and maybe even a theme in the book.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Man in the Car Paradox: No one is impressed with your possessions
   as much as you are.<ul>
<li>(3) Rich man in the car paradox</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Wealth is What You Don't See: Spending money to show people how
   much money you have is the fastest way to have less money.<ul>
<li>(11) The social utility of money coming at the direct expense of
  growing money; wealth is what you don’t see.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Save Money: The only factor you can control generates one of the
    only things that matters. How wonderful.<ul>
<li>Also new, and quite explicitly advice.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Reasonable &gt; Rational: Aiming to be mostly reasonable works better
    than trying to be coldly rational.<ul>
<li>There's some of the "avoid Russian roulette" idea here, but this
  is mostly new... It's a little bit like how the "snowball
  method" of paying off small debts first is often a bad idea
  financially - unless doing it that way makes the difference
  between paying off debt and not doing so. Also sort of related
  to the idea of knowing the price of things: there can be a
  psychological price, which can be meaningful for an individual.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Surprise! History is the study of change, ironically used as a map
    of the future.<ul>
<li>(6) Historians are Prophets fallacy: Not seeing the irony that
  history is the study of surprises and changes while using it as
  a guide to the future. An overreliance on past data as a signal
  to future conditions in a field where innovation and change is
  the lifeblood of progress.</li>
<li>Vonnegut: “History is merely a list of surprises,' I said. 'It
  can only prepare us to be surprised yet again. Please write that
  down.” Housel has written it down.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Room for Error: The most important part of every plan is planning
    on your plan not going according to plan.<ul>
<li>(13) Underestimating the need for room for error, not just
  financially but mentally and physically.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>You'll Change: Long-term planning is harder than it seems because
    people's goals and desires change over time.<ul>
<li>(4) A tendency to adjust to current circumstances in a way that
  makes forecasting your future desires and actions difficult,
  resulting in the inability to capture long-term compounding
  rewards that come from current decisions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Nothing's Free: Everything has a price, but not all prices appear
    on labels.<ul>
<li>(2) Cost avoidance syndrome: A failure to identify the true
  costs of a situation, with too much emphasis on financial costs
  while ignoring the emotional price that must be paid to win a
  reward.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>You &amp; Me: Beware taking financial cues from people playing a
    different game than you are.<ul>
<li>(14) A tendency to be influenced by the actions of other people
  who are playing a different financial game than you are.</li>
<li>He's talking about bubbles. People driving up bubbles are not
  long-term investors, he says.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The Seduction of Pessimism: Optimism sounds like a sales pitch.
    Pessimism sounds like someone trying to help you.<ul>
<li>(7) The seduction of pessimism in a world where optimism is the
  most reasonable stance.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>When You'll Believe Anything: Appealing fictions, and why stories
    are more powerful than statistics.<ul>
<li>(18) Denial of inconsistencies between how you think the world
  should work and how the world actually works, driven by a desire
  to form a clean narrative of cause and effect despite the
  inherent complexities of everything involving money.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>All Together Now: What we've learned about the psychology of your
    own money.<ul>
<li>This is just a summary, as the heading suggests.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Confessions: The psychology of my own money.<ul>
<li>And here the author describes his own money choices, which I
  find reasonable.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p>It's not all great, but it's not bad. Mostly reasonable advice, I
think. I feel like I agree with this guy. The repeated focus on
<em>survival,</em> for example, fits well with my ongoing vendetta against
expected value as the be-all and end-all of decision-making.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.png"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Most of the reason why, I believe, is that we think about and are
taught about money in ways that are too much like physics (with
rules and laws) and not enough like psychology (with emotions and
nuance).</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Someone else agreeing with you is like evidence of being right that
doesn’t have to prove itself with facts.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Money has competition, rules, upsets, wins, losses, heroes,
villains, teams, and fans that makes it tantalizingly close to a
sporting event.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Everyone just believes what they want to believe, even when the
evidence shows something else. Stories over statistics.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The New York Times wrote in 1955 about the growing desire, but
continued inability, to retire: “To rephrase an old saying: everyone
talks about retirement, but apparently very few do anything about
it.”</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Mr. Madoff’s firm can execute trades so quickly and cheaply that it
actually pays other brokerage firms a penny a share to execute their
customers’ orders, profiting from the spread between bid and ask
prices that most stocks trade for.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The End of History Illusion is what psychologists call the tendency
for people to be keenly aware of how much they’ve changed in the
past, but to underestimate how much their personalities, desires,
and goals are likely to change in the future.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Jason Zweig, the Wall Street Journal investment columnist, worked
with psychologist Daniel Kahneman on writing Kahneman’s book
Thinking, Fast and Slow. Zweig once told a story about a personality
quirk of Kahneman’s that served him well: “Nothing amazed me more
about Danny than his ability to detonate what we had just done,”
Zweig wrote. He and Kahneman could work endlessly on a chapter, but:</p>
<p>The next thing you know, [Kahneman] sends a version so utterly
transformed that it is unrecognizable: It begins differently, it
ends differently, it incorporates anecdotes and evidence you never
would have thought of, it draws on research that you’ve never heard
of.</p>
<p>“When I asked Danny how he could start again as if we had never
written an earlier draft,” Zweig continued, “he said the words I’ve
never forgotten: ‘I have no sunk costs.’”</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Bubbles form when the momentum of short-term returns attracts enough
money that the makeup of investors shifts from mostly long term to
mostly short term.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>And since big events come out of nowhere, forecasts may do more harm
than good, giving the illusion of predictability in a world where
unforeseen events control most outcomes.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>We’re so far committed to the independence camp that we’ve done
things that make little sense on paper. We own our house without a
mortgage, which is the worst financial decision we’ve ever made but
the best money decision we’ve ever made. Mortgage interest rates
were absurdly low when we bought our house. Any rational advisor
would recommend taking advantage of cheap money and investing extra
savings in higher-return assets, like stocks. But our goal isn’t to
be coldly rational; just psychologically reasonable.</p>
<p>The independent feeling I get from owning our house outright far
exceeds the known financial gain I’d get from leveraging our assets
with a cheap mortgage. Eliminating the monthly payment feels better
than maximizing the long-term value of our assets. It makes me feel
independent. I don’t try to defend this decision to those pointing
out its flaws, or those who would never do the same. On paper it’s
defenseless. But it works for us. We like it. That’s what matters.
Good decisions aren’t always rational. At some point you have to
choose between being happy or being “right.”</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>One of my deeply held investing beliefs is that there is little
correlation between investment effort and investment results.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Benedict Evans says, “The more the Internet exposes people to new
points of view, the angrier people get that different views exist.”</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251228-psychology_of_money_by_housel/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251228-psychology_of_money_by_housel/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Amazon's Leadership Principles</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<ol>
<li><strong>Customer Obsession</strong> (initial core principle, 1998)</li>
<li><strong>Ownership</strong> (initial core principle, 1998)</li>
<li><strong>Invent and Simplify</strong> (early 2000s)</li>
<li><strong>Are Right, A Lot</strong> (early 2000s)</li>
<li><strong>Learn and Be Curious</strong> (added 2015)</li>
<li><strong>Hire and Develop the Best</strong> (initial core principle, as "high bar
   for talent", 1998)</li>
<li><strong>Insist on the Highest Standards</strong> (early 2000s)</li>
<li><strong>Think Big</strong> (early 2000s)</li>
<li><strong>Bias for Action</strong> (initial core principle, 1998)</li>
<li><strong>Frugality</strong> (initial core principle, 1998)</li>
<li><strong>Earn Trust</strong> (early 2000s)</li>
<li><strong>Dive Deep</strong> (early 2000s)</li>
<li><strong>Have Backbone; Disagree and Commit</strong> (early 2000s)</li>
<li><strong>Deliver Results</strong> (early 2000s)</li>
<li><strong>Strive to be Earth’s Best Employer</strong> (added 2021)</li>
<li><strong>Success and Scale Bring Broad Responsibility</strong> (added 2021)</li>
</ol>
<p>Lots more detail on <a href="https://www.amazon.jobs/content/en/our-workplace/leadership-principles">Amazon's page</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Former:</p>
<ul>
<li>Innovation (added to the initial core principles, circa 1998)</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>I don't know any company that's as into a set of principles as Amazon
is. See <a href="/20210903-working_backwards_by_bryar_and_carr/">Working Backwards</a>, for example, on how they're deeply
integrated into hiring and performance review processes.</p>
<p>The Leadership Principles started as company core principles in 1998,
part of spreading Amazon culture across newly acquired companies.
("Customer Obsession" might be considered to precede even this list,
as it was sort of a founding ethos of Amazon.)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Amazon’s purchase of Telebuch in Germany and BookPages in the UK in
1998 gave Bezos an opportunity to articulate the company’s core
principles. Alison Algore, a D. E. Shaw transplant who worked in
human resources, pondered Amazon’s values with Bezos as he prepared
for an introductory conference call with the Telebuch founders. They
agreed on five core values and wrote them down on a whiteboard in a
conference room: <em>customer obsession, frugality, bias for action,
ownership,</em> and <em>high bar for talent.</em> Later Amazon would add a
sixth value, innovation. (from <a href="https://prachititg.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/the-everything-store-jeff-bezos-and-the-age-of-amazon.pdf">The Everything Store</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Leadership Principles appeared with that name at some point in the
early 2000s, though I haven't been able to lock down precise details
on this. It seems they were fairly stable as a list of 13 principles
from the early 2000s until 2015.</p>
<p>Leadership Principle 5 was <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/executive-insights/content/leading-and-innovating-with-leadership-principles/">added</a> in 2015.</p>
<p>In 2021, Amazon
<a href="https://www.aboutamazon.com/news/company-news/two-new-leadership-principles">added</a>
Leadership Principles 15 and 16 as Andy Jassy was becoming CEO.</p>
<hr>
<p>It sounds like teams at Amazon also often have around five or six
"<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5raEKA57PMY">tenets</a>," which are about what the team aims to be and do. This
<a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90334069/these-are-amazons-38-rules-for-success">article</a> includes Amazon HR's tenets, for example.</p>
<p>Amazon often accompanies tenets with the <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/enterprise-strategy/tenets-supercharging-decision-making/">phrase</a> "unless you know
better ones," which is a neat way of trying to keep them evolving.</p>
<hr>
<p>That same <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90334069/these-are-amazons-38-rules-for-success">article</a> has a list of ways that Amazon is peculiar, in
their parlance. (There's a mascot named <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90329525/amazon-peccy">Peccy</a>!)</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251216-amazon_leadership_principles/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251216-amazon_leadership_principles/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Your money or your life, by Robin and Dominguez</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://files.addictbooks.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Your-Money-or-Your-Life.pdf">This</a> is the 2018 revised edition, not the 1992 original, but it's
still arguably the antecedent to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FIRE_movement">FIRE</a> (Financial Independence,
Retire Early) movement and now even features a foreword from
<a href="https://www.mrmoneymustache.com/">Mr. Money Mustache</a>. It's a nine-step program.</p>
<ol>
<li>Figure out how much money you've earned in your whole life, and
   your current net worth.</li>
<li>Figure out your "real hourly wage," and track all your income and
   spending.</li>
<li>Catalog monthly spending into custom categories for you.</li>
<li>Evaluate how you feel about your spending, by category.</li>
<li>Make a monthly chart tracking your income and spending.</li>
<li>Minimize spending.</li>
<li>Maximize income.</li>
<li>Accumulate money toward a crossover point where you can live on
   investment income.</li>
<li>Invest in fairly boring ways to generate income you can live on.</li>
</ol>
<p>It's reasonable advice and I generally agree. I was a little surprised
by the extent to which the book is really "degrowth," in the sense of
<a href="/20240519-survival_of_the_richest_by_rushkoff/">Rushkoff</a>. It's really not about "fat FIRE," but about
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simple_living">simple living</a>, or voluntary simplicity, not just as an expedient
for retirement, but as a moral-environmental imperative.</p>
<p>I liked how <a href="/20241116-weve_got_you_covered_by_einav_and_finkelstein/">We've got you covered</a> was very clear about the
decision inherent in health insurance about what to cover versus not
cover. This book is clear about the decision regarding how much is
"enough" spending for life in general.</p>
<p>I think the choice about how much is "enough" is interesting as a
personal choice, and also an interesting topic in connection with
<a href="/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>. (What level of luxury?) I don't
think this figure ("The Fulfillment Curve") is super great though:</p>
<p><img src="fulfillment.jpg" width="480px"></p>
<p>The justification in the text is that people report similar
"fulfillment" across a wide range of incomes, and that at some point
you get more "clutter" than real fulfillment. I don't think it's
<em>completely</em> wrong, but it's close. I feel like there could be
something here about finding fulfillment in better ways, living in
community and participating in the work that supports that community,
equality being healthier than subjugation of the poor by the rich,
that kind of thing. But at the very least this kind of claim needs
more evidence and fewer headstones tossed on the graph.</p>
<p>It's a fine book with a distinct voice. It talks about "consciousness"
and "life energy" constantly. It says that since you spend time
earning money, money is equivalent with "life energy," which kind of
works in the framework of the book but doesn't raise to the next
natural level, as a critique of the conditions of capitalism.</p>
<p>The author is also into "<a href="http://conversationcafe.org/">conversation café</a>s," which seem like they
could be neat.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251123-your_money_or_your_life/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251123-your_money_or_your_life/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Breakneck, by Dan Wang</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>It's about China as contrasted with the US, mostly via critiques as in
<a href="/20251120-abundance_klein_thompson/">Abundance</a>. The US is "the lawyerly society" and China is "the
engineering state," and while the one child and zero covid policies
are criticized (for example) the eventual recommendation is to be more
like China, more like Robert Moses.</p>
<hr>
<p>I learned about China's "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Industrial_Party_(China)">Industrial Party</a>," which is interesting.
Sort of techno-optimism as a nationalist prescription.</p>
<p>Does anybody else remember Vonnegut's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slapstick_(novel)">Slapstick</a>? In which "Western
civilization is nearing collapse as oil runs out, and the Chinese are
making vast leaps forward by miniaturizing themselves and training
groups of hundreds to think as one. Eventually, the miniaturization
proceeds to the point that the Chinese become so small they cause a
plague among those who accidentally inhale them, ultimately destroying
Western civilization beyond repair."</p>
<hr>
<p>There's some interesting stuff about process knowledge and encouraging
communities of practice. I don't know whether this is what makes
Shenzhen successful, or whether the lack of it is what's troubled
Boeing, but I agree that process knowledge is <em>something</em> and that
it's too often ignored or undervalued.</p>
<p>Is Boeing's problem really loss of process knowledge, or is the
problem too much belief in the Friedman doctrine, too much blind focus
on near-term profit?</p>
<hr>
<p>I tried to find where Heidegger said that philosophy was dying, to be
replaced with cybernetics, and it seems to be
<a href="https://grattoncourses.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/22the-end-of-philosophy-and-the-task-of-thinking22.pdf">The End of Philosophy and the Task of Thinking</a>. How could anyone
ever be taken seriously who wrote like this?</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Only a country ruled by engineers could be so single-minded about
pursuing a number. (page 123)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This reminds me of <a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>, and the kind of cynical
"data driven" perversions you can find in industry.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In the United States, physics and mathematics PhDs hardly have a
chance to consider working in their field before a tech giant or
hedge fund picks them up at the sidelines of a conference, flashes
them with a humongous pay package, and folds these eager minds into
their glamorous embrace. Senior government advisers have more or
less stated that Beijing intends to block these temptations. Yao
Yang, a dean at Peking University, has remarked with satisfaction
that salaries have fallen in the financial industry after regulators
imposed a salary cap of $400,000 on the financial sector. Its idea,
Yao said, “is to reduce the attractiveness of finance and to
increase the development of manufacturing.” (page 162)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This reminds me of Jeff Hammerbacher's quote, "The best minds of my
generation are thinking about how to make people click ads. That
sucks."</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251120-breakneck_by_wang/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251120-breakneck_by_wang/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Abundance, by Klein and Thompson</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I started listening to Dunkelman's <a href="https://www.hachettebookgroup.com/titles/marc-j-dunkelman/why-nothing-works/9781541700215/">Why Nothing Works</a>, but
abandoned it. Ezra Klein's name, I think, is why I made it through the
similar <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abundance_(Klein_and_Thompson_book)">Abundance</a>. Crazy culturally mediated world.</p>
<p>I was very pleased that Klein explicitly references
<a href="/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>. <a href="https://wwnorton.com/books/9781324106036">Breakneck</a> turns out to be
substantially similar to Abundance as well, and references it. The
general vibe has been in the air.</p>
<p>The vibe is: Regulate less, build more. Less restriction, more
expansion. Less red tape, more research.</p>
<p>This requires giving government more room to act, which makes sense if
the government is going to do the right things. Power is needed to do
big things, but its tendency to corrupt may still be an issue.</p>
<p>Some interesting references: <a href="https://homelessnesshousingproblem.com/">Homelessness is a housing problem.</a>
<a href="https://wtfhappenedin1971.com/">WTF Happened In 1971?</a> Apparently the US has four times as many
lawyers per capita as France.</p>
<p>There are hints of <a href="/20221105-why_greatness_cannot_be_planned_by_stanley_and_lehman/">Why greatness cannot be planned</a> in Thompson's
second half on science and technology. It makes me wonder about the
limits of fully federated action, as opposed to central control. What
truly requires the power of a government, a university?</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Just as feudalism blocked production that only capitalism could
unleash, so did capitalism constrain an abundance that a new
paradigm might unleash. Core to this analysis of the economy was an
idea that has come to be called the “fettering of production.” Marx
observed that many companies’ obsession with profit kept the entire
economy from exploring ideas that threatened incumbent margins or
failed to produce immediate returns. Among capitalism’s many sins,
Marx wrote, was that it prevented the most wondrous and useful
technology from being invented and deployed in the first place. An
economy run amok with useless fettering serves the rich few at the
expense of the poorer many. (page 127)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251120-abundance_klein_thompson/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251120-abundance_klein_thompson/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Radically condensed instructions for being just as you are</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This funny little <a href="https://www.scribd.com/document/165080210/Radically-Condensed-Instructions-for-Bei-Matthews-J-Jennifer">book</a> was mentioned in <a href="/20250921-four_thousand_weeks_by_burkeman/">Four Thousand Weeks</a>.
It's on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nondualism">nonduality</a>. The title joke seems to be that usually people
say even more, writing on this topic, when arguably not much needs to
be said. There are still pretty many words here, and many of them are
"poignancy."</p>
<p>My personal philosophy has some affinity with this nondualism stuff.
My starting point is that experience is the only thing we have direct
experience of. Nondualists seem to argue that this should be both
starting point and ending point. I'm all about living in the moment
and all, but I tend to feel that just because we can't prove things
exist, it doesn't mean we shouldn't believe that they do. But it's
okay to grant that this is a leap.</p>
<p>There's some cute discussion of how trying too hard to live in the
moment is a good way to take yourself out of the moment. I think this
is kind of like falling asleep: trying to make yourself fall asleep is
stressful. You have to relax, and again, you don't relax by trying
hard to relax. Also like meditating, where you aim to let thoughts
come and let them go, not by trying hard to do this, but by not
trying. So we have a "philosophy of not-philosophy," and a perfect
practitioner doesn't need to read this book. I'm not sure the
comparison is perfect, but it reminds me of Star Wars: "I don't know;
fly casual."</p>
<p>Thinking about this more, I wonder if what <a href="/20250921-four_thousand_weeks_by_burkeman/">Four Thousand Weeks</a> is
really trying to offer is a time management of not-time-management.
The idea that you shouldn't be trying to manage time, but that you
should be living and doing things without worrying about the time
management. I think there's something here: getting in the flow of
doing something, not focusing on planning but on doing, etc. This
feels like a better interpretation of <a href="/20250921-four_thousand_weeks_by_burkeman/">Four Thousand Weeks</a> than I
had previously given it. (Maybe better than it really deserves...)</p>
<p>Anyway, sure, cute short book.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Life is the most incredible mystery.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>We can not get anything out of life. There is no outside where we
could take this thing to. There is no little pocket situated outside
of life, which would steal life’s provisions and squirrel them away.
The life of this moment has no outside where. (page 27)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Perception is the very fabric of experience! How could it exist in a
head? (page 44)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20251003-radically_condensed_instructions_by_matthews/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20251003-radically_condensed_instructions_by_matthews/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Four Thousand Weeks, by Burkeman</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
<p>“You could think of this book as an extended argument for the
empowering potential of giving up hope.” (page 231)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Burkeman's subtitle is "Time Management for Mortals," but the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_Thousand_Weeks:_Time_Management_for_Mortals">book</a>
is mostly (though not entirely) opposed to time management. Some
advice is decent, but the core focus on mortality is dead on arrival.
The book is fairly incoherent as a whole, but it has made me think.</p>
<p>The author has many critiques of (other) productivity books. These
critiques are mostly wrong or exaggerated. One that I did find
meaningful was that often productivity is tied to the false belief
that things that aren't measured aren't valuable, as in
<a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>. This makes "productivity" sort of
self-centered, often; it isn't "productive" to volunteer, or engage in
civic life generally, to know local issues, to vote. This kind of
measurement-obsessed productivity, usually implicitly career-oriented,
becomes a misdirection of energy.</p>
<p>Burkeman accuses productivity advice of being unsustainable, but comes
down too far in the other direction, as if noting that it isn't
possible to sprint forever before concluding that all attempts to
cover distance are futile. This feels like the common tension between
accepting things exactly as they are as opposed to hating things as
they are and pushing to change them at all costs. As usual, neither
extreme is really great.</p>
<p>Burkeman wants you to live in the moment, which I tend to support as
well, but I don't agree with the reasoning having to come from
mortality. Fear of death can't really make you live in the moment;
death is in the future. Infinite life also wouldn't mean that choices
become meaningless; you would still have only one walk through the
garden of forking paths. Yes, value every moment—but not out of fear.
Not out of a scarcity mindset.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman references Seneca's <a href="/20240105-seneca_de_brevitate_vitae/">De Brevitate Vitae</a> on page four. I
think at some point he mentioned <a href="/20201107-how_to_live_on_24_hours_a_day/">How to Live on 24 Hours a Day</a> as
well.</p>
<hr>
<p>On page eight Burkeman mentions three productivity books:
<a href="/2011/03/14/listened-to-four-hour-work-week/">The Four-Hour Work Week</a>, <a href="/20220327-smarter_faster_better_by_duhigg/">Smarter, Faster, Better</a>, and Extreme
Productivity. I've read the first two, and after looking briefly into
the last, it looks like all of them in fact do talk a lot about
prioritizing and saying "no" to things. Burkeman's characterization of
the productivity literature as somehow ignoring this seems unfair.</p>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman says on page nine that productivity works but makes us feel
busier. This has not been my experience. I feel less stress when
things are managed, and I'm able to confidently know that I've taken
care of what I needed to.</p>
<p>Some large chunk of good time management is just memory aids, I think:
Ways of organizing things so that they don't fall through the cracks
and create stressful problems later.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>This struggle against the distressing constraints of reality is what
some old-school psychoanalysts call "neurosis," and it takes
countless forms, from workaholism and commitment-phobia to
codependency and chronic shyness.</p>
<p>Our troubled relationship with time arises largely from the same
effort to avoid the painful constraints of reality. (page 30)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is an interesting characterization of neurosis, especially when
considered along with psychosis, in which neurosis is sort of fighting
against (or worrying about) reality, while psychosis is instead a
clear break with reality.</p>
<p>I'm not sure that's what people usually think of when they think
"neurosis," but it's kind of neat.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... I wrote this book for myself, as much as for anyone else,
putting my faith in the words of the author Richard Bach: "You teach
best what you most need to learn." (page 33)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Bach">Richard Bach</a> and his books including <em>Jonathan Livingston
Seagull</em> were apparently quite big in the 70s.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Think of it as “existential overwhelm”: the modern world provides an
inexhaustible supply of things that seem worth doing, and so there
arises an inevitable and unbridgeable gap between what you'd ideally
like to do and what you actually can do. (page 45)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The harder you struggle to fit everything in, the more of your time
you'll find yourself spending on the least meaningful things. Adopt
an ultra-ambitious time management system that promises to take care
of your entire to-do list, and you probably won't even get around to
the most important items on that list. Dedicate your retirement to
seeing as much of the world as you possibly can, and you probably
won't even get to see the most interesting parts. (page 48)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is ridiculous. Maybe this is where his whole argument falls
apart. It's just not true that you have to do everything, and I think
this passage illustrates the silliness of it. Who would literally aim
to see "as much of the world as you possibly can" and have that mean
devoting equal time to every square inch? For his claims here to make
any sense you have to imagine both having overwhelming and
indiscriminate FOMO and absolutely no sense of prioritization. Both
are problems to resolve, not axioms to reason from.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The most fundamental thing we fail to appreciate about the world,
Heidegger asserts in his magnum opus, <em>Being and Time,</em> is how
bafflingly astonishing it is that it’s there at all – the fact that
there is anything rather than nothing. Most philosophers and
scientists spend their careers pondering the <em>way</em> things are: what
sorts of things exist, where they come from, how they relate to each
other, and so on. But we’ve forgotten to be amazed <em>that</em> things are
in the first place – that ‘a world is worlding all around us’, as
Heidegger puts it. This fact – the fact that <em>there is being,</em> to
begin with – is ‘the brute reality on which all of us ought to be
constantly stubbing our toes’, in the splendid phrase of the writer
Sarah Bakewell. But instead, it almost always passes us by. (page
58)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I sometimes think a related thing, paraphrasing Descartes, "I think,
therefore something is going on." I tend to identify with this
Heidegger snippet. Existence is a miracle.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In his 2019 book, This Life, the Swedish philosopher Martin Hägglund
makes this all a bit clearer and less mystical by juxtaposing the
idea of facing our finitude with the religious belief in an eternal
life. If you really thought life would never end, he argues, then
nothing could ever genuinely matter, because you’d never be faced
with having to decide whether or not to use a portion of your
precious life on something. ‘If I believed that my life would last
forever,’ Hägglund writes, ‘I could never take my life to be at
stake, and I would never be seized by the need to do anything with
my time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This Hägglund may have some worthwhile things to say, but I think that
like Burkeman he's wrong to focus so much on death as the most
important thing, and wrong that without death nothing would matter.</p>
<p>I hear Hägglund is critical of capitalism, but I can't help but think
that the focus on finitude is a capitalist economic argument: if
supply (of time) is unlimited, then price (value) goes to zero. (I
don't believe this.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It is by consciously confronting the certainty of death, and what
follows from the certainty of death, that we finally become truly
present for our lives. (page 63)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>No, no, no. This might be one path of reasoning that helps a person
become more present, but it isn't the only or necessary path.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The real measure of any time management technique is <em>whether or not
it helps you neglect the right things.</em> (page 72)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>There's a section with these three principles:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pay yourself first</li>
<li>Limit your work in progress<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.personalkanban.com/">Personal Kanban</a> suggests
    limiting to three things.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Resist the allure of middling priorities</li>
</ul>
<p>This all seems like basically good advice.</p>
<hr>
<p>So this Bergson guy wrote <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_and_Free_Will">Time and free will</a> (mentioned on page
83) and, I mean, cool title, but otherwise doesn't seem that good,
especially if the thinking is similar in quality to Bergson's ideas
about motivated evolution.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Machine for misusing your life (page 94)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Burkeman mostly tries to avoid the appearance of value judgments by
framing the objective as spending time on what you value (whatever
that is) but he does come out clearly against social media. So you
better not value social media!</p>
<hr>
<p>There's an interesting sort of story about a monk's experience with
ice water, the point of which was that trying to ignore or deny the
experience of cold was worse than focusing on the experience and
accepting, living the experience.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>You're obliged to deal with how your experience is unfolding in this
moment, to resign yourself to the reality that <em>this is it.</em> (page
106)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He's trying to connect boredom to finitude in the sense of limited
lifespan, but he accidentally gives the lie to it. It isn't that
you're upset that you're using your limited time on Earth in a way
that isn't fun; it's that it isn't fun "in this moment."</p>
<p>He does talk about living in the moment, but doesn't seem to resolve
the conflict with the lifespan view.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The real problem isn’t planning. It’s that we take our plans to be
something they aren’t. What we forget, or can’t bear to confront, is
that, in the words of the American meditation teacher Joseph
Goldstein, ‘a plan is just a thought’. We treat our plans as though
they are a lasso, thrown from the present around the future, in
order to bring it under our command. But all a plan is – all it
could ever possibly be – is a present-moment statement of intent.
It’s an expression of your current thoughts about how you’d ideally
like to deploy your modest influence over the future. The future, of
course, is under no obligation to comply. (page 123)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This makes sense. What's the quote I think of... Eisenhower: "Plans
are worthless, but planning is everything." The plan has no influence
over the future, but it does help you make decisions in the moments
you encounter.</p>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman mentions
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/1456312030">Radically Condensed Instructions for Being Just as You Are</a>, which
is more nondualist, the-moment-is-all-there-is stuff.</p>
<p><em>Trying</em> to live in the moment is like trying too hard to sleep.
Trying to force it pushes you further from it. But on the other hand,
you have no other option but to be here now.</p>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman mentions Lafargue's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Right_to_Be_Lazy">The right to be lazy</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"According to Lafargue, wage labour is tantamount to slavery, and to
fight as a labour movement for the extension of slavery is
preposterous. In the book, Lafargue proposes the right to be lazy,
in contrast to the right to work, which he deems bourgeois."</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>‘Nothing is more alien to the present age than idleness,’ writes the
philosopher John Gray. He adds: ‘How can there be play in a time
when nothing has meaning unless it leads to something else?’ (page
154)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think Burkeman also talks about instrumental use of time and tourist
photography, the "stop taking pictures and experience it" argument.</p>
<p>I think of my "<a href="/20181204-worth_doing_even_if_it_fails/">Is it worth doing even if it fails?</a>" which I think
is somewhat related... value the act itself regardless of the outcome.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The publisher and editor Karen Rinaldi feels about surfing the same
way that I do about cheesy piano rock, only more so: she dedicates
every spare moment she can to it, and even wiped out her savings on
a plot of land in Costa Rica for better access to the sea. Yet she
readily admits that she remains an appalling surfer to this day. (It
took her five years of attempting to catch a wave before she first
managed to do so.) But ‘in the process of trying to attain a few
moments of bliss’, Rinaldi explains, ‘I experience something else:
patience and humility, definitely, but also freedom. Freedom to
pursue the futile. And the freedom to suck without caring is
revelatory.’ Results aren’t everything. Indeed, they’d better not
be, because results always come later – and later is always too
late. (page 160)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman talks about a painting called "Boy with a Squirrel," but that
painting is "A Boy with a Flying Squirrel." <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Boy_with_a_Flying_Squirrel">Flying</a>!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It depicts Copley's teenaged half-brother Henry Pelham with a pet
flying squirrel, a creature commonly found in colonial American
portraits as a symbol of the sitter's refinement.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>How cool is that!</p>
<hr>
<p>There are "Three principles of patience" (around page 180)</p>
<ul>
<li>Develop a taste for having problems<ul>
<li>This reminds me of my first "thinking card,"
   <a href="https://planspace.org/20201206-thinking_cards/#1">embrace problems</a>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Embrace radical incrementalism </li>
<li>Originality lies on the far side of unoriginality</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman has this idea, "cosmic insignificance therapy," which is
intended to be a relief. It reminds me of the
<a href="https://hitchhikers.fandom.com/wiki/Total_Perspective_Vortex">total perspective vortex</a> from The Hitchhiker's Guide to the
Galaxy, but of course there it was supposed to be a method of torture.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There is a sort of cruelty, Iddo Landau points out, in holding
yourself to standards nobody could ever reach (and which many of us
would never dream of demanding of other people). The more humane
approach is to drop such efforts as completely as you can. Let your
impossible standards crash to the ground. Then pick a few meaningful
tasks from the rubble and get started on them today. (page 222)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman mentions this documentary, <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt13675784/">A Life’s Work</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What's it like to dedicate your life to work that won't be completed
in your lifetime? Fifteen years ago, filmmaker David Licata focused
on four projects and the people behind them in an effort to answer
this universal question.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To me this is about caring about something, whether it makes sense or
not, making meaning for yourself, and not really at all about death.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>You could think of this book as an extended argument for the
empowering potential of giving up hope. (page 231)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20250921-four_thousand_weeks_by_burkeman/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20250921-four_thousand_weeks_by_burkeman/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) The Haves and Have-Yachts, by Osnos</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>It's kind of an interesting <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/The-Haves-and-Have-Yachts/Evan-Osnos/9781668204481">book</a>, collecting articles from The New
Yorker. "New gilded age" and so on. There's a whole chapter on
Zuckerberg, who sort of anchors the less-fraudulent side of the
spectrum. Wild and wacky stuff.</p>
<h3>The Haves and Have-Yachts</h3>
<ul>
<li>The rewards: How to spend it<ul>
<li>The floating world<ul>
<li>Yachts are the most expensive thing you can own.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Survival of the richest<ul>
<li>Bunkers and stuff. See also <a href="/20240519-survival_of_the_richest_by_rushkoff/" title="Survival of the Richest, by Rushkoff">Rushkoff</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>One for the money<ul>
<li>"Survival of the Richest, by Rushkoff"</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The mechanics: How to keep it<ul>
<li>Ghost in the machine<ul>
<li>"Can Mark Zuckerberg Fix Facebook Before It Breaks Democracy?"</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The Greenwich rebellion<ul>
<li>"How Greenwich Republicans Learned to Love Trump"</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Ruling-class rules<ul>
<li>"How to thrive in the power élite—while declaring it your enemy." (Tucker Carlson etc.)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Trust issues<ul>
<li>Grantor Retained Annuity Trusts (<a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/g/grat.asp">GRATs</a>) etc.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The perils: How to lose it<ul>
<li>Land of make-believe<ul>
<li>"The Biggest Ponzi Scheme in Hollywood History" (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zach_Avery">Zach Horwitz</a>)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Patriot games<ul>
<li>"How a Tycoon Linked to Chinese Intelligence Became a Darling of Trump Republicans" (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guo_Wengui">Guo Wengui</a>)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The big house<ul>
<li>"Life after white collar crime" (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeff_Grant_(attorney)">Jeff Grant</a>)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20250621-haves_and_have_yachts_by_osnos/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20250621-haves_and_have_yachts_by_osnos/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
