<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>Four Thousand Weeks, by Burkeman</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
<p>“You could think of this book as an extended argument for the
empowering potential of giving up hope.” (page 231)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Burkeman's subtitle is "Time Management for Mortals," but the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_Thousand_Weeks:_Time_Management_for_Mortals">book</a>
is mostly (though not entirely) opposed to time management. Some
advice is decent, but the core focus on mortality is dead on arrival.
The book is fairly incoherent as a whole, but it has made me think.</p>
<p>The author has many critiques of (other) productivity books. These
critiques are mostly wrong or exaggerated. One that I did find
meaningful was that often productivity is tied to the false belief
that things that aren't measured aren't valuable, as in
<a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>. This makes "productivity" sort of
self-centered, often; it isn't "productive" to volunteer, or engage in
civic life generally, to know local issues, to vote. This kind of
measurement-obsessed productivity, usually implicitly career-oriented,
becomes a misdirection of energy.</p>
<p>Burkeman accuses productivity advice of being unsustainable, but comes
down too far in the other direction, as if noting that it isn't
possible to sprint forever before concluding that all attempts to
cover distance are futile. This feels like the common tension between
accepting things exactly as they are as opposed to hating things as
they are and pushing to change them at all costs. As usual, neither
extreme is really great.</p>
<p>Burkeman wants you to live in the moment, which I tend to support as
well, but I don't agree with the reasoning having to come from
mortality. Fear of death can't really make you live in the moment;
death is in the future. Infinite life also wouldn't mean that choices
become meaningless; you would still have only one walk through the
garden of forking paths. Yes, value every moment—but not out of fear.
Not out of a scarcity mindset.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman references Seneca's <a href="/20240105-seneca_de_brevitate_vitae/">De Brevitate Vitae</a> on page four. I
think at some point he mentioned <a href="/20201107-how_to_live_on_24_hours_a_day/">How to Live on 24 Hours a Day</a> as
well.</p>
<hr>
<p>On page eight Burkeman mentions three productivity books:
<a href="/2011/03/14/listened-to-four-hour-work-week/">The Four-Hour Work Week</a>, <a href="/20220327-smarter_faster_better_by_duhigg/">Smarter, Faster, Better</a>, and Extreme
Productivity. I've read the first two, and after looking briefly into
the last, it looks like all of them in fact do talk a lot about
prioritizing and saying "no" to things. Burkeman's characterization of
the productivity literature as somehow ignoring this seems unfair.</p>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman says on page nine that productivity works but makes us feel
busier. This has not been my experience. I feel less stress when
things are managed, and I'm able to confidently know that I've taken
care of what I needed to.</p>
<p>Some large chunk of good time management is just memory aids, I think:
Ways of organizing things so that they don't fall through the cracks
and create stressful problems later.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>This struggle against the distressing constraints of reality is what
some old-school psychoanalysts call "neurosis," and it takes
countless forms, from workaholism and commitment-phobia to
codependency and chronic shyness.</p>
<p>Our troubled relationship with time arises largely from the same
effort to avoid the painful constraints of reality. (page 30)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is an interesting characterization of neurosis, especially when
considered along with psychosis, in which neurosis is sort of fighting
against (or worrying about) reality, while psychosis is instead a
clear break with reality.</p>
<p>I'm not sure that's what people usually think of when they think
"neurosis," but it's kind of neat.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... I wrote this book for myself, as much as for anyone else,
putting my faith in the words of the author Richard Bach: "You teach
best what you most need to learn." (page 33)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Bach">Richard Bach</a> and his books including <em>Jonathan Livingston
Seagull</em> were apparently quite big in the 70s.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Think of it as “existential overwhelm”: the modern world provides an
inexhaustible supply of things that seem worth doing, and so there
arises an inevitable and unbridgeable gap between what you'd ideally
like to do and what you actually can do. (page 45)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The harder you struggle to fit everything in, the more of your time
you'll find yourself spending on the least meaningful things. Adopt
an ultra-ambitious time management system that promises to take care
of your entire to-do list, and you probably won't even get around to
the most important items on that list. Dedicate your retirement to
seeing as much of the world as you possibly can, and you probably
won't even get to see the most interesting parts. (page 48)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is ridiculous. Maybe this is where his whole argument falls
apart. It's just not true that you have to do everything, and I think
this passage illustrates the silliness of it. Who would literally aim
to see "as much of the world as you possibly can" and have that mean
devoting equal time to every square inch? For his claims here to make
any sense you have to imagine both having overwhelming and
indiscriminate FOMO and absolutely no sense of prioritization. Both
are problems to resolve, not axioms to reason from.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The most fundamental thing we fail to appreciate about the world,
Heidegger asserts in his magnum opus, <em>Being and Time,</em> is how
bafflingly astonishing it is that it’s there at all – the fact that
there is anything rather than nothing. Most philosophers and
scientists spend their careers pondering the <em>way</em> things are: what
sorts of things exist, where they come from, how they relate to each
other, and so on. But we’ve forgotten to be amazed <em>that</em> things are
in the first place – that ‘a world is worlding all around us’, as
Heidegger puts it. This fact – the fact that <em>there is being,</em> to
begin with – is ‘the brute reality on which all of us ought to be
constantly stubbing our toes’, in the splendid phrase of the writer
Sarah Bakewell. But instead, it almost always passes us by. (page
58)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I sometimes think a related thing, paraphrasing Descartes, "I think,
therefore something is going on." I tend to identify with this
Heidegger snippet. Existence is a miracle.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In his 2019 book, This Life, the Swedish philosopher Martin Hägglund
makes this all a bit clearer and less mystical by juxtaposing the
idea of facing our finitude with the religious belief in an eternal
life. If you really thought life would never end, he argues, then
nothing could ever genuinely matter, because you’d never be faced
with having to decide whether or not to use a portion of your
precious life on something. ‘If I believed that my life would last
forever,’ Hägglund writes, ‘I could never take my life to be at
stake, and I would never be seized by the need to do anything with
my time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This Hägglund may have some worthwhile things to say, but I think that
like Burkeman he's wrong to focus so much on death as the most
important thing, and wrong that without death nothing would matter.</p>
<p>I hear Hägglund is critical of capitalism, but I can't help but think
that the focus on finitude is a capitalist economic argument: if
supply (of time) is unlimited, then price (value) goes to zero. (I
don't believe this.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It is by consciously confronting the certainty of death, and what
follows from the certainty of death, that we finally become truly
present for our lives. (page 63)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>No, no, no. This might be one path of reasoning that helps a person
become more present, but it isn't the only or necessary path.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The real measure of any time management technique is <em>whether or not
it helps you neglect the right things.</em> (page 72)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>There's a section with these three principles:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pay yourself first</li>
<li>Limit your work in progress<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.personalkanban.com/">Personal Kanban</a> suggests
    limiting to three things.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Resist the allure of middling priorities</li>
</ul>
<p>This all seems like basically good advice.</p>
<hr>
<p>So this Bergson guy wrote <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_and_Free_Will">Time and free will</a> (mentioned on page
83) and, I mean, cool title, but otherwise doesn't seem that good,
especially if the thinking is similar in quality to Bergson's ideas
about motivated evolution.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Machine for misusing your life (page 94)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Burkeman mostly tries to avoid the appearance of value judgments by
framing the objective as spending time on what you value (whatever
that is) but he does come out clearly against social media. So you
better not value social media!</p>
<hr>
<p>There's an interesting sort of story about a monk's experience with
ice water, the point of which was that trying to ignore or deny the
experience of cold was worse than focusing on the experience and
accepting, living the experience.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>You're obliged to deal with how your experience is unfolding in this
moment, to resign yourself to the reality that <em>this is it.</em> (page
106)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He's trying to connect boredom to finitude in the sense of limited
lifespan, but he accidentally gives the lie to it. It isn't that
you're upset that you're using your limited time on Earth in a way
that isn't fun; it's that it isn't fun "in this moment."</p>
<p>He does talk about living in the moment, but doesn't seem to resolve
the conflict with the lifespan view.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The real problem isn’t planning. It’s that we take our plans to be
something they aren’t. What we forget, or can’t bear to confront, is
that, in the words of the American meditation teacher Joseph
Goldstein, ‘a plan is just a thought’. We treat our plans as though
they are a lasso, thrown from the present around the future, in
order to bring it under our command. But all a plan is – all it
could ever possibly be – is a present-moment statement of intent.
It’s an expression of your current thoughts about how you’d ideally
like to deploy your modest influence over the future. The future, of
course, is under no obligation to comply. (page 123)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This makes sense. What's the quote I think of... Eisenhower: "Plans
are worthless, but planning is everything." The plan has no influence
over the future, but it does help you make decisions in the moments
you encounter.</p>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman mentions
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/1456312030">Radically Condensed Instructions for Being Just as You Are</a>, which
is more nondualist, the-moment-is-all-there-is stuff.</p>
<p><em>Trying</em> to live in the moment is like trying too hard to sleep.
Trying to force it pushes you further from it. But on the other hand,
you have no other option but to be here now.</p>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman mentions Lafargue's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Right_to_Be_Lazy">The right to be lazy</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"According to Lafargue, wage labour is tantamount to slavery, and to
fight as a labour movement for the extension of slavery is
preposterous. In the book, Lafargue proposes the right to be lazy,
in contrast to the right to work, which he deems bourgeois."</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>‘Nothing is more alien to the present age than idleness,’ writes the
philosopher John Gray. He adds: ‘How can there be play in a time
when nothing has meaning unless it leads to something else?’ (page
154)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think Burkeman also talks about instrumental use of time and tourist
photography, the "stop taking pictures and experience it" argument.</p>
<p>I think of my "<a href="/20181204-worth_doing_even_if_it_fails/">Is it worth doing even if it fails?</a>" which I think
is somewhat related... value the act itself regardless of the outcome.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The publisher and editor Karen Rinaldi feels about surfing the same
way that I do about cheesy piano rock, only more so: she dedicates
every spare moment she can to it, and even wiped out her savings on
a plot of land in Costa Rica for better access to the sea. Yet she
readily admits that she remains an appalling surfer to this day. (It
took her five years of attempting to catch a wave before she first
managed to do so.) But ‘in the process of trying to attain a few
moments of bliss’, Rinaldi explains, ‘I experience something else:
patience and humility, definitely, but also freedom. Freedom to
pursue the futile. And the freedom to suck without caring is
revelatory.’ Results aren’t everything. Indeed, they’d better not
be, because results always come later – and later is always too
late. (page 160)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman talks about a painting called "Boy with a Squirrel," but that
painting is "A Boy with a Flying Squirrel." <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Boy_with_a_Flying_Squirrel">Flying</a>!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It depicts Copley's teenaged half-brother Henry Pelham with a pet
flying squirrel, a creature commonly found in colonial American
portraits as a symbol of the sitter's refinement.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>How cool is that!</p>
<hr>
<p>There are "Three principles of patience" (around page 180)</p>
<ul>
<li>Develop a taste for having problems<ul>
<li>This reminds me of my first "thinking card,"
   <a href="https://planspace.org/20201206-thinking_cards/#1">embrace problems</a>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Embrace radical incrementalism </li>
<li>Originality lies on the far side of unoriginality</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman has this idea, "cosmic insignificance therapy," which is
intended to be a relief. It reminds me of the
<a href="https://hitchhikers.fandom.com/wiki/Total_Perspective_Vortex">total perspective vortex</a> from The Hitchhiker's Guide to the
Galaxy, but of course there it was supposed to be a method of torture.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There is a sort of cruelty, Iddo Landau points out, in holding
yourself to standards nobody could ever reach (and which many of us
would never dream of demanding of other people). The more humane
approach is to drop such efforts as completely as you can. Let your
impossible standards crash to the ground. Then pick a few meaningful
tasks from the rubble and get started on them today. (page 222)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Burkeman mentions this documentary, <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt13675784/">A Life’s Work</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What's it like to dedicate your life to work that won't be completed
in your lifetime? Fifteen years ago, filmmaker David Licata focused
on four projects and the people behind them in an effort to answer
this universal question.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To me this is about caring about something, whether it makes sense or
not, making meaning for yourself, and not really at all about death.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>You could think of this book as an extended argument for the
empowering potential of giving up hope. (page 231)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20250921-four_thousand_weeks_by_burkeman/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20250921-four_thousand_weeks_by_burkeman/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) The Haves and Have-Yachts, by Osnos</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>It's kind of an interesting <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/The-Haves-and-Have-Yachts/Evan-Osnos/9781668204481">book</a>, collecting articles from The New
Yorker. "New gilded age" and so on. There's a whole chapter on
Zuckerberg, who sort of anchors the less-fraudulent side of the
spectrum. Wild and wacky stuff.</p>
<h3>The Haves and Have-Yachts</h3>
<ul>
<li>The rewards: How to spend it<ul>
<li>The floating world<ul>
<li>Yachts are the most expensive thing you can own.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Survival of the richest<ul>
<li>Bunkers and stuff. See also <a href="/20240519-survival_of_the_richest_by_rushkoff/" title="Survival of the Richest, by Rushkoff">Rushkoff</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>One for the money<ul>
<li>"Survival of the Richest, by Rushkoff"</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The mechanics: How to keep it<ul>
<li>Ghost in the machine<ul>
<li>"Can Mark Zuckerberg Fix Facebook Before It Breaks Democracy?"</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The Greenwich rebellion<ul>
<li>"How Greenwich Republicans Learned to Love Trump"</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Ruling-class rules<ul>
<li>"How to thrive in the power élite—while declaring it your enemy." (Tucker Carlson etc.)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Trust issues<ul>
<li>Grantor Retained Annuity Trusts (<a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/g/grat.asp">GRATs</a>) etc.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The perils: How to lose it<ul>
<li>Land of make-believe<ul>
<li>"The Biggest Ponzi Scheme in Hollywood History" (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zach_Avery">Zach Horwitz</a>)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Patriot games<ul>
<li>"How a Tycoon Linked to Chinese Intelligence Became a Darling of Trump Republicans" (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guo_Wengui">Guo Wengui</a>)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The big house<ul>
<li>"Life after white collar crime" (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeff_Grant_(attorney)">Jeff Grant</a>)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20250621-haves_and_have_yachts_by_osnos/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20250621-haves_and_have_yachts_by_osnos/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Make everything into Roth IRA</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Retirement accounts are surprisingly flexible. Rules meant to keep
high earners from making certain contributions and to discourage
withdrawals before age 59½ can largely be worked around. Everything
can and often should get put into a Roth IRA.</p>
<p><img alt="table" src="table.png"></p>
<!--
diagram:
https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1lv1_2hIiCz4q23_Siprsgc9p6HuOAyg48Jw0dHDsBgw/edit

original sketch post:
https://www.linkedin.com/posts/ajschumacher_andre-nader-do-i-have-this-right-activity-7324466493012795392-BaJe?utm_source=share&utm_medium=member_desktop&rcm=ACoAAApS5jEBN0AnaiwMHLjFdiDNwOzHJdekDW8
-->

<p>All these accounts are about avoiding taxes, to encourage you to save
for retirement. “Traditional” accounts can be funded with “pre-tax
dollars,” and then you pay taxes when you move money out. Money you
put into “Roth” accounts has already been taxed, so when you take it
out it's “tax free.”</p>
<p>Traditional accounts can <em>also</em> be funded with after-tax dollars. If
your 401k plan allows it, you can contribute after-tax dollars beyond
the usual limit. This might seem pointless, except that you can then
<em>convert</em> those contributions to Roth. This allows you to put quite a
lot of money into a Roth 401k, and is sometimes called “mega backdoor
Roth 401k.” <em>(orange arrow in diagram)</em></p>
<p>People with <a href="https://www.schwab.com/ira/roth-ira/contribution-limits">high incomes</a> aren't allowed to contribute directly to
Roth IRAs (Individual Retirement Accounts) and (with slightly
different <a href="https://www.irs.gov/retirement-plans/ira-deduction-limits">limitations</a>) can't deduct contributions to a Traditional
IRA. But anyone can contribute after-tax dollars to a Traditional IRA
and then convert those contributions to Roth. This is sometimes called
“backdoor Roth IRA.” <em>(part of purple arrow in diagram)</em></p>
<p>After you've left an employer, you can convert your 401k accounts to
corresponding IRAs without tax implications. Mega backdoor Roth 401k
may be convertible to Roth IRA even while still employed. <em>(green
arrows in diagram)</em></p>
<p>You can also convert a Traditional 401k or Traditional IRA to a Roth
IRA. You pay tax on the converted amount. <em>(blue arrow, part of purple
arrow in diagram)</em> You can control the amounts of the conversions so
that you smooth your taxable income across years rather than having
large single conversion events that spike your annual income—and tax
rate.</p>
<p>Roth IRAs are particularly nice because they let you withdraw
contributions any time without penalty, which makes sense since they
were already taxed. In the case of roll-overs (conversions) you have
to wait five years before withdrawing penalty-free, but that can still
be years before age 59½, meaning money is not locked away to nearly
the same extent. Only investment gains are subject to penalty for
withdrawal before 59½. Additionally, Roth accounts are not subject to
Required Minimum Distributions starting around age 73 the way that
Traditional accounts are.</p>
<p>There are other exceptions to waiting until age 59½ (like if you leave
your job at 55 or older, or if you set up Substantially Equal Periodic
Payments under 72t) but you hardly need them.</p>
<h3>Example: $77k tax-advantaged in 2025</h3>
<p>The common employer-sponsored 401k has a $23,500 limit on total
pre-tax (“Traditional”) and Roth (after tax) employee contributions,
with a $70,000 total cap on employee and employer contributions.
Individual Retirement Accounts (IRAs) are limited to $7,000 in
contributions per year. (“Catch-up” adjustments increase these numbers
somewhat for people 50 and up.)</p>
<p>The choice of Traditional or Roth depends on your tax rate now
compared to when you expect to use the money, and there are
<a href="https://www.citizensbank.com/investing-and-wealth-management/products-services-and-calculators/financial-calculators/roth-401k-vs-traditional-401k-calculator.aspx">calculators</a> that can help you compare. If you are in a high tax
bracket currently, putting pre-tax money in a Traditional account can
help spread your income across years and lower the total effective tax
rate you pay.</p>
<p>Imagine a high-income individual under 50 who contributes $23,500
pre-tax to their 401k, reducing their tax for the current year. Say
they get 50% of that contribution matched by their employer ($11,750)
so the total pre-tax 401k contribution for the year is $35,250. After
they leave their employer, they can choose to convert that Traditional
401k to Roth IRA, paying tax when they make the conversion, and the
converted amount is withdrawable without penalty after five years.</p>
<p>Since the annual limit is $70,000, they can still contribute $34,750
more in after-tax dollars and convert that to Roth 401k. This can be
converted to Roth IRA at any point and the converted amount is
withdrawable without penalty after five years.</p>
<p>They can also contribute $7,000 (in after-tax dollars) toward a
Traditional IRA and then convert that to Roth, and the converted
amount is withdrawable without penalty after five years.</p>
<p>So in one year, this person has gotten $77,000 into tax-advantaged
retirement accounts, and the majority of it can be withdrawn without
penalty after just five years, regardless of their age.</p>
<hr>
<p>I am not a financial advisor, this is just my current understanding of
how these things work, please consult an expert before doing anything.
(And please tell me if I have anything wrong!)</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20250617-make_everything_into_roth_ira/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20250617-make_everything_into_roth_ira/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Consider tax on investments</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Taxes make everything more complicated. They vary based on your income
level, where you live, what investments you have, and what accounts
you have them in, and more. And they affect your real returns. Let's
compare income-generating investments.</p>
<form id="taxForm">

<h3>A nominally <input type="number" step="any" id="nominal_rate" value="5.00">% investment yields, after tax:</h3>

<ul>
  <li><b><span class="bignum" id="interest">3.50%</span></b> if it's regular interest from a bank, a CD, non-qualified dividends...
    <ul><li>Federal and state income tax apply.</li></ul>
  </li>
  <li><b><span class="bignum" id="dividend">3.75%</span></b> if it's <a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/q/qualifieddividend.asp">qualified dividends</a>
    <ul><li>Federal long-term capital gains and state tax apply.</li></ul>
  </li>
  <li><b><span class="bignum" id="bond">4.00%</span></b> if it's interest from a US government bond
    <ul><li>Federal income tax applies, but not state tax.</li></ul>
  </li>
  <li><b><span class="bignum" id="muni">4.50%</span></b> if it's interest from a municipal bond
    <ul><li>Just state tax. (Or not; depends on your state and <a href="https://www.schwab.com/learn/story/not-always-tax-free-7-municipal-bond-tax-traps">other factors</a>.)</li></ul>
  </li>
</ul>


<!--
<p>
<input type="submit" value="Update" />
</p>
-->

<p>
<input type="number" step="any" id="fed_rate" value="20">
<label for="fed_rate">% <a href="https://www.irs.gov/filing/federal-income-tax-rates-and-brackets">Federal income tax</a> rate</label>
</p>

<p>
<input type="number" step="any" id="gains_rate" value="15">
<label for="gains_rate">% <a href="https://www.irs.gov/taxtopics/tc409">Federal long-term capital gains tax</a> rate</label>
</p>

<p>
<input type="number" step="any" id="state_rate" value="10">
<label for="state_rate">% <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/data/all/state/state-income-tax-rates/">state income tax</a> rate</label>
</p>

</form>

<p>Most states don't differentiate between regular income and capital
gains, so there's just the one state tax box here. It probably makes
sense to use your overall effective (“blended”) tax rates here, though
you could use your marginal rates if you want. And of course this all
assumes we're in the US.</p>
<style>
input { width: 4em; }
.bignum {font-size: 1.17em; }
</style>


    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20250604-consider_tax_on_investments/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20250604-consider_tax_on_investments/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>What is real? by Becker</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
<p>“The fact that an adequate philsophical presentation
[of quantum physics] has been so long delayed is no doubt caused by
the fact that Niels Bohr brainwashed a whole generation of
theorists,” Gell-Mann wrote in 1976. (page 253)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As a former physics undergraduate student, I was excited to see if the
ugly Copenhagen interpretation had finally been retired. Becker gave
me some hope but in the end it looks like people are still mostly
shutting up and calculating. I still like the “what is real” framing,
even if the <a href="https://www.hachettebookgroup.com/titles/adam-becker/what-is-real/9781541698970/">book</a> can't completely deliver.</p>
<p>A few thoughts:</p>
<ul>
<li>One of the unique things about quantum physics is its ontic
   randomness. Even just skimming some of the book's references, like
   <a href="https://ia601501.us.archive.org/1/items/in.ernet.dli.2015.204850/2015.204850.Natural-Philosophy_text.pdf">Born</a> and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20190601184313/https://www.hcs.harvard.edu/~hrp/issues/1999/Hermann.pdf">Hermann</a>, it's clear people were wrestling with
   this a lot. But the author sort of puts it out of scope.</li>
<li>How, in a book on what is real, do you come so close as to discuss
   Quine's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Two_Dogmas_of_Empiricism">Two Dogmas</a> but not dive into the myth of physical
   objects? (To be clear, there is discussion of scientific realism,
   but this aspect of it isn't much explored, as I recall.)</li>
<li>Similarly, there isn't much discussion of what we really think
   exists. Pointlike particles? (In what sense does anybody believe in
   them?) Discrete space? Something else? In what may be a bit of
   humor, the very last note at the end of the book is about how many
   interpretations don't, in fact, believe in "particles" as such at
   all.</li>
<li>I would have liked for there to be more on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Map%E2%80%93territory_relation">map vs. territory</a> as
   it pertains to what is real. Where do we think the theory is "real"
   vs. where is it just a model? (There is some discussion of
   epistemic vs. ontic interpretations, though this could have been
   clearer too. I think this connects to
   <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Unreasonable_Effectiveness_of_Mathematics_in_the_Natural_Sciences">Unreasonable Effectiveness</a>, which also would have been
   interesting to see explored more.</li>
<li>Another connection that seems interesting is the mathematical idea
   of model theory, where you differentiate between a formal system
   and a model that satisfies it. With multiple interpretations that
   don't seem to have different predictions than "standard quantum
   physics" the interpretations start to feel like models in this
   sense.</li>
<li>It would have been nice to get more/clearer on Heisenberg's
   uncertainty principle. Looking into it more myself, I got as far as
   an interesting hint that you can understand it as position and
   momentum wave functions being mutually Fourier transforms, so if
   one is narrow the other is spread out.</li>
<li>In general, the author seemed sometimes to assume knowledge instead
   of clearly laying out enough to get up to speed. Part of this is
   probably just trying to avoid technicality that would put people
   off. To illustrate: DeWitt's <a href="https://cqi.inf.usi.ch/qic/deWitt1970.pdf">Quantum Mechanics and Reality</a> is
   great (and very approximately a short version of the whole book)
   but it has enough math notation in it that it probably puts off a
   lot of people who would otherwise read and enjoy it. (And it's
   trying to be gentle itself.) But if you don't explain spin or
   polarization (etc.) at all, people will also be left out. And when
   interpretation is largely about putting meaning to the math, it's
   hard to think about if you never see the math.</li>
<li>What kinds of things are eligible to constitute an interpretation?
   The math alone seems not to be. Do things have to reduce to
   <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Na%C3%AFve_physics">naïve physics</a> in order to be part of an interpretation? Is any
   (non-mathematical) abstraction acceptable? Must it satisfy some
   assumptions? (Some might have put locality in that bucket,
   previously?)</li>
</ul>
<p>What is the Copenhagen interpretation?</p>
<ul>
<li>divide quantum vs. classical scales (vague)</li>
<li>wave function collapse on observation (measurement problem)</li>
<li>no hidden variables (it's not just that we don't know the state
   yet)</li>
<li>says nothing about the world (?)</li>
<li>wave-particle duality ("complementarity")</li>
</ul>
<p>Other interpretations:</p>
<ul>
<li>Bohm pilot-wave</li>
<li>multiple worlds</li>
<li>superdeterminism</li>
<li>spontaneous collapse</li>
</ul>
<p>In the end, I still don't understand all of physics. Magnets are
weird. Light is weird. Gravity is weird. Becker has more to say
tearing down Copenhagen than in building any particular replacement;
as in the subtitle, the quest is unfinished. Excelsior?</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The soundest fact may fail or prevail in the style of its telling.”
(Ursula K. Le Guin)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is from <em>The Left Hand of Darkness.</em></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The godfather of quantum physics, Niels Bohr, talked about a
division between the world of big objects, where classical Newtonian
physics ruled, and small objects, where quantum physics reigned. But
Bohr was maddeningly unclear about the location of the boundary
between the world. (page 9)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This alone is not such a big deal. Different models apply to different
views, scales, etc. Statistical Mechanics doesn't apply to individual
particles, for example. It is weird if you treat the divide as
fundamental, but if you treat it as a matter of convenience or
approximation, I don't have a problem with it.</p>
<p>The heart of the Copenhagen weirdness is the measurement problem as in
Schrödinger's cat: denying decided existence until we look.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Born's book, <a href="https://ia601501.us.archive.org/1/items/in.ernet.dli.2015.204850/2015.204850.Natural-Philosophy_text.pdf"><em>Natural Philosophy of Cause and Chance</em></a>, made
quite an impression on Bell—especially the discussion of a proof by
the great mathematician and physicist John von Neumann. According to
Born, von Neumann had proven that the Copenhagen interpretation was
the only possible way of understanding quantum physics. So either
the Copenhagen interpretation was correct or quantum physics was
wrong. And, given the wild success of quantum physics, it seemed
that Copenhagen and its vagueness were here to stay. (pages 9-10)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Well, what does Born say?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It would be silly and arrogant to deny any possibility of a return
to determinism. For no physical theory is final; new experiences may
force us to alterations and even reversions. Yet scanning the
history of physics in the way we have done we see fluctuations and
vacillations, but hardly a reversion to more primitive conceptions.
I expect that our present theory will be profoundly modified. For it
is full of difficulties which I have not mentioned at all—the
self-energies of particles in interaction and many other quantities,
like collision cross-sections, lead to divergent integrals. But I
should never expect that these difficulties could be solved by a
return to classical concepts. I expect just the opposite, that we
shall have to sacrifice some current ideas and use still more
abstract methods. However, these are only opinions. A more concrete
contribution to this question has been made by J. v. Neumann in his
brillant book, <em>Mathematische Grundlagen der Quantenmechanik.</em> He
puts the theory on an axiomatic basis by deriving it from a few
postulates of a very plausible and general character, about the
properties of 'expectation values’ (averages) and their
representation by mathematical symbols. The result is that the
formalism of quantum mechanics is uniquely determined by these
axioms; in particular, no concealed parameters can be introduced
with the help of which the indeterministic description could be
transformed into a deterministic one. Hence if a future theory
should be deterministic, it cannot be a modification of the present
one but must be essentially different. How this should be possible
without sacrificing a whole treasure of well-established results I
leave to the determinists to worry about. (<em>Natural Philosophy of
Cause and Chance</em> pages 108-109)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This isn't about the Copenhagen interpretation, is it? This is about
hidden variables? (No-hidden-variables isn't what we mean by
Copenhagen, is it? I thought everybody agreed about no hidden
variables...)</p>
<p>This is fairly bad for the big structure of the book, which hinges on
the "proof of the Copenhagen interpretation" coming undone.</p>
<p>Coming back to this later: Maybe no-hidden-variables is/was part of
the Copenhagen interpretation? It seems like the author argues the
pilot-wave interpretation has hidden variables (but not locality) and
that shows von Neumann was wrong. But still, Born was talking about
determinism, and hidden variables also isn't the same thing as
determinism...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>What does quantum physics tell us about the world? According to the
Copenhagen interpretation, this question has a very simple answer:
quantum physics tells us nothing whatsoever about the world. (page
14)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is this quite fair? Doesn't it say the cat is both alive and dead?
It's a weird thing to say, but it seems to say it...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Quantum physics uses infinite collections of numbers called <em>wave
functions</em> to describe the world. (page 16)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is a little bit like calling a line an infinite collection of
numbers: technically true but not super helpful.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Once you do find that electron, a funny thing happens to its wave
function. Rather than following the Schrödinger equation like a good
wave function, it collapses—it instantly becomes zero everywhere
except in the place where you found the electron. (page 17)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is there a problem in treating the wave function as describing our
state of knowledge? We don't have any problem with making
probabilistic predictions, for example, and then when we get data we
switch from the probabilistic prediction to the observed data. How
different is the quantum wave function really?</p>
<p>(I think there <em>is</em> a problem in thinking about it this way, and it
would have been nice for the author to make this clearer... For
example, if the wave function is 50% along two paths, they shouldn't
interfere with one another if the wave function is just a description
of our knowledge.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>So what is real? Copenhagen's reply is silence—and a look of stern
disapproval for having the temerity to ask the question in the first
place. (page 20)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At some point we really can't say anything about the "underlying
reality" of what we observe. Is quantum mechanics that boundary?</p>
<p>(No.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernst_Mach">Mach</a> believed that science should be based on descriptive laws
that don't make any claims about the true nature of the world—he
dismissed such claims as unnecessary for the practice of science. To
Mach, one of the worst offenders was the great god of physics, Isaac
Newton himself. Newton's master-work, the <em>Principia,</em> opened with
the assumption that space and time were absolute entities unto
themselves, with real existence out in the world. This “conceptual
monstrosity of absolute space” was, in Mach's view, “purely a
thought-thing which cannot be pointed to in experience.” Mach
thought that a proper science of mechanics would dispense with these
kinds of ontological claims—claims about what things actually exist
in the real world—and instead simply lay down descriptive,
mathematical laws that accurately predict the observed motion of all
objects. Good theories, according to Mach, were about connecting
observations, not about positing things that couldn't be observed at
all. (page 25)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Map and territory... How different is it to have absolute space be
model, just "act as if," without the ontological claim?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Mach had loudly and repeatedly proclaimed that he did not believe in
atoms, as they were too small to be observable in principle. (page
27)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is silly. Nothing is <em>directly</em> observable in principle, and yet
we believe in chairs, other people, etc.</p>
<p>If he's <em>really</em> positivist, how does he believe in anything other
than claims about sense perceptions? "I see a chair" doesn't imply "I
believe there is a chair."</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Heisenberg started thinking about what would happen if you tried to
measure the position of a single particle, like an electron, to very
high precision. He realized that you could do this the same way
you'd look for a lost wallet in a dark field: shine a flashlight
around until you've found what you're looking for. An ordinary
flashlight wouldn't work for an electron, though—the wavelength of
visible light is far too large for that. But Heisenberg knew you
could find an electron using higher-energy light, with a shorter
wavelength: gamma rays. Shine a gamma-ray flashlight around a room,
and you'll find your electron. But gamma rays pack a punch—bounce
one gamma-ray photon off an electron, and the electron will go
careening off in some random direction. So you'll know where the
electron was, but you won't know how fast it's going or where it's
heading now. (page 38)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is a standard bad take. Even if there's some historicity to it,
in how Heisenberg was thinking, it's misleading to make uncertainty
seem like it's about physicality of measurement.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Bohr pointed to the Heisenberg uncertainty principle as further
justification for the inevitability of complementarity. Using
Heisenberg's gamma-ray flashlight as an example, he pointed out that
there was no way to precisely measure the momentum of an electron
when observing its position, and vice versa. Bohr then echoed Mach,
as Heisenberg had, and claimed the impossibility of measuring both
properties simultaneously. Position and momentum, like particles and
waves, were complementary—never used at once but both needed for the
complete description of a situation.</p>
<p>But Bohr was wrong. There was nothing inevitable or necessary about
complementarity—other interpretations of quantum physics are
possible. Indeed, the claim of inevitability is an awfully strong
and strange claim to make about any interpretive issue in science,
precisely because it is always possible to reinterpret any theory.
Yet Bohr was convinced that complementarity was the deepest insight
into nature found within the quantum theory.</p>
<p>Stranger still is Bohr's use of the gamma-ray flashlight to bolster
his claims. It's certainly true that the thought experiment
illustrates a world in which there are limits on our knowledge, but
it's also a world where particles have well-defined positions and
momenta at all times. Hitting an electron with a gamma ray can't
alter the electron's momentum unless it has a momentum in the first
place. We don't know what that momentum is—but that's certainly not
the same thing as saying it doesn't exist. (page 40)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Why were Bohr, Heisenberg, and others so convinced that the quantum
world couldn't be visualized? Why did they seem to think that things
couldn't be real until they were observed? Why did they insist that
the classical world obeyed fundamentally different rules from the
quantum world? Why, in short, did they believe the strange
assemblage of claims that came to be known as the Copenhagen
interpretation? (page 47)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>He dismissively said of another physicist's paper that “it is not
even wrong.” (page 48, quoting Pauli)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Huh! So that's where that came from!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>As Bohr put it years after Solvay, “It is wrong to think that that
task of physics is to find out how nature is. Physics concerns what
we can say about nature.” (page 49)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Writing koans, this guy...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In short, quantum physics is either incomplete or nonlocal. (page
56)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>But Einstein's concerns had little, if anything, to do with
determinism—they were about the importance of locality and a
physical reality that exists independently of anyone observing it.
(page 59)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Some took him [von Neumann] to be saying that consciousness itself
causes the collapse of the wave function; this was a view promoted
by physicists Fritz London and Edmond Bauer in a book they wrote
several years later, heavily influenced by von Neumann's work.
Wigner also adopted this view later. But this is a weird view.
Stating that consciousness collapses wave functions does arguably
solve the measurement problem but only at the price of introducing
new problems. (page 68)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... the Nazi bomb program, unlike the Manhattan Project, was a
disorganized mess, with vital information compartmentalized and no
clear vision of how to proceed. (page 77)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The conditions we work under today certainly aren't hastening [a]
breakthrough,” he [Goudsmit] said in 1953. (page 81)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is in a part about how the militarization of physics made it less
concerned with philosophy and "understanding" as it focused on
shutting up and calculating...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Research into the meaning of quantum physics was one of the
casualties of the war. With all these new students crowding
classrooms around the country, professors found it impossible to
teach the philosophical questions at the foundations of quantum
physics. Before the war, courses in quantum physics on both sides of
the Atlantic, like Heisenberg's in Leipzig and Oppenheimer's in
Berkeley, spent a great deal of time on conceptual issues. Textbooks
and exams from the prewar period asked students to write detailed
essays on the nature of the uncertainty principle and the role of
the observer in the quantum world. But, with ballooning class sizes,
detailed discussion of philosophy became all but impossible. (page
82)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also kind of weird to have students write essays on the role of the
observer, if nobody had really good ideas on the topic anyway?</p>
<hr>
<p>"Atavistic" is used on page 83: "relating to or characterized by
reversion to something ancient or ancestral."</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Given the damage done to his reputation by his activities during the
war, Heisenberg's invention of a single unified Copenhagen
interpretation may have been an attempt to rework the history of
quantum physics to his benefit. (pages 83-84)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Questions of interpretation, while vital for the progress of science
in the long term, were immaterial when it came to the hard-nosed
applications of quantum theory that were so suddenly and desperately
prized. (page 84)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think I agree that interpretation is important for progress, but I
don't think the claim is very strongly established or supported in the
text.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>But Bohm's thesis research, on interactions between atomic nuclei,
was nonetheless very relevant for the work going on at Los Alamos—so
much so that it was immediately classified beyond Bohm's clearance.
His notes and calculations were seized by the Army, and he was
forbidden from writing his own thesis. (page 94)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Silly!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>He [Bohm] was assembling his quantum physics course materials into a
textbook, taking great care to explain and defend the Copenhagen
interpretation. But doubts had crept in, and, as the book neared
completion in the summer of 1950, those doubts grew. “When I
finished the book, I wasn't quite satisfied that I really understood
it,” Bohm said. (page 95)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Wild! (But also, maybe not that uncommon in the vicinity of quantum
books?)</p>
<p>The text is <a href="https://store.doverpublications.com/products/9780486659695">Quantum Theory</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In Bohm's interpretation of quantum physics, much of the mystery of
the quantum world simply falls away. Objects have definite positions
at all times, whether or not anyone is looking at them. Particles
have a wave nature, but there's nothing “complementary” about
it—particles are just particles, and their motions are guided by
pilot waves. Particles surf along these waves, guided by the waves'
motion (hence the name). Heisenberg's uncertainty principle still
holds—the more we know about a particle's position, the less we know
about its momentum, and vice versa—but according to Bohm, this is
simply a limitation on the information that the quantum world is
willing to yield to us. (page 98)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The difference between an answer being there but we can't know it,
versus there not being an answer apart from our attempt to know it.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aharonov%E2%80%93Bohm_effect">Aharonov–Bohm effect</a>, an unusual feature of the behavior of
electrons and other charged particles traveling near electromagnetic
fields. (page 115)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Neat! Seems to suggest that wave functions have some sort of "reality"
to them even when their real component is zero?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Each experiment, each quantum event, spun off new branches of the
universal wave function, creating a multitude of universes in which
that one event had every possible outcome. (page 124)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This doesn't solve the measurement problem! This makes measurement
central to the evolution of the universe(s), which is just as bad if
not worse!</p>
<p>And measurements don't have just simple binary outcomes; infinite
position outcomes (or nearly so, if we go to the nearest Planck
length) are possible, etc.</p>
<p>So we say the wave function doesn't collapse. In some sense the wave
function <em>is</em> the "multi-verse," then, and the "many worlds" aren't
really many but just aspects of the wave function multi-verse...</p>
<p>Coming back later: The book doesn't do it, but I am now suspecting
that there is some better definition of "quantum event" in terms of
when the wave function becomes decoherent or something... In
multi-worlds the wave function is sometimes behaving weirdly quantum,
interfering with itself and so on, and sometimes things settle into a
"branch" where one thing seems to have happened.</p>
<p>But: some people still <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_decoherence#cite_note-Adler2001-16">don't think</a> decoherence solves the
measurement problem.</p>
<hr>
<p>The annoying and typical tale of Wheeler advising Everett to do a lot
of work to get Bohr on board with ideas Bohr doesn't like. (around
page 130)</p>
<p>Also: Funny when DeWitt later says Wheeler is a backer of multiple
worlds.</p>
<hr>
<p>On page 145 the author does clarify that von Neumann's proof
(mentioned page 9) was purporting to show the impossibility of
hidden-variable interpretations. I still think this is quite a bit
more specific than "the Copenhagen interpretation"... Bohm's theory is
given as an example of one with hidden variables that does work.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Specifically, Bell found that a hidden-variables theory could avoid
the traps laid by these proofs if it had a rather peculiar property,
later dubbed <em>contextuality.</em> (page 146)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Wikipedia's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_contextuality">Quantum contextuality</a> notes that "Nonlocality, in the
sense of Bell's theorem, may be viewed as a special case of the more
general phenomenon of contextuality".</p>
<p>But this isn't good! This is more measurement problem!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In demolishing the no-hidden-variables proofs, Bell also
demonstrated that quantum physics describes a contextual world.
(page 147)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“What is proved by impossibility proofs,” concluded Bell, “is lack
of imagination.” (page 148)</p>
<p>Bell toyed with this EPR-Bohm thought experiment, trying to
construct a model that would maintain all the predicted results of
quantum physics while remaining purely local. “Everything I tried
didn't work,” Bell said. “I began to feel that it very likely
couldn't be done. Then I constructed an impossibility proof.” (page
150)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This has to be intentional, right? This is humor?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>This proof, now known as Bell's theorem, has rightly been called
“the most profound discovery of science.” (page 151)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This was by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Stapp">Stapp</a>, in <a href="https://escholarship.org/uc/item/7m59f6nz">Bell's theorem and world process</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>As Bell himself said, “I don't know any conception of locality which
works with quantum mechanics. So I think we're stuck with
nonlocality.” (page 160)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Bell's theorem is merely a claim about the world, independent of
quantum mechanics. (page 160)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In short, Bell's theorem really leaves only three unequivocal
possbilities: either nature is nonlocal in some way, or we live in
branching multiple worlds despite appearances to the contrary, or
quantum physics gives incorrect predictions about certain
experimental setups. (page 160)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The author is at pains to explain that "realism" is not a distinct
assumption that could be false, though I think I've seen this
explained differently...</p>
<p>Superdeterminism is also mentioned but dismissed.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Physicists certainly talked about electrons as if they were real,
but this was merely a shorthand for their perceptions and not to be
taken literally. (page 169)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This also works for chairs etc.</p>
<hr>
<p>"Rumbustious" is used on page 171: "boisterous or unruly."</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>He [Otto Neurath] worked to develop an international symbolic
language, ISOTYPE, that would precisely specify sense data in
unambiguous ways, to aid international collaboration in science and
philosophy. (page 171)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isotype_(picture_language)">Huh!</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>And few physicists truly believed, as the Vienna Circle did, that
electrons didn't exist. (page 177)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Books don't exist.</p>
<p>When I think I have a book in my hand I believe that in addition to my
conception of the book there is some "real thing" that is the book. I
believe that my sensation of holding the book is because of that real
thing. But I can't <em>directly</em> perceive that thing. I see light from
the book, I feel pressure from the book on my fingers.</p>
<p>Sense perception of many things is indirect. I've never been on the
dark side of the moon, but I believe it has a "real thing" existence
like a book.</p>
<p>This extends to electrons. They are not less real than anything else.
Other things aren't more real than them.</p>
<p>Why (and how?) make a distinction between things that are part of
"naïve physics" and things that are part of more sophisticated models?
They're all models, all map, none of them territory.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Quine's paper, “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Two_Dogmas_of_Empiricism">Two Dogmas of Empiricism</a>,” took aim at the core
of the positivist program, the verification theory of meaning. Quine
pointed out that there was no way to verify single statements—all
attempts to verify a statement inevitably involve the assumed truth
of other statements, which are themselves subject to the same
problem. (page 180)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Quine spends more time on the analytic-synthetic distinction than on
reductionism ("the verification theory of meaning").</p>
<p>On the analytic-synthetic distinction, I think Quine is pointing out
problems with human language, not proving the non-distinction he aims
to prove. Certainly mathematical tautologies are analytic.</p>
<p>It is indeed hard to talk about the world though (synthetic). From the wiki:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>According to Quine, there are two different results of his
reasoning. The first is a blurring of the line between metaphysics
and natural science. The common-sense theory about physical objects
is epistemologically comparable to the gods of Homer. Quine is a
physicalist, in the sense that he considers it a scientific error
not to adopt a theory which makes reference to physical objects.
However, like Gods of Homer, physical objects are posits, and there
is no great epistemic difference in kind; the difference is rather
that the theory of physical objects has turned out to be a more
efficient theory. After having defined himself an "empiricist",
Quine states in Two Dogmas: "The myth of physical objects is
epistemologically superior to most in that it has proved more
efficacious than other myths as a device for working a manageable
structure into the flux of experience".</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I like this "myth of physical objects;" maybe that's a helpful phrase
for thinking about things. As in the discussion of books and electrons
above: which myths do you think are useful? Which do you really
believe? Is it helpful to "really believe" in those things in Plato's
realm of ideals?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The interpretation of a physical theory, like quantum physics, is
important for the day-to-day practice of science itself. Logical
positivism couldn't account for this. (page 183)</p>
<p>Hanson dubbed the role that nonobservable entities play in
scientific work the “theory-laden” practice of science, a name that
stuck. (page 183)</p>
<p>And, while there was much they didn't agree on, a new consensus
began to form among professional philosophers of science, a position
in opposition to logical positivism, which they called <em>scientific
realism.</em> (page 183)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What do I think? I think it's asking too much to believe in
everything. Maybe I can call my point of view “deep agnosticism,” in
which nothing is officially believed, though of course you can't walk
around without having some beliefs in practice. <em>Something</em> is going
on. Hard to say exactly what. But that doesn't have to stop us living
with chairs and books and electrons.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>If the unobservable “metaphysical” content of our best scientific
theories—stuff like electrons—really bears no relation at all to the
actual stuff in the world, then why do our scientific theories work
at all?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>First, "bears no relation at all to the actual stuff in the world" is
not the same as "is the same as the actual stuff in the world."
Electrons can be a useful thing to act as if is real, regardless of
whether electrons "exist" in a physical sense or we're in a simulation
that's programmed as if there are electrons.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The theories themselves suggest explanations for the phenomena that
we see based on the unobserved stuff. But if the unobserved stuff is
just a convenient picture that just happens to come along with the
“real” content of the theory (i.e., the predictions about the
observable world) and that picture really doesn't line up with the
stuff in the world in any way, then we're astonishingly lucky that
our theories work so well! (page 185)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Astonishingly lucky? Unreasonably lucky? This reminds me of The
Unreasonable Effectiveness of Mathematics in the Natural Sciences,
which is not so different: We make models, and the models work really
well.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Hilary Putnam put it more succinctly. “Realism,” he claimed, “is the
only philosophy that doesn't make the success of science a miracle.”
(page 187)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>While Einstein and Bohr's generation was widely schooled in
philosophy, the push toward specialization after World War II had
taken its toll on the liberal arts education of the new crop of
physicists. (page 189)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The solution to the measurement problem, Wigner was convinced, lay
somewhere in the special qualities of human consciousness—a view he
also attributed to von Neumann. (page 199)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>"Samizdat" is used on page 214: "the clandestine copying and
distribution of literature banned by the state, especially formerly in
the communist countries of eastern Europe."</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“I am a quantum engineer,” he [Bell] once announced at the start of
a talk, “but on Sundays I have principles.” (page 222)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>And a celebrated series of articles on Bell's theorem by the
distinguished Cornell physicist N. David Mermin elucidated the
subject for his fellow physicists through a set of particularly
simple thought experiments, which rapidly became the standard way of
teaching the subject. (page 224)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Maybe one of them is this "<a href="https://www.ringnebula.com/CosIG/28e-Mermin-Quantum-mysteries-for-anyone-1981.pdf">Quantum mysteries for anyone</a>" which
features the example that our author presents as variations on
roulette wheels. (Credit is given, in a note on page 333.) It's nice that at the end Mermin explains a real
possible realization of the apparatus.</p>
<hr>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>One method, [of quantum cryptography] developed by Charles Bennett
and Gilles Brassard in 1984, was based on a result known as the
“<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No-cloning_theorem">no-cloning theorem</a>,” which had been proven in response done by the
Fundamental Fysiks Group. (page 226)</p>
<p>In physics, the no-cloning theorem states that it is impossible to
create an independent and identical copy of an arbitrary unknown
quantum state, a statement which has profound implications in the
field of quantum computing among others.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“I expect that the Copenhagen interpretation will some time be
called the greatest sophism in the history of science,” he [Zeh]
wrote to Wheeler in 1980, “but I would consider it a terrible
injustice if—when some day a solution should be found—some people
claim that ‘this is of course what Bohr always meant,’ only because
he was sufficiently vague.” (pages 232-233)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>(Wheeler himself misunderstood the Bell experiments as ruling out
determinism, rather than locality.) (page 234)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The reference is Wheeler and Zurek's 1983 <em>Quantum Theory and
Measurement,</em> page 188.</p>
<p>Wheeler says, in his chapter called "Law without Law":</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Not the slightest hard evidence has ever been found that would throw
doubt on the plain, straightforward prediction of quantum mechanics,
the prediction that no prediction is possible. Probability? Yes. A
definite forecast? No. Einstein could be unhappy that “God plays
dice”; but Bohr could tell him jokingly, “Einstein, stop telling God
what to do.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It isn't super clear to me that this ties directly to Bell
experiments, but I didn't look at the Wheeler book for long. And
didn't everybody agree that (non-probabilistic) determinism was out
anyway? Doesn't seem like you need Bell for that.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Why do we even need a different [from Copenhagen] interpretation,
much less a different theory altogether
[given quantum theory works so well]?</p>
<p>Bell framed his reply as a moral issue. “It is not right to tell the
public that a central role for conscious mind is integrated into
modern atomic physics. Or that ‘information’ is the real stuff of
physical theory. It seems to me irresponsible to suggest that
technical features of contemporary theory were anticipated by the
saints of ancient religions ... by introspection.” Bell felt an
urgent need to solve the problems at the core of quantum physics—but
he had little patience for purported solutions that were little more
than vague declarations of faith. He wanted something more definite,
something that wasn't a professional embarrassment, a true theory
that didn't shy away from questions about what happened during
measurement. His relentlessly clear writing gave no quarter to
anyone hoping to take solace in the comforting platitudes of the
Copenhagen interpretation. “Surely, after 62 years, we should have
an exact formulation of some part of quantum mechanics?” Bell said
in 1989. “[Measurement devices] should not be separated off from the
rest of the world into black boxes, as if [they] were not made of
atoms and not ruled by quantum mechanics.” In a talk he gave in
Geneva in January 1990, Bell acknowledged that the task at hand was
difficult and that his own theorem proved that there was some
radical change necessary, something that physics would have to come
to terms with. “I think you're stuck with the nonlocality,” Bell
told the small group who came to hear him speak that day. “I don't
know any conception of locality which works with quantum mechanics.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>On information specifically, I'm reminded of my old buddy <a href="/2012/05/18/quotes-from-frederick-w-kantor/">Kantor</a>,
whose work I've still never really understood.</p>
<p>But overall yes, I agree with Bell here.</p>
<hr>
<p>Looks like "the Jura" are another mountain range, like "the Alps" also
are. (page 239)</p>
<hr>
<p>"Pellucid" is used on page 240. It means "translucently clear."</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>DeWitt's article, “<a href="https://cqi.inf.usi.ch/qic/deWitt1970.pdf">Quantum Mechanics and Reality</a>,” did review
several interpretations. (page 243)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let's read that article.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Some writers have also insisted that the process described by
equation 4 merely prepares the system and that the measurement is
not complete until a more complicated piece of apparatus observes
the outcome of the preparation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is very funny, as the "more complicated piece of apparatus" is a
person: he's alluding to consciousness, but obliquely. (He gets to it
shortly.)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Quantum mechanics is a theory that attempts to describe in
mathematical language a world in which chance is not a measure of
our ignorance but is absolute.</p>
<p>This universe is constantly splitting into a stupendous number of
branches, all resulting from the measurementlike interactions
between its myriads of components.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>"Measurementlike" is key, and possibly confusing. Maybe "decoherent"
would be better?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For example, in the very early moments of the universe, during the
cosmological "Big Bang," the universal wave function may have
possessed an overall coherence as yet unimpaired by condensation
into noninterfering branches.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This was the bit that made me start to think I understood better what
decoherence means, and why the splitting of many worlds doesn't
necessarily have the observer problem any more.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Finally, the EWG ["many worlds"] interpretation of quantum mechanics
has an important contribution to make to the philosophy of science.
By showing that formalism alone is sufficient to generate
interpretation, it has breathed new life into the old idea of a
direct correspondence between formalism and reality. The reality
implied here is admittedly bizarre. To anyone who is awestruck by
the vastness of the presently known universe, the view from where
Everett, Wheeler and Graham sit is truly impressive. Yet it is a
completely causal view, which even Einstein might have accepted. At
any rate, it has a better claim than most to be the natural end
product of the interpretation program begun by Heisenberg in 1925.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I like some of <a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/">Deutsch's stuff</a>, but I hadn't been on board re: many
worlds, before. Maybe I'm getting convinced?</p>
<p>Something interesting happens then, doesn't it? Quantum mechanics is
indeed ontologically random, at the lowest level, and the wave
function captures that. But as we look backward in time, it's
epistemic from the point of view of the evolution of our specific
world vantage point. Before we start a Schrödinger's cat experiment,
we predict 50/50 odds and that's really true, there's an irreducible
randomness. After running the experiment, however, the wave function
describes our state of knowledge but not the reality. The cat really
is alive or dead and not both, in the world path that we're really in.</p>
<p>And that's how it always is, isn't it? Predictions forward, knowledge
backward...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>General relativity didn't merely deal with abstruse situations—it
was also written in abstruse mathematics. The theory is very
mathematically complex, far more so than quantum mechanics. (page
246)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>But it's not clear that Everett himself truly believed that the many
worlds implied by his interpretation were literally real, as DeWitt
did. (page 251)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I'm not sure it's even clear what "literally real" means here... It
seems clear they're not like islands in the sea, independent entities
that you can skip between. More like aspects of the wave function than
like separate wave functions, right?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>When Don Reisler, a physicist with a PhD in quantum foundations,
applied to work at Everett's company, Everett shyly asked if he was
a ware of the relative-state interpretation. Reisler immediately
thought, “Oh my God, you are <em>that</em> Everett, the crazy one.” (page
251)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(Everett's many-worlds interpretation was also called "relative-state.")</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>As Quine said, our beliefs about the world can only be tested
against the world as a group, not individually, and this holds for
falsification just as much as for verification. No theory, in
isolation, is falsifiable. (page 262)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(part of a takedown re: Popper)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Ultimately, arguments against a multiverse purportedly based on
falsifiability are really arguments based on ignorance and taste:
some physicists are unaware of the history and philosophy of their
own field and find multiverse theories unpalatable. But that does
not mean that multiverse theories are unscientific. (pages 263-264)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yikes! Who hurt you?</p>
<p>(It's right about here that the writing gets dramatically spicier.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Zeilinger has suggested that the “message of the quantum” is the
fairly positivist idea that “the distinction between reality and our
knowledge of reality, between reality and information, cannot be
made.” (page 271)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Just a few generations ago, at the birth of quantum physics, all
physicists received some schooling in philosophy. Einstein read
Mach, Bohr read Kant. But the shifts in research funding and physics
classrooms after World War II also led to broader shifts in
university curricula. For Einstein and Bohr's generation, philosophy
was part of the core educational curriculum in central Europe. But
in postwar America, it was (and is) relatively easy for an
intelligent student to go all the way from kindergarten to a PhD in
physics at a top-tier university without ever darkening the door of
a philosophy classroom. (page 273)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(part of a section decrying lack of love for philosophy)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>But with the massive increase in knowledge and information in the
last century, education became unavoidably specialized. (page 273)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Unavoidably? I think this is an exaggerated claim. I think maybe we've
done a poor job in organizing and explaining the knowledge we (should)
have. Not to mention all the people who seem to get a lot of education
and still come out knowing basically nothing.</p>
<p>A contributing factor might be the allegedly unopinionated kitchen
sink nature of curricula, where the view is wide and often historical
even when the knowledge isn't fundamentally historical in nature.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“All of the proposals we have for solving the measurement problem
are weird in one way or another,” said David Albert. “Bell's theorem
proves they have to be weird. ... [But] there's a huge difference
between being weird and being incoherent or unintelligible.” And,
Albert added, many physicists still do not seem to appreciate this
point. “Physicists will say, ‘Yes, the Copenhagen interpretation is
weird, but so is everything else.’ And you sort of want to slap them
and say, ‘No! The Copenhagen interpretation is not <em>weird,</em> it's
gibberish, it's unintelligible.’” (page 283)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I agree with this; it seems generous to even call Copenhagen an
interpretation.</p>
<p>Oh! And in this note (page 340) there's a quote from Bas van Fraassen:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“by today's standards [Copenhagen] is not an interpretation.”</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Science and culture form an undivided whole, now more than ever, in
our world whose every corner has been reshaped by human activity.
(page 285)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>The appendix, <em>Four Views of the Strangest Experiment,</em> is good.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... Copenhagen delenda est.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Copenhagen must be destroyed, following the shortened form of Cato's
repeated call for the destruction of Carthage.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In most versions of many-worlds, there are no particles as such; the
same is true for most versions of spontaneous-collapse theories. So
my use of the word “photon” is a bit of a fudge, but you can just
read it as “wave packet” if you're really persnickety. (page 342)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20250601-what_is_real_by_becker/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20250601-what_is_real_by_becker/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) I Hate the Ivy League, by Gladwell</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This is the first time I've seen a collection of podcasts packaged as
an <a href="https://www.pushkin.fm/audiobooks/i-hate-the-ivy-league-riffs-and-rants-on-elite-education">audiobook</a>. There is no corresponding printed book that you can
buy. Sort of weird, but Gladwell is good enough that it works.</p>
<hr>
<p>I tend to agree with Gladwell. Education shouldn't be an elitist thing
based on keeping people out.</p>
<hr>
<p>One thing Gladwell discusses is two opposing views of what education
should do, corresponding to two opposing views of what we need.</p>
<p>He uses basketball and soccer to illustrate the two views, saying that
in basketball you win based on your <em>best</em> players, while in soccer
you win based on your <em>worst</em> players. So in basketball it's okay to
have some weaker players, if your star/s is/are great, while in soccer
you might win more by improving your worst players.</p>
<p>I've heard this explicitly, for education. Kai-fu Lee <a href="/20200926-ai_superpowers_by_lee/" title="AI Superpowers, by Lee">says</a> that
good educational "programs seek to identify and realize the potential
of the country's top technical minds, an approach suited to creating
the material prosperity that can then be broadly shared across
society."</p>
<p>From another angle, it's the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_man_theory">great man theory</a> against the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ortega_hypothesis">Ortega hypothesis</a>, roughly.</p>
<p>From another angle, it's conservatism vs. progressivism: individuals
should be able to succeed wildly, vs. the poorest should be helped.</p>
<p>Gladwell also relates this idea to the Industrial Revolution happening
in England. He attributes it to the abundance of tinkerers/inventors
all working on things. (Cf. <a href="/20250322-power_and_progress_by_acemoglu_and_johnson/">Power and Progress</a>)</p>
<hr>
<p>Gladwell doesn't like timed tests. I'm a little torn, but I do have to
wonder: Did timed standardized tests influence my work style? Would I
have been better off with more focus on longer-term planning and
projects?</p>
<hr>
<p>“Mirror-tocracy”</p>
<hr>
<p>There's an interesting bit about how <a href="https://mcconville.rbind.io/">Kelly McConville</a>'s students
reverse-engineered the US News college rankings. It's a place where
regression makes sense, because the methodology of the rankings
matches up with what regression can do. It also reminded me of my old
project on <a href="/20190529-understanding_myintuition/">Understanding MyinTuition</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20250322-i_hate_the_ivy_league_by_gladwell/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20250322-i_hate_the_ivy_league_by_gladwell/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Power and Progress, by Acemoglu and Johnson</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This <a href="https://shapingwork.mit.edu/power-and-progress/">book</a> from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daron_Acemoglu" title="Daron Acemoglu">Acemoglu</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_Johnson_(economist)" title="Simon Johnson (economist)">Johnson</a> explains that
technological progress doesn't automatically make everyone better off.
They're right, but they're also too conventional to see beyond the
labor exchange paradigm, constraining the application of their thesis.</p>
<p>The authors understand that we make choices about who benefits from
technology, but they're also committed to the idea that people should
have to work for a living. This limits their imagination and results
in recommendations that pursue full employment instead of enabling a
vision of a yet brighter future.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Workers complained about conditions and the backbreaking effort.
Most egregious to many were the rules they had to follow in
factories. One weaver put it this way in 1834: “No man would like to
work in a power-loom, they do not like it, there is such a
clattering and noise it would almost make some men mad; and next, he
would have to be subject to a discipline that a hand-loom weaver can
never submit to.”</p>
<p>New machinery turned workers into mere cogs. As another weaver
testified before a parliamentary committee in April 1835, “I am
determined for my part, that if they will invent machines to
supersede manual labour, they must find iron boys to mind them.”
(page 8)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I include this selection because I found the phrase “iron boys”
weirdly evocative in its contrast. It reminds me a little bit of
“<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Windup_Girl" title="The Windup Girl">windup girls</a>.”</p>
<p>The point of the weaver is that working with the new machines is less
pleasant than his accustomed artisanal process. It is less humane. It
is dehumanizing.</p>
<p>It also highlights that the conversion is incomplete; the attempt “to
supersede manual labor” has not fully succeeded, while people still
have to work with the machines. I find myself agreeing that “they must
find iron boys to mind them.”</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“In <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Novum_Organum"><em>Novum Organum</em></a>, published in 1620, Bacon had argued that
scientific knowledge would enable nothing less than human control
over nature.” (page 12)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I feel like I should have recognized this immediately, but I had to
look it up. It is the shift from pure logic to focus on observation.
Pure logic is limited or full of madness; science has shaky
foundations but remarkable technological fruit.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Optimism regarding shared benefits from technological progress is
founded on a simple and powerful idea: the “productivity bandwagon.”
This idea maintains that new machines and production methods that
increase productivity will also produce higher wages. As technology
progresses, the bandwagon will pull along everybody, not just
entrepreneurs and owners of capital. (page 15)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>On the one hand, it seems ridiculous that anyone would believe in such
a “productivity bandwagon,” but on the other hand, people do seem to
believe something like it, often.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>technology is about control, not just over nature but often over
other humans. It is not simply that technological change benefits
some more than others. More fundamentally, different ways of
organizing production enrich and empower some people and disempower
others. (page 26)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This could be a thesis for the book.</p>
<p>There is perhaps a false divide between “nature” and “other humans.”
In both cases there is an “othering.”</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Central to this volte-face was a change in the direction of
technology away from new tasks and opportunities for workers and
toward a preoccupation with automating work and cutting labor costs.
(page 32)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Listening to the audiobook and unfamiliar with “volte-face,” which is
French for “about-face” (a complete and sudden change) I made a quick
mental note to look it up later. Only half-remembering the context, I
thought it might be some proper noun I was unfamiliar with. I guessed
it was spelled “voltfass” and that it might be German. Asking ChatGPT
about this, it was happy to hallucinate and send me on a merry chase
around the internet. It took me quite some time to track it to what it
actually was.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>To understand <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_de_Lesseps" title="Ferdinand de Lesseps">Lesseps</a>’s vision, we must first turn to the ideas
of the French social reformer Henri de Saint-Simon and his colorful
followers. Saint-Simon was an aristocratic writer who maintained
that human progress is driven by scientific invention and the
application of new ideas to industry. But he also thought that the
right leadership was critical for this progress: “All enlightened
peoples will adopt the view that men of genius should be given the
highest social standing.” (page 36)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Okay so <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_de_Lesseps" title="Ferdinand de Lesseps">Lesseps</a> was this canal guy who made the Suez Canal and
then failed to make the Panama Canal because he stubbornly wanted to
do it the same way. The chapter is called “Canal Vision” and it's
basically saying look, the best ideas don't win automatically.
Personality matters, reputation matters, rhetoric matters. And if you
put all your faith in this one guy, he can screw it up.</p>
<p>This all hits fairly close to home. At work, I sometimes feel like I'm
witnessing a Panama Canal effect, where someone who had past success
is forging ahead with something new regardless of whether the new
thing is a good idea really. “Vision is power,” influence without
authority, etc.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daron_Acemoglu" title="Daron Acemoglu">Acemoglu</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_Johnson_(economist)" title="Simon Johnson (economist)">Johnson</a> are the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_institutional_economics">New Institutional Economics</a>
guys, and they talk about how they think the Industrial Revolution
happened in Britain because people could try to get rich and were
allowed to.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Friedman, who, like Hayek and Stigler, was awarded the Nobel Prize
in economics, made important contributions to many areas, including
macroeconomics, price theory, and monetary policy. Arguably,
however, his most influential work did not appear in an academic
journal but in a short piece published in September 1970 in the New
York Times Magazine, immodestly titled “<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1970/09/13/archives/a-friedman-doctrine-the-social-responsibility-of-business-is-to.html" title="A Friedman doctrine‐- The Social Responsibility of Business Is to Increase Its Profits">A Friedman Doctrine</a>.”
Friedman argued that the “social responsibility” of business was
misconstrued. Business should care only about making profits and
generating high returns for their shareholders. Simply put, “The
social responsibility of business is to increase its profits.” (page
205)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Oh my. I think I hadn't realized that this had been put so explicitly.</p>
<hr>
<p>They go on about “Machine Usefulness” and automation vs. creating new
tasks, and there's something to it, but I don't think it amounts to an
optimal path forward. They're focused on ensuring that benefits go to
workers, but I think we need to get beyond making everybody be a
worker.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20250322-power_and_progress_by_acemoglu_and_johnson/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20250322-power_and_progress_by_acemoglu_and_johnson/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Superconvergence, by Metzl</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jamie_Metzl">Metzl</a> rubs me the wrong way, a little bit, the way the heros of
LinkedIn do. He's been bio-focused, and still is, but AI is hot so AI
is in the book. He's not wrong, exactly, but it still feels
attention-seeking. <a href="https://www.hachettebookgroup.com/titles/jamie-metzl/superconvergence/9781643263007/">The book</a> has very low information density, and
then weirdly his main objective in the end is to get people excited
about regulation.</p>
<p>Metzl advocates for the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ortega_hypothesis">Ortega hypothesis</a>, but mostly because it
fits well with his story of exponential scientific progress: if we
don't have to wait for geniuses, then progress can keep accelerating.
Interesting take.</p>
<p>He talks a lot about god-like powers, and how we need to regulate
them. He's at pains to say this shouldn't be a global body imposing
rules, but that every country should do things in line with their own
culture and values. Ignoring that requiring countries to regulate
where they wouldn't on their own is already an imposition, this
federated approach only works if we have fairly strong assumptions
about every government's culture and values playing well with what we
think is reasonable. But then he goes on to say that also there should
be international coordination, seemingly with more teeth than the WHO
and so on, so he is arguing for global control in the end as well.</p>
<p>Metzl also believes <a href="https://jamiemetzl.com/origins-of-sars-cov-2/">fairly strongly</a> that COVID-19 was produced by
humans. It makes sense to talk about this in the book because it adds
weight to the discussion of risks, making it not just hypothetical.
This kind of talk always makes me think of the assassination germ idea
in <a href="/20200124-three_body_problem_remembrance_of_earths_past/">The Three Body Problem</a>. Scary stuff indeed.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241230-superconvergence_by_metzl/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241230-superconvergence_by_metzl/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Playing with Reality, by Clancy</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I think <a href="https://www.npr.org/people/724387257/darian-woods">Darian Woods</a> mentioned <a href="https://www.kellybclancy.com/">Clancy</a>'s book in an episode of
The Indicator. Great recommendation! <em>Playing with Reality</em> could be
the best book of the year. Beautifully written, rich with information,
humane in perspective. The thesis is basically that the map is not the
territory, and games can be kinds of maps. Sort of like
<a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>, it explores ways that simplified and
quantified models can mislead. Fascinating throughout.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<h3>History of education</h3>
<p>The first game in the book is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rithmomachia">Rithmomachia</a>, the math game you
played as part of your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadrivium">Quadrivium</a> education, which was a thing
from Greek to Medieval times. The history of education is fascinating.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trivium">Trivium</a><ul>
<li>grammar</li>
<li>logic</li>
<li>rhetoric</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadrivium">Quadrivium</a><ul>
<li>“arithmetic (pure numbers)”</li>
<li>“geometry (numbers in space)”</li>
<li>“music (numbers in time)”</li>
<li>“astronomy (numbers in space and time)” (page 5)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>“Some medieval historians blame the quadrivial curriculum for
holding European scholarship back hundreds of years. Its focus on
harmony blinkered scientists to fundamental advances, such as the
discovery of irrational numbers and celestial mechanics. The
quadrivial curriculum was largely abandoned by the seventeenth
century, as new mathematical techniques from Persia and India led to
breakthroughs in calculus and probability theory. Rithmomachia
similarly fell by the wayside.” (page 7)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This idea, of education hampering progress, is very interesting. I
wonder whether things like the Chinese exam system might have had a
similar effect. What about the current education system? What is
blocking rather than enabling progress?</p>
<p>The book doesn't talk about it, but according to Wikipedia an
intermediate successor curriculum was the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humanitas#Revival">studia humanitatis</a>
around the 14th century, with Petrarch.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humanitas#Revival">studia humanitatis</a><ul>
<li>grammar</li>
<li>rhetoric</li>
<li>poetry</li>
<li>history</li>
<li>moral philosophy</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Later, the book describes "required training for nobility in Europe
and the Near East."</p>
<ul>
<li>an eighteenth century aristocrat was expected to master<ul>
<li>calligraphy</li>
<li>horseback riding</li>
<li>history</li>
<li>philosophy</li>
<li>weaponry</li>
<li>music</li>
<li>astrology</li>
<li>games, especially chess</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>“Kriegsspiel roots back to the late eighteenth century, when
mathematician Johann Hellwig invented a variant of chess. Chess was
then considered to be required training for nobility in Europe and
the Near East; an aristocrat was expected to master calligraphy,
horseback riding, history, philosophy, weaponry, music, astrology,
and games, especially chess. Tutors used chess to teach strategic
thinking and mathematics to their pupils. Chess, originally
chaturanga, originated in India as an explicit abstraction of war.”
(page 47)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Lots of the book is about how we learn from games, but in explicitly
educational contexts and elsewhere.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Psychohistory</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“The new field’s [statistics'] success expanded to other social
sciences. The nineteenth-century Belgian mathematician Adolphe
Quetelet was a tireless advocate for a new science he called “social
physics,” whereby he hoped to work out a human correlate of
celestial mechanics and describe the trajectories of civilization.
Quetelet used massive datasets to detect underlying patterns. He
found regularities in births, deaths, suicides, and even crime
rates. He argued that crimes should not be considered acts of
individual volition. Instead, he found that they obeyed statistical
laws at the population level. “Society itself contains the germs of
all the crimes committed. It is the social state, in some measure,
that prepares these crimes, and the criminal is merely the
instrument that executes them.” Criminals were themselves victims,
helpless to the laws of social physics acting on society, a
necessary sacrifice to preserve civilization. He suggested that
evidence-based legislation—aimed more at ameliorating the
institutional causes of crime and less at punishing individual
criminals themselves—was the best hope for reforming society.
Quetelet’s ideas were so pervasive that physicist James Clerk
Maxwell often illustrated his work in statistical mechanics using
analogies drawn from social physics. To those armed with the hammer
of probability theory, the world looked like a statistics problem.
If we could use math to understand even chance, why not use it to
understand humanity itself?” (page 40)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>“Social physics” is yet another name for <a href="/20200714-foundation_trilogy/">psychohistory</a>!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The historian Hans Delbrück recognized that military and political
history are inextricably tangled. He was committed to establishing a
quantitative study of history. Throughout his career, Delbrück pored
over historical data, hoping to develop a science of war,
relentlessly workshopping historical battles to test his theories.
He argued that Germany’s failures in World War I were primarily
strategic in nature. He advocated for their neutered military to
take up historical study and simulations. By embracing these
simulations during the interwar period, the Germans developed a new
form of combat using theoretical forces that did not yet exist but
soon would. It promised to solve the stagnant trench warfare that
had characterized World War I, leveraging surprise to dominate and
demoralize the enemy. In World War II, this tactic would rain terror
from the skies across Europe. It would come to be known throughout
the world as the Blitzkrieg.” (page 52)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And again!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The real question,” he [Skinner] writes, “is not whether machines
think but whether men do. The mystery which surrounds a thinking
machine already surrounds a thinking man.” (page 21)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think Skinner is getting at the questions of consciousness and free
will. Provocative phrasing.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Like many scientists of the era, such as Galileo, Cardano was made
a celebrity by the horoscopes he drew up for the ruling class.
Astrology played the role of today’s science-funding agencies.”
(page 34)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sometimes data science work feels a little like this. People want
predictions, and they don't always want a careful accounting of
uncertainty. They want to hear what they want to hear. And like magic
or divination, why not just take a stab at it? You'll be right
sometimes!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“It seemed so ubiquitous that many scientists used it to simplify
the measurement of errors in a wide range of datasets, including
many they shouldn’t have. They were, as mathematician Nassim
Nicholas Taleb puts it, “blinded by bell curves.” (page 40)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This idea is applied to Black–Scholes, and Taleb's “ludic fallacy” is
described: the mistake of applying the rules of games to real-life
situations.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Through seemingly objective arguments like these, the status quo
keeps its finger tipping the scales in the marketplace of ideas,
assigning invented values to justify arbitrary ideologies.” (page
45)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The example is weird MacAskill argument. These "Effective Altruism"
people, jeez.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“His [Hilbert's] student Hermann Weyl writes: “Mathematics is no
longer knowledge but a game of formulae, ruled by certain
conventions, which is very well comparable to the game of chess.”
(page 58)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“We may still choose to make a wager with a low likelihood of
success if the outcome is something we want enough—like putting in
the effort to apply for a highly competitive job, even if it’s
unlikely we’ll get it. In this framework, a rational actor will
always make choices that they believe will maximize their expected
utility, balancing their desire for a given option with its risks.
Given certain assumptions, their preferences can be described by a
utility function, which can be used to predict their strategies and
choices. Von Neumann’s elegant formulation transmuted subjective
individual desire into a shared frame of reference, defined entirely
by an agent’s actions in a collective playing field. He derived all
of this in the span of a single afternoon. Morgenstern later wrote
in his diary that watching von Neumann solve in one day a problem
that had plagued economists for years “gave me great satisfaction,
and moved me so much that afterwards I could not think about
anything else.” (page 66)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This presentation of von Neumann as a 10x genius is interesting.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“In game theory, players’ preferences are usually assumed to be
fixed. But psychologists have found that people’s choices are
sensitive to a game’s context. Players behave differently in a
prisoner’s dilemma depending on how it’s presented to them. If it’s
called the Wall Street Game, players are more likely to defect. If
it’s called the Community Game, they’re more likely to cooperate.
The two games have the exact same structure, payoffs, and penalties
(e.g., jail time), yet their titles alone cause players to act
differently.” (page 76)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Game theory, pioneered by a traumatized man hoping to plumb the
depths of human nature, has only ever been about math: the dynamics
of a maximizing function, not of real people. We must be careful not
to let its models mean anything about ourselves, and careful to
prevent its fables from seeping into the domain of accepted wisdom.
Let’s consider the zero-sum bias. People across the globe tend to
believe that all resources are limited, even when this is not the
case. An isolationist might oppose immigration because they think
that immigrants “steal” from a fixed number of available jobs, not
realizing that immigrants also drive economic growth and create new
jobs.” (page 80)</p>
<p>“Game theory’s power lies in its expressiveness: it can convey
dynamic stories with simple mechanics. Unfortunately, game theory
has been used to launder dubious beliefs and present racist,
nativist policies as objective or inevitable. Some of these sinister
fables have been taken out of context and integrated into the
foundations of accepted common sense. If game theory continues to be
used as a model of human behavior, it needs major revisions to
reflect the fact that most people aren’t singularly focused on
personal gain. Even then, we’d be better off modeling people for
what they are: flexible learners.” (page 86)</p>
<p>“In his book <em>Economic Fables</em>, mathematician Ariel Rubinstein
likens game theory—mathematical abstractions of complex
situations—to fables with oversimple morals. We should be careful
not to mistake these for reality. Game theory should be studied for
its mathematical beauty, but it cannot pretend to tell us about the
real world. Rubinstein argues that even many academics don’t fully
understand it and often fail to communicate its limitations. This
would not be an issue if game theory remained a purely academic
pursuit. But it’s been adopted for use in modern systems that impact
billions of people worldwide.” (page 98)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“In 1930, Fisher collected and extended his genetic insights in his
opus, The Genetical Theory of Natural Selection, which almost
single-handedly revitalized Darwin’s ideas and rescued them from
years of neglect by academics. In the book, Fisher elaborates—in his
characteristically cryptic style—what is now one of the most
celebrated arguments in evolutionary biology and an early seed of
game-theoretic thinking in the life sciences.” (page 113)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The part I'm interested in here is that Fisher is said to have a
"characteristically cryptic style." This is the guy who wrote
"Statistical Methods for Research Workers" and "The Design of
Experiments." Is his cryptic style part of why frequentist statistics
is such a poorly understood mess?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Price_equation">Price equation</a> is the fundamental theorem of evolution and
can be used to derive other basic theorems of evolution. The
equation’s generality lends it its power. This same generality
invites misuse from researchers unfamiliar with its nuances. Some
have dismissed it as a tautology, nothing more than a statistical
identity. Others have praised its depth.” (page 123)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Games remain an impressive way to evaluate a program’s
capabilities. In the early 1980s, graduate students Shafi Goldwasser
and Silvio Micali invented a powerful new form of mathematical proof
by imagining how they might play a secure poker game over the phone.
The resulting technique, interactive proof systems, consists of two
subparts, a prover and a verifier. These exchange messages until the
verifier is “convinced” that an answer is correct. Interactive
proofs became a foundational technique in computer science and
cryptography. They’re also the metaphoric heart of how we hope to
verify intelligence through games. Traditional math proofs are
inevitable, each step an irresistible conclusion unfolding from the
last. Interactive proofs, on the other hand, are probabilistically
true. By testing again and again, the verifier becomes increasingly
convinced of the prover’s claim. The Turing test, for instance, can
be mathematically formalized in this framework. Games take the same
form: human experts repeatedly test a game-playing computer program
to convince themselves of its capabilities. There is no single
measure of intelligence, or its mechanical approximation. Its
evaluation will be, by nature, interactive: the iterated probing of
a system.” (pages 137-138)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“To borrow social theorist Sherry Turkle’s phrase, we too easily
abdicate authority to simulations. Simulations are ultimately
constrained by their creators’ assumptions: games are self-contained
universes ticking along to preprogrammed logic. They don’t
necessarily reflect anything fundamental about the world. Models’
conclusions are less interesting than the assumptions on which
they’re based—assumptions that are typically hidden.” (page 159)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Utopia is the process of making a better world, the name for one
path history can take, a dynamic, tumultuous, agonizing process,
with no end. Struggle forever.” (page 160, quoting Kim Stanley
Robinson)</p>
<p>“The game Moksha Patam (today’s Snakes and Ladders) is often
credited to the thirteenth-century Marathi saint Dnyaneshwar, though
it may have been invented hundreds of years earlier. It was designed
to teach players about karma and illustrate the precarity of fate.
In it, souls ascend to the heavenly realms, dragged down by vices
(snakes) and buoyed by virtues (ladders). Snakes are labeled with
the names of demons and the vices they represent, and players
recount stories from Hindu mythology as they play.” (page 160)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Scholars have sought to find a purely logical foundation for the
question of morality and how society should be structured. In the
mid-twentieth century, philosopher John Rawls began a line of
inquiry that culminated in his celebrated 1971 treatise, <em>A Theory
of Justice</em>. In this work, he posits fairness as the foundational
principle, or “first virtue,” on which society should be built.”
(page 163)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“In the 1950s, game theorists discovered that some repeated games
support an infinite number of stable equilibrium strategies. This
became known as the folk theorem, because it was such an obvious
outcome that no one bothered formally publishing it.” (page 165)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Board game designer Reiner Knizia claims that the scoring system is
the most important part of designing a new game. It’s the score that
drives players’ behaviors. Similarly, in a subfield of game theory
known as mechanism design, or reverse game theory, mathematicians
design institutional rules that incentivize players to behave in
particular ways.” (page 174)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is pretty neat. Start with the end in mind, and then rather than
thinking we can influence people directly, imagine we can control "the
rules of the game" (through policy, etc.) - how do they get set up to
achieve the desired end? Possible connection also to "nudge" ideas,
etc.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241226-playing_with_reality_by_clancy/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241226-playing_with_reality_by_clancy/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) The Next Millionaire Next Door</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>It's sweet that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_J._Stanley">Stanley</a>'s daughter finished this 2020 follow-up to
his 1996 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Millionaire_Next_Door">Millionaire Next Door</a> after he died in 2015. There are
refreshed surveys, but not a lot that's new, as far as I can tell,
apart from attempts to defend the family legacy from criticism.</p>
<p>The core concept is still spending less money than you get. More pages
are given to spending less than to getting more. Conscientiousness and
discipline are emphasized. America is presented as uniquely suited to
building wealth because of freedom.</p>
<p>One criticism of the original book was that the core thesis (that
normal people can become millionaires) was an artifact of survivorship
bias observed toward the end of a bull market. I didn't hear a really
good response to this criticism, but I don't think it's a particularly
interesting criticism either.</p>
<p>I think the deeper latent criticism is about what level of the system
to blame. Stanley is all about the individual level. "The game is
winnable!" he says. Critics, I think, are often talking about
something fundamentally different. "The rules of the game are unfair!"
they say. Both these things can be true at the same time.</p>
<p>It's easy to wag a finger at someone with a high income who's still
barely making their house and car payments. But far more people have
low income, not much room to cut expenses, and little opportunity to
increase their income. These books have more advice for the former
than the latter.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241224-next_millionaire_next_door/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241224-next_millionaire_next_door/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Matilda, by Dahl</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>A local middle school put on Matilda, the musical, which made me
curious enough to read the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matilda_(novel)">book</a>. It's strange and cute. It's very
episodic, with the main resolution appearing with less warning in the
book than the musical. Apparently in early versions of the book
Matilda was even more malicious.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It's not fair," Lavender said. "How can she do it and we can't?"
(page 69)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"You are so much wiser than your years, my dear," Miss Honey went
on, "that it quite staggers me. Although you look like a child, you
are not really a child at all because your mind and your powers of
reasoning seem to be fully grown-up. So I suppose we might call you
a grown-up child, if you see what I mean." (page 189)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Without stories we're just eating machines with shoes." (Dennis
Kelly, script-writer for the musical, in an afterward)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Tim Minchin did the music and lyrics for the musical. He also did
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fCNvZqpa-7Q">White Wine In The Sun</a>.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241221-matilda_by_dahl/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241221-matilda_by_dahl/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Financial calculators exist</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>When you take the <a href="/20241123-what_are_cfps_supposed_to_know/" title="Certified Financial Planner">CFP</a> exam, you are allowed to use a
<a href="https://www.cfp.net/-/media/files/cfp-board/cfp-certification/exam/calculator-policy.pdf">dedicated financial calculator</a> like the Texas Instruments
"Business Analyst" <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Texas-Instruments-Advanced-Financial-Calculator/dp/B0029F1OKE">BA II Plus</a>. How wild is that?</p>
<p><img alt="calculator" src="ba2plus.jpg"></p>
<p>What does it do? You can start to guess from buttons like "IRR," but
the <a href="https://education.ti.com/en/guidebook/details/en/ADF11FB65B284B6195B0A7E9502784BA/baiiplus">manual</a> explains much more about how the functionality is
organized into "worksheets" and so on.</p>
<p><img alt="functions" src="functions.png"></p>
<p>Do people use these for real, in their work? My guess is that they're
sort of an archaic thing that persists only for the exam? Surely
people use one of many <a href="https://www.calculator.net/finance-calculator.html">online calculators</a>, or Excel, or some other
more user-friendly tool? (Although I don't really know what a great
example is; most of the ones I see at a quick look seem pretty
crummy...)</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241123-financial_calculators_exist/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241123-financial_calculators_exist/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>What are CFPs supposed to know?</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>To be a Certified Financial Planner, you have to have a bachelor's
degree (in anything) and do (<a href="https://www.cfp.net/get-certified/certification-process/education-requirement/certification-coursework-requirement/accelerated-path">usually</a>) seven <a href="https://www.cfp.net/">CFP Board</a>-approved
classes and pass a test covering many <a href="https://www.cfp.net/get-certified/certification-process/education-requirement/certification-coursework-requirement/what-youll-learn">topics</a>. The classes are
Fundamentals, Insurance, Investments, Tax, Retirement, Estate, and a
capstone case study class. Then you do 30 hours of continuing
education every two years.</p>
<p>The CFP Board <a href="https://www.cfp.net/get-certified/certification-process/education-requirement/certification-coursework-requirement/find-an-education-program/">lists</a> about 250 institutions with approved
offerings, mostly universities. These can be outsourced offerings, for
example from <a href="https://cerifi.com/">Cerifi</a>'s <a href="https://dalton-education.com/university-partnerships">Dalton Education</a> or
<a href="https://www.greeneconsults.com/">Greene Consulting</a>'s <a href="https://www.financialplannerprogram.com/#school">Financial Planner Program</a> or <a href="https://www.kenzahn.com/">Zahn</a>.</p>
<p>There seem to be two main lines of textbooks. One is <a href="https://cerifi.com/">Cerifi</a>'s
<a href="https://www.money-education.com/">Money Education</a>, which <a href="https://cerifi.com/our-brands">claims</a> to by “chosen by 200
universities nationwide.” The <a href="https://www.nationalunderwriter.com/series/academic.html">other</a> is from
<a href="https://www.nationalunderwriter.com/">National Underwriter</a>, mostly in their <a href="https://www.nationalunderwriter.com/series/the-leimberg-library.html">Leimberg Library</a>. There
used to be books from Keir, but they <a href="https://www.keirsuccess.com/products/cfp-certification-products/education-courses/university-textbooks">joined forces</a> with
<a href="https://www.money-education.com/">Money Education</a>.</p>
<p>From <a href="https://www.opensyllabus.org/">Open Syllabus</a>, it isn't clear which books are most popular. I
find <a href="https://analytics.opensyllabus.org/record/works?syllabus_query=money+education">one entry each</a> for two of the Money Education books, and
<a href="https://analytics.opensyllabus.org/record/works?syllabus_query=leimberg">no mention</a> of Leimberg books. It seems like <a href="https://www.cffp.edu/cfp-education">Kaplan</a> and
<a href="https://www.brettdanko.com/">Danko</a> also have materials, but may only offer them to participants
in their courses.</p>
<p>There are also lots of exam prep and study materials. <a href="https://www.kenzahn.com/">Zahn</a> for
example makes supplemental books and flashcards, and Money Education
has “QuickSheets.”</p>
<p>There's also a thing called a <a href="/20241123-financial_calculators_exist/">financial calculator</a>, which can be a
physical object that CFPs may learn to use.</p>
<p>For continuing education, every two years a CFP has to do 30 hours of
programs, selected from <a href="https://www.cfp.net/career-and-growth/continuing-education/find-a-ce-program">thousands</a> that are approved by the CFP
Board.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241123-what_are_cfps_supposed_to_know/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241123-what_are_cfps_supposed_to_know/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) We've got you covered, by Einav and Finkelstein</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I read <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/690632/weve-got-you-covered-by-liran-einav-and-amy-finkelstein/" title="We've Got You Covered: Rebooting American Health Care">this book</a> because Furman recommended it, and his
<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/10/21/books/review/economics-business-books.html" title="5 Books to Help You Understand the Economy Before Voting">description</a> is good. I admire the economist authors' ability to
take a normative stand while staying clear-headed about measured
realities. I'm on board.</p>
<p>The central claim of the book is that we <em>should</em> provide free basic
health care to everyone. They support this by arguing that the US has
been <em>trying</em> to do this: trying to honor an implicit social contract.</p>
<p>The issue then is that the US has been doing a very poor job of it.
The authors propose that health insurance should instead be free and
automatic for everyone, with no sign-up hoops or costs incurred for
receiving care.</p>
<p>Problems with the current US system include its complexity itself, and
health insurance being tied to employment (therefore subject to
termination at any time) and medical costs being a potentially
unbounded burden for individuals, sometimes even for those <em>with</em>
insurance.</p>
<p>They point out that insurance doesn't actually have that much
influence on health outcomes, because impact on health is dominated by
behaviors that correlate with wealth, for example, and because people
generally still <em>get</em> health care even if not insured, even if it also
saddles them with debt. So universal health insurance won't resolve
disparities in health outcomes. (This does appear somewhat at odds
with the authors' frequent complaint that the US system often pays for
treatment only after conditions become acute dangers, while earlier
treatment might have been cheaper and prevented the worst health
outcomes.)</p>
<p>The book is also full of interesting current and historical detail
about the US and international health systems.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“We have therefore intentionally focused on what we <em>should</em> do,
rather than what some may think we currently <em>can</em> do. In this
sense, our book is in the spirit of the famous Chicago economist
Milton Friedman. He argued that the role for economists in public
policy is to develop the best ideas, and keep them alive and ripe in
the public imagination until the day when “the politically
impossible becomes the politically inevitable.” (page 14)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Let’s start with the precarious insurance of the privately insured.
Almost half of the US population—over 150 million people—receive
private health insurance through their employers or a family
member’s employer. That’s almost all Americans who have private
health insurance.</p>
<p>There’s no natural reason why their boss doubles as their insurer.
This unusual arrangement arose through an accident of history, a
common theme of US health-care policy. During World War II, the
federal government imposed wage and price controls to try to prevent
inflation. Employers—desperate to attract and retain scarce
workers—soon discovered a way to get around the wage ceilings and
provide higher compensation. They could offer—and pay for—their
workers’ health insurance, because these payments weren’t counted as
“wages.”</p>
<p>The practice of excluding employer payments for their employees’
health insurance from the definition of employee earnings has
remained in place to this day. As a result, any such payments are
tax-free. An employee doesn’t have to pay income tax on any
contributions her employer makes to her workplace-based health
insurance premium.” (page 17)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Moral commitments are not limitless. Even FDR implicitly
acknowledged this in his Second Bill of Rights. He spoke of rights
such as “a decent home,” “a good education,” and “adequate medical
care.” The economist Arthur Okun, writing a few decades later,
likewise espoused a right to health care while simultaneously
cautioning that these rights are not unbounded. With the customary
bluntness of an economist rather than a politician, he described “a
heated debate with an audience of medical administrators.” As Okun
described it, “Taking what I viewed as an outlandish example, I
suggested that any national health program should not grant me at
public expense all the pairs of eyeglasses I might like. I learned
to my surprise that they favored an unlimited right to eyeglasses.”
(page 74)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The technical term for this quality of life measure is <em>quality
adjusted life year,</em> or QALY (rhymes with <em>jolly</em>). A year in
perfect health is given a QALY score of one, a year of being dead
scores zero. Much scientific effort and squabbling go into assigning
scores to all the various ways a year can be spent in
less-than-perfect health. (footnote, page 100)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is part of a section which is a great example of the challenges
of trying to linearize multiple things into one measure. In this case
they were using a ratio of benefits to cost, so a cheap and decent
thing showed up as better than an expensive but essential thing.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The faithful and accurate application of cost-benefit analysis had
produced unacceptable results. Even the commissioners agreed,
acknowledging that their rankings often conflicted with their own
intuition. They quickly abandoned the formulaic application of
cost-effectiveness rankings in favor of a more “holistic” approach.
They used their judgment—and that of members of the community who
provided input through public forums—to create broad categories of
health care that they ranked in order of importance. Effective care
for acute fatal conditions (such as appendectomies) was ranked high,
while minimally effective treatments for nonfatal conditions (such
as tooth capping or medical therapy for diaper rash) were in a
category near the bottom.” (page 100)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241116-weve_got_you_covered_by_einav_and_finkelstein/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241116-weve_got_you_covered_by_einav_and_finkelstein/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Technofeudalism, by Varoufakis</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The generous interpretation is that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yanis_Varoufakis">Varoufakis</a> understands that
his <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/751443/technofeudalism-by-yanis-varoufakis/">technofeudalism</a> is not distinct from capitalism but that since
capitalism's valence is unassailable, perhaps a new word can be more
successfully attacked. (The less generous interpretation is that he
wants credit for a catchy idea.)</p>
<p>In the book, Varoufakis is personable. He's likeable. His writing is
friendly, and his stories about his father are charming. And he
<a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2024/04/01/has-capitalism-been-replaced-by-technofeudalism">likes Star Trek</a>, which is a great sign of character.</p>
<p>His technofeudalism refers to the monopolistic market capture,
"moats," and rent-seeking of (mostly) big tech. But this is just
capitalism as usual; <a href="/20240625-titan_by_chernow/">Rockefeller</a> would be on board. Thinking of
capitalism as pro-competition is ridiculous.</p>
<p>He says some things about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historical_materialism">historical materialism</a>, which is kind of
interesting. I buy into the importance of technology for enabling big
structural changes to standard of living, for example. (See also:
<a href="/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>)</p>
<p>There's also something interesting about separating the exchange or
commodity value vs. the experiential value of things (like work).
Varoufakis says employers profit because they pay commodity price for
workers' time but get the "experiential" (real?) value of their work.
In some sense, a company pays out less than it takes in, if it can,
but I'm not sure this decomposition holds in a meaningful way.
Generally I think Marx focused on labor too much in a similar way to
how physiocrats focused on agriculture (land) too much.</p>
<p>Varoufakis is a little too weird. His use of Amazon Alexa as an
example is unfortunate, given how it's largely a failed technology. He
doesn't seem technologically literate when he talks about ML, which
makes me wonder how good he is in fields I know less about. Like
Bernie, he's concerned about Black Rock/Vanguard/State Street, but I
think this concern is mostly silly. And he's into balancing trade
between nations. (Is this mercantilism?)</p>
<p>So while I'm not with him everywhere, I have a lot of respect for at
least proposing some alternative. (He summarizes his ideas from
<em>Another Now</em>.) And that may be the whole point of Technofeudalism -
getting more people to look at his ideas. It worked on me.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241109-technofeudalism_by_varoufakis/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241109-technofeudalism_by_varoufakis/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Utopia for Realists, by Bregman</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Utopia_for_Realists">Utopia for Realists</a> is a more accessible <a href="/20240929-inventing_the_future_by_srnicek_and_williams/" title="(Audio) Inventing the Future, by Srnicek and Williams">Inventing the Future</a>:
it's in favor of UBI and less work, against neoliberalism/<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mont_Pelerin_Society" title="Mont Pelerin Society">MPS</a>, and
Utopia's "underdog socialism" is like Inventing's "folk politics." It
differs slightly in being explicitly for open borders, like
<a href="/20191109-open_borders_by_caplan_and_weinersmith/" title="Open Borders, by Caplan and Weinersmith">Caplan</a>, and there are some other differences in focus and
examples. The original Dutch title is literally "free money for
everyone."</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Work is the refuge of people who have nothing better to do.” (Oscar
Wilde, quoted page 68)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think Bregman is too concerned with preserving the appearance of the
Puritan work ethic. Like many, he seems to think that giving people
money has to be shown not to reduce hours of work. This is silly and
backward. We should be trying to get people to stop working for pay.</p>
<p>I think it's fine to pull in <a href="/20180218-scarcity_by_sendhil_mullainathan_and_eldar_shafir/" title="Scarcity by Sendhil Mullainathan and Eldar Shafir">Mullainathan and Shafir</a>, as he does,
on the downsides of scarcity, but the reasoning should be that it is
unjust to let people be in bad situations. The trap here is getting
into an argument about who is deserving. If we have to prove that
people are deserving, we've lost already.</p>
<p>Some neat stuff:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cockaigne">Cockaigne</a>: "a land of plenty in medieval myth"</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speenhamland_system">Speenhamland</a>: 1795 "basic income" program, still argued over:
   Did it suppress wages? Did it increase sloth? More children? Loose
   morals?</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mincome">Mincome</a>: "Manitoba Basic Annual Income Experiment" (1970s)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physiocracy">Physiocracy</a>: some kind of economic theory that valued the
   productivity of land/agriculture (over generic labor, etc.)</li>
</ul>
<p>And there's a chapter on GDP (etc.) which made me think that one could
teach a whole course on the downsides or risks of data and data
science, much as in <a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/" title="The Tyranny of Metrics, by Muller">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The RAND Corporation, an influential think tank, foresaw a future
in which just 2% of the population would be able to produce
everything society needed.” (page 18)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But this cites not a RAND study, but “Hillel Ruskin (ed.), Leisure,
Toward a Theory and Policy (1984), p. 152,” and I don't see that
online, so it'll take me a while to check.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Not until 1978 was the plan for a basic income shelved once and for
all, however, following a fatal discovery upon publication of the
final results of the Seattle experiment. One finding in particular
grabbed everybody’s attention: The number of divorces had jumped
more than 50%. Interest in this statistic quickly overshadowed all
the other outcomes, such as better school performance and
improvements in health. A basic income, evidently, gave women too
much independence.</p>
<p>Ten years later, a reanalysis of the data revealed that a
statistical error had been made; in reality, there had been no
change in the divorce rate at all.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The citation here is <a href="https://www.irp.wisc.edu/publications/dps/pdfs/dp85788.pdf">Cain and Wissoker</a>... I've heard about this
divorce finding before ("It's bad!" "It's good!") but I don't think
I've heard about this nullifying result... Why not? I'm not digging
very deep here, but Bregman seems quite Pollyannaish in general
throughout the book, which makes him seem less reliable in general on
specifics.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The free books had made no difference. Test scores showed no
improvement.” (page 91)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But this isn't quite what the <a href="http://www.econ.yale.edu/~egcenter/infoconf/kremer_paper.pdf">study</a> said - and I didn't even read
beyond the abstract! "However, for those students in the top quintile
of the distribution of initial academic achievement, the program
raised test scores by at least 0.2 standard deviations."</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241102-utopia_for_realists_by_bregman/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241102-utopia_for_realists_by_bregman/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) How the World Works, by Chomsky</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>“How the World Works” is a collection of four Chomsky books:</p>
<ul>
<li>What Uncle Sam Really Wants</li>
<li>The Prosperous Few and the Restless Many</li>
<li>Secrets, Lies and Democracy</li>
<li>The Common Good</li>
</ul>
<p>Chomsky says the world is violent. Very violent! He agrees with
<a href="/20240825-principles_changing_world_order_dalio/" title="Principles for dealing with the changing world order, by Dalio">Dalio</a> that international law means little to power. He describes
the Pentagon as an economic stimulus mechanism, which I thought was an
interesting framing.</p>
<p>I first heard about Chomsky in connection with linguistics. The only
linguistic thing he talks about here is the idea of language being
debased, in a similar sense to Orwellian <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newspeak">Newspeak</a>, making it hard
to talk about certain things. I've felt something like this in trying
to talk about a post-work world. To stop selling your labor is called
"retiring," which connotes a kind of withdrawal, which I don't like.
One might also say that to retire is to "stop working," because "work"
can only mean "sell your labor," even if you carry on doing things you
think are useful and productive. It's a similar frustration to that of
the "stay-at-home" parent, who is engaged in effortful activity over
40 hours a week and yet said to "not work." (These aren't Chomsky's
examples.)</p>
<p>And Chomsky mentions interesting things here and there... I don't
think I'd known about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Party_(United_States)">New Party</a>, which continues in part as
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive_Dane">Progressive Dane</a>, a party in Dane County, where I went to college.
I had heard of Progressive Dane, I think, but I wasn't aware of its
historical context.</p>
<p>Some more interesting bits quoted below...</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<h3>“expanding the floor of the cage”</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“So Argentina is “minimizing the state”—cutting down public
expenditures, the way our government is doing, but much more
extremely. Of course, when you minimize the state, you maximize
something else—and it isn’t popular control. What gets maximized is
private power, domestic and foreign.</p>
<p>I met with a very lively anarchist movement in Buenos Aires, and
with other anarchist groups as far away as northeastern Brazil,
where nobody even knew they existed. We had a lot of discussions
about these matters. They recognize that they have to try to use the
state—even though they regard it as totally illegitimate.</p>
<p>The reason is perfectly obvious: When you eliminate the one
institutional structure in which people can participate to some
extent—namely the government—you’re simply handing over power to
unaccountable private tyrannies that are much worse. So you have to
make use of the state, all the time recognizing that you ultimately
want to eliminate it.</p>
<p>Some of the rural workers in Brazil have an interesting slogan. They
say their immediate task is “expanding the floor of the cage.” They
understand that they’re trapped inside a cage, but realize that
protecting it when it’s under attack from even worse predators on
the outside, and extending the limits of what the cage will allow,
are both essential preliminaries to dismantling it. If they attack
the cage directly when they’re so vulnerable, they’ll get murdered.</p>
<p>That’s something anyone ought to be able to understand who can keep
two ideas in their head at once, but some people here in the US tend
to be so rigid and doctrinaire that they don’t understand the point.
But unless the left here is willing to tolerate that level of
complexity, we’re not going to be of any use to people who are
suffering and need our help—or, for that matter, to ourselves.</p>
<p>In Brazil and Argentina, you can discuss these issues even with
people in the highest political echelons, and with elite journalists
and intellectuals. They may not agree with you, but at least they
understand what you’re talking about.” (page 174)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3>“rationality and science”</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“In the 1930s, left intellectuals were involved in worker education
and writing books like <em>Mathematics for the Millions.</em> They
considered it an ordinary, minimal responsibility of privileged
people to help others who’d been deprived of formal education to
enter into high culture.</p>
<p>Today’s counterparts of these 1930s left intellectuals are telling
people, <em>You don’t have to know anything. It’s all junk, a power
play, a white male conspiracy. Forget about rationality and
science.</em> In other words, put those tools in the hands of your
enemies. Let them monopolize everything that works and makes sense.</p>
<p>Plenty of very honorable left intellectuals think this tendency is
liberatory, but I think they’re wrong. A lot of personal
correspondence on related topics between me and my close, valued old
friend Marc Raskin has been published in a book of his. There were
similar interchanges in Z Papers in 1992–93, both with Marc and a
lot of other people with whom I basically feel in sympathy, but with
whom I differ very sharply on this issue.” (page 194)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This "Z" thing still exists, as <a href="https://znetwork.org/" title="ZNetwork - Independent Left News, Analysis, Vision and Strategy">ZNetwork</a>.</p>
<hr>
<h3>“the South Commission”</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“As recently as the early 1990s, the South Commission, which
represented the governments of nonaligned countries, came out with a
very important critique of the antidemocratic, neoliberal model
that’s being forced on the Third World. (The commission included
pretty conservative people, like Indonesia’s development minister.)</p>
<p>They published a book that called for a new world order (they
introduced the term before George [H. W.] Bush did) based on
democracy, justice, development and so on. The book wasn’t
obscure—it was published by Oxford University Press. I wrote about
it, but I couldn’t find much else. They subsequently published
another book of essays commenting on the first one, and I’ve never
seen a reference to that either.</p>
<p>The South Commission happened to represent most of the world’s
population, but the story they were telling just isn’t one the
Western media wanted to hear. So the “new world order” we learned
about was Bush’s, not the one advocated by the South Commission,
which reflects the interests of most of the people of the world.
Back in the 1950s, there were Nehru, Nasser, Tito, Nkrumah, Sukarno
and others…” (page 203)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3>“Here’s what I’m doing. What do you think about it?”</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“Over the years, I <em>have</em> noticed a very striking difference between
talks I give to more or less elite audiences, and meetings and
discussions I have with less privileged people. A while back I was
in a town in Massachusetts at a meeting set up by very good local
organizers in the urban community—people who were pretty poor, even
by world standards. Not long before that, I spent time in the West
Bengal countryside. Then I was in Colombia, talking to human rights
activists who are working under horrifying conditions.</p>
<p>In places like that, people never ask, <em>What should I do?</em> They say,
<em>Here’s what I’m doing. What do you think about it?</em> Maybe they’d
like reactions or suggestions, but they’re already dealing with the
problem. They’re not sitting around waiting for a magic answer,
which doesn’t exist.</p>
<p>When I speak to elite audiences, I constantly get asked, <em>What’s the
solution?</em> If I say obvious things like <em>Pick your cause and go
volunteer for a group that’s working on it,</em> that’s never the answer
they want. They want some sort of magic key that will solve
everything quickly, overwhelmingly and effectively. There are no
such solutions. There are only the kind that people are working on
in Massachusetts towns, in self-governing villages in India, at the
Jesuit Center in Colombia.” (page 206)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241026-how_the_world_works_by_chomsky/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241026-how_the_world_works_by_chomsky/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) After Work, by Hester and Srnicek</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Here's a feminist post-scarcity <a href="https://www.versobooks.com/products/496-after-work" title="After Work: A History of the Home and the Fight for Free Time by Helen Hester and Nick Srnicek">book</a> pointing out that abolishing
paid work won't automatically eliminate unpaid work. There's quite a
bit of unpaid work, and people may or may not want to do it.
Interesting history and ideas on what to do about it.</p>
<p>Did you know there was a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wages_for_housework" title="Wikipedia: Wages for housework">Wages for Housework</a> movement in the 70s?</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.png"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“As we know, domestic realism was not ultimately overthrown by the
communalism of the separatists or the hippies. While some
communities are still operational, Drop City and the vast majority
of initiatives like it proved to be relatively ephemeral
experiments, failing to outlive their moment of sociosexual
upheaval. This may well have been because, as sites of exodus, they
were not always effective at ensuring their own scalability. They
were often intended as prefigurative spaces, aiming to offer a taste
of post-suburban utopia in the here and now (or at least, a utopia
for the young, the healthy, the able bodied, and the middle class
with minimal caring responsibilities – that specific and limited
range of people who might be best able to thrive in a space like
Drop City). As such, they consciously operated as enclaves within
the society from which they sought to withdraw – bastions of
alternative values which were yet to flourish elsewhere – and the
interventions they staged were in certain respects hyperlocal to the
point of being site-specific. The ‘simple positing and practising of
a new world is insufficient to overcome’ the structural forces
preventing its generalisation.129 Or, as Mike Davis puts it,
‘demonstration projects in … rich countries will not save the
world’.” (page 114)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241019-after_work_by_hester_and_srnicek/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241019-after_work_by_hester_and_srnicek/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Inventing the Future, by Srnicek and Williams</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inventing_the_Future:_Postcapitalism_and_a_World_Without_Work">Inventing the Future</a>: Postcapitalism and a World Without Work is
by far the best exposition of a post-scarcity direction that I've
seen. The criticism of folk politics as impotent in important ways
because of its focus on immediacy is incisive. The authors invite us
to grow up and construct the world we want to live in.</p>
<p>I enjoyed their alternate interpretation of the phrase "resistance is
futile," emphasizing the difference between fighting some external
actor and being an active builder. Trying to stop someone else
(political, corporate, etc.) may or may not succeed, but regardless it
will not create a better alternative. If all we do is resist, we never
make anything new.</p>
<p>The authors demand full automation, as in
<a href="/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/" title="Fully Automated Luxury Communism, by Bastani">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>, and indeed Bastani might be
counted among the second-hand dealers in these ideas (though he has
contributions as well).</p>
<p>There's a bunch in the book on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mont_Pelerin_Society">Mont Pelerin Society</a> and the
authors recommend a leftist "ecology of organizations" might achieve
similar success. They mention the <a href="https://neweconomics.org/">New Economics Foundation</a>, but
otherwise I don't know a lot of organizations that might be part of
such an ecology.</p>
<hr>
<p>The authors advocate for higher wages. Higher wages can be good for
the people who get them, but the main focus is on higher wages
encouraging more automation. The authors also advocate for Universal
Basic Income (UBI). They note some challenges with UBI, but I don't
think they completely resolve a conflict here.</p>
<p>What happens to (market-based) wages if people have UBI? Probably lots
of jobs don't have takers any more. This must be the mechanism the
authors are thinking of, and why they emphasize that UBI must really
be enough to live on. But surely some jobs would be doable for <em>lower</em>
wages, if people sort of enjoy them to begin with.</p>
<p>There's no mention of inflation in connection with UBI, which
continues to concern me. How can it work without price controls or
similar? If everyone has more money, surely rent goes up, grocery
prices go up, etc. etc. just as we saw during the pandemic.</p>
<p>As with Universal Basic Services (UBS) I have to think that everything
currently sold on the market would have to edge away from being sold
for profit. A program of UBI can be undone by inflation, and indeed
the goal should be for deflation, as we achieve extreme supply, prices
go to zero, and eventually money can be retired. Postcapitalism is in
the subtitle, but there aren't many details here.</p>
<hr>
<h3>The book is better than the movie</h3>
<p>The book is not written in a broadly accessible style. It's inside
baseball for academics who appreciate Marxist criticism and don't
blink at phrases like "reproductive labor." So I was excited to hear
about a 2020 documentary based on the book, thinking it might speak to
a broader audience.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LY44I9P_QZU">film</a> is feature length, but the style is the unwatchable,
seizure-inducing kind you might walk quickly past in an art museum.
Voices read snippets from the book and other sources, sometimes
reminiscent of Waiting for Godot. Several times we watch sex toys
shimmy on a grey Lego baseplate. It's hard to imagine a movie that
could contribute less to spreading the message of Inventing the
Future. Avoid.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“A politics without demands is simply a collection of aimless
bodies.” (page 105)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One criticism of the book might be that it gets to demands but doesn't
go much farther in terms of concrete mechanisms for achieving them.
Four day work week! Full automation! Okay, but what can people do
apart from writing their senators?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Famously, Oscar Wilde once said that the problem with socialism was
that it took up too many evenings.” (page 177)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't think I'd heard this before; it's good, isn't it? Most people
just want to live their lives. Hence problems, hence opportunities.</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240929-inventing_the_future_by_srnicek_and_williams/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240929-inventing_the_future_by_srnicek_and_williams/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Fully Automated Luxury Communism, by Bastani</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Ridiculing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_End_of_History_and_the_Last_Man" title="The End of History and the Last Man">The End of History</a> and rejecting
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capitalist_Realism" title="Capitalist Realism">Capitalist Realism</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aaron_Bastani" title="Aaron Bastani">Bastani</a> says Marx was ahead of his time:
communism is only now becoming technologically possible. While
Rushkoff <a href="/20240519-survival_of_the_richest_by_rushkoff/" title="Survival of the Richest, by Rushkoff">is</a> anti-growth, Bastani was saying (even before ChatGPT)
that technology will save us. He says we should demand
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fully_Automated_Luxury_Communism" title="Fully Automated Luxury Communism">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>.</p>
<p>A lot of the book is detail on how technology is advancing (or may
advance) to produce "extreme supply." A surprisingly large amount is
about mining asteroids. Predictions on driverless cars and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finless_Foods">Finless Foods</a>, for example, seem premature. (The book only came
out five years ago; is it too early to judge?)</p>
<p>I think Bastani is right that the future he imagines is not
inevitable: it depends on political choices. He mostly assumes that
technological development is inevitable. I'm less sure about that.
They are related, of course.</p>
<p>Bastani has some recommendations. He likes municipal protectionism as
in <a href="https://atlasofthefuture.org/project/the-cleveland-model/">the Cleveland model</a>. He favors <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_basic_services">Universal Basic Services</a>
over <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_basic_income">Universal Basic Income</a>. (I tend to agree; can we also get
Universal Basic Stuff?) He wants a "One Planet Tax" on carbon, to fund
renewable energy in the global south via National Energy Investment
Banks, and socialized finance for autonomous state-owned companies.</p>
<p>I don't know that Bastani is a great spokesperson, and the book is to
some extent just something to put the title on. But still kind of a
neat book?</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>Summarizing the five crises from pages 22-23:</p>
<ol>
<li>Climate change</li>
<li>Resource scarcity</li>
<li>Societal aging</li>
<li>Global poor / "unnecessariat"</li>
<li>Technological unemployment</li>
</ol>
<p>(These last two, and maybe even the last three, don't seem <em>that</em>
different...)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Now we must build a workers’ party against work – one whose
politics are populist, democratic and open, all while fighting the
establishment which, through its power over civil society and the
state, won’t rest in ensuring FALC never comes to pass." (pag 194)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Furthermore, preferring UBS to UBI makes a great deal of sense
within the context of the Third Disruption and the turn to extreme
supply. As the price for everything shifts ever closer to zero, this
will imperil production for exchange and profit, meaning the price
mechanism is an increasingly inefficient way of allocating
resources. What is more UBS begins the work of communism in the
present, articulating resources necessary to a decent life – from
housing to health- care – as human rights rather than potential
sources of profit. Necessitous people are not free people, and the
UBS decisively ends such necessity." (page 226)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This references Roosevelt's quotation of "Necessitous men are not free
men" in the 1944 State of the Union (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Bill_of_Rights">Second Bill of Rights</a>).</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"While FALC is situated within a transformation as seismic as that
of the arrival of agriculture, its concrete politics consist in
specific, readily identifiable demands: a break with neoliberalism,
a shift towards worker-owned production, a state-financed transition
to renewable energy and universal services – rightly identified as
human rights – placed beyond commodity exchange and profit." (page
243)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
