<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>Financial calculators exist</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>When you take the <a href="/20241123-what_are_cfps_supposed_to_know/" title="Certified Financial Planner">CFP</a> exam, you are allowed to use a
<a href="https://www.cfp.net/-/media/files/cfp-board/cfp-certification/exam/calculator-policy.pdf">dedicated financial calculator</a> like the Texas Instruments
"Business Analyst" <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Texas-Instruments-Advanced-Financial-Calculator/dp/B0029F1OKE">BA II Plus</a>. How wild is that?</p>
<p><img alt="calculator" src="ba2plus.jpg"></p>
<p>What does it do? You can start to guess from buttons like "IRR," but
the <a href="https://education.ti.com/en/guidebook/details/en/ADF11FB65B284B6195B0A7E9502784BA/baiiplus">manual</a> explains much more about how the functionality is
organized into "worksheets" and so on.</p>
<p><img alt="functions" src="functions.png"></p>
<p>Do people use these for real, in their work? My guess is that they're
sort of an archaic thing that persists only for the exam? Surely
people use one of many <a href="https://www.calculator.net/finance-calculator.html">online calculators</a>, or Excel, or some other
more user-friendly tool? (Although I don't really know what a great
example is; most of the ones I see at a quick look seem pretty
crummy...)</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241123-financial_calculators_exist/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241123-financial_calculators_exist/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>What are CFPs supposed to know?</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>To be a Certified Financial Planner, you have to have a bachelor's
degree (in anything) and do (<a href="https://www.cfp.net/get-certified/certification-process/education-requirement/certification-coursework-requirement/accelerated-path">usually</a>) seven <a href="https://www.cfp.net/">CFP Board</a>-approved
classes and pass a test covering many <a href="https://www.cfp.net/get-certified/certification-process/education-requirement/certification-coursework-requirement/what-youll-learn">topics</a>. The classes are
Fundamentals, Insurance, Investments, Tax, Retirement, Estate, and a
capstone case study class. Then you do 30 hours of continuing
education every two years.</p>
<p>The CFP Board <a href="https://www.cfp.net/get-certified/certification-process/education-requirement/certification-coursework-requirement/find-an-education-program/">lists</a> about 250 institutions with approved
offerings, mostly universities. These can be outsourced offerings, for
example from <a href="https://cerifi.com/">Cerifi</a>'s <a href="https://dalton-education.com/university-partnerships">Dalton Education</a> or
<a href="https://www.greeneconsults.com/">Greene Consulting</a>'s <a href="https://www.financialplannerprogram.com/#school">Financial Planner Program</a> or <a href="https://www.kenzahn.com/">Zahn</a>.</p>
<p>There seem to be two main lines of textbooks. One is <a href="https://cerifi.com/">Cerifi</a>'s
<a href="https://www.money-education.com/">Money Education</a>, which <a href="https://cerifi.com/our-brands">claims</a> to by “chosen by 200
universities nationwide.” The <a href="https://www.nationalunderwriter.com/series/academic.html">other</a> is from
<a href="https://www.nationalunderwriter.com/">National Underwriter</a>, mostly in their <a href="https://www.nationalunderwriter.com/series/the-leimberg-library.html">Leimberg Library</a>. There
used to be books from Keir, but they <a href="https://www.keirsuccess.com/products/cfp-certification-products/education-courses/university-textbooks">joined forces</a> with
<a href="https://www.money-education.com/">Money Education</a>.</p>
<p>From <a href="https://www.opensyllabus.org/">Open Syllabus</a>, it isn't clear which books are most popular. I
find <a href="https://analytics.opensyllabus.org/record/works?syllabus_query=money+education">one entry each</a> for two of the Money Education books, and
<a href="https://analytics.opensyllabus.org/record/works?syllabus_query=leimberg">no mention</a> of Leimberg books. It seems like <a href="https://www.cffp.edu/cfp-education">Kaplan</a> and
<a href="https://www.brettdanko.com/">Danko</a> also have materials, but may only offer them to participants
in their courses.</p>
<p>There are also lots of exam prep and study materials. <a href="https://www.kenzahn.com/">Zahn</a> for
example makes supplemental books and flashcards, and Money Education
has “QuickSheets.”</p>
<p>There's also a thing called a financial calculator, which can be a
physical object that CFPs may learn to use.</p>
<p>For continuing education, every two years a CFP has to do 30 hours of
programs, selected from <a href="https://www.cfp.net/career-and-growth/continuing-education/find-a-ce-program">thousands</a> that are approved by the CFP
Board.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241123-what_are_cfps_supposed_to_know/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241123-what_are_cfps_supposed_to_know/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) We've got you covered, by Einav and Finkelstein</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I read <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/690632/weve-got-you-covered-by-liran-einav-and-amy-finkelstein/" title="We've Got You Covered: Rebooting American Health Care">this book</a> because Furman recommended it, and his
<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/10/21/books/review/economics-business-books.html" title="5 Books to Help You Understand the Economy Before Voting">description</a> is good. I admire the economist authors' ability to
take a normative stand while staying clear-headed about measured
realities. I'm on board.</p>
<p>The central claim of the book is that we <em>should</em> provide free basic
health care to everyone. They support this by arguing that the US has
been <em>trying</em> to do this: trying to honor an implicit social contract.</p>
<p>The issue then is that the US has been doing a very poor job of it.
The authors propose that health insurance should instead be free and
automatic for everyone, with no sign-up hoops or costs incurred for
receiving care.</p>
<p>Problems with the current US system include its complexity itself, and
health insurance being tied to employment (therefore subject to
termination at any time) and medical costs being a potentially
unbounded burden for individuals, sometimes even for those <em>with</em>
insurance.</p>
<p>They point out that insurance doesn't actually have that much
influence on health outcomes, because impact on health is dominated by
behaviors that correlate with wealth, for example, and because people
generally still <em>get</em> health care even if not insured, even if it also
saddles them with debt. So universal health insurance won't resolve
disparities in health outcomes. (This does appear somewhat at odds
with the authors' frequent complaint that the US system often pays for
treatment only after conditions become acute dangers, while earlier
treatment might have been cheaper and prevented the worst health
outcomes.)</p>
<p>The book is also full of interesting current and historical detail
about the US and international health systems.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“We have therefore intentionally focused on what we <em>should</em> do,
rather than what some may think we currently <em>can</em> do. In this
sense, our book is in the spirit of the famous Chicago economist
Milton Friedman. He argued that the role for economists in public
policy is to develop the best ideas, and keep them alive and ripe in
the public imagination until the day when “the politically
impossible becomes the politically inevitable.” (page 14)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Let’s start with the precarious insurance of the privately insured.
Almost half of the US population—over 150 million people—receive
private health insurance through their employers or a family
member’s employer. That’s almost all Americans who have private
health insurance.</p>
<p>There’s no natural reason why their boss doubles as their insurer.
This unusual arrangement arose through an accident of history, a
common theme of US health-care policy. During World War II, the
federal government imposed wage and price controls to try to prevent
inflation. Employers—desperate to attract and retain scarce
workers—soon discovered a way to get around the wage ceilings and
provide higher compensation. They could offer—and pay for—their
workers’ health insurance, because these payments weren’t counted as
“wages.”</p>
<p>The practice of excluding employer payments for their employees’
health insurance from the definition of employee earnings has
remained in place to this day. As a result, any such payments are
tax-free. An employee doesn’t have to pay income tax on any
contributions her employer makes to her workplace-based health
insurance premium.” (page 17)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Moral commitments are not limitless. Even FDR implicitly
acknowledged this in his Second Bill of Rights. He spoke of rights
such as “a decent home,” “a good education,” and “adequate medical
care.” The economist Arthur Okun, writing a few decades later,
likewise espoused a right to health care while simultaneously
cautioning that these rights are not unbounded. With the customary
bluntness of an economist rather than a politician, he described “a
heated debate with an audience of medical administrators.” As Okun
described it, “Taking what I viewed as an outlandish example, I
suggested that any national health program should not grant me at
public expense all the pairs of eyeglasses I might like. I learned
to my surprise that they favored an unlimited right to eyeglasses.”
(page 74)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The technical term for this quality of life measure is <em>quality
adjusted life year,</em> or QALY (rhymes with <em>jolly</em>). A year in
perfect health is given a QALY score of one, a year of being dead
scores zero. Much scientific effort and squabbling go into assigning
scores to all the various ways a year can be spent in
less-than-perfect health. (footnote, page 100)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is part of a section which is a great example of the challenges
of trying to linearize multiple things into one measure. In this case
they were using a ratio of benefits to cost, so a cheap and decent
thing showed up as better than an expensive but essential thing.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The faithful and accurate application of cost-benefit analysis had
produced unacceptable results. Even the commissioners agreed,
acknowledging that their rankings often conflicted with their own
intuition. They quickly abandoned the formulaic application of
cost-effectiveness rankings in favor of a more “holistic” approach.
They used their judgment—and that of members of the community who
provided input through public forums—to create broad categories of
health care that they ranked in order of importance. Effective care
for acute fatal conditions (such as appendectomies) was ranked high,
while minimally effective treatments for nonfatal conditions (such
as tooth capping or medical therapy for diaper rash) were in a
category near the bottom.” (page 100)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241116-weve_got_you_covered_by_einav_and_finkelstein/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241116-weve_got_you_covered_by_einav_and_finkelstein/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Technofeudalism, by Varoufakis</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The generous interpretation is that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yanis_Varoufakis">Varoufakis</a> understands that
his <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/751443/technofeudalism-by-yanis-varoufakis/">technofeudalism</a> is not distinct from capitalism but that since
capitalism's valence is unassailable, perhaps a new word can be more
successfully attacked. (The less generous interpretation is that he
wants credit for a catchy idea.)</p>
<p>In the book, Varoufakis is personable. He's likeable. His writing is
friendly, and his stories about his father are charming. And he
<a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2024/04/01/has-capitalism-been-replaced-by-technofeudalism">likes Star Trek</a>, which is a great sign of character.</p>
<p>His technofeudalism refers to the monopolistic market capture,
"moats," and rent-seeking of (mostly) big tech. But this is just
capitalism as usual; <a href="/20240625-titan_by_chernow/">Rockefeller</a> would be on board. Thinking of
capitalism as pro-competition is ridiculous.</p>
<p>He says some things about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historical_materialism">historical materialism</a>, which is kind of
interesting. I buy into the importance of technology for enabling big
structural changes to standard of living, for example. (See also:
<a href="/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>)</p>
<p>There's also something interesting about separating the exchange or
commodity value vs. the experiential value of things (like work).
Varoufakis says employers profit because they pay commodity price for
workers' time but get the "experiential" (real?) value of their work.
In some sense, a company pays out less than it takes in, if it can,
but I'm not sure this decomposition holds in a meaningful way.
Generally I think Marx focused on labor too much in a similar way to
how physiocrats focused on agriculture (land) too much.</p>
<p>Varoufakis is a little too weird. His use of Amazon Alexa as an
example is unfortunate, given how it's largely a failed technology. He
doesn't seem technologically literate when he talks about ML, which
makes me wonder how good he is in fields I know less about. Like
Bernie, he's concerned about Black Rock/Vanguard/State Street, but I
think this concern is mostly silly. And he's into balancing trade
between nations. (Is this mercantilism?)</p>
<p>So while I'm not with him everywhere, I have a lot of respect for at
least proposing some alternative. (He summarizes his ideas from
<em>Another Now</em>.) And that may be the whole point of Technofeudalism -
getting more people to look at his ideas. It worked on me.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241109-technofeudalism_by_varoufakis/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241109-technofeudalism_by_varoufakis/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Utopia for Realists, by Bregman</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Utopia_for_Realists">Utopia for Realists</a> is a more accessible <a href="/20240929-inventing_the_future_by_srnicek_and_williams/" title="(Audio) Inventing the Future, by Srnicek and Williams">Inventing the Future</a>:
it's in favor of UBI and less work, against neoliberalism/<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mont_Pelerin_Society" title="Mont Pelerin Society">MPS</a>, and
Utopia's "underdog socialism" is like Inventing's "folk politics." It
differs slightly in being explicitly for open borders, like
<a href="/20191109-open_borders_by_caplan_and_weinersmith/" title="Open Borders, by Caplan and Weinersmith">Caplan</a>, and there are some other differences in focus and
examples. The original Dutch title is literally "free money for
everyone."</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Work is the refuge of people who have nothing better to do.” (Oscar
Wilde, quoted page 68)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think Bregman is too concerned with preserving the appearance of the
Puritan work ethic. Like many, he seems to think that giving people
money has to be shown not to reduce hours of work. This is silly and
backward. We should be trying to get people to stop working for pay.</p>
<p>I think it's fine to pull in <a href="/20180218-scarcity_by_sendhil_mullainathan_and_eldar_shafir/" title="Scarcity by Sendhil Mullainathan and Eldar Shafir">Mullainathan and Shafir</a>, as he does,
on the downsides of scarcity, but the reasoning should be that it is
unjust to let people be in bad situations. The trap here is getting
into an argument about who is deserving. If we have to prove that
people are deserving, we've lost already.</p>
<p>Some neat stuff:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cockaigne">Cockaigne</a>: "a land of plenty in medieval myth"</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speenhamland_system">Speenhamland</a>: 1795 "basic income" program, still argued over:
   Did it suppress wages? Did it increase sloth? More children? Loose
   morals?</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mincome">Mincome</a>: "Manitoba Basic Annual Income Experiment" (1970s)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physiocracy">Physiocracy</a>: some kind of economic theory that valued the
   productivity of land/agriculture (over generic labor, etc.)</li>
</ul>
<p>And there's a chapter on GDP (etc.) which made me think that one could
teach a whole course on the downsides or risks of data and data
science, much as in <a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/" title="The Tyranny of Metrics, by Muller">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The RAND Corporation, an influential think tank, foresaw a future
in which just 2% of the population would be able to produce
everything society needed.” (page 18)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But this cites not a RAND study, but “Hillel Ruskin (ed.), Leisure,
Toward a Theory and Policy (1984), p. 152,” and I don't see that
online, so it'll take me a while to check.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Not until 1978 was the plan for a basic income shelved once and for
all, however, following a fatal discovery upon publication of the
final results of the Seattle experiment. One finding in particular
grabbed everybody’s attention: The number of divorces had jumped
more than 50%. Interest in this statistic quickly overshadowed all
the other outcomes, such as better school performance and
improvements in health. A basic income, evidently, gave women too
much independence.</p>
<p>Ten years later, a reanalysis of the data revealed that a
statistical error had been made; in reality, there had been no
change in the divorce rate at all.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The citation here is <a href="https://www.irp.wisc.edu/publications/dps/pdfs/dp85788.pdf">Cain and Wissoker</a>... I've heard about this
divorce finding before ("It's bad!" "It's good!") but I don't think
I've heard about this nullifying result... Why not? I'm not digging
very deep here, but Bregman seems quite Pollyannaish in general
throughout the book, which makes him seem less reliable in general on
specifics.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The free books had made no difference. Test scores showed no
improvement.” (page 91)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But this isn't quite what the <a href="http://www.econ.yale.edu/~egcenter/infoconf/kremer_paper.pdf">study</a> said - and I didn't even read
beyond the abstract! "However, for those students in the top quintile
of the distribution of initial academic achievement, the program
raised test scores by at least 0.2 standard deviations."</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241102-utopia_for_realists_by_bregman/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241102-utopia_for_realists_by_bregman/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) How the World Works, by Chomsky</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>“How the World Works” is a collection of four Chomsky books:</p>
<ul>
<li>What Uncle Sam Really Wants</li>
<li>The Prosperous Few and the Restless Many</li>
<li>Secrets, Lies and Democracy</li>
<li>The Common Good</li>
</ul>
<p>Chomsky says the world is violent. Very violent! He agrees with
<a href="/20240825-principles_changing_world_order_dalio/" title="Principles for dealing with the changing world order, by Dalio">Dalio</a> that international law means little to power. He describes
the Pentagon as an economic stimulus mechanism, which I thought was an
interesting framing.</p>
<p>I first heard about Chomsky in connection with linguistics. The only
linguistic thing he talks about here is the idea of language being
debased, in a similar sense to Orwellian <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newspeak">Newspeak</a>, making it hard
to talk about certain things. I've felt something like this in trying
to talk about a post-work world. To stop selling your labor is called
"retiring," which connotes a kind of withdrawal, which I don't like.
One might also say that to retire is to "stop working," because "work"
can only mean "sell your labor," even if you carry on doing things you
think are useful and productive. It's a similar frustration to that of
the "stay-at-home" parent, who is engaged in effortful activity over
40 hours a week and yet said to "not work." (These aren't Chomsky's
examples.)</p>
<p>And Chomsky mentions interesting things here and there... I don't
think I'd known about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Party_(United_States)">New Party</a>, which continues in part as
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive_Dane">Progressive Dane</a>, a party in Dane County, where I went to college.
I had heard of Progressive Dane, I think, but I wasn't aware of its
historical context.</p>
<p>Some more interesting bits quoted below...</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<h3>“expanding the floor of the cage”</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“So Argentina is “minimizing the state”—cutting down public
expenditures, the way our government is doing, but much more
extremely. Of course, when you minimize the state, you maximize
something else—and it isn’t popular control. What gets maximized is
private power, domestic and foreign.</p>
<p>I met with a very lively anarchist movement in Buenos Aires, and
with other anarchist groups as far away as northeastern Brazil,
where nobody even knew they existed. We had a lot of discussions
about these matters. They recognize that they have to try to use the
state—even though they regard it as totally illegitimate.</p>
<p>The reason is perfectly obvious: When you eliminate the one
institutional structure in which people can participate to some
extent—namely the government—you’re simply handing over power to
unaccountable private tyrannies that are much worse. So you have to
make use of the state, all the time recognizing that you ultimately
want to eliminate it.</p>
<p>Some of the rural workers in Brazil have an interesting slogan. They
say their immediate task is “expanding the floor of the cage.” They
understand that they’re trapped inside a cage, but realize that
protecting it when it’s under attack from even worse predators on
the outside, and extending the limits of what the cage will allow,
are both essential preliminaries to dismantling it. If they attack
the cage directly when they’re so vulnerable, they’ll get murdered.</p>
<p>That’s something anyone ought to be able to understand who can keep
two ideas in their head at once, but some people here in the US tend
to be so rigid and doctrinaire that they don’t understand the point.
But unless the left here is willing to tolerate that level of
complexity, we’re not going to be of any use to people who are
suffering and need our help—or, for that matter, to ourselves.</p>
<p>In Brazil and Argentina, you can discuss these issues even with
people in the highest political echelons, and with elite journalists
and intellectuals. They may not agree with you, but at least they
understand what you’re talking about.” (page 174)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3>“rationality and science”</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“In the 1930s, left intellectuals were involved in worker education
and writing books like <em>Mathematics for the Millions.</em> They
considered it an ordinary, minimal responsibility of privileged
people to help others who’d been deprived of formal education to
enter into high culture.</p>
<p>Today’s counterparts of these 1930s left intellectuals are telling
people, <em>You don’t have to know anything. It’s all junk, a power
play, a white male conspiracy. Forget about rationality and
science.</em> In other words, put those tools in the hands of your
enemies. Let them monopolize everything that works and makes sense.</p>
<p>Plenty of very honorable left intellectuals think this tendency is
liberatory, but I think they’re wrong. A lot of personal
correspondence on related topics between me and my close, valued old
friend Marc Raskin has been published in a book of his. There were
similar interchanges in Z Papers in 1992–93, both with Marc and a
lot of other people with whom I basically feel in sympathy, but with
whom I differ very sharply on this issue.” (page 194)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This "Z" thing still exists, as <a href="https://znetwork.org/" title="ZNetwork - Independent Left News, Analysis, Vision and Strategy">ZNetwork</a>.</p>
<hr>
<h3>“the South Commission”</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“As recently as the early 1990s, the South Commission, which
represented the governments of nonaligned countries, came out with a
very important critique of the antidemocratic, neoliberal model
that’s being forced on the Third World. (The commission included
pretty conservative people, like Indonesia’s development minister.)</p>
<p>They published a book that called for a new world order (they
introduced the term before George [H. W.] Bush did) based on
democracy, justice, development and so on. The book wasn’t
obscure—it was published by Oxford University Press. I wrote about
it, but I couldn’t find much else. They subsequently published
another book of essays commenting on the first one, and I’ve never
seen a reference to that either.</p>
<p>The South Commission happened to represent most of the world’s
population, but the story they were telling just isn’t one the
Western media wanted to hear. So the “new world order” we learned
about was Bush’s, not the one advocated by the South Commission,
which reflects the interests of most of the people of the world.
Back in the 1950s, there were Nehru, Nasser, Tito, Nkrumah, Sukarno
and others…” (page 203)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3>“Here’s what I’m doing. What do you think about it?”</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“Over the years, I <em>have</em> noticed a very striking difference between
talks I give to more or less elite audiences, and meetings and
discussions I have with less privileged people. A while back I was
in a town in Massachusetts at a meeting set up by very good local
organizers in the urban community—people who were pretty poor, even
by world standards. Not long before that, I spent time in the West
Bengal countryside. Then I was in Colombia, talking to human rights
activists who are working under horrifying conditions.</p>
<p>In places like that, people never ask, <em>What should I do?</em> They say,
<em>Here’s what I’m doing. What do you think about it?</em> Maybe they’d
like reactions or suggestions, but they’re already dealing with the
problem. They’re not sitting around waiting for a magic answer,
which doesn’t exist.</p>
<p>When I speak to elite audiences, I constantly get asked, <em>What’s the
solution?</em> If I say obvious things like <em>Pick your cause and go
volunteer for a group that’s working on it,</em> that’s never the answer
they want. They want some sort of magic key that will solve
everything quickly, overwhelmingly and effectively. There are no
such solutions. There are only the kind that people are working on
in Massachusetts towns, in self-governing villages in India, at the
Jesuit Center in Colombia.” (page 206)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241026-how_the_world_works_by_chomsky/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241026-how_the_world_works_by_chomsky/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) After Work, by Hester and Srnicek</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Here's a feminist post-scarcity <a href="https://www.versobooks.com/products/496-after-work" title="After Work: A History of the Home and the Fight for Free Time by Helen Hester and Nick Srnicek">book</a> pointing out that abolishing
paid work won't automatically eliminate unpaid work. There's quite a
bit of unpaid work, and people may or may not want to do it.
Interesting history and ideas on what to do about it.</p>
<p>Did you know there was a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wages_for_housework" title="Wikipedia: Wages for housework">Wages for Housework</a> movement in the 70s?</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.png"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“As we know, domestic realism was not ultimately overthrown by the
communalism of the separatists or the hippies. While some
communities are still operational, Drop City and the vast majority
of initiatives like it proved to be relatively ephemeral
experiments, failing to outlive their moment of sociosexual
upheaval. This may well have been because, as sites of exodus, they
were not always effective at ensuring their own scalability. They
were often intended as prefigurative spaces, aiming to offer a taste
of post-suburban utopia in the here and now (or at least, a utopia
for the young, the healthy, the able bodied, and the middle class
with minimal caring responsibilities – that specific and limited
range of people who might be best able to thrive in a space like
Drop City). As such, they consciously operated as enclaves within
the society from which they sought to withdraw – bastions of
alternative values which were yet to flourish elsewhere – and the
interventions they staged were in certain respects hyperlocal to the
point of being site-specific. The ‘simple positing and practising of
a new world is insufficient to overcome’ the structural forces
preventing its generalisation.129 Or, as Mike Davis puts it,
‘demonstration projects in … rich countries will not save the
world’.” (page 114)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241019-after_work_by_hester_and_srnicek/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241019-after_work_by_hester_and_srnicek/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Inventing the Future, by Srnicek and Williams</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inventing_the_Future:_Postcapitalism_and_a_World_Without_Work">Inventing the Future</a>: Postcapitalism and a World Without Work is
by far the best exposition of a post-scarcity direction that I've
seen. The criticism of folk politics as impotent in important ways
because of its focus on immediacy is incisive. The authors invite us
to grow up and construct the world we want to live in.</p>
<p>I enjoyed their alternate interpretation of the phrase "resistance is
futile," emphasizing the difference between fighting some external
actor and being an active builder. Trying to stop someone else
(political, corporate, etc.) may or may not succeed, but regardless it
will not create a better alternative. If all we do is resist, we never
make anything new.</p>
<p>The authors demand full automation, as in
<a href="/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/" title="Fully Automated Luxury Communism, by Bastani">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>, and indeed Bastani might be
counted among the second-hand dealers in these ideas (though he has
contributions as well).</p>
<p>There's a bunch in the book on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mont_Pelerin_Society">Mont Pelerin Society</a> and the
authors recommend a leftist "ecology of organizations" might achieve
similar success. They mention the <a href="https://neweconomics.org/">New Economics Foundation</a>, but
otherwise I don't know a lot of organizations that might be part of
such an ecology.</p>
<hr>
<p>The authors advocate for higher wages. Higher wages can be good for
the people who get them, but the main focus is on higher wages
encouraging more automation. The authors also advocate for Universal
Basic Income (UBI). They note some challenges with UBI, but I don't
think they completely resolve a conflict here.</p>
<p>What happens to (market-based) wages if people have UBI? Probably lots
of jobs don't have takers any more. This must be the mechanism the
authors are thinking of, and why they emphasize that UBI must really
be enough to live on. But surely some jobs would be doable for <em>lower</em>
wages, if people sort of enjoy them to begin with.</p>
<p>There's no mention of inflation in connection with UBI, which
continues to concern me. How can it work without price controls or
similar? If everyone has more money, surely rent goes up, grocery
prices go up, etc. etc. just as we saw during the pandemic.</p>
<p>As with Universal Basic Services (UBS) I have to think that everything
currently sold on the market would have to edge away from being sold
for profit. A program of UBI can be undone by inflation, and indeed
the goal should be for deflation, as we achieve extreme supply, prices
go to zero, and eventually money can be retired. Postcapitalism is in
the subtitle, but there aren't many details here.</p>
<hr>
<h3>The book is better than the movie</h3>
<p>The book is not written in a broadly accessible style. It's inside
baseball for academics who appreciate Marxist criticism and don't
blink at phrases like "reproductive labor." So I was excited to hear
about a 2020 documentary based on the book, thinking it might speak to
a broader audience.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LY44I9P_QZU">film</a> is feature length, but the style is the unwatchable,
seizure-inducing kind you might walk quickly past in an art museum.
Voices read snippets from the book and other sources, sometimes
reminiscent of Waiting for Godot. Several times we watch sex toys
shimmy on a grey Lego baseplate. It's hard to imagine a movie that
could contribute less to spreading the message of Inventing the
Future. Avoid.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“A politics without demands is simply a collection of aimless
bodies.” (page 105)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One criticism of the book might be that it gets to demands but doesn't
go much farther in terms of concrete mechanisms for achieving them.
Four day work week! Full automation! Okay, but what can people do
apart from writing their senators?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Famously, Oscar Wilde once said that the problem with socialism was
that it took up too many evenings.” (page 177)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't think I'd heard this before; it's good, isn't it? Most people
just want to live their lives. Hence problems, hence opportunities.</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240929-inventing_the_future_by_srnicek_and_williams/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240929-inventing_the_future_by_srnicek_and_williams/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Fully Automated Luxury Communism, by Bastani</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Ridiculing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_End_of_History_and_the_Last_Man" title="The End of History and the Last Man">The End of History</a> and rejecting
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capitalist_Realism" title="Capitalist Realism">Capitalist Realism</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aaron_Bastani" title="Aaron Bastani">Bastani</a> says Marx was ahead of his time:
communism is only now becoming technologically possible. While
Rushkoff <a href="/20240519-survival_of_the_richest_by_rushkoff/" title="Survival of the Richest, by Rushkoff">is</a> anti-growth, Bastani was saying (even before ChatGPT)
that technology will save us. He says we should demand
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fully_Automated_Luxury_Communism" title="Fully Automated Luxury Communism">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>.</p>
<p>A lot of the book is detail on how technology is advancing (or may
advance) to produce "extreme supply." A surprisingly large amount is
about mining asteroids. Predictions on driverless cars and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finless_Foods">Finless Foods</a>, for example, seem premature. (The book only came
out five years ago; is it too early to judge?)</p>
<p>I think Bastani is right that the future he imagines is not
inevitable: it depends on political choices. He mostly assumes that
technological development is inevitable. I'm less sure about that.
They are related, of course.</p>
<p>Bastani has some recommendations. He likes municipal protectionism as
in <a href="https://atlasofthefuture.org/project/the-cleveland-model/">the Cleveland model</a>. He favors <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_basic_services">Universal Basic Services</a>
over <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_basic_income">Universal Basic Income</a>. (I tend to agree; can we also get
Universal Basic Stuff?) He wants a "One Planet Tax" on carbon, to fund
renewable energy in the global south via National Energy Investment
Banks, and socialized finance for autonomous state-owned companies.</p>
<p>I don't know that Bastani is a great spokesperson, and the book is to
some extent just something to put the title on. But still kind of a
neat book?</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>Summarizing the five crises from pages 22-23:</p>
<ol>
<li>Climate change</li>
<li>Resource scarcity</li>
<li>Societal aging</li>
<li>Global poor / "unnecessariat"</li>
<li>Technological unemployment</li>
</ol>
<p>(These last two, and maybe even the last three, don't seem <em>that</em>
different...)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Now we must build a workers’ party against work – one whose
politics are populist, democratic and open, all while fighting the
establishment which, through its power over civil society and the
state, won’t rest in ensuring FALC never comes to pass." (pag 194)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Furthermore, preferring UBS to UBI makes a great deal of sense
within the context of the Third Disruption and the turn to extreme
supply. As the price for everything shifts ever closer to zero, this
will imperil production for exchange and profit, meaning the price
mechanism is an increasingly inefficient way of allocating
resources. What is more UBS begins the work of communism in the
present, articulating resources necessary to a decent life – from
housing to health- care – as human rights rather than potential
sources of profit. Necessitous people are not free people, and the
UBS decisively ends such necessity." (page 226)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This references Roosevelt's quotation of "Necessitous men are not free
men" in the 1944 State of the Union (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Bill_of_Rights">Second Bill of Rights</a>).</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"While FALC is situated within a transformation as seismic as that
of the arrival of agriculture, its concrete politics consist in
specific, readily identifiable demands: a break with neoliberalism,
a shift towards worker-owned production, a state-financed transition
to renewable energy and universal services – rightly identified as
human rights – placed beyond commodity exchange and profit." (page
243)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) On the Edge, by Nate Silver</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>When Trump won the 2016 election despite 538's needle showing less
than 50% for him, it split the world. There were people who gave Nate
Silver a hard time about it ("the village") and people who still
thought he was cool ("the river"). Since then, Silver has been hanging
out with his buddies, having a good time playing poker, and he can
write a book about whatever he wants, so here it is. It reads,
unintentionally, as a warning about the risks of seeing the world only
in calculating, risk-taking terms.</p>
<hr>
<p>Silver tries to explain why there are more men than women playing
poker. He suggests that men are more aggressive, and aggression makes
you better at poker. I think Silver misses the big picture: It isn't
really a good idea to play poker in the first place. It's anti-social.
Elsewhere, Silver does explain that the poker ecosystem requires
"fish" for people to take money from. Why are there more men playing
poker? Because they're dumb!</p>
<p>(There is an apparent contradiction here, in that I myself enjoy the
occasional social poker game, and have even played to make money at
casinos a couple times. But I still believe that if you're
consistently playing to make money, it is a kind of legal theft, a
kind of con, as bad as the casino itself. The divide between a
friendly game and stealing wallets from drunk strangers is not always
perfectly clear, but I think it exists.)</p>
<hr>
<p>Silver comes closest to explicitly warning against "the river" way of
thinking in his extended coverage of Sam Bankman-Fried (SBF) and FTX.
He thinks SBF's problem (one of them) was that he bet too big. Silver
references the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kelly_criterion">Kelly criterion</a> for bet-sizing and suggests that
SBF was willing to make bets that were too large.</p>
<p>I think Silver missed another aspect, which is that even very small
bets can be bad bets to make - even when they're positive EV. The
thing to consider is the probability of ending up better off or worse
off than currently. Even if the EV is very positive, if the chance of
"hitting it" is low and the chance of getting worse off is high, it's
very sensible to not make that bet.</p>
<p>I wrote up my way of thinking about this a while ago as
<a href="/2012/06/04/expected-value-is-not-useful-for-making/">Expected value is not useful for making decisions about lottery tickets</a>.
See also notes on expected value in connection with
<a href="/20200925-how_not_to_be_wrong_by_ellenberg/">How Not to Be Wrong, by Ellenberg</a> and
<a href="/20210502-the_scout_mindset_by_galef/">The Scout Mindset, by Galef</a>. A related question to ask is:
<a href="/20181204-worth_doing_even_if_it_fails/">Is it worth doing even if it fails?</a></p>
<hr>
<p>At one point Silver quotes Oppenheimer:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“It is a profound and necessary truth that the deep things in
science are not found because they are useful; they are found
because it was possible to find them.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I like this quote. It reminds me of
<a href="/20221105-why_greatness_cannot_be_planned_by_stanley_and_lehman/">Why greatness cannot be planned (Stanley and Lehman)</a>. We often
expand our knowledge along the current frontiers and only later
identify the applications. See also
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Unreasonable_Effectiveness_of_Mathematics_in_the_Natural_Sciences">The Unreasonable Effectiveness of Mathematics in the Natural Sciences</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Silver talks some about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secular_stagnation">secular stagnation</a>, which reminded me of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rise_and_Fall_of_American_Growth" title="The Rise and Fall of American Growth, by Robert J. Gordon">The Rise and Fall of American Growth</a> and that despite claims of
stagnation <a href="/20240407-mortality_rates_have_improved/">Mortality rates have improved</a> without pause until the
present (apart from the recent impact of Covid). Of course Silver is
really just trying to talk about AI and whether it will kill us all.
(He thinks it might.)</p>
<hr>
<p>Silver tries to conclude with some sort of morality or politics, but
it feels bolted on. When he was talking about SBF and being critical
of Effective Altruism and Rationalism, I had some thought that perhaps
Silver was self-aware and the conclusion of the book was going to be a
big reveal that he had realized that "the river" was itself a risk to
humanity. But I don't think he got there. So while he does say some
things about the risks of quantification (shades of
<a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>) Silver is still mostly just hanging out
with his friends and following his interests. Good for him?</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240915-on_the_edge_by_silver/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240915-on_the_edge_by_silver/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How much money do I need to retire? by Tresidder</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Tresidder is in some ways likeable and reasonable, and in other ways
sort of a skinny-FIRE <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Kiyosaki">Robert Kiyosaki</a> who is "retired" but still
shills constantly in the direction of his $1,750 <a href="https://members.financialmentor.com/product/step-3/">online course</a>
like he read <a href="/2011/03/14/listened-to-four-hour-work-week/">The 4-hour work week</a>.</p>
<p>Most of the book is criticism. On page one we get "Traditional
retirement planning has failed." It all feels mostly like a sales
tactic: His approach is the one that works!</p>
<p>He spends a lot of time criticizing Monte Carlo methods. His
explanation of the approach in general is so bad it must be
deliberately so. Unsavory rhetoric.</p>
<p>There is a reasonable argument buried in his hate for MC methods: He
thinks they don't go far enough in considering more extreme possible
futures, while their confidence intervals make them <em>seem</em> all-knowing
when they're not. They generally won't model Social Security
disappearing altogether, for example, but they'll still allocate 100%
of probability, as if there's a 0% chance of these sorts of "extreme"
futures.</p>
<p>So his solution is a sort of manual Monte Carlo, putting lots of weird
things into (his, of course) calculators.</p>
<p>He also correctly, I think, focuses on the human reality of living
just one life, not a probability distribution of lives, so what we
really need is to eliminate extreme downside risk as much as possible.</p>
<p>How much of the retirement planning literature is just confusion about
inflation? Possibly a lot, I think.</p>
<p>It turns out his solution is mostly from the skinny-FIRE school of
thought: Spend less! Then there's the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Kiyosaki">Robert Kiyosaki</a> part: Cash
flow! Real estate!</p>
<p>I object to telling people to become landlords like it's easy, good,
and risk-free. The general idea of not dipping into your capital seems
fine though. But now are we just back to the original methods he
despises, only worse off because we're imagining the capital is safe
(and even grows with inflation)? I think yes.</p>
<p>There are some good vibes about enjoying your life, and maybe his
recommendation to consider a longevity annuity is reasonable, but for
the most part this book is more an advertisement than a resource.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Every act of creation is first an act of destruction." (page 21)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think this is supposed to be Picasso? But his usage is unattributed?
Sort of weird, given how much he likes to include well-known quotes
otherwise.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>(Regarding long-term increases in life expectancy) "There is some
debate about this statistic with some people claiming the gains came
from reductions in infant mortality." (page 46)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is not a debate! See, for example,
<a href="/20200806-life_expectancy_is_historically_misleading/">Life expectancy is historically misleading </a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>investment returns over longer time periods of seven years or more
are not random. (page 69)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is part of his idea that he can time the market based on P/E.
Valuations aren't nothing, but his takes are a bit much.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"let’s apply conservative estimates by cutting my pension and social
security in half so that my combined income sources provide just
$15,000 per year instead of $50,000." (page 129)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>How does this make sense?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Different tax rates would only be marginally meaningful if your
income fell dramatically after retirement. Are you planning on
poverty or financial security?)" (page 142)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's sort of amazing that he would say this. Your effective tax rate
could easily be cut in half at retirement if you're earning a bunch
and saving most of it before retirement.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"“Today’s scientists have substituted mathematics for experiments,
and they wander off through equation after equation, and eventually
build a structure which has no relation to reality.”-Nikola Tesla,
inventor" (page 149)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I do like this quote.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Complicated math is usually more symptomatic of covering up
ignorance than expressing wisdom." (page 192)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also not terrible.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Retirement planning done right is really about life planning, not
calculating magic numbers." (page 151)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Every dollar bill you spend in your twenties is like spending a
hundred dollar bill in retirement." (page 179)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What? Really?</p>
<p>This is assuming 10% annual return over 45 years? And it's nominal?
(With inflation, more like $20 purchasing power?)</p>
<p>I guess he's just trying to be dramatic, but I would rather he not be
dramatic with numbers.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The main thing to note is how every other model relies on history
to be your guide. This cash flow-based model is the only approach
that requires no historical analysis because it is entirely based on
numbers fully known in the present. This is important because the
past is not the future." (page 199)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Tresidder paints "cash flow" methods as immune from risk, and
generally somehow automatically protected from inflation. This isn't
the case!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Lifestyle planning isn’t really a separate retirement model per
se." (page 208)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(The book is structured and presented as if it is.)</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240910-how_much_money_do_i_need_to_retire_by_tresidder/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240910-how_much_money_do_i_need_to_retire_by_tresidder/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Bullshit Jobs, by Graeber</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
<p>“There is only one success – to be able to spend your life in your
own way.” (Christopher Morley)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Graeber">Graeber</a> had a <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180807024932/http://strikemag.org/bullshit-jobs/">popular article</a> and this is the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullshit_Jobs">book version</a>. As with <a href="/20240519-survival_of_the_richest_by_rushkoff/">Rushkoff's</a>, the titular concept is
mostly a hook. I'm more interested in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Critique_of_work">critique of work</a>
generally.</p>
<p>The first part of the book, most directly on "bullshit jobs" and
related surveys and interviews, isn't very good, compared to Graeber's
<a href="/20240906-debt_by_graeber/" title="(Audio) Debt: The first 5,000 years, by Graeber">Debt</a>. He wants to have it both ways, for one thing: We must trust
the people who say their jobs are bullshit, and at the same time not
trust people who say their jobs aren't.</p>
<p>Then there's the definition of a bullshit job, which is never done
quite consistently. I think it's supposed to be jobs that don't make
any difference (if they aren't done, nothing changes). But this bleeds
in at least two directions: Jobs where we may not <em>like</em> the
difference they make, and jobs that <em>wouldn't</em> be necessary if things
were set up differently.</p>
<p>So Graeber repeatedly criticizes Obama for using job preservation as a
reason to not completely upend the health care system. If the current
employees were all sent home, it would be bad: people wouldn't get
insurance reimbursement, etc. The current jobs are only (or primarily)
"bullshit" to Graeber because he thinks a single payer (or similar)
system could take care of people with fewer employees.</p>
<p>And while I know part of Graeber's point is to critique the Puritan
work ethic and "middle class thinking" in general, many of his
malcontent subjects just aren't very sympathetic.</p>
<p>Graeber did an academic thesis on "life cycle service," the historical
practice in northern Europe in which a young person would spend seven
or so years as an apprentice or servant, with some other family,
collecting some pay until they could set off on their own. I thought
this was interesting in relation to the modern idea of FIRE (Financial
Independence, Retire Early) in which a person similarly works for
others until they have enough money to be independent and then does
whatever they want.</p>
<p>Graeber talks a lot about "spiritual violence," and while this may be
worse when a job feels pointless (see also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sayre%27s_law">Sayre's Law</a>) I don't
think it's unique to "bullshit jobs" but common to any job that has
you doing what you really don't want to do. Hence the Morley quote
about success as being "able to spend your life in your own way."
People really like self-determination.</p>
<p>Graeber does connect at least a little bit with Black's
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Abolition_of_Work">Abolition of Work</a> and the idea given book form in
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fully_Automated_Luxury_Communism">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>. He spends some time on work as
caring work rather than factory production. And he also comes out in
support of UBI.</p>
<p>(Oh right - I read <a href="/20180125-no_more_work_by_james_livingston/" title="No More Work by James Livingston">No more work</a> back in 2018...)</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240907-bullshit_jobs_by_graeber/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240907-bullshit_jobs_by_graeber/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Debt: The first 5,000 years, by Graeber</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Graeber">Graeber</a> doesn't like debt, in the modern quantified, financial
sense. Also he thinks people are wrong about the history of money, and
that we should listen to anthropologists more. Graeber's equation is
something like "obligation + measurement + violence = debt."</p>
<p>A smattering of his ideas as I remember them:</p>
<ul>
<li>The standard economics story of money (as arising because barter is
   too hard) is silly because people hardly ever barter in the first
   place, except sometimes with strangers.</li>
<li>The standard economics story of money starting with coinage, then
   later developing debt instruments (see also <a href="/20240825-principles_changing_world_order_dalio/" title="(Audio) Principles for dealing with the changing world order, by Dalio">Dalio</a>, "money as
   starting from metal, then notes exchangeable for metal, then fiat
   money") is silly because ideas and methods of debt come <em>first</em>.</li>
<li>The moralism of "always paying your debts" in culture and language.</li>
<li>No single theory of money (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chartalism">Chartalism</a>, etc.) is right on its
   own because "money has no essence" and money is just one piece of a
   big evolving world. (Similarly, Graeber has no single thesis on
   debt.)</li>
<li>"Baseline communism" refers to the natural "from each according to
   his ability, to each according to his needs" that we have in real
   human relations, like feeding a child or asking for someone to hand
   you something.</li>
<li>Debt as two equals agreeing to no longer be equal: Now <em>you</em> owe
   <em>me</em>. (In the extreme: debt peonage.)</li>
<li>The difference of kind that comes from quantification: Not just
   owing me a favor, but owing me $47.39. The relation to
   dehumanization, as when slavery puts a price on a person, which is
   only possible by removing or denying their complex real
   (unquantifiable) value. (Reminds me of <a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/" title="The Tyranny of Metrics, by Muller">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>.)</li>
<li>The necessity of violence to make people pay back debts, as when
   military power stands behind the IMF.</li>
<li>Occasional hints of primitivism or anarcho-primitivism.</li>
<li>And really, shouldn't we get rid of capitalism?</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240906-debt_by_graeber/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240906-debt_by_graeber/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Principles for dealing with the changing world order, by Dalio</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray_Dalio">Ray Dalio</a> likes gold, doesn't like when <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/money-printer-go-brrr">money printer go brrr</a>,
and does like China. He also likes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Kissinger">Kissinger</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genghis_Khan">Genghis Khan</a>.
Dalio says some reasonable and some interesting things, but it isn't
clear he <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/11/01/business/how-does-the-worlds-largest-hedge-fund-really-make-its-money.html" title="How Does the World’s Largest Hedge Fund Really Make Its Money?">practices</a> what he preaches, or that he's right.</p>
<p><img alt="bump" src="bump.png"></p>
<p>Dalio has a bunch of signals and a framework of big cycles organizing
history. It's a little bit <a href="/20200714-foundation_trilogy/" title="Asimov's Foundation trilogy">psychohistory</a> and a little bit
<a href="/20200728-technological_revolutions_and_financial_capital/" title="Technological Revolutions and Financial Capital, by Perez">cycle-finding</a>. For Dalio, the biggest cycle is the debt cycle,
followed by cycles of internal disorder and external disorder. He
describes money as starting from metal, then notes exchangeable for
metal, then fiat money.</p>
<p><img alt="empires" src="empires.png"></p>
<p>For Dalio, the step after fiat money is collapse. He cares a lot about
whether a currency is The Reserve Currency. Combining his signals, he
gets charts that show the rise and fall of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_guilder">Dutch guilder</a>, the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pound_sterling">British pound</a>, and (soon) the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US dollar</a>. China is ascendant,
never mind that their currency has been fiat longer than the dollar.</p>
<p>Dalio says he's identifying timeless principles of cause and effect.
Is he right? Historical causality is hard to test, but there are at
least a few problems with Dalio's claims.</p>
<p>For most of history, the idea of a reserve currency hasn't really made
sense. The modern monetary system is in this light novel, not
timeless. Dalio has a narrow understanding of money compared to the
anthroplogical view in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debt:_The_First_5,000_Years">Debt: The First 5,000 Years</a>, for example.</p>
<p>It's hard to find falsifiable predictions in Dalio's science. He
admits to not having good tools for predicting <em>when</em> any given thing
might happen. In this sense, his whole system is basically noticing
that things have fallen apart in the past and concluding that things
could fall apart in the future. It isn't even wrong.</p>
<p>Looking at the charts, I'm reminded of a common tension in data work:
Is data leading to theory, or is theory leading to data? Data can be
found to support most theories; what was the process here? It's rather
easy to imagine that Dalio's employees are skilled in finding what he
thinks is there.</p>
<p>Not that Dalio hasn't looked at history and so on. The
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriottentijd">Patriot movement</a> in the Netherlands does kind of feel like it
rhymes with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Make_America_Great_Again">MAGA</a> energy. He knows about
<a href="https://deloitte.wsj.com/riskandcompliance/china-spotlight-triangular-debt-considerations-1413864154">triangular debt in China</a>. He's even concerned about inequality,
though mostly because it can lead to wealth-destroying crises.</p>
<p>Does Dalio have the courage of his convictions? Perhaps not. He
frequently comes off as defensive, and digresses substantially into
his concerns about public scrutiny of the prominent. The historical
theory he seems to hold most instinctively is a great man theory in
which he and the people he talks to are great; he sounds like Trump
talking about how he knows the best people.</p>
<p>If you think your ideas are timeless, you may be right about what
happens next, but you probably won't predict things that have never
happened before. So Dalio is limited to predicting rearrangements of
the world order, not substantially new things. If Marx thought much
change was inevitable, Dalio thinks real change is fundamentally
impossible, that recurrence is the nature of society.</p>
<p>So Dalio picks China as the new king of the hill.</p>
<p>I'm curious about many of the things Dalio talks about. What causes
what in the world? How do we operate in reality? What lessons can we
learn from history? I have to think Dalio believes he's sincere about
his program. At the same time, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/11/01/business/how-does-the-worlds-largest-hedge-fund-really-make-its-money.html" title="How Does the World’s Largest Hedge Fund Really Make Its Money?">reporting</a> suggests his ability to
follow his own advice is as constrained as his ability to imagine a
better world. For all the lip service to evolution, Dalio doesn't seem
to be its exemplar.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240825-principles_changing_world_order_dalio/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240825-principles_changing_world_order_dalio/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Explanations enhance equity</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>In achieving understanding, a poor explanation can still be sufficient
for people who are relatively advantaged. Better explanations make it
possible for more people to achieve understanding more easily.</p>
<p>For a new idea, there was by definition no prior explanation. It is
generally quite difficult to come up with new useful ideas, and often
takes many years. Only very few people have any understanding of the
new idea at first.</p>
<p>Someone, maybe the discoverer, tries to communicate the new idea. This
may not be a great explanation. It may be cloaked in specialist
language, heavy with background preconceptions, hidden from broader
communities.</p>
<p>The trap of a poor explanation is that it can still be good enough for
the most active, prepared, diligent seekers. Some will realize it
isn't a good explanation, but understand anyway and move on. Others
will fight through the poor explanation and conclude, with a kind of
Stockholm syndrome, that the explanation is canonical. The poor
explanation starts to be repeated to students.</p>
<p>This cycle can get harder to break as it becomes common knowledge that
a subject is difficult, even if the difficulty is not innate but due
to the poor explanation. It becomes hard to differentiate between
removing unneeded complication and "dumbing down" the subject because
people have become attached to the way they learned it. Maybe the
subject is now a "filter class" that people take pride in having
overcome.</p>
<p>An explanation should not be a filter but a fortifier, lifting up the
listener from ignorance to understanding. Things should not be
oversimplified, but should be made as simple as possible, so that as
many people as possible can profit, as quickly as possible, from
sharing in mastery—and contribute to the next ideas.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240723-explanations_enhance_equity/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240723-explanations_enhance_equity/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Loonshots, by Bahcall</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>It's a fun book, especially at the beginning, where Bahcall has a lot
of underdog success stories. I think some of the ideas are decent, but
it's also more like an unfinished brainstorming session than a settled
science, and it's hard to distinguish useful theory from just-so
history. I'm fundamentally on board for more discoveries though!</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<p>A major metaphor in the book is "phase transitions," like solid to
liquid. Bahcall offers "The Innovation Equation" (details in
<a href="https://hbr.org/2019/03/the-innovation-equation" title="The Innovation Equation">HBR article</a>) for \( M \), "a certain size at which human groups
shift from embracing radical ideas to quashing them."</p>
<p>\[ M = \frac{E S^{2} F}{G} \]</p>
<p>The only right hand term that isn't unitless is \( S \), "management
span," which is the average number of direct reports that managers
have. Since \( S \) is squared, the result is in units of people
squared, which I don't think makes sense. With his training as a
physicist, it's a little surprising that Bahcall would do this. (Am I
missing something?)</p>
<p>Also surprising is that there's no constant term. (For example,
gravity isn't mass times mass divided by distance squared; there's a
constant that we have to get from data.) Bahcall plugs in \( E = 50\%
\), meaning compensation is 50% equity, which seems rare, then
management span of 6, and \( F = 1 \) meaning equal returns to
project work and politics, finishing with \( G = 12\% \) meaning 12%
compensation increase at promotion. Ignoring the units, this gives
150, and he claims a connection with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunbar%27s_number" title="Wikipedia: Dunbar's number">Dunbar's number</a>, saying
"That's interesting."</p>
<p>I have to think Bahcall doesn't really take this equation seriously;
he must intend it as an illustration for his narrative. Still, it
offends my sensibilities because it seems like math-washing:
presenting something that looks "fancy" to make it seem more
legitimate. In this case, the evidence isn't really anything more than
suggestive.</p>
<p>One issue is boundaries: Where does an organization begin and end?
DARPA is considered an example of an innovative organization. Do we
consider just the DARPA PMs? Also their contractors? The whole
Department of Defense?</p>
<p>I think a much more promising attempt might be made by switching from
the organization to the individual view: At what point does an
individual change their behavior, based on the local structure of
their organization and incentives? This would also be more coherent
with Bahcall's ideas about having different parts of an organization
working on different goals (loonshots vs. "franchise" work). How do
you get loonshots? Support people who work on them.</p>
<p>A deeper critique is that Bahcall's "loonshot" forces here seem more
about <em>doing your job</em> than about working on crazy innovative ideas
specifically. "Project work" is not necessarily loonshot work.</p>
<hr>
<p>This "Goals Gone Wild" <a href="https://www.hbs.edu/ris/Publication%20Files/09-083.pdf">paper</a> is pretty fun, and reminds me of
<a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/" title="The Tyranny of Metrics, by Muller">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>. The paper includes this warning label:</p>
<p><img alt="warning" src="warning.png"></p>
<hr>
<p>Also referenced (a lot) is Vannevar Bush's 1945
<a href="https://www.nsf.gov/about/history/vbush1945.htm">Science: The Endless Frontier</a>, which reminds me of
<a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/" title="The Beginning of Infinity, by Deutsch">The Beginning of Infinity</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The graveyard of unexplained experiments, as Land would soon show,
is a great place to find a False Fail.” (page 76)</p>
<p>“Some companies are the equivalent of an innovation landfill,” wrote
one senior Apple executive, who helped lure some of PARC’s best
engineers to Apple. “They are garbage dumps where great ideas go to
die. At PARC, the key development people kept leaving because they
never saw their products get into the market.” (page 115)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is an interesting idea: What's out there that's known but
ignored, currently, when it shouldn't be ignored? Bahcall uses the
example of radar's foundations being known but ignored by the Navy for
nearly 20 years. What fun things are out there, already discovered but
not yet exposed to sunlight?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“While the individual man is an insoluble puzzle, in the aggregate
he becomes a mathematical certainty.” (Sherlock Holmes, in The Sign
of the Four, quoted page 117)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Seems like everybody wants to do <a href="/20200714-foundation_trilogy/" title="Asimov's Foundation trilogy">psychohistory</a>!</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240722-loonshots_by_bahcall/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240722-loonshots_by_bahcall/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Brave New Words, by Khan</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
<p>“... a teacher has to be adjusted to fit the mind of each boy and
girl it teaches ... each kid has to be taught differently.” (Asimov,
<a href="https://www.bartlettschools.org/pdf/TheFunTheyHad.pdf">The Fun They Had</a>, 1951)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The title of this book refers to LLM text generation and Khan's call
for “educated bravery” in meeting new technologies, but it also refers
to Brave New World, a distopia. In his introduction, Khan mentions
<a href="https://planspace.org/20210422-the_diamond_age_by_stephenson/" title="The Diamond Age, by Stephenson">Diamond Age</a>, Ender's Game, and <a href="https://www.bartlettschools.org/pdf/TheFunTheyHad.pdf">The Fun They Had</a> as fiction
that “has gone on to inspire very real innovation.” In
<a href="https://planspace.org/20210422-the_diamond_age_by_stephenson/" title="The Diamond Age, by Stephenson">Diamond Age</a>, three “AI” books are really humans behind the scenes,
and the actual AI books train a child army. In Ender's Game, the
educational technology serves the goal of genocide. And in Asimov's
<a href="https://www.bartlettschools.org/pdf/TheFunTheyHad.pdf">The Fun They Had</a>, the joke is that AI education would make
children long for the current world of schooling. I'm fascinated by
the same fiction as Khan. I also think of the Star Trek post-scarcity
world (<a href="/20201109-economics_of_star_trek_by_webb/" title="The Economics of Star Trek, by Webb">1</a>, <a href="/20210401-trekonomics_by_saadia/" title="Trekonomics, by Saadia">2</a>) as an inspiration. I think Khan is right that
LLMs present opportunities, but they also face persistent challenges
of education.</p>
<p>There is a kind of “AI exceptionalism” that imagines generative AI as
immune to problems faced elsewhere. For example, Khan criticizes
Google for having ads. But will commercial LLMs remain disinterested?
Khan Academy doesn't offer its Khanmigo AI tutor for free to students
because of the cost of AI inference, and it's hard to imagine that
LLMs are permanently immune to the attentions of advertisers. And
while Khan speaks glowingly of Khanmigo, there is already at least one
<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/01/us/ai-chatbot-los-angeles-schools.html" title="A.I. ‘Friend’ for Public School Students Falls Flat">example</a> of a failed AI ed-bot effort.</p>
<p>More generally, Khan would have education and LLMs as somehow beyond
having a point of view, absolutely impartial. Researchers have worked
hard on “alignment” that creates this illusion, and certainly a
Socratic approach can have value in education. But fundamentally there
<em>is no</em> impartial view of the world, and the effect in aiming for one
is to allow the inane while preventing progress.</p>
<p>Khan wants to engage students by “incorporating their interests” in
ways that are superficial and misleading. One way to fail in this is
to imagine content as irredeemably rigid, and try to apply a false
veneer. Another way is to imagine there is no content in particular
worth focusing on.</p>
<p>Khan gives one example of imagining a soccer coach modeling goals
scored with a polynomial, and then asking for the degree of this
polynomial and the leading coefficient. This is a weak trick at best,
and doesn't at all get to <em>why</em> anyone would care about the question.
Applications can be motivating, but this one is so artificial that it
seems more likely to damage credibility.</p>
<p>Later Khan imagines restructuring a class's study of World War 2
through a focus on baseball, in a way that seems to suggest that
baseball was just as important an aspect of World War 2 as anything
else. I could see a research project on this narrow subject for an
interested student, but I also think that the bigger features of WW2
should not be deprioritized in order to pander to interests.</p>
<p>One theme here is that part of education is learning what's
interesting about things you weren't previously interested in. You
shouldn't come out of a class with only the same interests that you
went in with.</p>
<p>On history specifically, there's probably a lot more to discuss. Khan
offers that “it is impossible to engage in calculus if you don’t know
Algebra 2 well, but one can imagine engaging in college-level history
even without a strong foundation in history from high school.” I don't
know whether all history teachers would agree. To me, to the extent
that this is true, it suggests a problem with history as a discipline
at least as it is taught. I think we should ask more of history, make
more connections, draw more conclusions, have more of a sense of both
the theory and application of history. I think Khan is imagining
history as if, were it math, in high school students would learn one
table of equations and then in college learn a second table of
equations, never learning what they mean or how to use them. Perhaps
because lessons learned from history can have a political
interpretation, history is kept in schools with its hands tied? And so
we repeat the errors of the past.</p>
<p>In attempting to be impartial, existing curricula can become dogma.
Khan is so focused on how to teach everyone Pre-Algebra, Algebra 1,
and Algebra 2, that there doesn't seem to be room for re-thinking our
choices in what we teach. The “how” of education is important, but I
think the “what” and “why” are keystones, and at least as in need of
attention in light of technological advancement.</p>
<p>One pet peeve of mine is titles that are not conceptually coherent.
This is the case for Pre-Algebra, Algebra 1, and Algebra 2. These are
not good titles for courses. They reflect a bulk-frozen structure that
we should be embarrassed to offer students. Imagine if a student
submitted an outline so lousy, where the top-level bullets were "first
stuff," "second chunk," and "last bits." We should expect more clarity
of thought. No student should be given a grab bag of things to learn
without better organizing concepts and rationale, and that starts at
the level of course titles.</p>
<p>I suspect much of what is taught in schools could be improved
(dropped, modified, added to). This is not necessarily easy to do
(<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Math" title="Wikipedia: New Math">New Math</a>?) but there have been improvements over time and I
expect they can be extended. It has become rare for students to
memorize and recite <a href="https://allpoetry.com/Against-Idleness-and-Mischief">Against Idleness and Mischief</a>, for example,
while calculus, which used to be exclusively a university topic, is
now encountered by many in high school. Improving <em>what</em> is taught
should get more attention.</p>
<p>It seems like AI may move some classroom setups in directions that
feel old-fashioned: More in-person writing and tests, more focus on
spoken communication. Perhaps it will seem more obvious that teachers
are a specific type of manager, which has always been the case though
not always widely acknowledged. The toolkit expands.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240718-brave_new_words_by_khan/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240718-brave_new_words_by_khan/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Titan, by Chernow</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I wouldn't have chosen this, but it was a book club pick. It did turn
out to be interesting enough for me to make it through over 35 hours
of audio. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron_Chernow" title="Ron Chernow">Chernow</a> does well, and there's lots to say about
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_D._Rockefeller" title="John D. Rockefeller">Rockefeller</a>. His dad was quite a character, and his son funded
Colonial Williamsburg, turns out. Topics of business, wealth, and the
good life remain relevant.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240625-titan_by_chernow/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240625-titan_by_chernow/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>A brief development of matrix multiplication</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Linear Algebra is math for multiple dimensions. Linearity is a
constraint that makes handling multi-dimensional complexity more
tractable. The structure of linear transformations quickly gives rise
to the dot product and matrix multiplication.</p>
<p>In Linear Algebra, a function is linear if \( f(u+v) = f(u) + f(v)
\) and \( f(cu) = cf(u) \). This is a powerful constraint. The
common equation of a line, \( y = f(x) = mx + b \), is not linear by
this definition when \( b \neq 0 \). In the situation of one numeric
input and output, linear functions are multiplication by a constant
coefficient, \( y = f(x) = mx \).</p>
<p>If there are two inputs and one output, linear functions are
multiplications followed by addition, \( y = f(x_1, x_2) = m_1 x_1 +
m_2 x_2 \). This is the dot product of the vector \( \vec{x} = (x_1,
x_2) \) and the coefficient vector \( \vec{m} = (m_1, m_2) \). The
result is a linear combination of the inputs.</p>
<p>If there are two inputs and two outputs, each output is a linear
combination of the inputs, \( (y_1, y_2) = f(x_1, x_2) = (m_1 x_1 +
m_2 x_2, m_3 x_1 + m_4 x_2) \), also written \( \vec{y} = M \vec{x}
\).</p>
<p>Applying a second linear transform \( N \) to the output of \( M
\), the new outputs \( y_1 \) and \( y_2 \) are:</p>
<p>\[ n_1 (m_1 x_1 + m_2 x_2) + n_2 (m_3 x_1 + m_4 x_2), \\
    n_3 (m_1 x_1 + m_2 x_2) + n_4 (m_3 x_1 + m_4 x_2)  \]</p>
<p>Re-grouping shows that applying these two linear transforms one after
the other is the same as applying just one linear transform with
different coefficients:</p>
<!--
n_1 m_1 x_1 + n_1 m_2 x_2 + n_2 m_3 x_1 + n_2 m_4 x_2,
n_3 m_1 x_1 + n_3 m_2 x_2 + n_4 m_3 x_1 + n_4 m_4 x_2

n_1 m_1 x_1 + n_2 m_3 x_1 + n_1 m_2 x_2 + n_2 m_4 x_2,
n_3 m_1 x_1 + n_4 m_3 x_1 + n_3 m_2 x_2 + n_4 m_4 x_2
-->

<p>\[ (n_1 m_1 + n_2 m_3) x_1 + (n_1 m_2 + n_2 m_4) x_2, \\
    (n_3 m_1 + n_4 m_3) x_1 + (n_3 m_2 + n_4 m_4) x_2  \]</p>
<p>If \( N M = T \), then \( t_1 \) is the dot product of \( (n_1,
n_2) \) and \( (m_1, m_3) \), and so on. The coefficients can be
arranged so that each pair that appears is adjacent horizontally or
vertically.</p>
<p>\[
\begin{bmatrix}
n_1 &amp; n_2 \\
n_3 &amp; n_4
\end{bmatrix}
\begin{bmatrix}
m_1 &amp; m_2 \\
m_3 &amp; m_4
\end{bmatrix} =
\begin{bmatrix}
n_1 m_1 + n_2 m_3 &amp; n_1 m_2 + n_2 m_4 \\
n_3 m_1 + n_4 m_3 &amp; n_3 m_2 + n_4 m_4
\end{bmatrix}
\]</p>
<p>There is a choice here: The coefficients are written in English
reading order, left to right and top to bottom. They could just as
well be placed top to bottom and right to left, for example. This
choice is arbitrary, but the nature of matrix multiplication is not.</p>
<hr>
<p>This is a terse version of what I think could be a good way to
introduce Linear Algebra and matrix multiplication. It is a more
traditionally symbolic version of
<a href="/20210915-flow_metaphor_for_matrix_multiplication/">the flow metaphor for matrix multiplication</a>, with more focus on
linearity as a driving part of the meaning of Linear Algebra.</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240624-brief_development_matrix_multiplication/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240624-brief_development_matrix_multiplication/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Linear Algebra Done Right, by Axler</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Axler's beautiful <a href="https://linear.axler.net/">textbook</a>, now in Open Access for the fourth
edition, is sort of an expansion of his 1995
<a href="https://www.axler.net/DwD.html" title="Down with Determinants!">Down with Determinants!</a> and is full of his characteristic
humanity, humor, joy, and good sense. I love the book's title most for
the implication that there <em>are</em> different ways that linear algebra
can be done—and Axler's book is convincing evidence that developing
the subject without prioritizing determinants can be done well.</p>
<p>The equation on the cover is the closed form solution for the \( n
\)th Fibonacci number, derived using linear algebra in an exercise on
page 174, just one of the book's treasures.</p>
<p><img src="cover.png" height="640"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Do not memorize the formula for the product of two complex
numbers—you can always rederive it by recalling that \( i^2 = -1
\) and then using the usual rules of arithmetic (as given by 1.3).
(page 2)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I love seeing advice like this in textbooks; sort of a didactic
principle of emphasizing what's fundamental and what's a
consequence... On the other hand you don't want to re-derive
everything every time, but there's some optimization of what gets a
spot in memory...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>When we think of an element of \( \mathbb{R}^2 \) as an arrow, we
refer to it as a vector.</p>
<p>Whenever we use pictures in \( \mathbb{R}^2 \) or use the somewhat
vague language of points and vectors, remember that these are just
aids to our understanding, not substitutes for the actual
mathematics that we will develop. (page 8)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also good pedagogy here, I think: making a distinction between the
thing itself and a mental model or metaphor for it.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Mathematical models of the economy can have thousands of variables,
say \( x_1, ..., x_{5000} \), which means that we must work in \(
\mathbb{R}^{5000} \). Such a space cannot be dealt with
geometrically. However, the algebraic approach works well. Thus our
subject is called <strong>linear algebra</strong>. (page 8)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I appreciate the attempt to justify the name, but I feel like this one
isn't completely satisfying... Good aspect: Gets at the centrality of
multi-dimensionality. Less good aspect: Doesn't really justify the
"linear" part.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>We could define a multiplication in \( \mathbb{F}^n \) in a
similar fashion, starting with two elements of \( \mathbb{F}^n \)
and getting another element of \( \mathbb{F}^n \) by multiplying
corresponding coordinates. Experience shows that this definition is
not useful for our purposes. Another type of multiplication, called
scalar multiplication, will be central to our subject. (page 9)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I feel like the appeal to experience is not a satisfying justification
for matrix multiplication. I like the <a href="/20210915-flow_metaphor_for_matrix_multiplication/" title="The flow metaphor for matrix multiplication">flow metaphor</a>, and I think
even better can be done than my exposition there...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In general, a vector space is an abstract entity whose elements
might be lists, functions, or weird objects. (page 14)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Fun example of being both mathematically rigorous and friendly in
communication.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>I at once gave up my former occupations, set down natural history
and all its progeny as a deformed and abortive creation, and
entertained the greatest disdain for a would-be science which could
never even step within the threshold of real knowledge. In this mood
I betook myself to the mathematics and the branches of study
appertaining to that science as being built upon secure foundations,
and so worthy of my consideration.</p>
<p>—Frankenstein, Mary Wollstonecraft Shelley (page 50)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Axler has inserted some fun quotes at the ends of sections here and
there; this is one I liked.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>We will frequently use the powerful fundamental theorem of linear
maps, which states that the dimension of the domain of a linear map
equals the dimension of the subspace that gets sent to 0 plus the
dimension of the range. (page 51)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Thus the linear functions of high school algebra are not the same as
linear maps in the context of linear algebra. (page 56)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He's using zero-to-zero to show this here. I think this is a really
helpful thing to emphasize immediately.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Consider linear maps \( T: U \to V \) and \(S: V \to W \). The
composition \( ST \) is a linear map from \( U \) to \( W \).
Does \( M(ST) \) equal \( M(S)M(T) \)? This question does not
yet make sense because we have not defined the product of two
matrices. We will choose a definition of matrix multiplication that
forces this question to have a positive answer. (page 72)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here is at least some justification of matrix multiplication. I think
it comes a little late, since matrices were introduced already, and
really they sort of co-design...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Note that we define the product of two matrices only when the number
of columns of the first matrix equals the number of rows of the
second matrix. (73)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Couldn't this be made to feel less arbitrary?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The fundamental theorem of algebra is an existence theorem. Its
proof does not lead to a method for finding zeros. The quadratic
formula gives the zeros explicitly for polynomials of degree 2.
Similar but more complicated formulas exist for polynomials of
degree 3 and 4. No such formulas exist for polynomials of degree 5
and above. (page 124)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Axler does a lot to connect these algebra ideas and linear algebra,
which is pretty cool.</p>
<p>It's the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abel%E2%80%93Ruffini_theorem" title="Abel–Ruffini theorem">Abel–Ruffini theorem</a> that shows there aren't formulas for
degree five and up. Is this mentioned when teaching the quadratic
formula? Would be cool to at least show the crazy equations for degree
three and four...</p>
<p>A later example:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This exercise shows that every monic polynomial is the minimal
polynomial of some operator. Hence a formula or an algorithm that
could produce exact eigenvalues for each operator on each \(
\mathbb{F}^n \) could then produce exact zeros for each polynomial
[by 5.27(a)]. Thus there is no such formula or algorithm. However,
efficient numeric methods exist for obtaining very good
approximations for the eigenvalues of an operator. (page 152)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Now we begin our investigation of operators, which are linear maps
from a vector space to itself. Their study constitutes the most
important part of linear algebra. (page 132)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The word eigenvalue is half-German, half-English. The German prefix
eigen means “own” in the sense of characterizing an intrinsic
property. (page 134)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I like this kind of explanation.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The main reason that a richer theory exists for operators (which map
a vector space into itself) than for more general linear maps is
that operators can be raised to powers. (page 137)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>A central goal of linear algebra is to show that given an operator
\( T \) on a finite-dimensional vector space \( V \), there
exists a basis of \( V \) with respect to which \( T \) has a
reasonably simple matrix. (page 154)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>You may recall from a previous course that every matrix of numbers
can be changed to a matrix in what is called row echelon form. If
one begins with a square matrix, the matrix in row echelon form will
be an upper-triangular matrix. Do not confuse this upper-triangular
matrix with the upper-triangular matrix of an operator with respect
to some basis whose existence is proclaimed by 5.47 (if \(
\mathbb{F} = \mathbb{C} \))—there is no connection between these
upper-triangular matrices. (page 160)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The Euclidean algorithm for polynomials (look it up) can quickly
determine the greatest common divisor of two polynomials, without
requiring any information about the zeros of the polynomials. (page
173)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I'm just amused by the "look it up".</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Thus the pseudoinverse provides what is called a best fit to the
equation above. (page 222)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I thought a bit about how linear regression is solved. The thing
that's usually written down, \( (X^T X)^{-1} X^T y \), is really
crummy computationally if \( X \) isn't well-behaved, because of the
inverse...</p>
<p>It seems like nobody actually implements regression this way. In R,
<code>lm</code> is done via QR decomposition, anyway.</p>
<p>The pseudoinverse seems to work too, but doesn't always give the same
solution, when multiple solutions are possible. I suspect it isn't
used in practice because SVD is more work than QR. There may be more
reasons.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Recall that an operator on \( V \) is called diagonalizable if the
operator has a diagonal matrix with respect to some basis of \( V
\). Recall also that this happens if and only if there is a basis
of \( V \) consisting of eigenvectors of the operator (see 5.55).
(page 243)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>7.54 eigenvalues of unitary operators have absolute value 1 (page 262)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Makes me want to see some quantum examples...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>8.50 trace of matrix of operator does not depend on basis (page 327)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>How cool is this? Could it come earlier?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Our definition of the determinant leads to the following magical
proof that the determinant is multiplicative. (page 357)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We're having fun!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Vandermonde matrices have important applications in polynomial
interpolation, the discrete Fourier transform, and other areas of
mathematics. (page 366)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Makes me want to read an applied book.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>I find that in my own elementary lectures, I have, for pedagogical
reasons, pushed determinants more and more into the background. Too
often I have had the experience that, while the students acquired
facility with the formulas, which are so useful in abbreviating long
expressions, they often failed to gain familiarity with their
meaning, and skill in manipulation prevented the student from going
into all the details of the subject and so gaining a mastery.</p>
<p>—Elementary Mathematics from an Advanced Standpoint: Geometry, Felix
Klein (page 369)</p>
</blockquote>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240616-linear_algebra_done_right/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240616-linear_algebra_done_right/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
