<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>Mortality rates have improved</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>A misleading graph from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rise_and_Fall_of_American_Growth" title="The Rise and Fall of American Growth, by Robert J. Gordon">The Rise and Fall of American Growth</a> was
reproduced and again misinterpreted in <a href="/20240128-outlive_by_attia/" title="Outlive, by Peter Attia">Outlive</a>. The graph
correctly shows that US deaths from infectious disease have decreased
a lot over the last hundred years. The graph incorrectly makes it seem
like death rates from other causes have been stable over this period.
The age-adjusted death rate has decreased by around 50% since 1950.
Death rates at every age band have been meaningfully decreasing, apart
from the impact of COVID-19.</p>
<p>Here's the graph in <a href="/20240128-outlive_by_attia/" title="Outlive, by Peter Attia">Outlive</a>:</p>
<p><img alt="in Outlive" src="outlive.png"></p>
<p>What a remarkably horizontal white line! It supports Attia's position,
in that he's arguing that we need to invest more in fighting other
causes of death (heart disease, cancer, dementia, diabetes) so he's
trying to make them seem like big unsolved problems. And certainly,
they are big unsolved problems. But the claim that mortality rates
haven't been improving is misleading.</p>
<p>Let's first go to the graph in
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rise_and_Fall_of_American_Growth" title="The Rise and Fall of American Growth, by Robert J. Gordon">The Rise and Fall of American Growth</a>:</p>
<p><img alt="in The Rise and Fall of American Growth" src="growth.png"></p>
<p>Attia copied this graph fairly exactly, except for adding "top" before
and removing the asterisk after "diseases," which is just as well
since the asterisk doesn't seem to have an explanation in <em>Growth</em>
anyway.</p>
<p>Such a horizontal white line! Here, it supports Gordon's position, in
that he's arguing that things were getting better in the US from
1870-1970, but things aren't getting better so much any more. So
here's a decrease that stops decreasing by 1970.</p>
<p>The biggest problem with this presentation is that the data is not
age-adjusted, and as such it's sensitive to the distribution of ages
in the population. For example, with low death rates for people in
their early years, one way to lower the raw death rate is to arrange
for the birth of a lot of babies. The raw death rate doesn't tell us
much about anything in particular, and certainly isn't the "real"
death rate in any meaningful way. Let's compare with a <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data-visualization/mortality-trends/index.htm" title="Mortality Trends in the United States, 1900–2018">CDC graph</a>
that is age-adjusted:</p>
<p><img alt="CDC graph" src="cdc.png"></p>
<p>The green line is the age-adjusted death rate. It was 1,446 in 1950,
1,222.6 in 1970, and 723.6 in 2018. That's a 50% improvement from
1950, and a 41% improvement from 1970.</p>
<p>Adjusting for age is important, because for example, when people don't
die young, you get more old people. Baby booms and so on also matter.
The population pyramid looks different now than it did in 1900.
Compare the 1900 and 2000 shapes as presented in a
<a href="http://vis.stanford.edu/jheer/d3/pyramid/shift.html" title="U.S. Census Population Pyramid, 1850-2000">Stanford visualization</a>:</p>
<p><img alt="population pyramids" src="stanford.png"></p>
<p>Both the raw and age-adjusted overall death rates don't tell us
everything about what's happening at every age, so let's look at that.
Here are death rates for the oldest nine age buckets in
<a href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/annual-death-rate-by-age-group" title="Annual death rate by age group, United States, 2021">data from the Human Mortality Database</a> from 1933 to 2021, shown
with a <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1VjBsxGqajqBThla0JDQGSAnS2fXUeUTVBG95PD6pbE4/edit" title="age-band death rates over time">quick graph</a> I made.</p>
<p><img alt="death rates by age group" src="by_age_group.png"></p>
<p>Every age group is seeing decreasing death rates up until COVID-19
impacts 2020 numbers. I left out younger age bands to avoid crowding,
but those also show improvement, especially for the youngest.</p>
<p>For people 85-89, the death rate per 1,000 was 179.87 in 1950, and
154.77 in 1970. It was 103.14 in 2018. That's a 43% improvement since
1950, and 33% improvement from 1970. Even the COVID-19 spike takes us
back only to around the same levels as we saw in 2000.</p>
<p>Things have been improving. Improving since 1950, improving since
1970, improving since 2000 apart from COVID-19. It just isn't accurate
to suggest that death rates haven't been going down over these
periods. There's still room for improvement, but the real gains should
be celebrated, not ignored.</p>
<p>The question of whether life expectancies have leveled off or even
decreased over shorter, more recent periods is quite distinct from the
trend over these longer periods.</p>
<p>I attempted to <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/19kuO6mIAi-f3etXZtVNndLEqoGOHACjLvzokBCrYGqQ/edit" title="death rates from HSUS">replicate</a> Gordon's graph using the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historical_Statistics_of_the_United_States" title="Historical Statistics of the United States">HSUS</a> data.
He cites Ab929-943, which includes ten columns of infectious disease
death, by my count. He uses Ab952 for the total death rate, I believe.</p>
<p>It adds only confusion that Gordon's figure is titled "Mortality Rate
<em>as Percentage of GNP</em>" (emphasis added). He also cites HSUS series
Bd46 (percentage of GNP spent on health care from 1929 to 1997) and
2012 SAUS table 134 (health care spending). This seems to be a
leftover of an idea from an earlier paper. Gordon's footnote 22 says
that his figure "is an update of McKinlay and McKinlay (1977, figure
3, p. 416)" so let's track that down.</p>
<p>The paper is
<a href="https://www.milbank.org/wp-content/uploads/mq/volume-55/issue-03/55-3-The-Questionable-Contribution-of-Medical-Measures-to-the-Decline-of-Mortality-in-the-United-States-in-the-Twentieth-Century.pdf">The Questionable Contribution of Medical Measures to the Decline of Mortality in the United States in the Twentieth Century</a>.
It has this Figure 3:</p>
<p><img alt="Figure 3" src="figure3.png"></p>
<p>There is no horizontal white line here. The presentation is quite
different, arguably better for showing the decrease in death from
infectious disease. McKinlay and McKinlay seem to have known to use
age-adjusted statistics as well. More relevant to the discussion of
GNP, however, their paper has this Figure 2:</p>
<p><img alt="Figure 2" src="figure2.png"></p>
<p>The point it's making is that increased spending on health care
doesn't seem to be driving a lot of increased reduction in death rate.
There's something to this argument, but 50 years later we can also see
(in the CDC graph above) that the period roughly 1955-1965 was a
fairly flat spot on the death rate graph, with improvement continuing
after it.</p>
<p>Gordon mentions the concern that spending on health care isn't
delivering matching results in death rate improvement, but it doesn't
make it into his figure apart from the title and data citations.</p>
<p>The horizontal white line is basically a coincidence as death has been
shifting from younger to older people over time and the population
pyramid has been changing shape. This graph is misleading.</p>
<p><img alt="warning" src="warning.png"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240407-mortality_rates_have_improved/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240407-mortality_rates_have_improved/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Homo Deus, by Harari</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>It feels like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yuval_Noah_Harari" title="Yuval Noah Harari">Harari</a> got the advance for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homo_Deus:_A_Brief_History_of_Tomorrow" title="Homo Deus: A Brief History of Tomorrow">Homo Deus</a> before
really thinking it through. It's rambling, over-long, without cohesive
thesis, and like a time capsule of science and tech news from 2014:
Big Data! Watson! Quantified Self! Mild <a href="/20191108-accelerando_by_stross/" title="Accelerando, by Stross">Accelerando</a> flavor. I wish
I'd read the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yuval_Noah_Harari#Critical_reception">Critical Reception</a> section from Harari's Wikipedia
entry and skipped this book.</p>
<p>My biggest gripe is probably that Harari argues (at length) that
animals have consciousness, and that animals are algorithms, and then
also claims without a second thought that algorithms implemented via
computer have no consciousness.</p>
<p>Harari also makes the fairly common error of scientific
exceptionalism: the belief that scientific ways of knowing are
fundamentally distinct from all others. For the number of words he
releases on related topics, this is frustrating.</p>
<p>Harari does say some reasonable things. I think he's correct in
pointing out limitations in our understanding of consciousness. (I
think this is such an interesting topic I wrote a <a href="/20230325-conversion_of_guelph_energy_to_mass/" title="Conversion of Guelph energy to mass (p=0.049)">short story</a>
about it.)</p>
<p>I also like Harari's phrasing around learning history in order to be
liberated from it. But throughout the book, the moments of lucidity
make the languid and ludicrous majority that much more unbearable.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240331-homo_deus_by_harari/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240331-homo_deus_by_harari/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Lifespan, by Sinclair</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I heard about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lifespan:_Why_We_Age_%E2%80%93_and_Why_We_Don%27t_Have_To" title="Lifespan: Why We Age – and Why We Don't Have To">this book</a> from a neighbor after I was talking about
<a href="/20240128-outlive_by_attia/" title="(Audio) Outlive, by Attia">Outlive</a>. Compared to Attia, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_A._Sinclair" title="David A. Sinclair">Sinclair</a> is more academic, not as
into protein (especially animal protein), and more extreme in his
claims that aging is a curable disease explained by his "Information
Theory" of epigenetic aging. Sinclair takes metformin, resveratrol,
and NMN. (After the book he started taking rapamycin as well, based on
a YouTube interview.) The book is longer than it needs to be to cover
the topics of Sinclair's expertise. The audio book has little
interludes between Sinclair and his writer, which is sort of a fun
idea but I'm not sure it added much.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.png"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240319-lifespan_by_sinclair/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240319-lifespan_by_sinclair/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) The Body, by Bryson</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Bryson's intonation is a little like Werner Herzog's. His book on the
body is charmingly, gently amusing. It's a selection of fun facts and
good advice: exercise more, eat less, maybe get some more vitamin D
and choline. One reference is Haldane's 1926
<a href="https://www.phys.ufl.edu/courses/phy3221/spring10/HaldaneRightSize.pdf">On Being the Right Size</a>, which has a similar sense of humor.
Bryson has a good time, and so does the reader (or listener).</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240303-the_body_by_bryson/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240303-the_body_by_bryson/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) The Comfort Crisis, by Easter</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Built from Men's Health articles, Easter's book gathers tales of his
hunting trips with the bros. Sometimes there are scientific and
philosophical digressions. I liked how the chapter about death came at
the moment between shooting and killing the wild reindeer.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<p>Easter talks about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B._J._Fogg" title="B. J. Fogg">Fogg</a> Behavior Model (action requires
Motivation, Ability, and a Prompt) and suggests that scrolling on your
phone all the time is a bad idea. Okay. He also suggests that audible
white noise is caused by EM radiation in air. I struggle to find a
reasonable interpretation that makes this true. There's also a good
deal of "people used to do this long ago, therefore it's a good idea,"
which isn't necessarily wrong, but it's too easy to ignore whether
there's a good argument beyond the appeal to nature.</p>
<p>The thesis is basically that we should get off the couch, eat
healthier, and challenge ourselves. I agree, basically. I'm now
listening to Rushkoff's Survival of the Richest, which has some advice
which is similar in effect: Focus on the real world rather than
disappearing into a technologically mediated isolation pod. Rushkoff
gets there by a different path, and from his mouth it sounds like a
call to a pro-social future. From Easter, it sounds like rugged
individualism for reclaiming masculinity.</p>
<p>We're very lucky to be able to choose our level of difficulty, when we
can.</p>
<p><a href="https://webcomicname.com/"><img alt="comic" src="comic.png"></a></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240211-comfort_crisis_by_easter/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240211-comfort_crisis_by_easter/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Outlive, by Attia</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I was already thinking about improving my health, then my last
grandparent died, and this book was recommended in Spotify and by a
friend. It was gratifying to listen to while running because <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/">Attia</a>
kept saying how good exercise is.</p>
<p>He's a little bit of a tech bro. He talks about how he mellowed and
started taking one (1) day off per week. And is he responsible for the
popularity of <a href="https://www.goruck.com/pages/what-is-rucking">rucking</a>? He used to be very into <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ketogenic_diet">keto</a> and
fasting. He still seems to be a little quick to assume causation. But
still: Who doesn't want more healthspan?</p>
<ul>
<li>Recommendations<ul>
<li>Exercise<ul>
<li>"Zone 2" sustained cardio</li>
<li>Intense cardio for improving VO2-max</li>
<li>Strength (with weights)</li>
<li>Stability (core, <a href="https://www.posturalrestoration.com/">posture</a>, flexitility...)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Diet<ul>
<li>A lot of protein and fiber</li>
<li>Avoid too much other stuff</li>
<li>Keep bad cholesterol (LDL, but he prefers measuring
   <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apolipoprotein_B">ApoB</a>) <em>very</em> low (usual guideline is under 100; he says
   under 20)<ul>
<li>Maybe use statins and/or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metformin">metformin</a> etc.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Minimal to no alcohol</li>
<li><em>Don't get diabetes</em></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Get lots of tests done, screen early for cancer, etc.</li>
<li>Sleep (lots of good)</li>
<li>Emotional health (good)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sirolimus">Rapamycin</a> taken once a week<ul>
<li>You can get this from <a href="https://agelessrx.com/">AgeLessRx</a> or <a href="https://gethealthspan.com/">HealthSpan</a>, for
   example.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Anchor phrases<ul>
<li>Medicine 3.0: Where 1.0 was witchcraft/superstition, 2.0 is
   scientific "treat the disease" modern medicine, and 3.0 is his
   style of life-long health improvement to avoid diseases of
   aging etc. (Attia's practice is called "Early.")</li>
<li>The Four Horsemen<ul>
<li>Heart disease, stroke, etc.</li>
<li>Cancer</li>
<li>Dementia etc.</li>
<li>Diabetes and friends ("metabolic disfunction") which he
   says is related to the other three</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The Centenarian Decathlon: Work toward being able to do things
   when you're really old; overprepare because you will age.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Oh also he talks a little bit about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mendelian_randomization">Mendelian randomization</a>, which
it turns out is just using genetics as an <a href="/20210430-a_simple_instrumental_variable/">instrumental variable</a>.
Also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bradford_Hill_criteria">Bradford Hill criteria</a> for causation. Neat!</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240128-outlive_by_attia/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240128-outlive_by_attia/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fundamentals: Ten Keys to Reality, by Wilczek</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I liked <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank_Wilczek" title="Wikipedia: Frank Wilczek">Wilczek</a> on <a href="/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/" title="The Strangest Man, by Farmelo">Dirac</a> in <a href="/20231119-it_must_be_beautiful/" title="It must be beautiful, edited by Farmelo">It must be beautiful</a>, and I
like him a lot <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fundamentals:_Ten_Keys_to_Reality" title="Wikipedia: Fundamentals: Ten Keys to Reality">here</a>! This is Nobel-prize-winning <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_chromodynamics" title="Wikipedia: Quantum chromodynamics">QCD</a> and also
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_crystal" title="Wikipedia: Time crystal">time crystal</a> guy. Just a beautiful intro to modern particle
physics, scientific perspective, an an optimism for open-ended future
development across all scientific disciplines that reminds me of
<a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/" title="The Beginning of Infinity, by Deutsch">The Beginning of Infinity</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Fundamentals</em> is meant, as well, to offer an alternative to
traditional religious fundamentalism. It takes up some of the same
basic questions, but addresses them by consulting physical reality,
rather than texts or traditions. (page xiii)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Of course, consulting physical reality is its own tradition...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The method of Kepler, Galileo, and Newton combines the humble
discipline of respecting the facts and learning from Nature with the
systematic chutzpah of using what you think you've learned
aggressively, applying it everywhere you can, even in situations
that go beyond your original evidence. If it works, then you've
discovered something useful; if it doesn't, then you've learned
something important. I've called that attitude Radical Conservatism,
and to me it's the essential innovation of the Scientific
Revolution. (pages 4-5)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't know if he has priority, but I'm pretty sure Wilczek's sense
of Radical Conservatism isn't the most common...</p>
<p>See also <a href="/20170825-characteristics_of_good_theories/">Characteristics of good theories</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Ptolemy's [geocentric] synthesis was a magnificent achievement, but
it had two shortcomings. One was its complexity and, related to
this, its ugliness. In particular, the recipes it used to calculate
planetary motions brought in many numbers that were determined
purely by fitting the calculations to observations, without deeper
guiding principles connecting them. Copernicus (1473-1543) noticed
that the values of some of those numbers were related to one another
in surprisingly simple ways. These otherwise mysterious,
"coincidental" relationships could be explained geometrically, if
one assumed that Earth together with Venus, Mars, Jupiter, and
Saturn all revolve around the Sun as center (and the Moon further
revolves around Earth). (page 6)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't think I'd heard quite this explanation before... In light of
"end of science" arguments that big data pushes us more toward
"numbers ... determined purely by fitting the calculations to
observations" this Ptolemaic narrative could almost fit into a kind of
"we were once less wise in our theory, and now we become less wise
again" story.</p>
<p>Wilczek goes on to briefly cover how Kepler's work made the system
still simpler and better-working. Have we simplified everything as
much as it can be? Could we do better?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But Galileo aspired to a different kind of understanding. He wanted
to understand <em>something</em> precisely, rather than <em>everything</em>
vaguely. (page 7)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Finding the right questions, etc. etc.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>A more recent quotation from John R. Pierce, a pioneer of modern
information science, beautifully captures the contrast between the
modern concept of scientific understanding and all other approaches:
"We require that our theories harmonize in detail with the very wide
range of phenomena they seek to explain. And we insist that they
provide us with useful guidance rather than with rationalizations."
(page 9)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This reminds me of <a href="/20170825-characteristics_of_good_theories/">Characteristics of good theories</a>.</p>
<p>Also, this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_R._Pierce" title="Wikipedia: John R. Pierce">Pierce</a> character came up a bunch in <a href="/20231231-myth_of_ai_by_larson/" title="The myth of artificial intelligence, by Larson">Larson's book</a>
as well. (But this book is much, much better.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Unlike the situation for stars or planets, which almost invariably
are separated from their neighbors by distances many times their own
size, the typical separation between galaxies is not vastly larger
than the galaxies themselves. (page 27)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Huh! Neat.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The Roman philosopher Seneca expressed the opposite of this thought
[that human life is short] in "On the Shortness of Life." "Why do we
complain about nature?" he writes. "It has acted generously; life,
if you know how to use it, is long." (pages 43-44)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Oh interesting! It seems like <a href="/20201107-how_to_live_on_24_hours_a_day/" title="How to Live on 24 Hours a Day, by Bennett">Bennett</a> didn't know (or at least
didn't reference) Seneca's <a href="https://archive.org/stream/SenecaOnTheShortnessOfLife/Seneca+on+the+Shortness+of+Life_djvu.txt" title="Full text of 'Seneca On The Shortness Of Life'">work</a> in his How to Live on 24 Hours a
Day.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li><em>The basic laws describe change.</em> It is useful to separate the
   description of the world into two parts: states and laws. States
   describe "what there is," while laws describe "how things
   change."</li>
<li><em>The basic laws are universal.</em> That is, the basic laws hold
   everywhere, and for all times.</li>
<li><em>The basic laws are local.</em> That is, the behavior of an object in
   the immediate future depends only on current conditions in its
   immediate vicinity. The standard scientific jargon for this
   principle is <em>locality.</em></li>
<li><em>The basic laws are precise.</em> The laws are precise, and they
   admit no exceptions. Thus, they can be formulated as mathematical
   equations. (pages 64-65)</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Locality over reality.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Fields, rather than particles, are the fundamental building blocks
of matter in modern physics. (page 67)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Wilczek identifies "Mass" and "Charge" and "Spin" as the only three
basic, primary properties of matter. (page 73)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>(There's an interesting mathematical reason why physicists call the
basic unit of angular momentum spin 1/2, rather than spin 1, but it
is beyond the scope of this book.) (page 75)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It seems like this is related to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spin%E2%80%93statistics_theorem">spin–statistics theorem</a> or
something? But come on, Wilczek, you big tease...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Contrary to Democritus, though, our modern basic ingredients don't
have hooks. They aren't even solid bodies. Indeed, thought it's
convenient to call them "elementary particles," they aren't really
particles. (That is, they have little in common with what the word
"particle" suggests.) Our modern fundamental ingredients have no
intrinsic size or shape. If we insist on visualizing them, we should
think of structureless points where concentrations of mass, charge,
and spin reside. We have, in places of "atoms and the void,"
space-time and properties. (page 77)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Democritus was the early atomic theory guy.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>By being first, Franklin got to choose which kind of charge to call
positive and which negative. He chose to call the charge that
accumulates on glass, after it is rubbed with silk, positive. This
was long before people knew about electrons. Unfortunately, it turns
out that according to Franklin's choice the electron's charge is
negative. It's much too late to undo that choice, since it has
seeped into thousands of books, papers, and circuit diagrams.
Therefore, we list the electron's charge as -1. (pages 81-82)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Benjamin Franklin.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Once you get to thinking about materials as homes to quasiparticles,
a profound question is not far off: Can we consider "empty space"
itself to be a material, whose quasiparticles are our "elementary
particles"? We can, and we should. It is a very fruitful line of
thought, as you'll see in later chapters. (page 90)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I'm not sure that last promise was ever paid off very well...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>John Wheeler, the poet of relativity, summed it up this way:
"Space-time tells matter how to move; matter tells space-time how to
bend." (page 117)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is that really a good way to sum up? It reminds me of the
stretched-sheet-of-rubber image, which I think is not so good...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The Future of Comprehension (page 119)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I just thought this was a cool section heading.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>You should not fail to notice that 500 trillion is a great deal
larger than 25, or even 95. (page 127)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Cute!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>H. G. Wells caught the spirit of thermal equilibrium memorably: "If
anything is possible, then nothing is interesting." (page 151)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>How the Universe got Interesting (page 161)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another fun heading.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There are several kinds of anomalous color perception, misnamed
"color blindness," that are not terribly rare. Around 95 percent of
humans have similar color vision, based on three types of cone cells
that vary little between individuals. There are theoretical reasons,
based on genetics, to believe that a significant fraction of humans,
specifically mothers and full sisters of males with the most common
color anomaly, have four kinds of cone cells. These "tetrachromats"
might have super-normal color vision. But as far as I know, direct
evidence for this is surprisingly rare. (page 170)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetrachromacy">Huh!</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Let's recall that John Wheeler, the poet of general relativity,
summed it up this way: "Space-time tells matter how to move; matter
tells space-time how to bend." Wheeler's summary is catchy, but it
is misleading, or at least incomplete, whithout this important
addition: <em>Space-time is a form of matter, too.</em> (page 178)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Although we understand <em>a lot</em> about how the world works, there are
still big mysteries. These three great questions came up earlier:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>What triggered the big bang? Could it happen again?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Are there meaningful patterns hidden in the apparent sprawl of
  fundamental particles and forces?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>How, concretely, does mind emerge from matter? (Or does it?) (page
  187)</p>
</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>On page 190, he uses "rock bottom" to refer to that final point in
explanation beyond which there is no further "why?" I think it's a
good thing to remember, that we can't avoid having such a rock bottom.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Dark energy" is another theoretically motivated modification to the
law of gravity, also considered by Einstein. He called it by a
different name: the cosmological constant. (page 195)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There is immense satisfaction in describing the world in terms of
its most elementary building blocks. It is tempting to say that this
is the ideal description, while other, high-level descriptions are
mere approximations—compromises, which reflect weakness in
understanding. That attitude, which makes the perfect the enemy of
the good, is superficially deep, but deeply superficial.</p>
<p>In order to answer questions of interest, we often need to change
focus. To discover—or invent—new concepts, and new ways of working
with them, is an open-ended, creative activity. Computer scientists
and software engineers are well aware that in designing useful
algorithms, it is important to pay attention to how knowledge is
represented. A good representation can make the difference between
usable knowledge and knowledge that is there "in principle" but not
really available, because it takes too long and too much trouble to
locate and process. It's like the difference between owning bars of
gold and knowing that in principle there are vast stores of gold
atoms floating dissolved in the ocean.</p>
<p>For that reason, complete understanding of the fundamental laws, if
we ever achieved it, would be neither "the Theory of Everything" nor
"the End of Science." (Those are two phrases, endemic in popular
science journalism, that I find extremely irritating.) We would
still need complementary descriptions of reality. There would still
be plenty of great questions left unanswered, and plenty of great
scientific work left to do.</p>
<p>There always will be. (pages 215-216)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is just the conclusion of a longer section on this topic, which I
like quite a lot. It reminds me of Deutsch's
<a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/">Beginning of Infinity</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Do people have choice in what they do, or are they puppets who dance
to the tune of mathematical physics? That is a bad question, not
unlike asking whether music is harmony or melody. (page 218)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>...what the great biologist Francis Crick has called "the
astonishing hypothesis": that mind, in all its aspects, is "no more
than the behavior of a vast assembly of nerve cells and their
associated molecules." (pages 225-226)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... there are three different kinds [sic] color charge, and eight
different kinds of gluons that respond to them. (page 234)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What? This seems cool and fun.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Now we come to a group of elementary particles nobody really knows
what to make of. The bonus particles are all unstable. They were
discovered among the debris of high-energy collisions, either in
cosmic rays (early in the twentieth century) or at parcle
accelerators (more recently). When the first of them, the muon, was
discovered in 1936, the renowned physicist I. I. Rabi captured the
community's bewilderment in a quip that's become legendary: "Who
ordered that?" (page 236)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>These are the charm, top, strange, and bottom quark, together with the
muon and tauon.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The website of the Particle Data Group is http://pdg.lbl.gov. (page 238)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Nice!</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240114-fundamentals_by_wilczek/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240114-fundamentals_by_wilczek/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Hidden Potential, by Grant</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Spotify has audiobooks now! Fifteen hours per month before charging
more. So I listened to <a href="https://adamgrant.net/book/hidden-potential/">Hidden Potential</a> while running. It was a
fun, inspiring listen. Everyone can be great!</p>
<p>I don't take many notes on audiobooks, but one study caught my ear:
<a href="https://www.sesp.northwestern.edu/docs/publications/142575725559b6ba6c4706e.pdf">Are tenure track professors better teachers?</a> Grant presented it as
saying that less experienced professors were better teachers, but that
isn't quite right; it's comparing tenure track professors to teaching
adjuncts. Also, it says the bad performance of tenure track folks is
because roughly a quarter of them were particularly bad, not that all
of them were bad. Neat study, anyway.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240113-audio_hidden_potential_grant/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240113-audio_hidden_potential_grant/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Seneca's De Brevitate Vitae</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I guess it's just an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_Brevitate_Vitae_(Seneca)" title="Wikipedia: De Brevitate Vitae (Seneca)">essay</a>, but I spent a dollar and highlighted a
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B084QKS7PG/" title="Amazon: On the Shortness of Life Kindle Edition">Kindle version</a> of On the Shortness of Life, so I'm probably making
the most of mine. It's a little bit like a much earlier version of
<a href="/20201107-how_to_live_on_24_hours_a_day/" title="How to Live on 24 Hours a Day, by Bennett">How to Live on 24 Hours a Day</a>, except that it's quite specific in
what you <em>should</em> be doing with your life: philosophy. Okay, senator.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Of all men they alone are at leisure who take time for philosophy,
they alone really live; for they are not content to be good
guardians of their own lifetime only.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It is not that we have a short space of time, but that we waste much
of it.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>the life we receive is not short, but we make it so,</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Everyone hurries his life on and suffers from a yearning for the
future and a weariness of the present.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Men trifle with the most precious thing in the world; but they are
blind to it because it is an incorporeal thing, because it does not
come beneath the sight of the eyes, and for this reason it is
counted a very cheap thing—nay, of almost no value at all.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>busy men find life very short.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>so enfeebled are they by the excessive lassitude of a pampered mind
that they cannot find out by themselves whether they are hungry!</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>it seems the part of a man who is very lowly and despicable to know
what he is doing.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>They annex every age to their own; all the years that have gone
before them are an addition to their store.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Has some time passed by? This he embraces by recollection. Is time
present? This he uses. Is it still to come? This he anticipates. He
makes his life long by combining all times into one.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>They lose the day in expectation of the night, and the night in fear
of the dawn.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Reasons for anxiety will never be lacking, whether born of
prosperity or of wretchedness; life pushes on in a succession of
engrossments. We shall always pray for leisure, but never enjoy it.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>knowledge of their disease has caused the death of many.</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240105-seneca_de_brevitate_vitae/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240105-seneca_de_brevitate_vitae/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The myth of artificial intelligence, by Larson</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The relevant point in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erik_J._Larson" title="Wikipedia: Erik J. Larson">Larson</a>'s <a href="https://www.hup.harvard.edu/books/9780674278660" title="The Myth of Artificial Intelligence: Why Computers Can’t Think the Way We Do">book</a> is that advances in AI
shouldn't undermine human intellectual flourishing. We shouldn't hand
over all our thinking to machines. He explores the example of the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_Brain_Project" title="Wikipedia: Human Brain Project">Human Brain Project</a>, arguing convincingly that its "big data"
computational focus was not effective. While I think it isn't quite so
black and white (AI can be a useful tool) I also support human
learning, not just machine learning.</p>
<p>The book doesn't deliver on its subtitle, "Why computers can't think
the way we do." It doesn't even really argue for "can't," but only for
"don't, so far." Like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary_Marcus" title="Wikipedia: Gary Marcus">Marcus</a>, Larson is arguing that we need
something more than deep learning and other extant approaches.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The myth of artificial intelligence is that its arrival is
inevitable, and only a matter of time—that we have already embarked
on the path that will lead to human-level AI, and then
superintelligence. (page 1)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Larson's main argument is that current machine learning doesn't do
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abductive_reasoning" title="Wikipedia: Abductive reasoning">abduction</a>, and it should. This is close to Marcus arguing for
algebraic reasoning. It is even close to me, <a href="/20170429-from_behaviorist_to_constructivist_ai/" title="From Behaviorist to Constructivist AI">arguing</a> for going
from Behaviorist to Constructivist AI.</p>
<p>This book came out before ChatGPT, which is relevant in at least two
ways.</p>
<p>First, it's more possible now to take seriously the idea that neural
generative models might really be, eventually, enough for AGI; this is
roughly what Sutskever seems to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YEUclZdj_Sc" title="Youtube: Why next-token prediction is enough for AGI - Ilya Sutskever (OpenAI Chief Scientist)">say</a>. The human brain is a big mess
that somehow does smart-seeming things. A generative transformer is a
big mess that somehow does smart-seeming things. Maybe they can
achieve equivalent results? This is not a proof, but it might be a
plausibility argument.</p>
<p>Second, Larson spends a good deal of time on examples to show that
models weren't solving some problems very well, when he published.
Many of these examples haven't aged well for his argument, as models
now do better.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For instance (and ironically), Google Translate as of October 2020
still gets Bar-Hillel's 1960s example wrong. Bar-Hillel asked how to
program a machine to translate <em>The box is in the pen</em> correctly.
Here, <em>pen</em> is ambiguous. (page 202)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In December 2023, Google Translate still fails.</p>
<p><img alt="Google Translate" src="google_translate.png"></p>
<p>But ChatGPT <a href="https://chat.openai.com/share/b4dfff5f-413b-466c-af57-c0c4d64e2e7e">succeeds</a>, as far as I can tell.</p>
<p><img alt="ChatGPT translating" src="gpt_translate.png"></p>
<p>ChatGPT similarly has no problem with challenges like "Can a crocodile
run a steeplechase?" (page 196) (It even titles the <a href="https://chat.openai.com/share/97595ce1-03c3-4c99-bc52-942752615dbb">chat</a>,
"Crocodile Steeplechase: Not Feasible.") And where Larson wrote "Their
[AI's] performance on Winograd schemas is not much better than random
guessing," (page 197) his 2016 reference score of <a href="https://cs.nyu.edu/~davise/papers/WinogradSchemas/WS.html">58%</a> has been
improved as of 2022 to <a href="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wsc">90%</a> (or higher).</p>
<p>Whether or not AGI will require explicit architectural support for
abduction (or symbolic reasoning, etc.) the performance limits of
current approaches are not entirely clear.</p>
<p>Really I wish Larson was a better spokesperson for ideas I agree with.
Supporting human learning is a good idea, I think (though Larson
unfortunately takes even this in strange hero-oriented directions).
Larson doesn't really address at all the point that LeCun sometimes
foregrounds, that current AI is hugely data-inefficient (it requires
tons of data) which could actually point to future directions for AI.
I can't endorse this book.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Data science (the application of AI to “big data”) is at best a
prosthetic for human ingenuity, which if used correctly can help us
deal with our modern “data deluge.” (page 4)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Somewhat routinely, Larson defines things strangely. Data science is
not the application of AI to “big data,” and foundational
misalignments like this make it hard for Larson to land arguments.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The Turing test is actually very difficult—no computer has ever
passed it. (page 10)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There are plenty of articles claiming that this or that passed the
Turing test, but it seems that
<a href="https://isturingtestpassed.github.io/">isturingtestpassed.github.io</a>
is correct: the answer is still no.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Turing's great genius, and his great error, was in thinking that
human intelligence reduces to problem-solving. (page 23)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There's a bunch of unclear language here. How is problem-solving
defined? What is excluded from that definition? What even is
intuition?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Turing and colleagues called it the “weight of evidence,” borrowing
a term coined by the American scientist and logician C. S. Peirce
(who is prominently featured in Part Two of this book). (page 24)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The "it" here has no clear referent, but as it happens I've been
interested in <a href="/20210917-weight_of_evidence_is_logistic_coefficients/" title="Weight of Evidence is logistic coefficients">weight of evidence</a> before, and it seems that this is
the same thing! How neat, to know it traces to Turing. One interesting
work of interpretation is Gillies' short <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/688010">paper</a>, "The Turing-Good
Weight of Evidence Function and Popper's Measure of the Severity of a
Test."</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Japan had invested millions in its high-profile
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fifth_Generation_Computer_Systems" title="Fifth Generation Computer Systems">Fifth Generation project</a> aimed at achieving success in robotics,
and Japan too had failed, rather spectacularly. (page 55)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At a quick search, Larson seems to be the only person saying the Fifth
Generation project was principally interested in robotics.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Here, it's best to be clear: equating a mind with a computer is not
scientific, it's philosophical. (page 69)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Dan Gardner's excellent book <em>Future Babble</em> documents the success
rate of predictions in realms from history and geopolitics to the
sciences. He found that theorists—experts with big visions of the
future based on a particular theory they endorse—tend to make worse
predictions than pragmatic people, who see the world as complicated
and lacking a clear fit with any single theory. (page 69)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Werner Heisenberg discovered his uncertainty principle by working
out the consequences of the new physics of quanta. The principle
states that it is impossible to isolate the position and the
momentum of a subatomic particle simultaneously. This places
fundamental limits on our ability to predict the individual
movements of particles at the subatomic realm (because “seeing” the
position of a particle requires impinging it with a photon, which
also has the effect of knocking it off course). (page 72)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But it isn't "because" of that; this is a common misconception. Even
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncertainty_principle" title="Uncertainty principle">wikipedia</a> does better:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Historically, the uncertainty principle has been confused with a
related effect in physics, called the observer effect, which notes
that measurements of certain systems cannot be made without
affecting the system, that is, without changing something in a
system. Heisenberg used such an observer effect at the quantum level
(see below) as a physical "explanation" of quantum uncertainty. It
has since become clearer, however, that the uncertainty principle is
inherent in the properties of all wave-like systems, and that it
arises in quantum mechanics simply due to the matter wave nature of
all quantum objects.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Statistical AI ends up with a long-tail problem, where common
patterns (in the fat head of a distribution curve) are easy, but
rare ones (in the long tail) are hard. (page 128)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is true, and something of a missed opportunity to better tie into
the overall argument.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Calling such systems <em>learners</em> is ironic, because the meaning of
the word <em>learn</em> for humans essentially involves escaping narrow
performances to gain more general understanding of things in the
world. (page 141)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There's a good point in here somewhere on function approximation vs.
model-building; on interpolation vs. extrapolation.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Big data is an inevitable consequence of Moore's law: as computers
become more powerful, statistical techniques like machine learning
become better, and new business models emerge—all from data and its
analysis. (page 144)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I pulled this out just as an example of the kind of muddy reasoning
and poor use of language found throughout the book. This is the kind
of sort-of-but-are-you-sure-you-want-to-say-it-that-way output that
I'd expect from a language model.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Much inference in the real world is defeasible, that is, proven
wrong or incomplete by subsequent observation or learning (say, by
reading a book). (page 163)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Work on so-called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-monotonic_logic" title="Non-monotonic logic">non-monotonic</a> reasoning peaked in the 1980s
and 1990s, but has since been largely abandoned, in large part
because the extensions of deduction to make it more flexible for
language understanding work only on “toy” examples that aren't
useful in the real world. (page 167)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Many of the same researchers who worked on extending deduction in AI
to make it defeasible also worked out deductive-based approaches to
abduction in the 1980s and 1990s, notably with
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abductive_logic_programming" title="Abductive logic programming">abductive logic programming</a> (ALP). (page 168)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Page 172 has a breakdown like this:</p>
<ul>
<li>Deduction: A→B; A ∴ B</li>
<li>Induction: A; B ∴ A→B</li>
<li>Abduction: A→B; B ∴ A</li>
</ul>
<p>Nice to see compactly this way, I think...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The strategy of exposing supervised learning systems to foreseeable
exceptions, as is done with ongoing work on driverless cars, is a
Sisyphean undertaking, because exceptions by their very nature
cannot be completely foreseen. (pages 173-174)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(See the selection above from page 128.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>a once-prominent field in AI known as
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knowledge_representation_and_reasoning" title="Knowledge representation and reasoning">knowledge representation and reasoning</a> (KR&amp;R) (page 175)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>technically, entailment is stronger than material implication (page
176)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Poking around online, there are lots of people making claims about the
difference here, but it doesn't seem like everyone agrees... It seems
roughly like entailment is more causal, while implication can be
correlative.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>To abduce we must solve the selection problem among competing causes
or factors, and to solve this problem, we must somehow grasp what is
relevant in some situation or other. The problem is that no one has
a clue how to do this. (page 183)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>noetic, or knowledge-based. (page 185)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This does not seem to be the sense in which the word is typically used.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>What people mean is almost never a literal function of what they
word-for-word say. (page 206)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes... Though the world-knowledge bits of the book are the ones that
most fail in the face of LLMs.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cooperative_principle#Grice's_maxims">Grice's Maxims</a> (page 215)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Quantity, Quality, Relation, Manner</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Text_Retrieval_Conference">Text REtrieval Conferences</a> (page 221)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Writing about the experience
[of working on early computing machines] in 1887 in an oddly
prescient paper titled "Logical Machines," in the <em>American Journal
of Psychology,</em> Peirce begins characteristically with cautionary
comment. "In the 'Voyage to Laputa' there is a description of a
machine for evolving science automatically," he writes. "The
intention is to ridicule the Organon of Aristotle and the Organon of
Bacon by showing the absurdity of supposing any 'instrument' can do
the work of the mind." Peirce, the skeptic, no doubt appreciated the
wisdom of Swift's imagination. (page 232)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is <a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/829/829-h/829-h.htm#part03">Gulliver's Travels</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Every one knew how laborious the usual method is of attaining to
arts and sciences; whereas, by his contrivance, the most ignorant
person, at a reasonable charge, and with a little bodily labour,
might write books in philosophy, poetry, politics, laws,
mathematics, and theology, without the least assistance from genius
or study.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is there a better description of ChatGPT than as a contrivance by
which "the most ignorant person, at a reasonable charge, and with a
little bodily labour, might write books in philosophy, poetry,
politics, laws, mathematics, and theology, without the least
assistance from genius or study"?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>He assured me “that this invention had employed all his thoughts
from his youth; that he had emptied the whole vocabulary into his
frame, and made the strictest computation of the general proportion
there is in books between the numbers of particles, nouns, and
verbs, and other parts of speech.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A very early statistical NLP! And with a charming illustration:</p>
<p><img alt="the frame" src="theframe.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>For scientists don't believe in vagaries like the "evolution of
science" except as frosting, as backdrop. They really believe in
scientific genius. They really are all possessed by Prometheus, by
what innovators can dream and achieve. (page 239)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is quite the generalization... Maybe you're not a real scientist
if you don't go in for a Great Man theory of science? Maybe the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ortega_hypothesis">Ortega hypothesis</a> is for the weak?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>principles linking neurons together into circuits and larger
functional units (mesa circuits) (page 250)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't find a lot of support for "mesa circuits" as a term people
use...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>we are actively attempting to cover up a key deficiency—a lack of
flourishing human culture—with rhetoric about the inevitable rise of
machines. (page 277)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The problem of inference, like the problem of consciousness, is
entrenched at the center of ongoing grand mysteries, and is really
presupposed in our understanding of everything else. We should not
be surprised that the undiscovered mind resists technological
answers. It's possible that, as Horgan worried, we're out of ideas.
If so, the myth represents our final, unrecoverable turn away from
human possibility—a darkly comforting fairy tale, a pretense that
out of our ashes something else, something great and alive, must
surely and inevitably arise.</p>
<p>If we're <em>not</em> out of ideas, then we must do the hard and deliberate
work of reinvesting in a culture of invention and human flourishing.
For we will need our own general intelligence to find paths to the
future, and a future better than the past. (pages 280-281)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is interesting material.</p>
<p>I think a lot of "AI isn't as good as people" reduces to how we feel
about consciousness. You can't prove consciousness by behaviors or any
other observable. So do we extend our belief in consciousness to
machines?</p>
<p>On whether we're out of ideas, I like the arguments of <a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/" title="The Beginning of Infinity, by Deutsch">Deutsch</a> and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank_Wilczek" title="Wikipedia: Frank Wilczek">Wilczek</a>, which suggest that we're not.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20231231-myth_of_ai_by_larson/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20231231-myth_of_ai_by_larson/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Social Security is a great deal</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Social Security in its current form pays out, with no volatility, a
perpetual inflation-adjusted annual yield of up to 51% on what
individuals pay in tax. 15% is common, and 5% is the worst you can
get.</p>
<p>I know it's not really an individual investment; younger Americans are
supposed to be supporting older ones and so on. But I had no idea how
good Social Security is for recipients, relative to how much they put
in.</p>
<p>Social Security pays out a percentage of your income. In monthly
terms, it's 90% of up to $1,115/month, then 32% up to $6,721/month,
then 15% up to $13,350/month. These are 2023 dollars and give the
maximum full retirement age monthly payment of $3,792.</p>
<p>Full retirement age for me is 67. If I start collecting Social
Security early, at 62, payments are locked in at 70% of the “full”
value. If instead I delay until 70, payments are 124%.</p>
<p>Social Security is based on inflation-adjusted income over your 35
highest-earning years. (If you're working your 36th year and earning
no more than any other year, this calculation won't apply.)</p>
<p>The last factor we need is the 6.2% tax you pay in to Social Security.
Your employer also separately pays as much, but most people don't
consider that part of their income.</p>
<p>So the best “return” you can get is if you have lifetime earnings so
far under $468,300 and you plan to start collecting Social Security as
late as possible:</p>
<pre><code>0.9 * 1.24 / 35 / 0.062  # 51.4%</code></pre>

<p>The worst non-zero return you can get is if your lifetime Social
Security earnings are already over $2.8M and you plan to collect
Social Security as soon as possible.</p>
<pre><code>0.15 * 0.7 / 35 / 0.062  # 4.8%</code></pre>

<p>A conservative mid-career value is likely about 15%.</p>
<pre><code>0.32 * 1.0 / 35 / 0.062  # 14.7%</code></pre>

<p>Social Security adjusts for inflation, so these are all returns <em>over</em>
inflation. I just can't think of anything that gets returns like this.</p>
<p>You get the same return on your last year's contribution before
collecting, so comparative investments can't really be allowed <em>any</em>
time for compounding. Still, most contributions will sit for some time
before the contributor starts collecting, so a full comparison could
be more complicated and depend on age at contribution etc.</p>
<p>Social Security is less flexible than an investing account. But is
there <em>anything</em> that comes close to delivering what Social Security
does, for someone contributing at 60 who lives to be 90, say?</p>
<hr>
<p>The calculations above may seem opaque. I simplified a little,
dropping things that cancel out. More explicitly:</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">($100 new income this year / 35 years considered)
 * 90% income replacement factor
 * 1.24 late start factor
 = annual Social Security benefit from income
-------------------------------------------------------
($100 new income this year * 6.2% tax = tax paid on income)</code></pre>

<p>I rearranged terms a little, and I'm still leaving out conversion
to/from monthly basis which is just a distraction.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20231202-social_security_is_a_great_deal/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20231202-social_security_is_a_great_deal/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>It must be beautiful, edited by Farmelo</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This is a nice collection of essays about some beautiful equations,
edited by the author of <a href="/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/" title="The Strangest Man, by Farmelo">a biography of Dirac</a>. Not every equation
is fully explained, but there's great history and big-picture
explanation. The authors are frequently major contributors to the
fields.</p>
<ol>
<li>The Planck-Einstein Equation for the Energy of a Quantum: \( E = hf\)</li>
<li>The Logistic Map: \( x_{next} = a x_{initial} (1 - x_{initial}) \)</li>
<li>The Drake Equation: \( N = R^* \cdot f_p \cdot n_e \cdot f_l \cdot f_i \cdot f_c \cdot L \)</li>
<li>\( E = m c^2 \)</li>
<li>The Molina-Rowland Chemical Equations<ul>
<li>\( CFCl_3 \rightarrow CFCl_2 + Cl \)</li>
<li>\( Cl + O_3 \rightarrow ClO + O_2 \)</li>
<li>\( ClO + O \rightarrow Cl + O_2\)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Schrödinger's Wave Equation: \( \hat{H} \psi = E \psi \)</li>
<li>The Dirac Equation: \( \left[ \gamma^\mu \left( i \frac{\partial}{\partial x^\mu} - e A_\mu (x) \right) + m \right] \psi (x) = 0 \)</li>
<li>Evolutionarily Stable Strategy: \( E(S, S) &gt; E(T, S) \)</li>
<li>The Einstein Equation of General Relativity: \( R_{ab} - \frac{1}{2}Rg_{ab} = -8\pi G T_{ab} \)</li>
<li>Shannon's Equations<ul>
<li>\( I = -p \log_2 p \)</li>
<li>\( C = W \log_2 (1 + S/N) \)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The Yang-Mills Equation: \( \partial \mathbf{f}_{μν} / \partial x_ν + 2 \varepsilon (\mathbf{b}_ν \cdot \mathbf{f}_{μν}) + \mathbf{J}_μ = 0 \)</li>
</ol>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It was in large part thanks to this [logistic map] equation, one so
simple that children can study it at school, that scientists in the
1970s came to see that some equations that appear to predict the
future in terms of the past are completely unable to make such
predictions, contrary to what most scientists had thought." (page
xvii)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Maybe children <em>should</em> study it at school, if they're not,
currently...</p>
<p>See also: <a href="/20200714-foundation_trilogy/" title="Asimov's Foundation trilogy">psychohistory</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The [wave-particle] problem's resolution came in the late 1920s,
when physicists developed quantum theory into what became known as
quantum field theory, which made possible a unified description of
radiation and matter." (page 24)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2021/04/09/period-three-implies-chaos/" title="explainer">Period three implies chaos</a> is one of the best paper names of all
time.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Avoiding detailed assumptions about this or that feature of the way
particular objects were built or interacted, Einstein's theory
hardly resembled the work of senior physicists of the time. Instead,
it had an outsider's style—or perhaps a return to an older form of
clarity." (page 75)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The sense of aesthetics that Shcrödinger alludes to here is his
preference for a mathematics that is more familiar and also not as
ugly as Heisenberg's 'transcendental algebra' (or matrices), but
which also permits visualizability of atomic processes." (page 117)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Transcendental algebra?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In the pantheon of twentieth-century physics, Heisenberg is second
only to Einstein." (page 129)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Feel like somebody told me that was <a href="/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/" title="The Strangest Man, by Farmelo">Dirac</a>...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As the physicist who did more to delve into the foundations of
quantum theory than anyone else since Bohr, Einstein and Heisenberg,
John Bell, once put it, 'for all practical purposes' quantum
mechanics works well. He forcefully reminded us, however, that we
still do not fully understand the Schrödinger equation." (page 131)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The citation here is <a href="https://www.informationphilosopher.com/solutions/scientists/bell/Against_Measurement.pdf">Against 'measurement'</a>, which is straight FIRE.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Is it really possible, by logical processing or calculation, to
arrive at essentially new insights—to get out more than you put in?</p>
<p>"This question is especially timely today, since it lies at the
heart of debates regarding the nature of machine
intelligence—whether it may develop into a species of mind on a par
with human intelligence, or even its eventual superior." (pages
155-156)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This was in <em>2002.</em></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"They [Dirac, Maxwell, Einstein] proceed by <em>experimental logic.</em>
That concept is an oxymoron only on the surface. In experimental
logic, one formulates hypotheses in equations, and experiments with
those equations. That is, one tries to improve the equations from
the point of view of beauty and consistency, and then checks whether
the 'improved' equations elucidate some feature of nature.
Mathematicians recognize the technique of 'proof by contradiction':
to prove <em>A,</em> you assume the opposite of <em>A,</em> and reach a
contradiction. Experimental logic is 'validation by fruitfulness':
to validate <em>A,</em> assume it, and show that it leads to fruitful
consequences. Relative to routine deductive logic, experimental
logic abides by the Jesuit credo: 'It is more blessed to ask
forgiveness than permission.'" (page 159)</p>
<p>"Creative mathematics and physics rely not on perfect logic, but
rather on an experimental logic. Experimental logic involves
noticing patterns, playing with them, making assumptions to explain
them, and—especially—recognizing beauty."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Abduction? With guess-and-check? And aesthetics?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As the anthropologists Robert Boyd and Peter Richerson once
remarked, ‘To replace a world you do not understand by a model of
the world you do not understand is no advance.’" (page 165)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There are questions that are too hard to think about without the
aid of mathematics." (page 179)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In fact, in the four dimensions of space-time, there are <em>twenty</em>
independent components to the curvature, and these can be collected
together to describe a mathematical entity referred to as the
'Rieman curvature tensor'. (page 191)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In 1918, the young German mathematician Emmy Noether discovered a
deeply fundamental relationship between symmetry and the
conservation of physical quantities, such as electric charge. She
found that for every conserved quantity there is a related
symmetry—and vice versa." (page 236)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In an essay on 'Beauty and theoretical physics,' Yang quotes
Heisenberg as saying in 1973, 'We will have to abandon the
philosophy of Democritus and the concept of elementary particles. We
should accept instead the concept of fundamental symmetries.'" (page
251)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Dirac has a paper called "Pretty mathematics."</p>
<hr>
<p>Something about the Einstein summation convention...</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20231119-it_must_be_beautiful/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20231119-it_must_be_beautiful/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fireside Chat / Pro Tips (with Codecademy)</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>My <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/minhzy/" title="Jonathan (Minhzy) Truong">friend</a> at Codecademy invited me to do a sort of AMA on my
career working with data, in an event that was variously promoted as a
“<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7108029659493138432/" title="We’re hosting a fireside chat with Meta Data Scientist Aaron Schumacher next Tuesday.">fireside chat</a>” and “<a href="https://community.codecademy.com/events/details/codecademy-official-community-events-presents-pro-tips-with-aaron-schumacher-meta/" title="Pro Tips with Aaron Schumacher, Meta">pro tips</a>.”</p>
<ul>
<li>I made some <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/19qy_rOaPYbEgF5ykJeA39a2XjgPVE4Tp2a_YvSc9hXQ/edit" title="Fireside Chat / Pro Tips">slides</a> to introduce myself and some recommendations.</li>
<li>It's <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8PCL5ogz7xM&amp;ab_channel=Codecademy" title="Pro Tips with Aaron Schumacher, Meta">on YouTube</a>!</li>
</ul>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230919-fireside_chat_pro_tips/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230919-fireside_chat_pro_tips/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Strangest Man, by Farmelo</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I think I like this Graham Farmelo, and I like his book about Dirac.
Farmelo is interested in connections between mathematics and physics,
and aesthetics in both. I think I'll read some of his other books too.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>[Charlie] Broad was a wonderfully idiosyncratic lecturer. He always
appeared with a carefully prepared script, and he read every
sentence twice, except for the jokes, which he delivered three
times. (page 39)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In the space-time of the special theory of relativity, things are
different: the square of the distance between two points in
space-time is equal to the sum of the squares of the spatial lengths
<em>minus</em> the square of the time. (page 42)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is it fair to say that a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spacetime#Spacetime_interval">spacetime interval</a> <em>is</em> “the square of
the distance between two points in space-time”? Maybe?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><em>A System of Logic,</em> published in 1843, is a plain-spoken if
laborious account of how empiricism can shape every aspect of human
life. The book features Mill's agenda for science, which assumes
that there is an underlying ‘uniformity of nature’. The aim of
scientists should be to explain more and more observations in terms
of fewer and fewer laws, every one of them grounded in experience
and induced from it. (page 43)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mill%27s_Methods">Mill's Methods</a>!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>All his life, Dirac had the same attitude to the written word as his
contemporary George Orwell: ‘Good prose is like a window pane.’
(page 75)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Dirac knew that it was impossible to deduce the equation from first
principles and that he would find it only through a happy guess.
(page 141)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See also Polya on guessing...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>‘Don't despise philosophers too much,’ she had counselled him after
one of his visits, ‘a great deal that they say may be useless, but
they are after something which matters.’ Mrs Whitehead had been on
the receiving end of one of Dirac's tirades against the only
academic discipline he openly disdained. One of his <em>bêtes noire</em>
was teh internationally admired Trinity College philosopher Ludwig
Wittgenstein, regarded by many as one of the cleverest academics in
Cambridge. Several decades later, Dirac remarked that he was an
‘Awful fellow. Never stopped talking.’ (page 220)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>When Dirac focuses on the transcience of life, he is driven to an
important moral conclusion: ‘A termination of one's life is
necessary in the scheme of things <u>to provide a logical reason for
unselfishness</u>. [...] The fact that there is an end to one's life
compels one to take an interest in things that will continue to live
after one is dead.’ (page 221)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think one could argue exactly the opposite...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In my case this article of faith is that the human race will
continue to live for ever and will develop and progress <u>without
limit</u>. This is an assumption that I must make for my peace of
mind. Living is worthwhile if one can contribute in some small way
to the endless chain of progress. (quoting Dirac, page 221)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See also: <a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/">The Beginning of Infinity</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Anderson later remarked that any experimenter who took the theory
[Dirac's hole theory] at face value and who was working in a
well-equipped laboratory ‘could have discovered the positron in a
single afternoon’ using radioactive soures. (page 225)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This kind of thing is fascinating... What's still out there, that
could be seen in an afternoon, if we knew what to look for?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>He [Dirac] rarely spoke about science but did once exchange a few
words with her about mathematics: she thought it was a human
invention, while Dirac maintained that it had ‘always existed’ and
had been ‘discovered’ by humans. (page 251)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>She [Manci] would probably not have welcomed Dirac's view that his
religion was simply that ‘the world has to improve’. (page 257)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>For the physicists who were interested, a treat was in store:
[at the 1945-12-06 lecture] they heard Dirac coin two of the
best-known technical terms that he introduced: ‘fermions’, quantum
particles that obey the laws that he and Fermi had set out in 1926,
and ‘bosons’, the other type of quantum particles, which obey laws
set out by Einstein and the Indian theoretician Stayendra Bose.
(page 331)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Dirac made the theme of his 1980 lecture ‘The Engineer and the
Physicist’: ‘The main problem of the engineer is to decide which
approximations to make.’ Good engineers make wise choices, often
based on physical intuition, about the mathematical terms they can
ignore in their equations: ‘The terms neglected must be small and
their neglect must not have a big influence on the result. He must
not neglect terms that are not small.’ (page 337)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>He brought the same attention to detail to Dostoevsky's <em>Crime and
Punishment,</em> which he thought was ‘nice’, though he pointed out that
‘In one of the chapters the author makes a mistake: he describes the
sun as rising twice on the same day.’ (page 339)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is there such a mistake???</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Bertrand Russell's fictional don, Professor Driuzdustades (page 347)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Russell has fiction!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>When you ask what are electrons and protons I ought to answer that
this question is not a profitable one to ask and does not really
have a meaning. The important thing about electrons and protons is
not what they are but how they behave — how they move. I can
describe the situation by comparing it to the game of chess. In
chess, we have various chessmen, kings, knights, pawns and so on. If
you ask what a chessman is, the answer would be [that] it is a piece
of wood, or a piece of ivory, or perhaps just a sign written on
paper, [or anything whatever]. It does not matter. Each chessman has
a characteristic way of moving and this is all that matters about
it. The whole game of chess follows from this way of moving the
various chessmen [...] (page 354, quoting Dirac)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>PHYSICAL LAWS SHOULD HAVE MATHEMATICAL BEAUTY. (page 359, quoting
Dirac's blackboard writing)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Thought is not a monolith</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Any particular argument can in principle be formalized in a particular
system of assumptions and inference rules, but flexibility in level of
formality and use of different systems for different arguments is both
practical and inevitable.</p>
<p>The plurality of systems of thought is particularly transparent in
mathematics, where for example to know whether a statement of geometry
is correct one must first ask which system of geometry is determining
correctness. In one system the interior angles of a triangle always
add to two right angles, but in another this is not the case.
Conflicting results do not imply cognitive dissonance when each is
correct in its respective system. The ability to choose among systems
is a great power.</p>
<p>Mathematical formal systems are in a sense complete articulations, but
they are also generally quite verbose and not necessarily easily
understood. In another sense, by their very self-completeness formal
systems close themselves off from meaning beyond their symbols,
requiring something beyond themselves and in that sense being
incomplete.</p>
<p>In practice, it is rare to completely formalize an argument. Ideally,
the nearest acceptable assumptions and clearest steps of reasoning are
described clearly and expediently. Often, assumptions and reasoning
are just implied, or even elided. There may be more or less
uncertainty in excavating the underlying argument.</p>
<p>Natural language is an imperfect tool. Spoken, written, or purely in
thought, a statement of natural language is a phenomon not purely tied
to any particular semantics. As in the Shannon–Weaver model of
communication, language is a signal, and it is the only part of the
system that we have meaningfully direct access to. Everyone speaks
their own constantly-evolving language. Much of philosophy can be seen
as postcards from Sisyphus visiting the ruins of Babel.</p>
<p>Meaning is built based on language, but the meaning cannot be directly
inspected. Reading my own notes, I may find that now they mean nothing
to me, or I may otherwise understand them differently from what I was
understanding as I wrote them. It isn't clear that it is possible to
understand a statement twice in exactly the same way. In the case of
communication with others, the best we can hope for is roughly
compatible understandings.</p>
<p>In stimulating meanings, even if not always perfectly identical,
natural language is a powerful tool. By relying on shared
understandings, which can be built, natural language can be very
efficient and effective. Very often, it is the best option. Care
should be taken to avoid the extremes of its weaknesses.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230723-thought_is_not_a_monolith/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230723-thought_is_not_a_monolith/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Assume some proved things cannot be disproved</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Given a valid proof in a system of assumptions and inference rules,
there is no sure way to know that there isn't also a contradictory
proof, except by assumption outside the system.</p>
<p>Some systems allow a proof of every statement. For example, take a
system where <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principle_of_explosion" title="Principle of explosion, ex falso quodlibet">anything follows from a contradiction</a>, as is common,
and also assume a contradiction.</p>
<p>Systems that prove everything are not honest. In such systems, you can
prove that the system is consistent. You can prove the law of
non-contradiction, and that the system contains no contradictions.
Seeing such a proof does not establish that an opposite proof doesn't
exist. The situation is akin to the futile exercise of trying to
determine whether a person is a liar by asking them.</p>
<p>The situation is also bad even if attempting to show for just one
proved statement that there isn't a proof of its negation. Socrates
presents argument 1, demonstrating conclusion A. Socrates then
presents argument 2, demonstrating conclusion B, which is that there
is no argument for the negation of A. Socrates then presents argument
3, demonstrating conclusion C, which is that there is no argument for
the negation of B. And so on, forever, for every initial conclusion A.</p>
<p>A proof of consistency cannot be convincing, whether it be for a
system overall or even for a single statement in the system (that for
a specific proof, there isn't a proof for the opposite conclusion).</p>
<p>Stepping up a level, to a meta-system where the consistency of the
original system can be proved, does not solve the problem, because the
meta-system hasn't itself been shown to be consistent.</p>
<p>Gödel's second incompleteness theorem is a special case of this
phenomenon. It shows that for formal systems with certain properties,
they can't prove that they are consistent.</p>
<p>Introducing the law of non-contradiction as an axiom, or assuming that
the system contains no contradictions, does not solve the problem.
Such a claim made within the system can always coexist with its
negation, if it is present.</p>
<p>If a system proves both a statement and its negation, there is no
ambiguity. If a system proves a statement but its negation is not
proved, it is necessary to assume that there is no such proof.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230716-assume_some_proved_things_cannot_be_disproved/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230716-assume_some_proved_things_cannot_be_disproved/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Room, by Karlsson</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Karlsson's <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/235739/the-room-by-jonas-karlsson/" title="The Room: A Novel, by Jonas Karlsson">Room</a> is set in a kind of office, but more than that
it's a novel (almost a long parable) about epistemology, how people
believe in conspiracy theories, and the tragedy of modern retreats
from reality. By early reviews, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corner_Office_(film)" title="Corner Office (film)">film version</a> isn't as good.</p>
<p>The narrator, Björn, seems to have (at least) an autism spectrum
disorder that brings to mind
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Curious_Incident_of_the_Dog_in_the_Night-Time">The Curious Incident of the Dog in the Night-Time</a>. He also has
tons of self-importance, zero self-awareness, and a disdain for women
that all make him seem like an easy Proud Boys recruit. He describes
himself as working at an office for a non-corporate Authority but it's
easy to wonder whether it isn't really a care facility for people with
psychological difficulties. (And aren't we all limited in our ability
to know truth?)</p>
<p>Björn believes in, and apparently experiences, a room that none of his
colleagues at the office can see. When Björn finds that by measurement
there couldn't be a room where he thinks there is one, he concludes
that some trick must be at work as part of a conspiracy amongst the
office. A medical professional confesses to thinking that Björn is
just pretending to believe in the room—and who hasn't thought
similarly of flat-earthers?</p>
<p>After a confrontation at work and a tearful breakdown at home, Björn
changes. He describes himself having success at work. Is this real, or
has he inhabited his fantasies from earlier? Is he somehow really
successful, and the point is that people with strange views can
contribute to society? I lean toward the interpretation that the
narrator has become even less reliable.</p>
<p>As Björn becomes less and less connected with reality, his false sense
of power grows and he demands more and more, until he collides with
some aspects of office reality that he can't reinterpret. His
persecution complex runs wild and he eventually disappears completely
into his alternate reality. His isolation, once partial, is total.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Someone had made a snowman in the courtyard below my window, but it
wasn’t very good at all. (page 48)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He doesn't understand context, doesn't think there's any purpose or
measure other than his own.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Stupid people don’t always know that they’re stupid. They might be
aware that something is wrong, they might notice that things don’t
usually turn out the way they imagined, but very few of them think
it’s because of them. That they’re the root of their own problems,
so to speak. And that sort of thing can be very difficult to
explain. (page 49)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Irony via anosognosia.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>I tried to remember when I had last slept.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Almost a Tyler Durden vibe?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Since the time we agreed to have you working here, things have
evidently changed dramatically. I still thought you might be able to
cope with the relatively simple tasks you were given. Sorting,
archiving, et cetera. We knew you were a complex character, but no
one mentioned anything about you being delusional.” (page 88, Karl
the manager speaking)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Jan,” he said. “Thanks, I noticed,” I said, pointing at the name
tag. (page 91)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is one of at least two times that Björn is oblivious of his turn
to introduce himself.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“I’d say that you’re putting it on.” (page 98)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is the frustrated final comment from the medical assessor who
decides Björn doesn't need anything from a psychiatrist.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“I think you maximize your potential better if you imagine a
customer at the other end.” (page 112)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Björn is thinking of himself as a business, focused on performance and
success in terms of exchange. This may be partly his autistic bent,
but also partly a critique of some modern attitudes toward work and
success. “You are a brand” etc.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“How’s anyone supposed to know if he’s there or not? This way we can
never be sure.” (page 118)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is someone asking how they can tell, if Björn is acting as if
he's believing in the room, they can tell whether he's actually
believing in the room or just acting that way.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>On the way home I felt I was being watched by a whole load of
people. I thought everyone was looking at me. I had to stand at the
front of the aisle on the bus because all the seats were taken, so
anyone who felt like it could stare at me as much as they wanted. A
small child with a pacifier in her mouth stared me right in the eyes
for ages. In the end I couldn’t help saying: “Do we know each
other?” I got no answer. The little girl just went on sucking the
pacifier. Her mother gave me a disapproving stare. (page 119)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>On the radio, an actor was reading a novella he’d written himself.
The story included a number, sixty-nine. The actor was claiming that
it became ninety-six if you turned it round, which is obviously a
total lie, and I suddenly felt how lonely it is, constantly finding
yourself the only person who can see the truth in this gullible
world. (page 120)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Perhaps we could agree on the formulation ‘the room does not exist
for everyone’?” (page 168)</p>
<p>“Either there is a room there, or there isn’t,” Ann said. “It’s not
quite that simple,” Karl said. (page 169)</p>
<p>“Can’t we say that the room exists a little bit?” (page 171)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Some fun epistemology talk... I can't help but wonder whether Karl
(the manager) is supposed to bring to mind Karl Popper.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“In some ways it’s such a grandiose and detailed project,” I went
on, “and so ingeniously malicious that I can’t help being rather
fascinated.” (page 174)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Björn is referring to the conspiracy of everyone else pretending there
isn't a room.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The DG says that on this, the fourth floor, between the lift and
the three toilets… there is absolutely no other space.” (page 180)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That's Karl the manager speaking, and the DG is the Director General,
who is at least the local "authority" of The Authority.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>This was really just a classic ruling-class tactic, wasn’t it?
Making someone think they were mentally ill? (page 184)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Björn continues to think everybody's gaslighting him.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>I closed my eyes, took a deep breath, and walked into the wall. The
wall closed around me, like yogurt around a spoon. (page 185)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is right at the end; Björn's final hiding place, free from the
complexity of other people and the rest of the real world, "No angles
or corners for dirt to get into and hide." His retreat from reality is
complete.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230715-the_room_by_karlsson/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230715-the_room_by_karlsson/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Assume the ability to discern argument validity</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>To make any progress in reasoning requires assuming the ability to
correctly determine whether arguments are valid given their inference
rules. This is both a mechanical and fundamental process.</p>
<p>Validity is the correctness of the form of an argument, assuming its
inference rules, regardless of the truth of its assumptions. This is a
valid argument:</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">Assumption: If Socrates drinks hemlock, then Socrates will die.
Assumption: Socrates drinks hemlock.
Inference rule: If P implies Q, and P is true, then Q. (Modus Ponens)
Conclusion: Socrates will die.</code></pre>

<p>Any other conclusion from the inference rule and assumptions here is
invalid, a non sequitur. (No other inference rules are included in the
example, not even the law of identity.)</p>
<p>When assumptions and inference rules are all stated clearly, and
especially when every step of multi-step arguments are laid out, it
appears to be a mechanical process to verify whether an argument is
valid. But it is possible to doubt that it can be done correctly, and
impossible to prove that it can, so the ability must be assumed.</p>
<p>As Descartes <a href="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Meditations_on_First_Philosophy/Meditation_I" title="Meditations on First Philosophy by René Descartes">asks</a> in connection with his demon, “how do I know
that I am not also deceived each time I add together two and three?”
This is hard to imagine, but that is by construction. Perhaps the
demon causes Descartes to conclude from the example above that
Socrates is in France, and completely believe that this follows from
the inference rule and assumptions given. He believes his argument is
valid, but he is wrong, and he is incapable of determining this,
totally anosognostic, unaware of his condition.</p>
<p>The ability to identify whether an argument is valid cannot be proved,
because any proof offered would need to be assumed valid. Any attempt
at a proof begs the question. To assume the validity of just a
specific proof of the ability to determine validity of other proofs
might be possible, but the validity assumption would then be
simultaneous with others needed for that proof, which introduces
additional restrictions but unclear benefit.</p>
<p>Arguments are not always stated sufficiently clearly and completely as
to make confirming validity easy, but this is fundamentally a
challenge in understanding the argument. In principle any argument can
be expressed clearly and completely.</p>
<p>The assumption here is that it is possible to identify valid arguments
that really are valid, not that there will never be an accidental,
correctible mistake. The assumption is that when there aren't any
mistakes, the claim that an argument is valid is meaningful.</p>
<p>So while verifying the validity of an argument can be a mechanical
process, the assumption here really is fundamental. The assumption is
first that reasoning can be, in some deep sense, really truly valid,
that this is possible, and second that it is possible to know whether
a given argument has this property.</p>
<p>Validity is tautological but universal truth. If the assumptions and
the inference rules, then the conclusions. This is the first and
deepest sense of correctness.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230714-assume_ability_to_discern_argument_validity/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230714-assume_ability_to_discern_argument_validity/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Progress beyond radical skepticism</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Radical skepticism claims that nothing is knowable, but such a claim
is not itself knowable. The solution is to remove all claims, and then
choose to build.</p>
<p>The traditional argument for radical skepticism is from doubt. For any
claim, an inconsistent alternative can be introduced that cannot be
disproved, leaving the original claim less than perfectly justified.
In this way, all knowledge can be removed, meaning made uncertain.</p>
<p>An analytic argument for radical skepticism is that if all knowledge
requires sufficient reason, and arguments are neither circular nor
infinite, there can be no knowledge because there is no “first”
knowledge, which would be knowledge without sufficient reason. In this
way, no knowledge can be built up.</p>
<p>The arguments for radical skepticism are good, but it is difficult to
then state exactly what the claim of radical skepticism is.</p>
<p>The so-called Socratic paradox is the statement that “I know that I
know nothing.” Read strictly, this is not a paradox, but simply a
false statement, regardless of whether Socrates knows anything.</p>
<p>If Socrates says instead “I know that I know nothing, including this,”
he has contradicted himself, as he says both that he knows and he
doesn't know. A contradiction cannot constitute knowledge, and
variants like “I am uncertain about everything, including this,” sound
less problematic only superficially.</p>
<p>If Socrates says, “I know that I know nothing, other than this
knowledge of my limitation,“ he is still incorrect. Either he knows
some reason to hold this belief, in which case he knows more than he
says, or he knows without reason, which is not knowledge but
assumption.</p>
<p>The trouble is that if we manage to know anything, then radical
skepticism is falsified. The radical skepticism that makes a claim is
not the true radical skepticism.</p>
<p>The most defensible expression of radical skepticism is silence, and
in this form it is correct. Nothing comes from nothing, and anything
can be doubted.</p>
<p>True radical skepticism is in a sense pre-rational. Even to reason
about radical skepticism requires assuming the ability to reason. Any
thought is outside the pure domain of radical skepticism.</p>
<p>From the primordial void of radical skepticism, thought can grow. At
every stage of this evolution, what is known is contingent on what
developed prior. Every addition is a choice.</p>
<p>Socrates could say, “I assume that I know nothing other than this one
assumption,” but this would be a dead end.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230712-progress_beyond_radical_skepticism/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230712-progress_beyond_radical_skepticism/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Russell's History of Western Philosophy</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Russell attempts to understand all of western social, political, and
philosophical history in one charming and often funny <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_History_of_Western_Philosophy">book</a>. His
attitude is frequently as expressed on page 760: “This may seem odd,
but that is not my fault.” Russell is a fine guide through the weird
world of human thought, highlighting important developments and gaps.</p>
<p>Summarizing several levels further, here are nine big names in western
philosophy:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pythagoras (570–495) mathematical reasoning (also much silliness)</li>
<li>Socrates (470–399) Socratic method (questioning), fixation on definitions</li>
<li>Plato (428–348) Realm of Ideals (and other silliness)</li>
<li>Aristotle (384–322) syllogisms (and fairly bad science)</li>
<li>Descartes (1596–1650) cogito (“I think, therefore I am.”)</li>
<li>Locke (1632–1704) empiricism, social contract</li>
<li>Hume (1711–1776) scepticism re: induction, causation</li>
<li>Kant (1724–1804) Critique of Pure Reason (synthetic a priori), categorical imperative</li>
<li>Hegel (1770–1831) dialectic (thesis/antithesis/synthesis; really from Fichte)</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>To teach how to live without certainty, and yet without being
paralyzed by hesitation, is perhaps the chief thing that philosophy,
in our age, can still do for those who study it. (page xiv)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Modern philosophy begins with Descartes, whose fundamental certainty
is the existence of himself and his thoughts, from which the
external world is to be inferred. This was only the first stage in a
development, through Berkeley and Kant, to Fichte, for whom
everything is only an emanation of the ego. This was insanity, and,
from this extreme, philosophy has been attempting, ever since, to
escape into the world of every-day common sense. (page xxi)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Social cohesion is a necessity, and mankind has never yet succeeded
in enforcing cohesion by merely rational arguments. (page xxiii)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The gentleman is to be defined as one of a society of equals who
live on slave labour, or at any rate upon the labour of men whose
inferiority is unquestioned.</p>
<p>...</p>
<p>Whatever may be thought of a social system which tolerates slavery,
it is to gentlemen in the above sense that we owe pure mathematics.
(page 34)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>On pages 35-36 Russell notes the Pythagorean schism between arithmetic
and geometry, which led to much confusion.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The influence of geometry upon philosophy and scientific method has
been profound. Geometry, as established by the Greeks, starts with
axioms which are (or are deemed to be) self-evident, and proceeds,
by deductive reasoning, to arrive at theorems that are very far from
self-evident. The axioms and theorems are held to be true of actual
space, which is something given in experience. It thus appeared to
be possible to discover things about the actual world by first
noticing what is self-evident and then using deduction. This view
influenced Plato and Kant, and most of the intermediate
philosophers. When the Declaration of Independence says “we hold
these truths to be self-evident,” it is modeling itself on Euclid.
The eighteenth-century doctrine of natural rights is a search for
Euclidean axioms in politics. The form of Newton's <em>Principia,</em> in
spite of its admittedly empirical material, is entirely dominated by
Euclid. Theology, in its exact scholastic forms, takes its style
from the same source. Personal religion is derived from ecstasy,
theology from mathematics, and both are to be found in Pythagoras.
(pages 36-37)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The certain truth there is no man who knows, nor ever shall be,
about the gods and all the things whereof I speak. Yea, even if a
man should chance to say something utterly right, still he himself
knows it not—there is nowhere anything but guessing.” (page 40,
quoting Xenophanes from Bevan, 1913)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The search for something permanent is one of the deepest instincts
leading men to philosophy. (page 45)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>One of the main ambitions of philosophers has been to revive hopes
that science seemed to have killed. (page 47)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... the ethical and religious preoccupations which, passing from the
Pythagoreans to Socrates and from Socrates to Plato, brought an
obscurantist bias into Greek philosophy. (page 63)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Causation must start from something, and wherever it starts no cause
can be assigned for the initial datum. The world may be attributed
to a Creator, but even then the Creator Himself is unaccounted for.
(page 66)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>When we ask “why?” concerning an event, we may mean either of two
things. We may mean: “What purpose did this event serve?” or we may
mean: “What earlier circumstances caused this event?” The answer to
the former question is a teleological explanation, or an explanation
by final causes; the answer to the latter question is a mechanistic
explanation. I do not see how it could have been known in advance
which of these two questions science ought to ask, or whether it
ought to ask both. But experience has shown that the mechanistic
question leads to scientific knowledge, while the teleological
question does not. The atomists asksed the mechanistic question, and
gave a mechanistic answer. Their successors, until the Renaissance,
were more interested in the teleological question, and thus led
science up a blind alley. (page 67)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Plato is always concerned to advocate views that will make people
what he thinks virtuous; he is hardly ever intellectually honest,
because he allows himself to judge doctrines by their social
consequences. Even about this, he is not honest; he pretends to
follow the argument and to be judging by purely theoretical
standards, when in fact he is twisting the discussion so as to lead
to a virtuous result. He introduced this vice into philosophy, where
it has persisted ever since. It was probably largely hostility to
the Sophists that gave this character to his dialogues. One of the
defects of all philosophers since Plato is that their inquiries into
ethics proceed on the assumption that they already know the
conclusions to be reached. (page 79)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>A stupid man's report of what a clever man says is never accurate,
because he unconsciously translates what he hears into something
that he can understand. (page 83)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The earliest of the Platonic dialogues, which are generally supposed
to be the most Socratic, are mainly occupied with the search for
definitions of ethical terms. The <em>Charmides</em> is concerned with the
definition of temperance or moderation; the <em>Lysis</em> with friendship;
the <em>Laches</em> with courage. In all of these, no conclusion is arrived
at, but Socrates makes it clear that he thinks it important to
examine such questions. The Platonic Socrates consistently maintains
that he knows nothing, and is only wiser than others in knowing that
he knows nothing; but he does not think knowledge unobtainable. On
the contrary, he thinks the search for knowledge of the utmost
importance. He maintains that no man sins wittingly, and therefore
only knowledge is needed to make all men perfectly virtuous.</p>
<p>The close connection between virtue and knowledge is characteristic
of Socrates and Plato. To some degree, it exists in all Greek
thought, as opposed to that of Christianity. In Christian ethics, a
pure heart is the essential, and is at least as likely to be found
among the ignorant as among the learned. This difference between
Greek and Christian ethics has persisted down to the present day.
(pages 91-92)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It has always been correct to praise Plato, but not to understand
him. This is the common fate of great men. (page 105)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It seems to us unwise to have insisted on teaching geometry to the
younger Dionysius, tyrant of Syracuse, in order to make him a good
king, but from Plato's point of view it was essential. He was
sufficiently Pythagorean to think that without mathematics no true
wisdom is possible. This view implies oligarchy.</p>
<p>... Plato, in common with most Greek philosophers, took the view
that leisure is essential to wisdom, which will therefore not be
found among those who have to work for their living, but only among
those who have independent means, or who are relieved by the state
from anxieties as to their subsistence. This point of view is
essentially aristocratic. (page 106)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It might be suggested that men could be given political wisdom by a
suitable training. But the question would arise: what is a suitable
training? And this would turn out to be a party question.</p>
<p>The problem of finding a collection of “wise” men and leaving the
government to them is thus an insoluble one. That is the ultimate
reason for democracy. (page 107)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Although all the rulers are to be philosophers, there are to be no
innovations: a philosopher is to be, for all time, a man who
understands and agrees with Plato. (page 115, on Plato's Utopia)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... the fundamental question of ethics and politics, namely: Is
there any standard of “good” and “bad,” except what the man using
these words desires? (page 117)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... any one who agrees with Thrasymachus will say: “There is no
question of proving or disproving; the only question is whether you
<em>like</em> the kind of State that Plato desires.” ... This is one of the
issues in philosophy that are still open; on each side there are men
who command respect. ... This problem is a difficult one, and I do
not profess to be able to solve it. (page 118)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>We may continue, if we like, to say that numbers are eternal,
immutable, and so on, but we must add that they are logical
fictions. (page 157)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Scepticism, as a doctrine of the schools, was first proclaimed by
Pyrrho, ... (page 233)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The manner in which Arcesilaus taught would have had much to commend
it, if the young men who learnt from him had been able to avoid
being paralysed by it. He maintained no thesis, but would refute any
thesis set up by a pupil. Sometimes he would himself advance two
contradictory propositions on successive occasions, showing how to
argue convincingly in favour of either. ... So great was the
influence of Arcesilaus that the Academy remained sceptical for
about two hundred years. (pages 235-236)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In the middle of this sceptical period, an amusing incident
occurred. Carneades, a worthy successor of Arcesilaus as head of the
Academy, was one of three philosophers sent by Athens on a
diplomatic mission to Rome in the year 156 B.C. He saw no reason why
his ambassadorial dignity should interfere with the main chance, so
he announced a course of lectures in Rome. The young men, who, at
that time, were anxious to ape Greek manners and acquire Greek
culture, flocked to hear him. His first lecture expounded the views
of Aristotle and Plato on justice, and was thoroughly edifying. His
second, however, was concerned in refuting all that he had said in
his first, not with a view of establishing opposite conclusions, but
merely to show that every conclusion is unwarranted. (page 236)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Without answering the arguments of the Sceptics, the ancient world
turned aside from them. (page 239)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Another doctrine of theirs [the Stoics] in theory of knowledge was
more influential, though more questionable. This was their belief in
innate ideas and principles. Greek logic was wholly deductive, and
this raised the question of first premises. First premises had to
be, at least in part, general, and no method existed of proving
them. The Stoics held that there are certain principles, which are
luminously obvious, and are admitted by all men; these could be
made, as in Euclid's <em>Elements,</em> the basis of deduction. Innate
ideas, similarly, could be used as the starting-point of
definitions. This point of view was accepted throughout the Middle
Ages, and even by Descartes. (page 269)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... the most effective men of action are often intellectually
second-rate. (page 381)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Damian was the author of a treatise <em>On Divine Omnipotence,</em> which
maintained that God can do things contrary to the law of
contradiction, and can undo the past. (page 413)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It seems Russell has this one wrong; Damian <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/peter-damian/#GodRestVirg" title="Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy: Peter Damian">didn't say</a> quite that.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In Hume, the empiricist philosophy culminated in a scepticism which
none could refute and none could accept. (page 494)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The ancient world found an end to anarchy in the Roman Empire, but
the Roman Empire was a brute fact, not an idea. The Catholic world
sought an end to anarchy in the Church, which was an idea, but was
never adequately embodied in fact. Neither the ancient nor the
medieval solution was satisfactory—the one because it could not be
idealized, the other because it could not be actualized. The modern
world, at present, seems to be moving towards a solution like that
of antiquity: a social order imposed by force, representing the will
of the powerful rather than the hopes of common men. The problem of
a durable and satisfactory social order can only be solved by
combining the solidity of the Roman Empire with the idealism of
Saint Augustine's City of God. To achieve this a new philosophy will
be needed. (pages 494-495)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The political conditions of the Renaissance favoured individual
development, but were unstable; the instability and the
individualism were closely connected, as in ancient Greece. A stable
social system is necessary, but every stable system hitherto devised
has hampered the development of exceptional artistic or intellectual
merit. How much murder and anarchy are we prepared to endure for the
sake of great achievements such as those of the Renaissance? In the
past, a great deal; in our own time, much less. No solution of this
problem has hitherto been found, although increase of social
organization is making it continually more important. (page 503)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There are some respects in which the concepts of modern theoretical
physics differ from those of the Newtonian system. To begin with,
the conception of “force,” which is prominent in the seventeenth
centurey, has been found to be superfluous. “Force,” in Newton, is
the cause of change of motion, whether in magnitude or direction. To
notion of cause is regarded as important, and force is conceived
imaginatively as the sort of thing that we experience when we push
or pull. For this reason it was considered an objection to
gravitation that it acted at a distance, and Newton himself conceded
that there must be some medium by which is was transmitted.
Gradually it was found that all the equations could be written down
without bringing in forces. What was observable was a certain
relation between acceleration and configuration; to say that this
relationship was brought about by the intermediacy of “force” was to
add nothing to our knowledge. Observation shows that the planets
have at all times an acceleration towards the sun, which varies
inversely as the square of their distance from it. To say that this
is due to the “force” of gravitation is merely verbal, like saying
that opium makes people sleep because it has a dormitive virtue. The
modern physicist, therefore, merely states formulæ which determine
accelerations, and avoids the word “force” altogether. “Force” was
the faint ghost of the vitalist view as to the causes of motions,
and gradually the ghost has been exorcized. (page 539)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>After five years spent in retirement, he [Francis Bacon] died of a
chill caught while experimenting on refrigeration by stuffing a
chicken full of snow. (page 542)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>One of the most famous parts of Bacon's philosophy is his
enumeration of what he calls “idols,” by which he means bad habits
of mind that cause people to fall into error. Of these he enumerates
five kinds. “Idos of the tribe” are those that are inherent in human
nature; he mentions in particular the habit of expecting more order
in natural phenomena than is actually to be found. “Idols of the
cave” are personal prejudices, characteristic of the particular
investigator. “Idols of the market-place” are those that have to do
with the tyranny of words and the difficulty of escaping from their
influence over our minds. “Idols of the theatre” are those that have
to do with received systems of thought; of these, naturally
Aristotle and the scholastics afforded him the most noteworthy
instances. Lastly there are “idols of the schools,” which consist in
thinking that some blind rule (such as the syllogism) can take the
place of judgement in investigation. (page 544)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think this is interesting as compared to modern collections of
logical fallacies, like Almossawi's cute <a href="/20201012-bad_arguments_by_almossawi/">Bad Arguments</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Bacon's inductive method is faulty through insufficient emphasis on
hypothesis. He hoped that mere orderly arrangement of data would
make the right hypothesis obvious, but this is seldom the case. As a
rule, the framing of a hypothesis is the most difficult part of
scientific work, and the part where great ability is indispensable.
So far, no method has been found which would make it possible to
invent hypotheses by rule. Usually some hypothesis is a necessary
preliminary to the collection of facts, since the selection of facts
demands some way of determining relevance. Without something of this
kind, the mere multiplicity of facts is baffling. (pages 544-545)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is related to modern thought around data science, data mining,
etc.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>So long as national States exist and fight each other, only
inefficiency can preserve the human race. (page 557)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is in relation to Hobbes's Leviathan...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Therefore corporeal nature in general, involving such matters as
extension, magnitude, and number, is less easy to question than
beliefs about particular things. Arithmetic and geometry, which are
not concerned with particular things, are therefore more certain
than physics and astronomy; they are true even of dream objects,
which do not differ from real ones as regards number and extension.
Even in regard to arithmetic and geometry, however, doubt is
possible. It may be that God causes me to make mistakes whenever I
try to count the sides of a square or add 2 to 3. Perhaps it is
wrong, even in imagination, to attribute such unkindness to God, but
there might be an evil demon, no less cunning and deceitful than
powerful, employing all his industry in misleading me. If there be
such a demon, it may be that all the things I see are only illusions
of which he makes use as traps for my credulity. (pages 563-564)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>But these considerations have not disposed of the sceptical
arguments which threw doubt on the existence of the external world.
This can only be done by first proving the existence of God. (page
566)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Spinoza (1634-77) is the noblest and most lovable of the great
philosophers. Intellectually, some others have surpassed him, but
ethically he is supreme. (page 569)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>[Arnauld had a negative opinion of some of the ideas Spinoza had
related in letters to Arnauld.] This hostile opinion no doubt led
Leibniz, thenceforth, to adopt a policy of secrecy as to his real
thoughts on philosophical subject. (page 591)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I wonder how often this kind of thing has happened through history.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There is a general belief (which I have never understood) that it is
better to exist than not to exist; on this ground children are
exhorted to be grateful to their parents. (page 594)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“For where is the man that has uncontestable evidence of the truth
of all that he holds, or of the falsehood of all he condemns; or can
say, that he has examined to the bottom all his own or other men's
opinions? The necessity of believing without knowledge, nay, often
upon very slight grounds, in this fleeting state of action and
blindness we are in, should make us more busy and careful to inform
ourselves than to restrain others. ... There is reason to think,
that if men were better instructed themselves, they would be less
imposing on others.” (page 609, quoting Locke)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Locke may be regarded as the founder of empiricism, which is the
doctrine that all our knowledge (with the possible exception of
logic and mathematics) is derived from experience. Accordingly the
first book of the <em>Essay</em> is concerned in arguing, as against Plato,
Descartes, and the scholastics, that there are no innate ideas or
principles. (page 609)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Empiricism and idealism alike are faced with a problem to which, so
far, philosophy has found no satisfactory solution. This is the
problem of showing how we have knowledge of other things than
ourself and the operations of our own mind. (page 611)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>No one has yet succeeded in inventing a philosophy at once credible
and self-consistent. (page 613)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Belief in the harmony between private and public interests is
characteristic of liberalism, and long survived the theological
foundation that it had in Locke.</p>
<p>Locke states that liberty depends upon the necessity of pursuing
true happiness and upon the government of our passions. This opinion
he derives from his doctrine that private and public interests are
identical in the long run, though not necessarily over short
periods.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I feel like there's a prisoner's dilemma in here.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The hereditary principle has almost vanished from politics. During
my lifetime, the emperors of Brazil, China, Russia, Germany, and
Austria have disappeared, to be replaced by dictators who do not aim
at the foundation of a hereditary dynasty. Aristocracy has lost its
privileges throughout Europe, except in England, where they have
become little more than a historical form. All this, in most
countries, is very recent, and has much to do with the rise of
dictatorships, since the traditional basis of power has been swept
away, and the habits of mind required for the successful practice of
democracy have not had time to grow up. There is one great
institution that has never had any hereditary element, namely, the
Catholic Church. We may expect the dictatorships, if they survive,
to develop gradually a form of government analogous to that of the
Church. This has already happened in the case of the great
corporations in America, which have, or had until Pearl Harbor,
powers almost equal to those of the government. (pages 621-622)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In Locke's theory of government, I repeat, there is little that is
original. In this Locke resembles most of the men who have won fame
for their ideas. As a rule, the man who first thinks of a new idea
is so much ahead of his time that every one thinks him silly, so
that he remains obscure and is soon forgotten. Then, gradually, the
world becomes ready for the idea, and the man who proclaims it at
the fortunate moment gets all the credit. So it was, for example,
with Darwin; poor Lord Monboddo was a laughing-stock. (page 624)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Monboddo was also a nudist, <a href="https://www.scottishlegal.com/articles/our-legal-heritage-lord-monboddo-the-nudist-judge-who-pre-empted-darwin-s-theory-of-evolution" title="Our Legal Heritage: Lord Monboddo – the nudist judge who pre-empted Darwin’s theory of evolution">apparently</a>?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>[One view on the origin of government] maintained that God had
bestowed power on certain persons, and that these persons, or their
heirs, constituted the legitimate government, rebellion against
which is not only treason, but impiety. This view was sanctioned by
sentiments of immemorial antiquity: in almost all early
civilizations, the king is a sacred person. Kings, naturally,
considered it an admirable theory. Aristocracies had motives for
supporting it and motives for opposing it. In its favour was the
fact that it emphasized the hereditary principle, and that gave
august support to resistance against the upstart merchant class.
Where the middle class was more feared or hated by the aristocracy
than the king was, these motives prevailed. Where the contrary was
the case, and especially where the aristocracy had a chance of
obtaining supreme power itself, it tended to oppose the king, and
therefore to reject theories of divine right. (page 629)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is just a really good example of Russell's pragmatic, realpolitik
explanations: he frequently points out that people tend to believe
whatever tends to advantage them.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The question of the rights of the individual as against the
government is a very difficult one. It is too readily assumed by
democrats that, when the government represents the majority, it has
a right to coerce the minority. Up to a point, this must be true,
since coercion is of the essence of government. But the divine right
of majorities, if pressed too far, may become almost as tyrannical
as the divine right of kings. (page 633)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Berkeley (Chapter XVI, starting page 647) is interesting for his focus
on perception. “<a href="https://www.britannica.com/topic/esse-est-percipi-doctrine" title="esse est percipi doctrine">esse est percipi</a>” It seems too strong to say that
we can know that things <em>don't</em> exist without being perceived though.
On what basis?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It remains to be asked whether any meaning can be attached to the
words “mind” and “matter.” Every one knows that “mind” is what an
idealist thinks there is nothing else but, and “matter” is what a
materialist thinks the same about. The reader knows also, I hope,
that idealists are virtuous and materialists are wicked. But perhaps
there may be more than this to be said.</p>
<p>My own definition of “matter” may seem unsatisfactory; I should
define it as what satisfies the equations of physics. There may be
nothing satisfying these equations; in that case either physics of
the concept “matter” is a mistake. If we reject substance, “matter”
will have to be a logical construction. Whether it can be any
construction composed of events—which may be partly inferred—is a
difficult question, but by no means an insoluble one.</p>
<p>As for “mind,” when substance has been rejected a mind must be some
group or structure of events. The grouping must be effected by some
relation which is characteristic of the sort of phenomena we wish to
call “mental.” We may take memory as typical. We might—though this
would be rather unduly simple—define a “mental” event as one which
remembers or is remembered. Then the “mind” to which a given mental
event belongs is the group of events connected with the given event
by memory-chains, backwards or forwards.</p>
<p>It will be seen that, according to the above definition, a mind and
a piece of matter are, each of them, a group of events. There is no
reason why every event should belong to a group of one kind or the
other, and there is no reason why some events should not belong to
both groups; therefore some events may be neither mental nor
material, and other events may be both. As to this, only detailed
empirical considerations can decide. (pages 658-659)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is about as nearly as Russell gives his own metaphysics. He has
some idea that “events” are fundamental. I don't see any clear reason
to think that his ideas here are good.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In the Cartesian philosophy, as in that of the Scholastics, the
connection of cause and effect was supposed to be necessary, as
logical connections are necessary. The first really serious
challenge to this view came from Hume, with whom the modern
philosophy of causation begins. (page 664)</p>
<p>“We have no other notion of cause and effect, but that of certain
objects, which have been <em>always conjoined</em> together... We canot
penetrate into the reason of the conjunction.” (page 665, quoting
Hume)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“All probable reasoning is nothing but a species of sensation. 'Tis
not solely in poetry and music, we must follow our taste and
sentiment, but likewise in philosophy. When I am convinced of any
principle, 'tis only an idea, which strikes more strongly upon me.
When I give the preference to one set of arguments above another, I
do nothing but decide from my feeling concerning the superiority of
their influence. Objects have no discoverable connexion together;
nor is it from any other principle but custom operating upon the
imagination, that we can draw any inference from the appearance of
one to the existence of another.” (page 670, quoting Hume)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The growth of unreason throughout the nineteenth century and what
has passed of the twentieth is a natural sequel to Hume's
destruction of empiricism. (page 673)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>What these arguments [against induction] prove—and I do not think
the proof can be controverted—is that induction is an independent
logical principle, incapable of being inferred either from
experience or from other logical principles, and that without this
principle science is impossible. (page 674)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Man is not a solitary animal, and so long as social life survives,
self-realization cannot be the supreme principle of ethics. (page
684)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>After satisfying himself that there is a God, the Vicar [Rousseau]
goes on to consider rules of conduct. “I do not deduce these rules,”
he says, “from the principles of a high philosophy, but I find them
in the depths of my heart, written by Nature in ineffaceable
characters.” From this he goes on to develop the view that
conscience is in all circumstances an infallible guide to right
action. “Thanks be to Heaven,” he concludes this part of his
argument, “we are thus freed from all this terrifying apparatus of
philosophy; we can be men without being learned; dispensed from
wasting our life in the study of morals, we have at less cost a more
assured guide in this immense labyrinth of human opinions.” Our
natural feelings, he contends, lead us to serve the common interest,
while our reason urges selfishness. We have therefore only to follow
feeling rather than reason in order to be virtuous. (page 693)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Rouseau is a dork.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“categorical imperative” ... <em>“Act only according to a maxim by
which you can at the same time will that it shall become a general
law.”</em> (pages 710-711)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Kant...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>To frame a philosophy capable of coping with men intoxicated with
the prospect of almost unlimited power and also with the apathy of
the powerless is the most pressing task of our time. (page 729)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>This may seem odd, but that is not my fault. (page 760)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Russell is saying this of his comparison between Nietzsche's superman
and Siegfried as in Wagner's <em>Ring</em> cycle, but it is also a fair
summary of Russell's attitude toward most ideas of most philosophers.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>One of the bad effects of an anti-intellectual philosophy, such as
that of Bergson, is that it thrives upon the errors and confusions
of the intellect. Hence it is led to prefer bad thinking to good, to
declare every momentary difficulty insoluble, and to regard every
foolish mistake as revealing the bankruptcy of intellect and the
triumph of intuition. (page 803)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>[William] James's doctrine of radical empiricism was first published
in 1904, in an <a href="http://fair-use.org/william-james/essays-in-radical-empiricism/does-consciousness-exist" title="Does Consciousness Exist? (1904)">essay</a> called “Does ‘Consciousness’ Exist?” The
main purpose of this essay was to deny that the subject-object
relation is fundamental. It had, until then, been taken for granted
by philosophers that there is a kind of occurrence called “knowing,”
in which one entity, the knower or subject, is aware of another, the
thing known or the object. The knower was regarded as a mind or
soul; the object known might be a material object, an eternal
essence, another mind, or, in self-consciousness, identical with the
knower. Almost everything in accepted philosophy was bound up with
the dualism of subject and object. The distinction of mind and
matter, the contemplative ideal, and the traditional notion of
“truth,” all need to be radically reconsidered if the distinction of
subject and object is not accepted as fundamental.</p>
<p>For my part, I am convinced that James was right on this matter, and
would, on this ground alone, deserve a high place among
philosophers. I had thought otherwise until he, and those who agreed
with him, persuaded me of the truth of his doctrine. But let us
proceed to his arguments. (page 812)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>By the form of the words, radical empiricism's focus on pure
experience seems like it could be something I agree with. If
experience is central, and James is denying a material existence of
consciousness but not denying the state of being conscious, then maybe
it's just linguistic weirdness, and just my preference to say instead
that perhaps <em>only</em> consciousness exists. But the weirdness runs much
deeper.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>My thesis is that if we start with the supposition that there is
only one primal stuff or material in the world, a stuff of which
everything is composed, and if we call that stuff pure experience,
then knowing can easily be explained as a particular sort of
relation towards one another into which portions of pure experience
may enter. (James's <a href="http://fair-use.org/william-james/essays-in-radical-empiricism/does-consciousness-exist" title="Does Consciousness Exist? (1904)">essay</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is as ridiculous as Leibniz's monads. What a jump! To claim you
can say what the whole universe is made of! To give it such a name!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>That entity [consciousness] is fictitious, while thoughts in the
concrete are fully real. But thoughts in the concrete are made of
the same stuff as things are. (James's <a href="http://fair-use.org/william-james/essays-in-radical-empiricism/does-consciousness-exist" title="Does Consciousness Exist? (1904)">essay</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>An underlying bad idea throughout, here, is that the physical world is
in a deep sense identical to our mental perception and ideas of the
physical world. I think this comes from the sense we have of directly
knowing the world around us, as when we see a cup, reach out and touch
it, and are assured of its existence as we expected. I would like to
get James a VR headset.</p>
<p>I guess this is where Russell gets his ideas about “events” that can
be combinations of mental and physical.</p>
<p>At least James doesn't deny conscious experience. Why he needs to go
all the way to a weird monism is beyond me.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>He defines “pure experience” as “the immediate flux of life which
furnishes the material to our later reflection.” (page 813, quoting
James's <em>Essays in Radical Empiricism</em>)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The concept of “truth” as something dependent upon facts largely
outside human control has been one of the ways in which philosophy
hitherto has inculcated the necessary element of humility. When this
check upon pride is removed, a further step is taken on the road
towards a certain kind of madness—the intoxication of power which
invaded philosophy with Fichte, and to which modern men, whether
philosophers or not, are prone. I am persuaded that this
intoxication is the greatest danger of our time, and that any
philosophy which, however unintentionally, contributes to it is
increasing the danger of vast social disaster. (page 828)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Modern analytical empirical, of which I have been giving an outline,
differs from that of Locke, Berkeley, and Hume by its incorporation
of mathematics and its development of a powerful logical technique.
It is thus able, in regard to certain problems, to achieve definite
answers, which have the quality of science rather than of
philosophy. It has the advantage, as compared with the philosophies
of the system-builders, of being able to tackle its problems one at
a time, instead of having to invent at one stroke a block theory of
the whole universe. Its methods, in this respect, resemble those of
science. I have no doubt that, in so far as philosophical knowledge
is possible, it is by such methods that it must be sought; I have
also no doubt that, by these methods, many ancient problems are
completely soluble.</p>
<p>There remains, however, a vast field, traditionally included in
philosophy, where scientific methods are inadequate. This field
includes ultimate questions of value; science alone, for example,
cannot prove that it is bad to enjoy the infliction of cruelty.
Whatever can be known, can be known by means of science; but things
which are legitimately matters of feeling lie outside its province.</p>
<p>Philosophy, throughout its history, has consisted of two parts
inharmoniously blended: on the one hand a theory as to the nature of
the world, on the other an ethical or political doctrine as to the
best way of living. The failure to separate these two with
sufficient clarity has been a source of much confused thinking.
(page 834)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is in the last chapter of the book, <em>The Philosophy of Logical
Analysis</em>.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230707-russell_history_of_western_philosophy/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230707-russell_history_of_western_philosophy/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
