<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>(Audio) I Hate the Ivy League, by Gladwell</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This is the first time I've seen a collection of podcasts packaged as
an <a href="https://www.pushkin.fm/audiobooks/i-hate-the-ivy-league-riffs-and-rants-on-elite-education">audiobook</a>. There is no corresponding printed book that you can
buy. Sort of weird, but Gladwell is good enough that it works.</p>
<hr>
<p>I tend to agree with Gladwell. Education shouldn't be an elitist thing
based on keeping people out.</p>
<hr>
<p>One thing Gladwell discusses is two opposing views of what education
should do, corresponding to two opposing views of what we need.</p>
<p>He uses basketball and soccer to illustrate the two views, saying that
in basketball you win based on your <em>best</em> players, while in soccer
you win based on your <em>worst</em> players. So in basketball it's okay to
have some weaker players, if your star/s is/are great, while in soccer
you might win more by improving your worst players.</p>
<p>I've heard this explicitly, for education. Kai-fu Lee <a href="/20200926-ai_superpowers_by_lee/" title="AI Superpowers, by Lee">says</a> that
good educational "programs seek to identify and realize the potential
of the country's top technical minds, an approach suited to creating
the material prosperity that can then be broadly shared across
society."</p>
<p>From another angle, it's the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_man_theory">great man theory</a> against the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ortega_hypothesis">Ortega hypothesis</a>, roughly.</p>
<p>From another angle, it's conservatism vs. progressivism: individuals
should be able to succeed wildly, vs. the poorest should be helped.</p>
<p>Gladwell also relates this idea to the Industrial Revolution happening
in England. He attributes it to the abundance of tinkerers/inventors
all working on things. (Cf. <a href="/20250322-power_and_progress_by_acemoglu_and_johnson/">Power and Progress</a>)</p>
<hr>
<p>Gladwell doesn't like timed tests. I'm a little torn, but I do have to
wonder: Did timed standardized tests influence my work style? Would I
have been better off with more focus on longer-term planning and
projects?</p>
<hr>
<p>“Mirror-tocracy”</p>
<hr>
<p>There's an interesting bit about how <a href="https://mcconville.rbind.io/">Kelly McConville</a>'s students
reverse-engineered the US News college rankings. It's a place where
regression makes sense, because the methodology of the rankings
matches up with what regression can do. It also reminded me of my old
project on <a href="/20190529-understanding_myintuition/">Understanding MyinTuition</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20250322-i_hate_the_ivy_league_by_gladwell/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20250322-i_hate_the_ivy_league_by_gladwell/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Power and Progress, by Acemoglu and Johnson</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This <a href="https://shapingwork.mit.edu/power-and-progress/">book</a> from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daron_Acemoglu" title="Daron Acemoglu">Acemoglu</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_Johnson_(economist)" title="Simon Johnson (economist)">Johnson</a> explains that
technological progress doesn't automatically make everyone better off.
They're right, but they're also too conventional to see beyond the
labor exchange paradigm, constraining the application of their thesis.</p>
<p>The authors understand that we make choices about who benefits from
technology, but they're also committed to the idea that people should
have to work for a living. This limits their imagination and results
in recommendations that pursue full employment instead of enabling a
vision of a yet brighter future.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Workers complained about conditions and the backbreaking effort.
Most egregious to many were the rules they had to follow in
factories. One weaver put it this way in 1834: “No man would like to
work in a power-loom, they do not like it, there is such a
clattering and noise it would almost make some men mad; and next, he
would have to be subject to a discipline that a hand-loom weaver can
never submit to.”</p>
<p>New machinery turned workers into mere cogs. As another weaver
testified before a parliamentary committee in April 1835, “I am
determined for my part, that if they will invent machines to
supersede manual labour, they must find iron boys to mind them.”
(page 8)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I include this selection because I found the phrase “iron boys”
weirdly evocative in its contrast. It reminds me a little bit of
“<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Windup_Girl" title="The Windup Girl">windup girls</a>.”</p>
<p>The point of the weaver is that working with the new machines is less
pleasant than his accustomed artisanal process. It is less humane. It
is dehumanizing.</p>
<p>It also highlights that the conversion is incomplete; the attempt “to
supersede manual labor” has not fully succeeded, while people still
have to work with the machines. I find myself agreeing that “they must
find iron boys to mind them.”</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“In <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Novum_Organum"><em>Novum Organum</em></a>, published in 1620, Bacon had argued that
scientific knowledge would enable nothing less than human control
over nature.” (page 12)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I feel like I should have recognized this immediately, but I had to
look it up. It is the shift from pure logic to focus on observation.
Pure logic is limited or full of madness; science has shaky
foundations but remarkable technological fruit.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Optimism regarding shared benefits from technological progress is
founded on a simple and powerful idea: the “productivity bandwagon.”
This idea maintains that new machines and production methods that
increase productivity will also produce higher wages. As technology
progresses, the bandwagon will pull along everybody, not just
entrepreneurs and owners of capital. (page 15)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>On the one hand, it seems ridiculous that anyone would believe in such
a “productivity bandwagon,” but on the other hand, people do seem to
believe something like it, often.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>technology is about control, not just over nature but often over
other humans. It is not simply that technological change benefits
some more than others. More fundamentally, different ways of
organizing production enrich and empower some people and disempower
others. (page 26)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This could be a thesis for the book.</p>
<p>There is perhaps a false divide between “nature” and “other humans.”
In both cases there is an “othering.”</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Central to this volte-face was a change in the direction of
technology away from new tasks and opportunities for workers and
toward a preoccupation with automating work and cutting labor costs.
(page 32)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Listening to the audiobook and unfamiliar with “volte-face,” which is
French for “about-face” (a complete and sudden change) I made a quick
mental note to look it up later. Only half-remembering the context, I
thought it might be some proper noun I was unfamiliar with. I guessed
it was spelled “voltfass” and that it might be German. Asking ChatGPT
about this, it was happy to hallucinate and send me on a merry chase
around the internet. It took me quite some time to track it to what it
actually was.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>To understand <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_de_Lesseps" title="Ferdinand de Lesseps">Lesseps</a>’s vision, we must first turn to the ideas
of the French social reformer Henri de Saint-Simon and his colorful
followers. Saint-Simon was an aristocratic writer who maintained
that human progress is driven by scientific invention and the
application of new ideas to industry. But he also thought that the
right leadership was critical for this progress: “All enlightened
peoples will adopt the view that men of genius should be given the
highest social standing.” (page 36)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Okay so <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_de_Lesseps" title="Ferdinand de Lesseps">Lesseps</a> was this canal guy who made the Suez Canal and
then failed to make the Panama Canal because he stubbornly wanted to
do it the same way. The chapter is called “Canal Vision” and it's
basically saying look, the best ideas don't win automatically.
Personality matters, reputation matters, rhetoric matters. And if you
put all your faith in this one guy, he can screw it up.</p>
<p>This all hits fairly close to home. At work, I sometimes feel like I'm
witnessing a Panama Canal effect, where someone who had past success
is forging ahead with something new regardless of whether the new
thing is a good idea really. “Vision is power,” influence without
authority, etc.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daron_Acemoglu" title="Daron Acemoglu">Acemoglu</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_Johnson_(economist)" title="Simon Johnson (economist)">Johnson</a> are the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_institutional_economics">New Institutional Economics</a>
guys, and they talk about how they think the Industrial Revolution
happened in Britain because people could try to get rich and were
allowed to.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Friedman, who, like Hayek and Stigler, was awarded the Nobel Prize
in economics, made important contributions to many areas, including
macroeconomics, price theory, and monetary policy. Arguably,
however, his most influential work did not appear in an academic
journal but in a short piece published in September 1970 in the New
York Times Magazine, immodestly titled “<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1970/09/13/archives/a-friedman-doctrine-the-social-responsibility-of-business-is-to.html" title="A Friedman doctrine‐- The Social Responsibility of Business Is to Increase Its Profits">A Friedman Doctrine</a>.”
Friedman argued that the “social responsibility” of business was
misconstrued. Business should care only about making profits and
generating high returns for their shareholders. Simply put, “The
social responsibility of business is to increase its profits.” (page
205)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Oh my. I think I hadn't realized that this had been put so explicitly.</p>
<hr>
<p>They go on about “Machine Usefulness” and automation vs. creating new
tasks, and there's something to it, but I don't think it amounts to an
optimal path forward. They're focused on ensuring that benefits go to
workers, but I think we need to get beyond making everybody be a
worker.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20250322-power_and_progress_by_acemoglu_and_johnson/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20250322-power_and_progress_by_acemoglu_and_johnson/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Superconvergence, by Metzl</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jamie_Metzl">Metzl</a> rubs me the wrong way, a little bit, the way the heros of
LinkedIn do. He's been bio-focused, and still is, but AI is hot so AI
is in the book. He's not wrong, exactly, but it still feels
attention-seeking. <a href="https://www.hachettebookgroup.com/titles/jamie-metzl/superconvergence/9781643263007/">The book</a> has very low information density, and
then weirdly his main objective in the end is to get people excited
about regulation.</p>
<p>Metzl advocates for the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ortega_hypothesis">Ortega hypothesis</a>, but mostly because it
fits well with his story of exponential scientific progress: if we
don't have to wait for geniuses, then progress can keep accelerating.
Interesting take.</p>
<p>He talks a lot about god-like powers, and how we need to regulate
them. He's at pains to say this shouldn't be a global body imposing
rules, but that every country should do things in line with their own
culture and values. Ignoring that requiring countries to regulate
where they wouldn't on their own is already an imposition, this
federated approach only works if we have fairly strong assumptions
about every government's culture and values playing well with what we
think is reasonable. But then he goes on to say that also there should
be international coordination, seemingly with more teeth than the WHO
and so on, so he is arguing for global control in the end as well.</p>
<p>Metzl also believes <a href="https://jamiemetzl.com/origins-of-sars-cov-2/">fairly strongly</a> that COVID-19 was produced by
humans. It makes sense to talk about this in the book because it adds
weight to the discussion of risks, making it not just hypothetical.
This kind of talk always makes me think of the assassination germ idea
in <a href="/20200124-three_body_problem_remembrance_of_earths_past/">The Three Body Problem</a>. Scary stuff indeed.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241230-superconvergence_by_metzl/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241230-superconvergence_by_metzl/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Playing with Reality, by Clancy</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I think <a href="https://www.npr.org/people/724387257/darian-woods">Darian Woods</a> mentioned <a href="https://www.kellybclancy.com/">Clancy</a>'s book in an episode of
The Indicator. Great recommendation! <em>Playing with Reality</em> could be
the best book of the year. Beautifully written, rich with information,
humane in perspective. The thesis is basically that the map is not the
territory, and games can be kinds of maps. Sort of like
<a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>, it explores ways that simplified and
quantified models can mislead. Fascinating throughout.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<h3>History of education</h3>
<p>The first game in the book is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rithmomachia">Rithmomachia</a>, the math game you
played as part of your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadrivium">Quadrivium</a> education, which was a thing
from Greek to Medieval times. The history of education is fascinating.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trivium">Trivium</a><ul>
<li>grammar</li>
<li>logic</li>
<li>rhetoric</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadrivium">Quadrivium</a><ul>
<li>“arithmetic (pure numbers)”</li>
<li>“geometry (numbers in space)”</li>
<li>“music (numbers in time)”</li>
<li>“astronomy (numbers in space and time)” (page 5)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>“Some medieval historians blame the quadrivial curriculum for
holding European scholarship back hundreds of years. Its focus on
harmony blinkered scientists to fundamental advances, such as the
discovery of irrational numbers and celestial mechanics. The
quadrivial curriculum was largely abandoned by the seventeenth
century, as new mathematical techniques from Persia and India led to
breakthroughs in calculus and probability theory. Rithmomachia
similarly fell by the wayside.” (page 7)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This idea, of education hampering progress, is very interesting. I
wonder whether things like the Chinese exam system might have had a
similar effect. What about the current education system? What is
blocking rather than enabling progress?</p>
<p>The book doesn't talk about it, but according to Wikipedia an
intermediate successor curriculum was the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humanitas#Revival">studia humanitatis</a>
around the 14th century, with Petrarch.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humanitas#Revival">studia humanitatis</a><ul>
<li>grammar</li>
<li>rhetoric</li>
<li>poetry</li>
<li>history</li>
<li>moral philosophy</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Later, the book describes "required training for nobility in Europe
and the Near East."</p>
<ul>
<li>an eighteenth century aristocrat was expected to master<ul>
<li>calligraphy</li>
<li>horseback riding</li>
<li>history</li>
<li>philosophy</li>
<li>weaponry</li>
<li>music</li>
<li>astrology</li>
<li>games, especially chess</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>“Kriegsspiel roots back to the late eighteenth century, when
mathematician Johann Hellwig invented a variant of chess. Chess was
then considered to be required training for nobility in Europe and
the Near East; an aristocrat was expected to master calligraphy,
horseback riding, history, philosophy, weaponry, music, astrology,
and games, especially chess. Tutors used chess to teach strategic
thinking and mathematics to their pupils. Chess, originally
chaturanga, originated in India as an explicit abstraction of war.”
(page 47)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Lots of the book is about how we learn from games, but in explicitly
educational contexts and elsewhere.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Psychohistory</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“The new field’s [statistics'] success expanded to other social
sciences. The nineteenth-century Belgian mathematician Adolphe
Quetelet was a tireless advocate for a new science he called “social
physics,” whereby he hoped to work out a human correlate of
celestial mechanics and describe the trajectories of civilization.
Quetelet used massive datasets to detect underlying patterns. He
found regularities in births, deaths, suicides, and even crime
rates. He argued that crimes should not be considered acts of
individual volition. Instead, he found that they obeyed statistical
laws at the population level. “Society itself contains the germs of
all the crimes committed. It is the social state, in some measure,
that prepares these crimes, and the criminal is merely the
instrument that executes them.” Criminals were themselves victims,
helpless to the laws of social physics acting on society, a
necessary sacrifice to preserve civilization. He suggested that
evidence-based legislation—aimed more at ameliorating the
institutional causes of crime and less at punishing individual
criminals themselves—was the best hope for reforming society.
Quetelet’s ideas were so pervasive that physicist James Clerk
Maxwell often illustrated his work in statistical mechanics using
analogies drawn from social physics. To those armed with the hammer
of probability theory, the world looked like a statistics problem.
If we could use math to understand even chance, why not use it to
understand humanity itself?” (page 40)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>“Social physics” is yet another name for <a href="/20200714-foundation_trilogy/">psychohistory</a>!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The historian Hans Delbrück recognized that military and political
history are inextricably tangled. He was committed to establishing a
quantitative study of history. Throughout his career, Delbrück pored
over historical data, hoping to develop a science of war,
relentlessly workshopping historical battles to test his theories.
He argued that Germany’s failures in World War I were primarily
strategic in nature. He advocated for their neutered military to
take up historical study and simulations. By embracing these
simulations during the interwar period, the Germans developed a new
form of combat using theoretical forces that did not yet exist but
soon would. It promised to solve the stagnant trench warfare that
had characterized World War I, leveraging surprise to dominate and
demoralize the enemy. In World War II, this tactic would rain terror
from the skies across Europe. It would come to be known throughout
the world as the Blitzkrieg.” (page 52)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And again!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The real question,” he [Skinner] writes, “is not whether machines
think but whether men do. The mystery which surrounds a thinking
machine already surrounds a thinking man.” (page 21)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think Skinner is getting at the questions of consciousness and free
will. Provocative phrasing.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Like many scientists of the era, such as Galileo, Cardano was made
a celebrity by the horoscopes he drew up for the ruling class.
Astrology played the role of today’s science-funding agencies.”
(page 34)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sometimes data science work feels a little like this. People want
predictions, and they don't always want a careful accounting of
uncertainty. They want to hear what they want to hear. And like magic
or divination, why not just take a stab at it? You'll be right
sometimes!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“It seemed so ubiquitous that many scientists used it to simplify
the measurement of errors in a wide range of datasets, including
many they shouldn’t have. They were, as mathematician Nassim
Nicholas Taleb puts it, “blinded by bell curves.” (page 40)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This idea is applied to Black–Scholes, and Taleb's “ludic fallacy” is
described: the mistake of applying the rules of games to real-life
situations.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Through seemingly objective arguments like these, the status quo
keeps its finger tipping the scales in the marketplace of ideas,
assigning invented values to justify arbitrary ideologies.” (page
45)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The example is weird MacAskill argument. These "Effective Altruism"
people, jeez.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“His [Hilbert's] student Hermann Weyl writes: “Mathematics is no
longer knowledge but a game of formulae, ruled by certain
conventions, which is very well comparable to the game of chess.”
(page 58)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“We may still choose to make a wager with a low likelihood of
success if the outcome is something we want enough—like putting in
the effort to apply for a highly competitive job, even if it’s
unlikely we’ll get it. In this framework, a rational actor will
always make choices that they believe will maximize their expected
utility, balancing their desire for a given option with its risks.
Given certain assumptions, their preferences can be described by a
utility function, which can be used to predict their strategies and
choices. Von Neumann’s elegant formulation transmuted subjective
individual desire into a shared frame of reference, defined entirely
by an agent’s actions in a collective playing field. He derived all
of this in the span of a single afternoon. Morgenstern later wrote
in his diary that watching von Neumann solve in one day a problem
that had plagued economists for years “gave me great satisfaction,
and moved me so much that afterwards I could not think about
anything else.” (page 66)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This presentation of von Neumann as a 10x genius is interesting.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“In game theory, players’ preferences are usually assumed to be
fixed. But psychologists have found that people’s choices are
sensitive to a game’s context. Players behave differently in a
prisoner’s dilemma depending on how it’s presented to them. If it’s
called the Wall Street Game, players are more likely to defect. If
it’s called the Community Game, they’re more likely to cooperate.
The two games have the exact same structure, payoffs, and penalties
(e.g., jail time), yet their titles alone cause players to act
differently.” (page 76)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Game theory, pioneered by a traumatized man hoping to plumb the
depths of human nature, has only ever been about math: the dynamics
of a maximizing function, not of real people. We must be careful not
to let its models mean anything about ourselves, and careful to
prevent its fables from seeping into the domain of accepted wisdom.
Let’s consider the zero-sum bias. People across the globe tend to
believe that all resources are limited, even when this is not the
case. An isolationist might oppose immigration because they think
that immigrants “steal” from a fixed number of available jobs, not
realizing that immigrants also drive economic growth and create new
jobs.” (page 80)</p>
<p>“Game theory’s power lies in its expressiveness: it can convey
dynamic stories with simple mechanics. Unfortunately, game theory
has been used to launder dubious beliefs and present racist,
nativist policies as objective or inevitable. Some of these sinister
fables have been taken out of context and integrated into the
foundations of accepted common sense. If game theory continues to be
used as a model of human behavior, it needs major revisions to
reflect the fact that most people aren’t singularly focused on
personal gain. Even then, we’d be better off modeling people for
what they are: flexible learners.” (page 86)</p>
<p>“In his book <em>Economic Fables</em>, mathematician Ariel Rubinstein
likens game theory—mathematical abstractions of complex
situations—to fables with oversimple morals. We should be careful
not to mistake these for reality. Game theory should be studied for
its mathematical beauty, but it cannot pretend to tell us about the
real world. Rubinstein argues that even many academics don’t fully
understand it and often fail to communicate its limitations. This
would not be an issue if game theory remained a purely academic
pursuit. But it’s been adopted for use in modern systems that impact
billions of people worldwide.” (page 98)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“In 1930, Fisher collected and extended his genetic insights in his
opus, The Genetical Theory of Natural Selection, which almost
single-handedly revitalized Darwin’s ideas and rescued them from
years of neglect by academics. In the book, Fisher elaborates—in his
characteristically cryptic style—what is now one of the most
celebrated arguments in evolutionary biology and an early seed of
game-theoretic thinking in the life sciences.” (page 113)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The part I'm interested in here is that Fisher is said to have a
"characteristically cryptic style." This is the guy who wrote
"Statistical Methods for Research Workers" and "The Design of
Experiments." Is his cryptic style part of why frequentist statistics
is such a poorly understood mess?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Price_equation">Price equation</a> is the fundamental theorem of evolution and
can be used to derive other basic theorems of evolution. The
equation’s generality lends it its power. This same generality
invites misuse from researchers unfamiliar with its nuances. Some
have dismissed it as a tautology, nothing more than a statistical
identity. Others have praised its depth.” (page 123)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Games remain an impressive way to evaluate a program’s
capabilities. In the early 1980s, graduate students Shafi Goldwasser
and Silvio Micali invented a powerful new form of mathematical proof
by imagining how they might play a secure poker game over the phone.
The resulting technique, interactive proof systems, consists of two
subparts, a prover and a verifier. These exchange messages until the
verifier is “convinced” that an answer is correct. Interactive
proofs became a foundational technique in computer science and
cryptography. They’re also the metaphoric heart of how we hope to
verify intelligence through games. Traditional math proofs are
inevitable, each step an irresistible conclusion unfolding from the
last. Interactive proofs, on the other hand, are probabilistically
true. By testing again and again, the verifier becomes increasingly
convinced of the prover’s claim. The Turing test, for instance, can
be mathematically formalized in this framework. Games take the same
form: human experts repeatedly test a game-playing computer program
to convince themselves of its capabilities. There is no single
measure of intelligence, or its mechanical approximation. Its
evaluation will be, by nature, interactive: the iterated probing of
a system.” (pages 137-138)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“To borrow social theorist Sherry Turkle’s phrase, we too easily
abdicate authority to simulations. Simulations are ultimately
constrained by their creators’ assumptions: games are self-contained
universes ticking along to preprogrammed logic. They don’t
necessarily reflect anything fundamental about the world. Models’
conclusions are less interesting than the assumptions on which
they’re based—assumptions that are typically hidden.” (page 159)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Utopia is the process of making a better world, the name for one
path history can take, a dynamic, tumultuous, agonizing process,
with no end. Struggle forever.” (page 160, quoting Kim Stanley
Robinson)</p>
<p>“The game Moksha Patam (today’s Snakes and Ladders) is often
credited to the thirteenth-century Marathi saint Dnyaneshwar, though
it may have been invented hundreds of years earlier. It was designed
to teach players about karma and illustrate the precarity of fate.
In it, souls ascend to the heavenly realms, dragged down by vices
(snakes) and buoyed by virtues (ladders). Snakes are labeled with
the names of demons and the vices they represent, and players
recount stories from Hindu mythology as they play.” (page 160)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Scholars have sought to find a purely logical foundation for the
question of morality and how society should be structured. In the
mid-twentieth century, philosopher John Rawls began a line of
inquiry that culminated in his celebrated 1971 treatise, <em>A Theory
of Justice</em>. In this work, he posits fairness as the foundational
principle, or “first virtue,” on which society should be built.”
(page 163)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“In the 1950s, game theorists discovered that some repeated games
support an infinite number of stable equilibrium strategies. This
became known as the folk theorem, because it was such an obvious
outcome that no one bothered formally publishing it.” (page 165)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Board game designer Reiner Knizia claims that the scoring system is
the most important part of designing a new game. It’s the score that
drives players’ behaviors. Similarly, in a subfield of game theory
known as mechanism design, or reverse game theory, mathematicians
design institutional rules that incentivize players to behave in
particular ways.” (page 174)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is pretty neat. Start with the end in mind, and then rather than
thinking we can influence people directly, imagine we can control "the
rules of the game" (through policy, etc.) - how do they get set up to
achieve the desired end? Possible connection also to "nudge" ideas,
etc.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241226-playing_with_reality_by_clancy/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241226-playing_with_reality_by_clancy/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) The Next Millionaire Next Door</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>It's sweet that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_J._Stanley">Stanley</a>'s daughter finished this 2020 follow-up to
his 1996 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Millionaire_Next_Door">Millionaire Next Door</a> after he died in 2015. There are
refreshed surveys, but not a lot that's new, as far as I can tell,
apart from attempts to defend the family legacy from criticism.</p>
<p>The core concept is still spending less money than you get. More pages
are given to spending less than to getting more. Conscientiousness and
discipline are emphasized. America is presented as uniquely suited to
building wealth because of freedom.</p>
<p>One criticism of the original book was that the core thesis (that
normal people can become millionaires) was an artifact of survivorship
bias observed toward the end of a bull market. I didn't hear a really
good response to this criticism, but I don't think it's a particularly
interesting criticism either.</p>
<p>I think the deeper latent criticism is about what level of the system
to blame. Stanley is all about the individual level. "The game is
winnable!" he says. Critics, I think, are often talking about
something fundamentally different. "The rules of the game are unfair!"
they say. Both these things can be true at the same time.</p>
<p>It's easy to wag a finger at someone with a high income who's still
barely making their house and car payments. But far more people have
low income, not much room to cut expenses, and little opportunity to
increase their income. These books have more advice for the former
than the latter.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241224-next_millionaire_next_door/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241224-next_millionaire_next_door/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Matilda, by Dahl</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>A local middle school put on Matilda, the musical, which made me
curious enough to read the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matilda_(novel)">book</a>. It's strange and cute. It's very
episodic, with the main resolution appearing with less warning in the
book than the musical. Apparently in early versions of the book
Matilda was even more malicious.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It's not fair," Lavender said. "How can she do it and we can't?"
(page 69)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"You are so much wiser than your years, my dear," Miss Honey went
on, "that it quite staggers me. Although you look like a child, you
are not really a child at all because your mind and your powers of
reasoning seem to be fully grown-up. So I suppose we might call you
a grown-up child, if you see what I mean." (page 189)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Without stories we're just eating machines with shoes." (Dennis
Kelly, script-writer for the musical, in an afterward)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Tim Minchin did the music and lyrics for the musical. He also did
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fCNvZqpa-7Q">White Wine In The Sun</a>.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241221-matilda_by_dahl/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241221-matilda_by_dahl/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Financial calculators exist</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>When you take the <a href="/20241123-what_are_cfps_supposed_to_know/" title="Certified Financial Planner">CFP</a> exam, you are allowed to use a
<a href="https://www.cfp.net/-/media/files/cfp-board/cfp-certification/exam/calculator-policy.pdf">dedicated financial calculator</a> like the Texas Instruments
"Business Analyst" <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Texas-Instruments-Advanced-Financial-Calculator/dp/B0029F1OKE">BA II Plus</a>. How wild is that?</p>
<p><img alt="calculator" src="ba2plus.jpg"></p>
<p>What does it do? You can start to guess from buttons like "IRR," but
the <a href="https://education.ti.com/en/guidebook/details/en/ADF11FB65B284B6195B0A7E9502784BA/baiiplus">manual</a> explains much more about how the functionality is
organized into "worksheets" and so on.</p>
<p><img alt="functions" src="functions.png"></p>
<p>Do people use these for real, in their work? My guess is that they're
sort of an archaic thing that persists only for the exam? Surely
people use one of many <a href="https://www.calculator.net/finance-calculator.html">online calculators</a>, or Excel, or some other
more user-friendly tool? (Although I don't really know what a great
example is; most of the ones I see at a quick look seem pretty
crummy...)</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241123-financial_calculators_exist/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241123-financial_calculators_exist/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>What are CFPs supposed to know?</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>To be a Certified Financial Planner, you have to have a bachelor's
degree (in anything) and do (<a href="https://www.cfp.net/get-certified/certification-process/education-requirement/certification-coursework-requirement/accelerated-path">usually</a>) seven <a href="https://www.cfp.net/">CFP Board</a>-approved
classes and pass a test covering many <a href="https://www.cfp.net/get-certified/certification-process/education-requirement/certification-coursework-requirement/what-youll-learn">topics</a>. The classes are
Fundamentals, Insurance, Investments, Tax, Retirement, Estate, and a
capstone case study class. Then you do 30 hours of continuing
education every two years.</p>
<p>The CFP Board <a href="https://www.cfp.net/get-certified/certification-process/education-requirement/certification-coursework-requirement/find-an-education-program/">lists</a> about 250 institutions with approved
offerings, mostly universities. These can be outsourced offerings, for
example from <a href="https://cerifi.com/">Cerifi</a>'s <a href="https://dalton-education.com/university-partnerships">Dalton Education</a> or
<a href="https://www.greeneconsults.com/">Greene Consulting</a>'s <a href="https://www.financialplannerprogram.com/#school">Financial Planner Program</a> or <a href="https://www.kenzahn.com/">Zahn</a>.</p>
<p>There seem to be two main lines of textbooks. One is <a href="https://cerifi.com/">Cerifi</a>'s
<a href="https://www.money-education.com/">Money Education</a>, which <a href="https://cerifi.com/our-brands">claims</a> to by “chosen by 200
universities nationwide.” The <a href="https://www.nationalunderwriter.com/series/academic.html">other</a> is from
<a href="https://www.nationalunderwriter.com/">National Underwriter</a>, mostly in their <a href="https://www.nationalunderwriter.com/series/the-leimberg-library.html">Leimberg Library</a>. There
used to be books from Keir, but they <a href="https://www.keirsuccess.com/products/cfp-certification-products/education-courses/university-textbooks">joined forces</a> with
<a href="https://www.money-education.com/">Money Education</a>.</p>
<p>From <a href="https://www.opensyllabus.org/">Open Syllabus</a>, it isn't clear which books are most popular. I
find <a href="https://analytics.opensyllabus.org/record/works?syllabus_query=money+education">one entry each</a> for two of the Money Education books, and
<a href="https://analytics.opensyllabus.org/record/works?syllabus_query=leimberg">no mention</a> of Leimberg books. It seems like <a href="https://www.cffp.edu/cfp-education">Kaplan</a> and
<a href="https://www.brettdanko.com/">Danko</a> also have materials, but may only offer them to participants
in their courses.</p>
<p>There are also lots of exam prep and study materials. <a href="https://www.kenzahn.com/">Zahn</a> for
example makes supplemental books and flashcards, and Money Education
has “QuickSheets.”</p>
<p>There's also a thing called a <a href="/20241123-financial_calculators_exist/">financial calculator</a>, which can be a
physical object that CFPs may learn to use.</p>
<p>For continuing education, every two years a CFP has to do 30 hours of
programs, selected from <a href="https://www.cfp.net/career-and-growth/continuing-education/find-a-ce-program">thousands</a> that are approved by the CFP
Board.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241123-what_are_cfps_supposed_to_know/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241123-what_are_cfps_supposed_to_know/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) We've got you covered, by Einav and Finkelstein</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I read <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/690632/weve-got-you-covered-by-liran-einav-and-amy-finkelstein/" title="We've Got You Covered: Rebooting American Health Care">this book</a> because Furman recommended it, and his
<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/10/21/books/review/economics-business-books.html" title="5 Books to Help You Understand the Economy Before Voting">description</a> is good. I admire the economist authors' ability to
take a normative stand while staying clear-headed about measured
realities. I'm on board.</p>
<p>The central claim of the book is that we <em>should</em> provide free basic
health care to everyone. They support this by arguing that the US has
been <em>trying</em> to do this: trying to honor an implicit social contract.</p>
<p>The issue then is that the US has been doing a very poor job of it.
The authors propose that health insurance should instead be free and
automatic for everyone, with no sign-up hoops or costs incurred for
receiving care.</p>
<p>Problems with the current US system include its complexity itself, and
health insurance being tied to employment (therefore subject to
termination at any time) and medical costs being a potentially
unbounded burden for individuals, sometimes even for those <em>with</em>
insurance.</p>
<p>They point out that insurance doesn't actually have that much
influence on health outcomes, because impact on health is dominated by
behaviors that correlate with wealth, for example, and because people
generally still <em>get</em> health care even if not insured, even if it also
saddles them with debt. So universal health insurance won't resolve
disparities in health outcomes. (This does appear somewhat at odds
with the authors' frequent complaint that the US system often pays for
treatment only after conditions become acute dangers, while earlier
treatment might have been cheaper and prevented the worst health
outcomes.)</p>
<p>The book is also full of interesting current and historical detail
about the US and international health systems.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“We have therefore intentionally focused on what we <em>should</em> do,
rather than what some may think we currently <em>can</em> do. In this
sense, our book is in the spirit of the famous Chicago economist
Milton Friedman. He argued that the role for economists in public
policy is to develop the best ideas, and keep them alive and ripe in
the public imagination until the day when “the politically
impossible becomes the politically inevitable.” (page 14)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Let’s start with the precarious insurance of the privately insured.
Almost half of the US population—over 150 million people—receive
private health insurance through their employers or a family
member’s employer. That’s almost all Americans who have private
health insurance.</p>
<p>There’s no natural reason why their boss doubles as their insurer.
This unusual arrangement arose through an accident of history, a
common theme of US health-care policy. During World War II, the
federal government imposed wage and price controls to try to prevent
inflation. Employers—desperate to attract and retain scarce
workers—soon discovered a way to get around the wage ceilings and
provide higher compensation. They could offer—and pay for—their
workers’ health insurance, because these payments weren’t counted as
“wages.”</p>
<p>The practice of excluding employer payments for their employees’
health insurance from the definition of employee earnings has
remained in place to this day. As a result, any such payments are
tax-free. An employee doesn’t have to pay income tax on any
contributions her employer makes to her workplace-based health
insurance premium.” (page 17)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Moral commitments are not limitless. Even FDR implicitly
acknowledged this in his Second Bill of Rights. He spoke of rights
such as “a decent home,” “a good education,” and “adequate medical
care.” The economist Arthur Okun, writing a few decades later,
likewise espoused a right to health care while simultaneously
cautioning that these rights are not unbounded. With the customary
bluntness of an economist rather than a politician, he described “a
heated debate with an audience of medical administrators.” As Okun
described it, “Taking what I viewed as an outlandish example, I
suggested that any national health program should not grant me at
public expense all the pairs of eyeglasses I might like. I learned
to my surprise that they favored an unlimited right to eyeglasses.”
(page 74)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The technical term for this quality of life measure is <em>quality
adjusted life year,</em> or QALY (rhymes with <em>jolly</em>). A year in
perfect health is given a QALY score of one, a year of being dead
scores zero. Much scientific effort and squabbling go into assigning
scores to all the various ways a year can be spent in
less-than-perfect health. (footnote, page 100)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is part of a section which is a great example of the challenges
of trying to linearize multiple things into one measure. In this case
they were using a ratio of benefits to cost, so a cheap and decent
thing showed up as better than an expensive but essential thing.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The faithful and accurate application of cost-benefit analysis had
produced unacceptable results. Even the commissioners agreed,
acknowledging that their rankings often conflicted with their own
intuition. They quickly abandoned the formulaic application of
cost-effectiveness rankings in favor of a more “holistic” approach.
They used their judgment—and that of members of the community who
provided input through public forums—to create broad categories of
health care that they ranked in order of importance. Effective care
for acute fatal conditions (such as appendectomies) was ranked high,
while minimally effective treatments for nonfatal conditions (such
as tooth capping or medical therapy for diaper rash) were in a
category near the bottom.” (page 100)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241116-weve_got_you_covered_by_einav_and_finkelstein/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241116-weve_got_you_covered_by_einav_and_finkelstein/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Technofeudalism, by Varoufakis</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The generous interpretation is that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yanis_Varoufakis">Varoufakis</a> understands that
his <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/751443/technofeudalism-by-yanis-varoufakis/">technofeudalism</a> is not distinct from capitalism but that since
capitalism's valence is unassailable, perhaps a new word can be more
successfully attacked. (The less generous interpretation is that he
wants credit for a catchy idea.)</p>
<p>In the book, Varoufakis is personable. He's likeable. His writing is
friendly, and his stories about his father are charming. And he
<a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2024/04/01/has-capitalism-been-replaced-by-technofeudalism">likes Star Trek</a>, which is a great sign of character.</p>
<p>His technofeudalism refers to the monopolistic market capture,
"moats," and rent-seeking of (mostly) big tech. But this is just
capitalism as usual; <a href="/20240625-titan_by_chernow/">Rockefeller</a> would be on board. Thinking of
capitalism as pro-competition is ridiculous.</p>
<p>He says some things about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historical_materialism">historical materialism</a>, which is kind of
interesting. I buy into the importance of technology for enabling big
structural changes to standard of living, for example. (See also:
<a href="/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>)</p>
<p>There's also something interesting about separating the exchange or
commodity value vs. the experiential value of things (like work).
Varoufakis says employers profit because they pay commodity price for
workers' time but get the "experiential" (real?) value of their work.
In some sense, a company pays out less than it takes in, if it can,
but I'm not sure this decomposition holds in a meaningful way.
Generally I think Marx focused on labor too much in a similar way to
how physiocrats focused on agriculture (land) too much.</p>
<p>Varoufakis is a little too weird. His use of Amazon Alexa as an
example is unfortunate, given how it's largely a failed technology. He
doesn't seem technologically literate when he talks about ML, which
makes me wonder how good he is in fields I know less about. Like
Bernie, he's concerned about Black Rock/Vanguard/State Street, but I
think this concern is mostly silly. And he's into balancing trade
between nations. (Is this mercantilism?)</p>
<p>So while I'm not with him everywhere, I have a lot of respect for at
least proposing some alternative. (He summarizes his ideas from
<em>Another Now</em>.) And that may be the whole point of Technofeudalism -
getting more people to look at his ideas. It worked on me.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241109-technofeudalism_by_varoufakis/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241109-technofeudalism_by_varoufakis/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Utopia for Realists, by Bregman</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Utopia_for_Realists">Utopia for Realists</a> is a more accessible <a href="/20240929-inventing_the_future_by_srnicek_and_williams/" title="(Audio) Inventing the Future, by Srnicek and Williams">Inventing the Future</a>:
it's in favor of UBI and less work, against neoliberalism/<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mont_Pelerin_Society" title="Mont Pelerin Society">MPS</a>, and
Utopia's "underdog socialism" is like Inventing's "folk politics." It
differs slightly in being explicitly for open borders, like
<a href="/20191109-open_borders_by_caplan_and_weinersmith/" title="Open Borders, by Caplan and Weinersmith">Caplan</a>, and there are some other differences in focus and
examples. The original Dutch title is literally "free money for
everyone."</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Work is the refuge of people who have nothing better to do.” (Oscar
Wilde, quoted page 68)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think Bregman is too concerned with preserving the appearance of the
Puritan work ethic. Like many, he seems to think that giving people
money has to be shown not to reduce hours of work. This is silly and
backward. We should be trying to get people to stop working for pay.</p>
<p>I think it's fine to pull in <a href="/20180218-scarcity_by_sendhil_mullainathan_and_eldar_shafir/" title="Scarcity by Sendhil Mullainathan and Eldar Shafir">Mullainathan and Shafir</a>, as he does,
on the downsides of scarcity, but the reasoning should be that it is
unjust to let people be in bad situations. The trap here is getting
into an argument about who is deserving. If we have to prove that
people are deserving, we've lost already.</p>
<p>Some neat stuff:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cockaigne">Cockaigne</a>: "a land of plenty in medieval myth"</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speenhamland_system">Speenhamland</a>: 1795 "basic income" program, still argued over:
   Did it suppress wages? Did it increase sloth? More children? Loose
   morals?</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mincome">Mincome</a>: "Manitoba Basic Annual Income Experiment" (1970s)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physiocracy">Physiocracy</a>: some kind of economic theory that valued the
   productivity of land/agriculture (over generic labor, etc.)</li>
</ul>
<p>And there's a chapter on GDP (etc.) which made me think that one could
teach a whole course on the downsides or risks of data and data
science, much as in <a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/" title="The Tyranny of Metrics, by Muller">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The RAND Corporation, an influential think tank, foresaw a future
in which just 2% of the population would be able to produce
everything society needed.” (page 18)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But this cites not a RAND study, but “Hillel Ruskin (ed.), Leisure,
Toward a Theory and Policy (1984), p. 152,” and I don't see that
online, so it'll take me a while to check.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Not until 1978 was the plan for a basic income shelved once and for
all, however, following a fatal discovery upon publication of the
final results of the Seattle experiment. One finding in particular
grabbed everybody’s attention: The number of divorces had jumped
more than 50%. Interest in this statistic quickly overshadowed all
the other outcomes, such as better school performance and
improvements in health. A basic income, evidently, gave women too
much independence.</p>
<p>Ten years later, a reanalysis of the data revealed that a
statistical error had been made; in reality, there had been no
change in the divorce rate at all.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The citation here is <a href="https://www.irp.wisc.edu/publications/dps/pdfs/dp85788.pdf">Cain and Wissoker</a>... I've heard about this
divorce finding before ("It's bad!" "It's good!") but I don't think
I've heard about this nullifying result... Why not? I'm not digging
very deep here, but Bregman seems quite Pollyannaish in general
throughout the book, which makes him seem less reliable in general on
specifics.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The free books had made no difference. Test scores showed no
improvement.” (page 91)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But this isn't quite what the <a href="http://www.econ.yale.edu/~egcenter/infoconf/kremer_paper.pdf">study</a> said - and I didn't even read
beyond the abstract! "However, for those students in the top quintile
of the distribution of initial academic achievement, the program
raised test scores by at least 0.2 standard deviations."</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241102-utopia_for_realists_by_bregman/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241102-utopia_for_realists_by_bregman/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) How the World Works, by Chomsky</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>“How the World Works” is a collection of four Chomsky books:</p>
<ul>
<li>What Uncle Sam Really Wants</li>
<li>The Prosperous Few and the Restless Many</li>
<li>Secrets, Lies and Democracy</li>
<li>The Common Good</li>
</ul>
<p>Chomsky says the world is violent. Very violent! He agrees with
<a href="/20240825-principles_changing_world_order_dalio/" title="Principles for dealing with the changing world order, by Dalio">Dalio</a> that international law means little to power. He describes
the Pentagon as an economic stimulus mechanism, which I thought was an
interesting framing.</p>
<p>I first heard about Chomsky in connection with linguistics. The only
linguistic thing he talks about here is the idea of language being
debased, in a similar sense to Orwellian <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newspeak">Newspeak</a>, making it hard
to talk about certain things. I've felt something like this in trying
to talk about a post-work world. To stop selling your labor is called
"retiring," which connotes a kind of withdrawal, which I don't like.
One might also say that to retire is to "stop working," because "work"
can only mean "sell your labor," even if you carry on doing things you
think are useful and productive. It's a similar frustration to that of
the "stay-at-home" parent, who is engaged in effortful activity over
40 hours a week and yet said to "not work." (These aren't Chomsky's
examples.)</p>
<p>And Chomsky mentions interesting things here and there... I don't
think I'd known about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Party_(United_States)">New Party</a>, which continues in part as
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive_Dane">Progressive Dane</a>, a party in Dane County, where I went to college.
I had heard of Progressive Dane, I think, but I wasn't aware of its
historical context.</p>
<p>Some more interesting bits quoted below...</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<h3>“expanding the floor of the cage”</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“So Argentina is “minimizing the state”—cutting down public
expenditures, the way our government is doing, but much more
extremely. Of course, when you minimize the state, you maximize
something else—and it isn’t popular control. What gets maximized is
private power, domestic and foreign.</p>
<p>I met with a very lively anarchist movement in Buenos Aires, and
with other anarchist groups as far away as northeastern Brazil,
where nobody even knew they existed. We had a lot of discussions
about these matters. They recognize that they have to try to use the
state—even though they regard it as totally illegitimate.</p>
<p>The reason is perfectly obvious: When you eliminate the one
institutional structure in which people can participate to some
extent—namely the government—you’re simply handing over power to
unaccountable private tyrannies that are much worse. So you have to
make use of the state, all the time recognizing that you ultimately
want to eliminate it.</p>
<p>Some of the rural workers in Brazil have an interesting slogan. They
say their immediate task is “expanding the floor of the cage.” They
understand that they’re trapped inside a cage, but realize that
protecting it when it’s under attack from even worse predators on
the outside, and extending the limits of what the cage will allow,
are both essential preliminaries to dismantling it. If they attack
the cage directly when they’re so vulnerable, they’ll get murdered.</p>
<p>That’s something anyone ought to be able to understand who can keep
two ideas in their head at once, but some people here in the US tend
to be so rigid and doctrinaire that they don’t understand the point.
But unless the left here is willing to tolerate that level of
complexity, we’re not going to be of any use to people who are
suffering and need our help—or, for that matter, to ourselves.</p>
<p>In Brazil and Argentina, you can discuss these issues even with
people in the highest political echelons, and with elite journalists
and intellectuals. They may not agree with you, but at least they
understand what you’re talking about.” (page 174)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3>“rationality and science”</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“In the 1930s, left intellectuals were involved in worker education
and writing books like <em>Mathematics for the Millions.</em> They
considered it an ordinary, minimal responsibility of privileged
people to help others who’d been deprived of formal education to
enter into high culture.</p>
<p>Today’s counterparts of these 1930s left intellectuals are telling
people, <em>You don’t have to know anything. It’s all junk, a power
play, a white male conspiracy. Forget about rationality and
science.</em> In other words, put those tools in the hands of your
enemies. Let them monopolize everything that works and makes sense.</p>
<p>Plenty of very honorable left intellectuals think this tendency is
liberatory, but I think they’re wrong. A lot of personal
correspondence on related topics between me and my close, valued old
friend Marc Raskin has been published in a book of his. There were
similar interchanges in Z Papers in 1992–93, both with Marc and a
lot of other people with whom I basically feel in sympathy, but with
whom I differ very sharply on this issue.” (page 194)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This "Z" thing still exists, as <a href="https://znetwork.org/" title="ZNetwork - Independent Left News, Analysis, Vision and Strategy">ZNetwork</a>.</p>
<hr>
<h3>“the South Commission”</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“As recently as the early 1990s, the South Commission, which
represented the governments of nonaligned countries, came out with a
very important critique of the antidemocratic, neoliberal model
that’s being forced on the Third World. (The commission included
pretty conservative people, like Indonesia’s development minister.)</p>
<p>They published a book that called for a new world order (they
introduced the term before George [H. W.] Bush did) based on
democracy, justice, development and so on. The book wasn’t
obscure—it was published by Oxford University Press. I wrote about
it, but I couldn’t find much else. They subsequently published
another book of essays commenting on the first one, and I’ve never
seen a reference to that either.</p>
<p>The South Commission happened to represent most of the world’s
population, but the story they were telling just isn’t one the
Western media wanted to hear. So the “new world order” we learned
about was Bush’s, not the one advocated by the South Commission,
which reflects the interests of most of the people of the world.
Back in the 1950s, there were Nehru, Nasser, Tito, Nkrumah, Sukarno
and others…” (page 203)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3>“Here’s what I’m doing. What do you think about it?”</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“Over the years, I <em>have</em> noticed a very striking difference between
talks I give to more or less elite audiences, and meetings and
discussions I have with less privileged people. A while back I was
in a town in Massachusetts at a meeting set up by very good local
organizers in the urban community—people who were pretty poor, even
by world standards. Not long before that, I spent time in the West
Bengal countryside. Then I was in Colombia, talking to human rights
activists who are working under horrifying conditions.</p>
<p>In places like that, people never ask, <em>What should I do?</em> They say,
<em>Here’s what I’m doing. What do you think about it?</em> Maybe they’d
like reactions or suggestions, but they’re already dealing with the
problem. They’re not sitting around waiting for a magic answer,
which doesn’t exist.</p>
<p>When I speak to elite audiences, I constantly get asked, <em>What’s the
solution?</em> If I say obvious things like <em>Pick your cause and go
volunteer for a group that’s working on it,</em> that’s never the answer
they want. They want some sort of magic key that will solve
everything quickly, overwhelmingly and effectively. There are no
such solutions. There are only the kind that people are working on
in Massachusetts towns, in self-governing villages in India, at the
Jesuit Center in Colombia.” (page 206)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241026-how_the_world_works_by_chomsky/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241026-how_the_world_works_by_chomsky/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) After Work, by Hester and Srnicek</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Here's a feminist post-scarcity <a href="https://www.versobooks.com/products/496-after-work" title="After Work: A History of the Home and the Fight for Free Time by Helen Hester and Nick Srnicek">book</a> pointing out that abolishing
paid work won't automatically eliminate unpaid work. There's quite a
bit of unpaid work, and people may or may not want to do it.
Interesting history and ideas on what to do about it.</p>
<p>Did you know there was a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wages_for_housework" title="Wikipedia: Wages for housework">Wages for Housework</a> movement in the 70s?</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.png"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“As we know, domestic realism was not ultimately overthrown by the
communalism of the separatists or the hippies. While some
communities are still operational, Drop City and the vast majority
of initiatives like it proved to be relatively ephemeral
experiments, failing to outlive their moment of sociosexual
upheaval. This may well have been because, as sites of exodus, they
were not always effective at ensuring their own scalability. They
were often intended as prefigurative spaces, aiming to offer a taste
of post-suburban utopia in the here and now (or at least, a utopia
for the young, the healthy, the able bodied, and the middle class
with minimal caring responsibilities – that specific and limited
range of people who might be best able to thrive in a space like
Drop City). As such, they consciously operated as enclaves within
the society from which they sought to withdraw – bastions of
alternative values which were yet to flourish elsewhere – and the
interventions they staged were in certain respects hyperlocal to the
point of being site-specific. The ‘simple positing and practising of
a new world is insufficient to overcome’ the structural forces
preventing its generalisation.129 Or, as Mike Davis puts it,
‘demonstration projects in … rich countries will not save the
world’.” (page 114)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20241019-after_work_by_hester_and_srnicek/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20241019-after_work_by_hester_and_srnicek/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Inventing the Future, by Srnicek and Williams</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inventing_the_Future:_Postcapitalism_and_a_World_Without_Work">Inventing the Future</a>: Postcapitalism and a World Without Work is
by far the best exposition of a post-scarcity direction that I've
seen. The criticism of folk politics as impotent in important ways
because of its focus on immediacy is incisive. The authors invite us
to grow up and construct the world we want to live in.</p>
<p>I enjoyed their alternate interpretation of the phrase "resistance is
futile," emphasizing the difference between fighting some external
actor and being an active builder. Trying to stop someone else
(political, corporate, etc.) may or may not succeed, but regardless it
will not create a better alternative. If all we do is resist, we never
make anything new.</p>
<p>The authors demand full automation, as in
<a href="/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/" title="Fully Automated Luxury Communism, by Bastani">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>, and indeed Bastani might be
counted among the second-hand dealers in these ideas (though he has
contributions as well).</p>
<p>There's a bunch in the book on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mont_Pelerin_Society">Mont Pelerin Society</a> and the
authors recommend a leftist "ecology of organizations" might achieve
similar success. They mention the <a href="https://neweconomics.org/">New Economics Foundation</a>, but
otherwise I don't know a lot of organizations that might be part of
such an ecology.</p>
<hr>
<p>The authors advocate for higher wages. Higher wages can be good for
the people who get them, but the main focus is on higher wages
encouraging more automation. The authors also advocate for Universal
Basic Income (UBI). They note some challenges with UBI, but I don't
think they completely resolve a conflict here.</p>
<p>What happens to (market-based) wages if people have UBI? Probably lots
of jobs don't have takers any more. This must be the mechanism the
authors are thinking of, and why they emphasize that UBI must really
be enough to live on. But surely some jobs would be doable for <em>lower</em>
wages, if people sort of enjoy them to begin with.</p>
<p>There's no mention of inflation in connection with UBI, which
continues to concern me. How can it work without price controls or
similar? If everyone has more money, surely rent goes up, grocery
prices go up, etc. etc. just as we saw during the pandemic.</p>
<p>As with Universal Basic Services (UBS) I have to think that everything
currently sold on the market would have to edge away from being sold
for profit. A program of UBI can be undone by inflation, and indeed
the goal should be for deflation, as we achieve extreme supply, prices
go to zero, and eventually money can be retired. Postcapitalism is in
the subtitle, but there aren't many details here.</p>
<hr>
<h3>The book is better than the movie</h3>
<p>The book is not written in a broadly accessible style. It's inside
baseball for academics who appreciate Marxist criticism and don't
blink at phrases like "reproductive labor." So I was excited to hear
about a 2020 documentary based on the book, thinking it might speak to
a broader audience.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LY44I9P_QZU">film</a> is feature length, but the style is the unwatchable,
seizure-inducing kind you might walk quickly past in an art museum.
Voices read snippets from the book and other sources, sometimes
reminiscent of Waiting for Godot. Several times we watch sex toys
shimmy on a grey Lego baseplate. It's hard to imagine a movie that
could contribute less to spreading the message of Inventing the
Future. Avoid.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“A politics without demands is simply a collection of aimless
bodies.” (page 105)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One criticism of the book might be that it gets to demands but doesn't
go much farther in terms of concrete mechanisms for achieving them.
Four day work week! Full automation! Okay, but what can people do
apart from writing their senators?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Famously, Oscar Wilde once said that the problem with socialism was
that it took up too many evenings.” (page 177)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't think I'd heard this before; it's good, isn't it? Most people
just want to live their lives. Hence problems, hence opportunities.</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240929-inventing_the_future_by_srnicek_and_williams/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240929-inventing_the_future_by_srnicek_and_williams/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Fully Automated Luxury Communism, by Bastani</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Ridiculing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_End_of_History_and_the_Last_Man" title="The End of History and the Last Man">The End of History</a> and rejecting
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capitalist_Realism" title="Capitalist Realism">Capitalist Realism</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aaron_Bastani" title="Aaron Bastani">Bastani</a> says Marx was ahead of his time:
communism is only now becoming technologically possible. While
Rushkoff <a href="/20240519-survival_of_the_richest_by_rushkoff/" title="Survival of the Richest, by Rushkoff">is</a> anti-growth, Bastani was saying (even before ChatGPT)
that technology will save us. He says we should demand
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fully_Automated_Luxury_Communism" title="Fully Automated Luxury Communism">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>.</p>
<p>A lot of the book is detail on how technology is advancing (or may
advance) to produce "extreme supply." A surprisingly large amount is
about mining asteroids. Predictions on driverless cars and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finless_Foods">Finless Foods</a>, for example, seem premature. (The book only came
out five years ago; is it too early to judge?)</p>
<p>I think Bastani is right that the future he imagines is not
inevitable: it depends on political choices. He mostly assumes that
technological development is inevitable. I'm less sure about that.
They are related, of course.</p>
<p>Bastani has some recommendations. He likes municipal protectionism as
in <a href="https://atlasofthefuture.org/project/the-cleveland-model/">the Cleveland model</a>. He favors <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_basic_services">Universal Basic Services</a>
over <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_basic_income">Universal Basic Income</a>. (I tend to agree; can we also get
Universal Basic Stuff?) He wants a "One Planet Tax" on carbon, to fund
renewable energy in the global south via National Energy Investment
Banks, and socialized finance for autonomous state-owned companies.</p>
<p>I don't know that Bastani is a great spokesperson, and the book is to
some extent just something to put the title on. But still kind of a
neat book?</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>Summarizing the five crises from pages 22-23:</p>
<ol>
<li>Climate change</li>
<li>Resource scarcity</li>
<li>Societal aging</li>
<li>Global poor / "unnecessariat"</li>
<li>Technological unemployment</li>
</ol>
<p>(These last two, and maybe even the last three, don't seem <em>that</em>
different...)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Now we must build a workers’ party against work – one whose
politics are populist, democratic and open, all while fighting the
establishment which, through its power over civil society and the
state, won’t rest in ensuring FALC never comes to pass." (pag 194)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Furthermore, preferring UBS to UBI makes a great deal of sense
within the context of the Third Disruption and the turn to extreme
supply. As the price for everything shifts ever closer to zero, this
will imperil production for exchange and profit, meaning the price
mechanism is an increasingly inefficient way of allocating
resources. What is more UBS begins the work of communism in the
present, articulating resources necessary to a decent life – from
housing to health- care – as human rights rather than potential
sources of profit. Necessitous people are not free people, and the
UBS decisively ends such necessity." (page 226)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This references Roosevelt's quotation of "Necessitous men are not free
men" in the 1944 State of the Union (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Bill_of_Rights">Second Bill of Rights</a>).</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"While FALC is situated within a transformation as seismic as that
of the arrival of agriculture, its concrete politics consist in
specific, readily identifiable demands: a break with neoliberalism,
a shift towards worker-owned production, a state-financed transition
to renewable energy and universal services – rightly identified as
human rights – placed beyond commodity exchange and profit." (page
243)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240921-fully_automated_luxury_communism_by_bastani/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) On the Edge, by Nate Silver</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>When Trump won the 2016 election despite 538's needle showing less
than 50% for him, it split the world. There were people who gave Nate
Silver a hard time about it ("the village") and people who still
thought he was cool ("the river"). Since then, Silver has been hanging
out with his buddies, having a good time playing poker, and he can
write a book about whatever he wants, so here it is. It reads,
unintentionally, as a warning about the risks of seeing the world only
in calculating, risk-taking terms.</p>
<hr>
<p>Silver tries to explain why there are more men than women playing
poker. He suggests that men are more aggressive, and aggression makes
you better at poker. I think Silver misses the big picture: It isn't
really a good idea to play poker in the first place. It's anti-social.
Elsewhere, Silver does explain that the poker ecosystem requires
"fish" for people to take money from. Why are there more men playing
poker? Because they're dumb!</p>
<p>(There is an apparent contradiction here, in that I myself enjoy the
occasional social poker game, and have even played to make money at
casinos a couple times. But I still believe that if you're
consistently playing to make money, it is a kind of legal theft, a
kind of con, as bad as the casino itself. The divide between a
friendly game and stealing wallets from drunk strangers is not always
perfectly clear, but I think it exists.)</p>
<hr>
<p>Silver comes closest to explicitly warning against "the river" way of
thinking in his extended coverage of Sam Bankman-Fried (SBF) and FTX.
He thinks SBF's problem (one of them) was that he bet too big. Silver
references the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kelly_criterion">Kelly criterion</a> for bet-sizing and suggests that
SBF was willing to make bets that were too large.</p>
<p>I think Silver missed another aspect, which is that even very small
bets can be bad bets to make - even when they're positive EV. The
thing to consider is the probability of ending up better off or worse
off than currently. Even if the EV is very positive, if the chance of
"hitting it" is low and the chance of getting worse off is high, it's
very sensible to not make that bet.</p>
<p>I wrote up my way of thinking about this a while ago as
<a href="/2012/06/04/expected-value-is-not-useful-for-making/">Expected value is not useful for making decisions about lottery tickets</a>.
See also notes on expected value in connection with
<a href="/20200925-how_not_to_be_wrong_by_ellenberg/">How Not to Be Wrong, by Ellenberg</a> and
<a href="/20210502-the_scout_mindset_by_galef/">The Scout Mindset, by Galef</a>. A related question to ask is:
<a href="/20181204-worth_doing_even_if_it_fails/">Is it worth doing even if it fails?</a></p>
<hr>
<p>At one point Silver quotes Oppenheimer:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“It is a profound and necessary truth that the deep things in
science are not found because they are useful; they are found
because it was possible to find them.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I like this quote. It reminds me of
<a href="/20221105-why_greatness_cannot_be_planned_by_stanley_and_lehman/">Why greatness cannot be planned (Stanley and Lehman)</a>. We often
expand our knowledge along the current frontiers and only later
identify the applications. See also
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Unreasonable_Effectiveness_of_Mathematics_in_the_Natural_Sciences">The Unreasonable Effectiveness of Mathematics in the Natural Sciences</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Silver talks some about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secular_stagnation">secular stagnation</a>, which reminded me of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rise_and_Fall_of_American_Growth" title="The Rise and Fall of American Growth, by Robert J. Gordon">The Rise and Fall of American Growth</a> and that despite claims of
stagnation <a href="/20240407-mortality_rates_have_improved/">Mortality rates have improved</a> without pause until the
present (apart from the recent impact of Covid). Of course Silver is
really just trying to talk about AI and whether it will kill us all.
(He thinks it might.)</p>
<hr>
<p>Silver tries to conclude with some sort of morality or politics, but
it feels bolted on. When he was talking about SBF and being critical
of Effective Altruism and Rationalism, I had some thought that perhaps
Silver was self-aware and the conclusion of the book was going to be a
big reveal that he had realized that "the river" was itself a risk to
humanity. But I don't think he got there. So while he does say some
things about the risks of quantification (shades of
<a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>) Silver is still mostly just hanging out
with his friends and following his interests. Good for him?</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240915-on_the_edge_by_silver/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240915-on_the_edge_by_silver/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How much money do I need to retire? by Tresidder</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Tresidder is in some ways likeable and reasonable, and in other ways
sort of a skinny-FIRE <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Kiyosaki">Robert Kiyosaki</a> who is "retired" but still
shills constantly in the direction of his $1,750 <a href="https://members.financialmentor.com/product/step-3/">online course</a>
like he read <a href="/2011/03/14/listened-to-four-hour-work-week/">The 4-hour work week</a>.</p>
<p>Most of the book is criticism. On page one we get "Traditional
retirement planning has failed." It all feels mostly like a sales
tactic: His approach is the one that works!</p>
<p>He spends a lot of time criticizing Monte Carlo methods. His
explanation of the approach in general is so bad it must be
deliberately so. Unsavory rhetoric.</p>
<p>There is a reasonable argument buried in his hate for MC methods: He
thinks they don't go far enough in considering more extreme possible
futures, while their confidence intervals make them <em>seem</em> all-knowing
when they're not. They generally won't model Social Security
disappearing altogether, for example, but they'll still allocate 100%
of probability, as if there's a 0% chance of these sorts of "extreme"
futures.</p>
<p>So his solution is a sort of manual Monte Carlo, putting lots of weird
things into (his, of course) calculators.</p>
<p>He also correctly, I think, focuses on the human reality of living
just one life, not a probability distribution of lives, so what we
really need is to eliminate extreme downside risk as much as possible.</p>
<p>How much of the retirement planning literature is just confusion about
inflation? Possibly a lot, I think.</p>
<p>It turns out his solution is mostly from the skinny-FIRE school of
thought: Spend less! Then there's the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Kiyosaki">Robert Kiyosaki</a> part: Cash
flow! Real estate!</p>
<p>I object to telling people to become landlords like it's easy, good,
and risk-free. The general idea of not dipping into your capital seems
fine though. But now are we just back to the original methods he
despises, only worse off because we're imagining the capital is safe
(and even grows with inflation)? I think yes.</p>
<p>There are some good vibes about enjoying your life, and maybe his
recommendation to consider a longevity annuity is reasonable, but for
the most part this book is more an advertisement than a resource.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Every act of creation is first an act of destruction." (page 21)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think this is supposed to be Picasso? But his usage is unattributed?
Sort of weird, given how much he likes to include well-known quotes
otherwise.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>(Regarding long-term increases in life expectancy) "There is some
debate about this statistic with some people claiming the gains came
from reductions in infant mortality." (page 46)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is not a debate! See, for example,
<a href="/20200806-life_expectancy_is_historically_misleading/">Life expectancy is historically misleading </a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>investment returns over longer time periods of seven years or more
are not random. (page 69)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is part of his idea that he can time the market based on P/E.
Valuations aren't nothing, but his takes are a bit much.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"let’s apply conservative estimates by cutting my pension and social
security in half so that my combined income sources provide just
$15,000 per year instead of $50,000." (page 129)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>How does this make sense?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Different tax rates would only be marginally meaningful if your
income fell dramatically after retirement. Are you planning on
poverty or financial security?)" (page 142)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's sort of amazing that he would say this. Your effective tax rate
could easily be cut in half at retirement if you're earning a bunch
and saving most of it before retirement.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"“Today’s scientists have substituted mathematics for experiments,
and they wander off through equation after equation, and eventually
build a structure which has no relation to reality.”-Nikola Tesla,
inventor" (page 149)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I do like this quote.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Complicated math is usually more symptomatic of covering up
ignorance than expressing wisdom." (page 192)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also not terrible.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Retirement planning done right is really about life planning, not
calculating magic numbers." (page 151)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Every dollar bill you spend in your twenties is like spending a
hundred dollar bill in retirement." (page 179)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What? Really?</p>
<p>This is assuming 10% annual return over 45 years? And it's nominal?
(With inflation, more like $20 purchasing power?)</p>
<p>I guess he's just trying to be dramatic, but I would rather he not be
dramatic with numbers.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The main thing to note is how every other model relies on history
to be your guide. This cash flow-based model is the only approach
that requires no historical analysis because it is entirely based on
numbers fully known in the present. This is important because the
past is not the future." (page 199)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Tresidder paints "cash flow" methods as immune from risk, and
generally somehow automatically protected from inflation. This isn't
the case!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Lifestyle planning isn’t really a separate retirement model per
se." (page 208)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(The book is structured and presented as if it is.)</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240910-how_much_money_do_i_need_to_retire_by_tresidder/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240910-how_much_money_do_i_need_to_retire_by_tresidder/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Bullshit Jobs, by Graeber</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
<p>“There is only one success – to be able to spend your life in your
own way.” (Christopher Morley)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Graeber">Graeber</a> had a <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180807024932/http://strikemag.org/bullshit-jobs/">popular article</a> and this is the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullshit_Jobs">book version</a>. As with <a href="/20240519-survival_of_the_richest_by_rushkoff/">Rushkoff's</a>, the titular concept is
mostly a hook. I'm more interested in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Critique_of_work">critique of work</a>
generally.</p>
<p>The first part of the book, most directly on "bullshit jobs" and
related surveys and interviews, isn't very good, compared to Graeber's
<a href="/20240906-debt_by_graeber/" title="(Audio) Debt: The first 5,000 years, by Graeber">Debt</a>. He wants to have it both ways, for one thing: We must trust
the people who say their jobs are bullshit, and at the same time not
trust people who say their jobs aren't.</p>
<p>Then there's the definition of a bullshit job, which is never done
quite consistently. I think it's supposed to be jobs that don't make
any difference (if they aren't done, nothing changes). But this bleeds
in at least two directions: Jobs where we may not <em>like</em> the
difference they make, and jobs that <em>wouldn't</em> be necessary if things
were set up differently.</p>
<p>So Graeber repeatedly criticizes Obama for using job preservation as a
reason to not completely upend the health care system. If the current
employees were all sent home, it would be bad: people wouldn't get
insurance reimbursement, etc. The current jobs are only (or primarily)
"bullshit" to Graeber because he thinks a single payer (or similar)
system could take care of people with fewer employees.</p>
<p>And while I know part of Graeber's point is to critique the Puritan
work ethic and "middle class thinking" in general, many of his
malcontent subjects just aren't very sympathetic.</p>
<p>Graeber did an academic thesis on "life cycle service," the historical
practice in northern Europe in which a young person would spend seven
or so years as an apprentice or servant, with some other family,
collecting some pay until they could set off on their own. I thought
this was interesting in relation to the modern idea of FIRE (Financial
Independence, Retire Early) in which a person similarly works for
others until they have enough money to be independent and then does
whatever they want.</p>
<p>Graeber talks a lot about "spiritual violence," and while this may be
worse when a job feels pointless (see also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sayre%27s_law">Sayre's Law</a>) I don't
think it's unique to "bullshit jobs" but common to any job that has
you doing what you really don't want to do. Hence the Morley quote
about success as being "able to spend your life in your own way."
People really like self-determination.</p>
<p>Graeber does connect at least a little bit with Black's
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Abolition_of_Work">Abolition of Work</a> and the idea given book form in
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fully_Automated_Luxury_Communism">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>. He spends some time on work as
caring work rather than factory production. And he also comes out in
support of UBI.</p>
<p>(Oh right - I read <a href="/20180125-no_more_work_by_james_livingston/" title="No More Work by James Livingston">No more work</a> back in 2018...)</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240907-bullshit_jobs_by_graeber/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240907-bullshit_jobs_by_graeber/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Debt: The first 5,000 years, by Graeber</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Graeber">Graeber</a> doesn't like debt, in the modern quantified, financial
sense. Also he thinks people are wrong about the history of money, and
that we should listen to anthropologists more. Graeber's equation is
something like "obligation + measurement + violence = debt."</p>
<p>A smattering of his ideas as I remember them:</p>
<ul>
<li>The standard economics story of money (as arising because barter is
   too hard) is silly because people hardly ever barter in the first
   place, except sometimes with strangers.</li>
<li>The standard economics story of money starting with coinage, then
   later developing debt instruments (see also <a href="/20240825-principles_changing_world_order_dalio/" title="(Audio) Principles for dealing with the changing world order, by Dalio">Dalio</a>, "money as
   starting from metal, then notes exchangeable for metal, then fiat
   money") is silly because ideas and methods of debt come <em>first</em>.</li>
<li>The moralism of "always paying your debts" in culture and language.</li>
<li>No single theory of money (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chartalism">Chartalism</a>, etc.) is right on its
   own because "money has no essence" and money is just one piece of a
   big evolving world. (Similarly, Graeber has no single thesis on
   debt.)</li>
<li>"Baseline communism" refers to the natural "from each according to
   his ability, to each according to his needs" that we have in real
   human relations, like feeding a child or asking for someone to hand
   you something.</li>
<li>Debt as two equals agreeing to no longer be equal: Now <em>you</em> owe
   <em>me</em>. (In the extreme: debt peonage.)</li>
<li>The difference of kind that comes from quantification: Not just
   owing me a favor, but owing me $47.39. The relation to
   dehumanization, as when slavery puts a price on a person, which is
   only possible by removing or denying their complex real
   (unquantifiable) value. (Reminds me of <a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/" title="The Tyranny of Metrics, by Muller">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>.)</li>
<li>The necessity of violence to make people pay back debts, as when
   military power stands behind the IMF.</li>
<li>Occasional hints of primitivism or anarcho-primitivism.</li>
<li>And really, shouldn't we get rid of capitalism?</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240906-debt_by_graeber/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240906-debt_by_graeber/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Principles for dealing with the changing world order, by Dalio</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray_Dalio">Ray Dalio</a> likes gold, doesn't like when <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/money-printer-go-brrr">money printer go brrr</a>,
and does like China. He also likes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Kissinger">Kissinger</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genghis_Khan">Genghis Khan</a>.
Dalio says some reasonable and some interesting things, but it isn't
clear he <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/11/01/business/how-does-the-worlds-largest-hedge-fund-really-make-its-money.html" title="How Does the World’s Largest Hedge Fund Really Make Its Money?">practices</a> what he preaches, or that he's right.</p>
<p><img alt="bump" src="bump.png"></p>
<p>Dalio has a bunch of signals and a framework of big cycles organizing
history. It's a little bit <a href="/20200714-foundation_trilogy/" title="Asimov's Foundation trilogy">psychohistory</a> and a little bit
<a href="/20200728-technological_revolutions_and_financial_capital/" title="Technological Revolutions and Financial Capital, by Perez">cycle-finding</a>. For Dalio, the biggest cycle is the debt cycle,
followed by cycles of internal disorder and external disorder. He
describes money as starting from metal, then notes exchangeable for
metal, then fiat money.</p>
<p><img alt="empires" src="empires.png"></p>
<p>For Dalio, the step after fiat money is collapse. He cares a lot about
whether a currency is The Reserve Currency. Combining his signals, he
gets charts that show the rise and fall of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_guilder">Dutch guilder</a>, the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pound_sterling">British pound</a>, and (soon) the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US dollar</a>. China is ascendant,
never mind that their currency has been fiat longer than the dollar.</p>
<p>Dalio says he's identifying timeless principles of cause and effect.
Is he right? Historical causality is hard to test, but there are at
least a few problems with Dalio's claims.</p>
<p>For most of history, the idea of a reserve currency hasn't really made
sense. The modern monetary system is in this light novel, not
timeless. Dalio has a narrow understanding of money compared to the
anthroplogical view in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debt:_The_First_5,000_Years">Debt: The First 5,000 Years</a>, for example.</p>
<p>It's hard to find falsifiable predictions in Dalio's science. He
admits to not having good tools for predicting <em>when</em> any given thing
might happen. In this sense, his whole system is basically noticing
that things have fallen apart in the past and concluding that things
could fall apart in the future. It isn't even wrong.</p>
<p>Looking at the charts, I'm reminded of a common tension in data work:
Is data leading to theory, or is theory leading to data? Data can be
found to support most theories; what was the process here? It's rather
easy to imagine that Dalio's employees are skilled in finding what he
thinks is there.</p>
<p>Not that Dalio hasn't looked at history and so on. The
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriottentijd">Patriot movement</a> in the Netherlands does kind of feel like it
rhymes with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Make_America_Great_Again">MAGA</a> energy. He knows about
<a href="https://deloitte.wsj.com/riskandcompliance/china-spotlight-triangular-debt-considerations-1413864154">triangular debt in China</a>. He's even concerned about inequality,
though mostly because it can lead to wealth-destroying crises.</p>
<p>Does Dalio have the courage of his convictions? Perhaps not. He
frequently comes off as defensive, and digresses substantially into
his concerns about public scrutiny of the prominent. The historical
theory he seems to hold most instinctively is a great man theory in
which he and the people he talks to are great; he sounds like Trump
talking about how he knows the best people.</p>
<p>If you think your ideas are timeless, you may be right about what
happens next, but you probably won't predict things that have never
happened before. So Dalio is limited to predicting rearrangements of
the world order, not substantially new things. If Marx thought much
change was inevitable, Dalio thinks real change is fundamentally
impossible, that recurrence is the nature of society.</p>
<p>So Dalio picks China as the new king of the hill.</p>
<p>I'm curious about many of the things Dalio talks about. What causes
what in the world? How do we operate in reality? What lessons can we
learn from history? I have to think Dalio believes he's sincere about
his program. At the same time, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/11/01/business/how-does-the-worlds-largest-hedge-fund-really-make-its-money.html" title="How Does the World’s Largest Hedge Fund Really Make Its Money?">reporting</a> suggests his ability to
follow his own advice is as constrained as his ability to imagine a
better world. For all the lip service to evolution, Dalio doesn't seem
to be its exemplar.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240825-principles_changing_world_order_dalio/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240825-principles_changing_world_order_dalio/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
