<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>Social Security is a great deal</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Social Security in its current form pays out, with no volatility, a
perpetual inflation-adjusted annual yield of up to 51% on what
individuals pay in tax. 15% is common, and 5% is the worst you can
get.</p>
<p>I know it's not really an individual investment; younger Americans are
supposed to be supporting older ones and so on. But I had no idea how
good Social Security is for recipients, relative to how much they put
in.</p>
<p>Social Security pays out a percentage of your income. In monthly
terms, it's 90% of up to $1,115/month, then 32% up to $6,721/month,
then 15% up to $13,350/month. These are 2023 dollars and give the
maximum full retirement age monthly payment of $3,792.</p>
<p>Full retirement age for me is 67. If I start collecting Social
Security early, at 62, payments are locked in at 70% of the “full”
value. If instead I delay until 70, payments are 124%.</p>
<p>Social Security is based on inflation-adjusted income over your 35
highest-earning years. (If you're working your 36th year and earning
no more than any other year, this calculation won't apply.)</p>
<p>The last factor we need is the 6.2% tax you pay in to Social Security.
Your employer also separately pays as much, but most people don't
consider that part of their income.</p>
<p>So the best “return” you can get is if you have lifetime earnings so
far under $468,300 and you plan to start collecting Social Security as
late as possible:</p>
<pre><code>0.9 * 1.24 / 35 / 0.062  # 51.4%</code></pre>

<p>The worst non-zero return you can get is if your lifetime Social
Security earnings are already over $2.8M and you plan to collect
Social Security as soon as possible.</p>
<pre><code>0.15 * 0.7 / 35 / 0.062  # 4.8%</code></pre>

<p>A conservative mid-career value is likely about 15%.</p>
<pre><code>0.32 * 1.0 / 35 / 0.062  # 14.7%</code></pre>

<p>Social Security adjusts for inflation, so these are all returns <em>over</em>
inflation. I just can't think of anything that gets returns like this.</p>
<p>You get the same return on your last year's contribution before
collecting, so comparative investments can't really be allowed <em>any</em>
time for compounding. Still, most contributions will sit for some time
before the contributor starts collecting, so a full comparison could
be more complicated and depend on age at contribution etc.</p>
<p>Social Security is less flexible than an investing account. But is
there <em>anything</em> that comes close to delivering what Social Security
does, for someone contributing at 60 who lives to be 90, say?</p>
<hr>
<p>The calculations above may seem opaque. I simplified a little,
dropping things that cancel out. More explicitly:</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">($100 new income this year / 35 years considered)
 * 90% income replacement factor
 * 1.24 late start factor
 = annual Social Security benefit from income
-------------------------------------------------------
($100 new income this year * 6.2% tax = tax paid on income)</code></pre>

<p>I rearranged terms a little, and I'm still leaving out conversion
to/from monthly basis which is just a distraction.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20231202-social_security_is_a_great_deal/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20231202-social_security_is_a_great_deal/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>It must be beautiful, edited by Farmelo</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This is a nice collection of essays about some beautiful equations,
edited by the author of <a href="/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/" title="The Strangest Man, by Farmelo">a biography of Dirac</a>. Not every equation
is fully explained, but there's great history and big-picture
explanation. The authors are frequently major contributors to the
fields.</p>
<ol>
<li>The Planck-Einstein Equation for the Energy of a Quantum: \( E = hf\)</li>
<li>The Logistic Map: \( x_{next} = a x_{initial} (1 - x_{initial}) \)</li>
<li>The Drake Equation: \( N = R^* \cdot f_p \cdot n_e \cdot f_l \cdot f_i \cdot f_c \cdot L \)</li>
<li>\( E = m c^2 \)</li>
<li>The Molina-Rowland Chemical Equations<ul>
<li>\( CFCl_3 \rightarrow CFCl_2 + Cl \)</li>
<li>\( Cl + O_3 \rightarrow ClO + O_2 \)</li>
<li>\( ClO + O \rightarrow Cl + O_2\)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Schrödinger's Wave Equation: \( \hat{H} \psi = E \psi \)</li>
<li>The Dirac Equation: \( \left[ \gamma^\mu \left( i \frac{\partial}{\partial x^\mu} - e A_\mu (x) \right) + m \right] \psi (x) = 0 \)</li>
<li>Evolutionarily Stable Strategy: \( E(S, S) &gt; E(T, S) \)</li>
<li>The Einstein Equation of General Relativity: \( R_{ab} - \frac{1}{2}Rg_{ab} = -8\pi G T_{ab} \)</li>
<li>Shannon's Equations<ul>
<li>\( I = -p \log_2 p \)</li>
<li>\( C = W \log_2 (1 + S/N) \)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The Yang-Mills Equation: \( \partial \mathbf{f}_{μν} / \partial x_ν + 2 \varepsilon (\mathbf{b}_ν \cdot \mathbf{f}_{μν}) + \mathbf{J}_μ = 0 \)</li>
</ol>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It was in large part thanks to this [logistic map] equation, one so
simple that children can study it at school, that scientists in the
1970s came to see that some equations that appear to predict the
future in terms of the past are completely unable to make such
predictions, contrary to what most scientists had thought." (page
xvii)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Maybe children <em>should</em> study it at school, if they're not,
currently...</p>
<p>See also: <a href="/20200714-foundation_trilogy/" title="Asimov's Foundation trilogy">psychohistory</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The [wave-particle] problem's resolution came in the late 1920s,
when physicists developed quantum theory into what became known as
quantum field theory, which made possible a unified description of
radiation and matter." (page 24)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2021/04/09/period-three-implies-chaos/" title="explainer">Period three implies chaos</a> is one of the best paper names of all
time.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Avoiding detailed assumptions about this or that feature of the way
particular objects were built or interacted, Einstein's theory
hardly resembled the work of senior physicists of the time. Instead,
it had an outsider's style—or perhaps a return to an older form of
clarity." (page 75)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The sense of aesthetics that Shcrödinger alludes to here is his
preference for a mathematics that is more familiar and also not as
ugly as Heisenberg's 'transcendental algebra' (or matrices), but
which also permits visualizability of atomic processes." (page 117)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Transcendental algebra?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In the pantheon of twentieth-century physics, Heisenberg is second
only to Einstein." (page 129)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Feel like somebody told me that was <a href="/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/" title="The Strangest Man, by Farmelo">Dirac</a>...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As the physicist who did more to delve into the foundations of
quantum theory than anyone else since Bohr, Einstein and Heisenberg,
John Bell, once put it, 'for all practical purposes' quantum
mechanics works well. He forcefully reminded us, however, that we
still do not fully understand the Schrödinger equation." (page 131)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The citation here is <a href="https://www.informationphilosopher.com/solutions/scientists/bell/Against_Measurement.pdf">Against 'measurement'</a>, which is straight FIRE.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Is it really possible, by logical processing or calculation, to
arrive at essentially new insights—to get out more than you put in?</p>
<p>"This question is especially timely today, since it lies at the
heart of debates regarding the nature of machine
intelligence—whether it may develop into a species of mind on a par
with human intelligence, or even its eventual superior." (pages
155-156)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This was in <em>2002.</em></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"They [Dirac, Maxwell, Einstein] proceed by <em>experimental logic.</em>
That concept is an oxymoron only on the surface. In experimental
logic, one formulates hypotheses in equations, and experiments with
those equations. That is, one tries to improve the equations from
the point of view of beauty and consistency, and then checks whether
the 'improved' equations elucidate some feature of nature.
Mathematicians recognize the technique of 'proof by contradiction':
to prove <em>A,</em> you assume the opposite of <em>A,</em> and reach a
contradiction. Experimental logic is 'validation by fruitfulness':
to validate <em>A,</em> assume it, and show that it leads to fruitful
consequences. Relative to routine deductive logic, experimental
logic abides by the Jesuit credo: 'It is more blessed to ask
forgiveness than permission.'" (page 159)</p>
<p>"Creative mathematics and physics rely not on perfect logic, but
rather on an experimental logic. Experimental logic involves
noticing patterns, playing with them, making assumptions to explain
them, and—especially—recognizing beauty."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Abduction? With guess-and-check? And aesthetics?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As the anthropologists Robert Boyd and Peter Richerson once
remarked, ‘To replace a world you do not understand by a model of
the world you do not understand is no advance.’" (page 165)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There are questions that are too hard to think about without the
aid of mathematics." (page 179)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In fact, in the four dimensions of space-time, there are <em>twenty</em>
independent components to the curvature, and these can be collected
together to describe a mathematical entity referred to as the
'Rieman curvature tensor'. (page 191)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In 1918, the young German mathematician Emmy Noether discovered a
deeply fundamental relationship between symmetry and the
conservation of physical quantities, such as electric charge. She
found that for every conserved quantity there is a related
symmetry—and vice versa." (page 236)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In an essay on 'Beauty and theoretical physics,' Yang quotes
Heisenberg as saying in 1973, 'We will have to abandon the
philosophy of Democritus and the concept of elementary particles. We
should accept instead the concept of fundamental symmetries.'" (page
251)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Dirac has a paper called "Pretty mathematics."</p>
<hr>
<p>Something about the Einstein summation convention...</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20231119-it_must_be_beautiful/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20231119-it_must_be_beautiful/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fireside Chat / Pro Tips (with Codecademy)</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>My <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/minhzy/" title="Jonathan (Minhzy) Truong">friend</a> at Codecademy invited me to do a sort of AMA on my
career working with data, in an event that was variously promoted as a
“<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7108029659493138432/" title="We’re hosting a fireside chat with Meta Data Scientist Aaron Schumacher next Tuesday.">fireside chat</a>” and “<a href="https://community.codecademy.com/events/details/codecademy-official-community-events-presents-pro-tips-with-aaron-schumacher-meta/" title="Pro Tips with Aaron Schumacher, Meta">pro tips</a>.”</p>
<ul>
<li>I made some <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/19qy_rOaPYbEgF5ykJeA39a2XjgPVE4Tp2a_YvSc9hXQ/edit" title="Fireside Chat / Pro Tips">slides</a> to introduce myself and some recommendations.</li>
<li>It's <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8PCL5ogz7xM&amp;ab_channel=Codecademy" title="Pro Tips with Aaron Schumacher, Meta">on YouTube</a>!</li>
</ul>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230919-fireside_chat_pro_tips/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230919-fireside_chat_pro_tips/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Strangest Man, by Farmelo</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I think I like this Graham Farmelo, and I like his book about Dirac.
Farmelo is interested in connections between mathematics and physics,
and aesthetics in both. I think I'll read some of his other books too.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>[Charlie] Broad was a wonderfully idiosyncratic lecturer. He always
appeared with a carefully prepared script, and he read every
sentence twice, except for the jokes, which he delivered three
times. (page 39)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In the space-time of the special theory of relativity, things are
different: the square of the distance between two points in
space-time is equal to the sum of the squares of the spatial lengths
<em>minus</em> the square of the time. (page 42)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is it fair to say that a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spacetime#Spacetime_interval">spacetime interval</a> <em>is</em> “the square of
the distance between two points in space-time”? Maybe?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><em>A System of Logic,</em> published in 1843, is a plain-spoken if
laborious account of how empiricism can shape every aspect of human
life. The book features Mill's agenda for science, which assumes
that there is an underlying ‘uniformity of nature’. The aim of
scientists should be to explain more and more observations in terms
of fewer and fewer laws, every one of them grounded in experience
and induced from it. (page 43)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mill%27s_Methods">Mill's Methods</a>!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>All his life, Dirac had the same attitude to the written word as his
contemporary George Orwell: ‘Good prose is like a window pane.’
(page 75)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Dirac knew that it was impossible to deduce the equation from first
principles and that he would find it only through a happy guess.
(page 141)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See also Polya on guessing...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>‘Don't despise philosophers too much,’ she had counselled him after
one of his visits, ‘a great deal that they say may be useless, but
they are after something which matters.’ Mrs Whitehead had been on
the receiving end of one of Dirac's tirades against the only
academic discipline he openly disdained. One of his <em>bêtes noire</em>
was teh internationally admired Trinity College philosopher Ludwig
Wittgenstein, regarded by many as one of the cleverest academics in
Cambridge. Several decades later, Dirac remarked that he was an
‘Awful fellow. Never stopped talking.’ (page 220)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>When Dirac focuses on the transcience of life, he is driven to an
important moral conclusion: ‘A termination of one's life is
necessary in the scheme of things <u>to provide a logical reason for
unselfishness</u>. [...] The fact that there is an end to one's life
compels one to take an interest in things that will continue to live
after one is dead.’ (page 221)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think one could argue exactly the opposite...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In my case this article of faith is that the human race will
continue to live for ever and will develop and progress <u>without
limit</u>. This is an assumption that I must make for my peace of
mind. Living is worthwhile if one can contribute in some small way
to the endless chain of progress. (quoting Dirac, page 221)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See also: <a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/">The Beginning of Infinity</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Anderson later remarked that any experimenter who took the theory
[Dirac's hole theory] at face value and who was working in a
well-equipped laboratory ‘could have discovered the positron in a
single afternoon’ using radioactive soures. (page 225)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This kind of thing is fascinating... What's still out there, that
could be seen in an afternoon, if we knew what to look for?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>He [Dirac] rarely spoke about science but did once exchange a few
words with her about mathematics: she thought it was a human
invention, while Dirac maintained that it had ‘always existed’ and
had been ‘discovered’ by humans. (page 251)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>She [Manci] would probably not have welcomed Dirac's view that his
religion was simply that ‘the world has to improve’. (page 257)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>For the physicists who were interested, a treat was in store:
[at the 1945-12-06 lecture] they heard Dirac coin two of the
best-known technical terms that he introduced: ‘fermions’, quantum
particles that obey the laws that he and Fermi had set out in 1926,
and ‘bosons’, the other type of quantum particles, which obey laws
set out by Einstein and the Indian theoretician Stayendra Bose.
(page 331)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Dirac made the theme of his 1980 lecture ‘The Engineer and the
Physicist’: ‘The main problem of the engineer is to decide which
approximations to make.’ Good engineers make wise choices, often
based on physical intuition, about the mathematical terms they can
ignore in their equations: ‘The terms neglected must be small and
their neglect must not have a big influence on the result. He must
not neglect terms that are not small.’ (page 337)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>He brought the same attention to detail to Dostoevsky's <em>Crime and
Punishment,</em> which he thought was ‘nice’, though he pointed out that
‘In one of the chapters the author makes a mistake: he describes the
sun as rising twice on the same day.’ (page 339)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is there such a mistake???</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Bertrand Russell's fictional don, Professor Driuzdustades (page 347)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Russell has fiction!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>When you ask what are electrons and protons I ought to answer that
this question is not a profitable one to ask and does not really
have a meaning. The important thing about electrons and protons is
not what they are but how they behave — how they move. I can
describe the situation by comparing it to the game of chess. In
chess, we have various chessmen, kings, knights, pawns and so on. If
you ask what a chessman is, the answer would be [that] it is a piece
of wood, or a piece of ivory, or perhaps just a sign written on
paper, [or anything whatever]. It does not matter. Each chessman has
a characteristic way of moving and this is all that matters about
it. The whole game of chess follows from this way of moving the
various chessmen [...] (page 354, quoting Dirac)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>PHYSICAL LAWS SHOULD HAVE MATHEMATICAL BEAUTY. (page 359, quoting
Dirac's blackboard writing)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Thought is not a monolith</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Any particular argument can in principle be formalized in a particular
system of assumptions and inference rules, but flexibility in level of
formality and use of different systems for different arguments is both
practical and inevitable.</p>
<p>The plurality of systems of thought is particularly transparent in
mathematics, where for example to know whether a statement of geometry
is correct one must first ask which system of geometry is determining
correctness. In one system the interior angles of a triangle always
add to two right angles, but in another this is not the case.
Conflicting results do not imply cognitive dissonance when each is
correct in its respective system. The ability to choose among systems
is a great power.</p>
<p>Mathematical formal systems are in a sense complete articulations, but
they are also generally quite verbose and not necessarily easily
understood. In another sense, by their very self-completeness formal
systems close themselves off from meaning beyond their symbols,
requiring something beyond themselves and in that sense being
incomplete.</p>
<p>In practice, it is rare to completely formalize an argument. Ideally,
the nearest acceptable assumptions and clearest steps of reasoning are
described clearly and expediently. Often, assumptions and reasoning
are just implied, or even elided. There may be more or less
uncertainty in excavating the underlying argument.</p>
<p>Natural language is an imperfect tool. Spoken, written, or purely in
thought, a statement of natural language is a phenomon not purely tied
to any particular semantics. As in the Shannon–Weaver model of
communication, language is a signal, and it is the only part of the
system that we have meaningfully direct access to. Everyone speaks
their own constantly-evolving language. Much of philosophy can be seen
as postcards from Sisyphus visiting the ruins of Babel.</p>
<p>Meaning is built based on language, but the meaning cannot be directly
inspected. Reading my own notes, I may find that now they mean nothing
to me, or I may otherwise understand them differently from what I was
understanding as I wrote them. It isn't clear that it is possible to
understand a statement twice in exactly the same way. In the case of
communication with others, the best we can hope for is roughly
compatible understandings.</p>
<p>In stimulating meanings, even if not always perfectly identical,
natural language is a powerful tool. By relying on shared
understandings, which can be built, natural language can be very
efficient and effective. Very often, it is the best option. Care
should be taken to avoid the extremes of its weaknesses.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230723-thought_is_not_a_monolith/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230723-thought_is_not_a_monolith/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Assume some proved things cannot be disproved</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Given a valid proof in a system of assumptions and inference rules,
there is no sure way to know that there isn't also a contradictory
proof, except by assumption outside the system.</p>
<p>Some systems allow a proof of every statement. For example, take a
system where <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principle_of_explosion" title="Principle of explosion, ex falso quodlibet">anything follows from a contradiction</a>, as is common,
and also assume a contradiction.</p>
<p>Systems that prove everything are not honest. In such systems, you can
prove that the system is consistent. You can prove the law of
non-contradiction, and that the system contains no contradictions.
Seeing such a proof does not establish that an opposite proof doesn't
exist. The situation is akin to the futile exercise of trying to
determine whether a person is a liar by asking them.</p>
<p>The situation is also bad even if attempting to show for just one
proved statement that there isn't a proof of its negation. Socrates
presents argument 1, demonstrating conclusion A. Socrates then
presents argument 2, demonstrating conclusion B, which is that there
is no argument for the negation of A. Socrates then presents argument
3, demonstrating conclusion C, which is that there is no argument for
the negation of B. And so on, forever, for every initial conclusion A.</p>
<p>A proof of consistency cannot be convincing, whether it be for a
system overall or even for a single statement in the system (that for
a specific proof, there isn't a proof for the opposite conclusion).</p>
<p>Stepping up a level, to a meta-system where the consistency of the
original system can be proved, does not solve the problem, because the
meta-system hasn't itself been shown to be consistent.</p>
<p>Gödel's second incompleteness theorem is a special case of this
phenomenon. It shows that for formal systems with certain properties,
they can't prove that they are consistent.</p>
<p>Introducing the law of non-contradiction as an axiom, or assuming that
the system contains no contradictions, does not solve the problem.
Such a claim made within the system can always coexist with its
negation, if it is present.</p>
<p>If a system proves both a statement and its negation, there is no
ambiguity. If a system proves a statement but its negation is not
proved, it is necessary to assume that there is no such proof.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230716-assume_some_proved_things_cannot_be_disproved/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230716-assume_some_proved_things_cannot_be_disproved/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Room, by Karlsson</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Karlsson's <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/235739/the-room-by-jonas-karlsson/" title="The Room: A Novel, by Jonas Karlsson">Room</a> is set in a kind of office, but more than that
it's a novel (almost a long parable) about epistemology, how people
believe in conspiracy theories, and the tragedy of modern retreats
from reality. By early reviews, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corner_Office_(film)" title="Corner Office (film)">film version</a> isn't as good.</p>
<p>The narrator, Björn, seems to have (at least) an autism spectrum
disorder that brings to mind
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Curious_Incident_of_the_Dog_in_the_Night-Time">The Curious Incident of the Dog in the Night-Time</a>. He also has
tons of self-importance, zero self-awareness, and a disdain for women
that all make him seem like an easy Proud Boys recruit. He describes
himself as working at an office for a non-corporate Authority but it's
easy to wonder whether it isn't really a care facility for people with
psychological difficulties. (And aren't we all limited in our ability
to know truth?)</p>
<p>Björn believes in, and apparently experiences, a room that none of his
colleagues at the office can see. When Björn finds that by measurement
there couldn't be a room where he thinks there is one, he concludes
that some trick must be at work as part of a conspiracy amongst the
office. A medical professional confesses to thinking that Björn is
just pretending to believe in the room—and who hasn't thought
similarly of flat-earthers?</p>
<p>After a confrontation at work and a tearful breakdown at home, Björn
changes. He describes himself having success at work. Is this real, or
has he inhabited his fantasies from earlier? Is he somehow really
successful, and the point is that people with strange views can
contribute to society? I lean toward the interpretation that the
narrator has become even less reliable.</p>
<p>As Björn becomes less and less connected with reality, his false sense
of power grows and he demands more and more, until he collides with
some aspects of office reality that he can't reinterpret. His
persecution complex runs wild and he eventually disappears completely
into his alternate reality. His isolation, once partial, is total.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Someone had made a snowman in the courtyard below my window, but it
wasn’t very good at all. (page 48)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He doesn't understand context, doesn't think there's any purpose or
measure other than his own.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Stupid people don’t always know that they’re stupid. They might be
aware that something is wrong, they might notice that things don’t
usually turn out the way they imagined, but very few of them think
it’s because of them. That they’re the root of their own problems,
so to speak. And that sort of thing can be very difficult to
explain. (page 49)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Irony via anosognosia.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>I tried to remember when I had last slept.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Almost a Tyler Durden vibe?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Since the time we agreed to have you working here, things have
evidently changed dramatically. I still thought you might be able to
cope with the relatively simple tasks you were given. Sorting,
archiving, et cetera. We knew you were a complex character, but no
one mentioned anything about you being delusional.” (page 88, Karl
the manager speaking)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Jan,” he said. “Thanks, I noticed,” I said, pointing at the name
tag. (page 91)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is one of at least two times that Björn is oblivious of his turn
to introduce himself.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“I’d say that you’re putting it on.” (page 98)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is the frustrated final comment from the medical assessor who
decides Björn doesn't need anything from a psychiatrist.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“I think you maximize your potential better if you imagine a
customer at the other end.” (page 112)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Björn is thinking of himself as a business, focused on performance and
success in terms of exchange. This may be partly his autistic bent,
but also partly a critique of some modern attitudes toward work and
success. “You are a brand” etc.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“How’s anyone supposed to know if he’s there or not? This way we can
never be sure.” (page 118)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is someone asking how they can tell, if Björn is acting as if
he's believing in the room, they can tell whether he's actually
believing in the room or just acting that way.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>On the way home I felt I was being watched by a whole load of
people. I thought everyone was looking at me. I had to stand at the
front of the aisle on the bus because all the seats were taken, so
anyone who felt like it could stare at me as much as they wanted. A
small child with a pacifier in her mouth stared me right in the eyes
for ages. In the end I couldn’t help saying: “Do we know each
other?” I got no answer. The little girl just went on sucking the
pacifier. Her mother gave me a disapproving stare. (page 119)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>On the radio, an actor was reading a novella he’d written himself.
The story included a number, sixty-nine. The actor was claiming that
it became ninety-six if you turned it round, which is obviously a
total lie, and I suddenly felt how lonely it is, constantly finding
yourself the only person who can see the truth in this gullible
world. (page 120)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“Perhaps we could agree on the formulation ‘the room does not exist
for everyone’?” (page 168)</p>
<p>“Either there is a room there, or there isn’t,” Ann said. “It’s not
quite that simple,” Karl said. (page 169)</p>
<p>“Can’t we say that the room exists a little bit?” (page 171)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Some fun epistemology talk... I can't help but wonder whether Karl
(the manager) is supposed to bring to mind Karl Popper.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“In some ways it’s such a grandiose and detailed project,” I went
on, “and so ingeniously malicious that I can’t help being rather
fascinated.” (page 174)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Björn is referring to the conspiracy of everyone else pretending there
isn't a room.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The DG says that on this, the fourth floor, between the lift and
the three toilets… there is absolutely no other space.” (page 180)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That's Karl the manager speaking, and the DG is the Director General,
who is at least the local "authority" of The Authority.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>This was really just a classic ruling-class tactic, wasn’t it?
Making someone think they were mentally ill? (page 184)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Björn continues to think everybody's gaslighting him.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>I closed my eyes, took a deep breath, and walked into the wall. The
wall closed around me, like yogurt around a spoon. (page 185)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is right at the end; Björn's final hiding place, free from the
complexity of other people and the rest of the real world, "No angles
or corners for dirt to get into and hide." His retreat from reality is
complete.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230715-the_room_by_karlsson/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230715-the_room_by_karlsson/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Assume the ability to discern argument validity</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>To make any progress in reasoning requires assuming the ability to
correctly determine whether arguments are valid given their inference
rules. This is both a mechanical and fundamental process.</p>
<p>Validity is the correctness of the form of an argument, assuming its
inference rules, regardless of the truth of its assumptions. This is a
valid argument:</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">Assumption: If Socrates drinks hemlock, then Socrates will die.
Assumption: Socrates drinks hemlock.
Inference rule: If P implies Q, and P is true, then Q. (Modus Ponens)
Conclusion: Socrates will die.</code></pre>

<p>Any other conclusion from the inference rule and assumptions here is
invalid, a non sequitur. (No other inference rules are included in the
example, not even the law of identity.)</p>
<p>When assumptions and inference rules are all stated clearly, and
especially when every step of multi-step arguments are laid out, it
appears to be a mechanical process to verify whether an argument is
valid. But it is possible to doubt that it can be done correctly, and
impossible to prove that it can, so the ability must be assumed.</p>
<p>As Descartes <a href="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Meditations_on_First_Philosophy/Meditation_I" title="Meditations on First Philosophy by René Descartes">asks</a> in connection with his demon, “how do I know
that I am not also deceived each time I add together two and three?”
This is hard to imagine, but that is by construction. Perhaps the
demon causes Descartes to conclude from the example above that
Socrates is in France, and completely believe that this follows from
the inference rule and assumptions given. He believes his argument is
valid, but he is wrong, and he is incapable of determining this,
totally anosognostic, unaware of his condition.</p>
<p>The ability to identify whether an argument is valid cannot be proved,
because any proof offered would need to be assumed valid. Any attempt
at a proof begs the question. To assume the validity of just a
specific proof of the ability to determine validity of other proofs
might be possible, but the validity assumption would then be
simultaneous with others needed for that proof, which introduces
additional restrictions but unclear benefit.</p>
<p>Arguments are not always stated sufficiently clearly and completely as
to make confirming validity easy, but this is fundamentally a
challenge in understanding the argument. In principle any argument can
be expressed clearly and completely.</p>
<p>The assumption here is that it is possible to identify valid arguments
that really are valid, not that there will never be an accidental,
correctible mistake. The assumption is that when there aren't any
mistakes, the claim that an argument is valid is meaningful.</p>
<p>So while verifying the validity of an argument can be a mechanical
process, the assumption here really is fundamental. The assumption is
first that reasoning can be, in some deep sense, really truly valid,
that this is possible, and second that it is possible to know whether
a given argument has this property.</p>
<p>Validity is tautological but universal truth. If the assumptions and
the inference rules, then the conclusions. This is the first and
deepest sense of correctness.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230714-assume_ability_to_discern_argument_validity/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230714-assume_ability_to_discern_argument_validity/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Progress beyond radical skepticism</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Radical skepticism claims that nothing is knowable, but such a claim
is not itself knowable. The solution is to remove all claims, and then
choose to build.</p>
<p>The traditional argument for radical skepticism is from doubt. For any
claim, an inconsistent alternative can be introduced that cannot be
disproved, leaving the original claim less than perfectly justified.
In this way, all knowledge can be removed, meaning made uncertain.</p>
<p>An analytic argument for radical skepticism is that if all knowledge
requires sufficient reason, and arguments are neither circular nor
infinite, there can be no knowledge because there is no “first”
knowledge, which would be knowledge without sufficient reason. In this
way, no knowledge can be built up.</p>
<p>The arguments for radical skepticism are good, but it is difficult to
then state exactly what the claim of radical skepticism is.</p>
<p>The so-called Socratic paradox is the statement that “I know that I
know nothing.” Read strictly, this is not a paradox, but simply a
false statement, regardless of whether Socrates knows anything.</p>
<p>If Socrates says instead “I know that I know nothing, including this,”
he has contradicted himself, as he says both that he knows and he
doesn't know. A contradiction cannot constitute knowledge, and
variants like “I am uncertain about everything, including this,” sound
less problematic only superficially.</p>
<p>If Socrates says, “I know that I know nothing, other than this
knowledge of my limitation,“ he is still incorrect. Either he knows
some reason to hold this belief, in which case he knows more than he
says, or he knows without reason, which is not knowledge but
assumption.</p>
<p>The trouble is that if we manage to know anything, then radical
skepticism is falsified. The radical skepticism that makes a claim is
not the true radical skepticism.</p>
<p>The most defensible expression of radical skepticism is silence, and
in this form it is correct. Nothing comes from nothing, and anything
can be doubted.</p>
<p>True radical skepticism is in a sense pre-rational. Even to reason
about radical skepticism requires assuming the ability to reason. Any
thought is outside the pure domain of radical skepticism.</p>
<p>From the primordial void of radical skepticism, thought can grow. At
every stage of this evolution, what is known is contingent on what
developed prior. Every addition is a choice.</p>
<p>Socrates could say, “I assume that I know nothing other than this one
assumption,” but this would be a dead end.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230712-progress_beyond_radical_skepticism/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230712-progress_beyond_radical_skepticism/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Russell's History of Western Philosophy</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Russell attempts to understand all of western social, political, and
philosophical history in one charming and often funny <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_History_of_Western_Philosophy">book</a>. His
attitude is frequently as expressed on page 760: “This may seem odd,
but that is not my fault.” Russell is a fine guide through the weird
world of human thought, highlighting important developments and gaps.</p>
<p>Summarizing several levels further, here are nine big names in western
philosophy:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pythagoras (570–495) mathematical reasoning (also much silliness)</li>
<li>Socrates (470–399) Socratic method (questioning), fixation on definitions</li>
<li>Plato (428–348) Realm of Ideals (and other silliness)</li>
<li>Aristotle (384–322) syllogisms (and fairly bad science)</li>
<li>Descartes (1596–1650) cogito (“I think, therefore I am.”)</li>
<li>Locke (1632–1704) empiricism, social contract</li>
<li>Hume (1711–1776) scepticism re: induction, causation</li>
<li>Kant (1724–1804) Critique of Pure Reason (synthetic a priori), categorical imperative</li>
<li>Hegel (1770–1831) dialectic (thesis/antithesis/synthesis; really from Fichte)</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>To teach how to live without certainty, and yet without being
paralyzed by hesitation, is perhaps the chief thing that philosophy,
in our age, can still do for those who study it. (page xiv)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Modern philosophy begins with Descartes, whose fundamental certainty
is the existence of himself and his thoughts, from which the
external world is to be inferred. This was only the first stage in a
development, through Berkeley and Kant, to Fichte, for whom
everything is only an emanation of the ego. This was insanity, and,
from this extreme, philosophy has been attempting, ever since, to
escape into the world of every-day common sense. (page xxi)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Social cohesion is a necessity, and mankind has never yet succeeded
in enforcing cohesion by merely rational arguments. (page xxiii)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The gentleman is to be defined as one of a society of equals who
live on slave labour, or at any rate upon the labour of men whose
inferiority is unquestioned.</p>
<p>...</p>
<p>Whatever may be thought of a social system which tolerates slavery,
it is to gentlemen in the above sense that we owe pure mathematics.
(page 34)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>On pages 35-36 Russell notes the Pythagorean schism between arithmetic
and geometry, which led to much confusion.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The influence of geometry upon philosophy and scientific method has
been profound. Geometry, as established by the Greeks, starts with
axioms which are (or are deemed to be) self-evident, and proceeds,
by deductive reasoning, to arrive at theorems that are very far from
self-evident. The axioms and theorems are held to be true of actual
space, which is something given in experience. It thus appeared to
be possible to discover things about the actual world by first
noticing what is self-evident and then using deduction. This view
influenced Plato and Kant, and most of the intermediate
philosophers. When the Declaration of Independence says “we hold
these truths to be self-evident,” it is modeling itself on Euclid.
The eighteenth-century doctrine of natural rights is a search for
Euclidean axioms in politics. The form of Newton's <em>Principia,</em> in
spite of its admittedly empirical material, is entirely dominated by
Euclid. Theology, in its exact scholastic forms, takes its style
from the same source. Personal religion is derived from ecstasy,
theology from mathematics, and both are to be found in Pythagoras.
(pages 36-37)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The certain truth there is no man who knows, nor ever shall be,
about the gods and all the things whereof I speak. Yea, even if a
man should chance to say something utterly right, still he himself
knows it not—there is nowhere anything but guessing.” (page 40,
quoting Xenophanes from Bevan, 1913)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The search for something permanent is one of the deepest instincts
leading men to philosophy. (page 45)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>One of the main ambitions of philosophers has been to revive hopes
that science seemed to have killed. (page 47)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... the ethical and religious preoccupations which, passing from the
Pythagoreans to Socrates and from Socrates to Plato, brought an
obscurantist bias into Greek philosophy. (page 63)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Causation must start from something, and wherever it starts no cause
can be assigned for the initial datum. The world may be attributed
to a Creator, but even then the Creator Himself is unaccounted for.
(page 66)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>When we ask “why?” concerning an event, we may mean either of two
things. We may mean: “What purpose did this event serve?” or we may
mean: “What earlier circumstances caused this event?” The answer to
the former question is a teleological explanation, or an explanation
by final causes; the answer to the latter question is a mechanistic
explanation. I do not see how it could have been known in advance
which of these two questions science ought to ask, or whether it
ought to ask both. But experience has shown that the mechanistic
question leads to scientific knowledge, while the teleological
question does not. The atomists asksed the mechanistic question, and
gave a mechanistic answer. Their successors, until the Renaissance,
were more interested in the teleological question, and thus led
science up a blind alley. (page 67)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Plato is always concerned to advocate views that will make people
what he thinks virtuous; he is hardly ever intellectually honest,
because he allows himself to judge doctrines by their social
consequences. Even about this, he is not honest; he pretends to
follow the argument and to be judging by purely theoretical
standards, when in fact he is twisting the discussion so as to lead
to a virtuous result. He introduced this vice into philosophy, where
it has persisted ever since. It was probably largely hostility to
the Sophists that gave this character to his dialogues. One of the
defects of all philosophers since Plato is that their inquiries into
ethics proceed on the assumption that they already know the
conclusions to be reached. (page 79)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>A stupid man's report of what a clever man says is never accurate,
because he unconsciously translates what he hears into something
that he can understand. (page 83)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The earliest of the Platonic dialogues, which are generally supposed
to be the most Socratic, are mainly occupied with the search for
definitions of ethical terms. The <em>Charmides</em> is concerned with the
definition of temperance or moderation; the <em>Lysis</em> with friendship;
the <em>Laches</em> with courage. In all of these, no conclusion is arrived
at, but Socrates makes it clear that he thinks it important to
examine such questions. The Platonic Socrates consistently maintains
that he knows nothing, and is only wiser than others in knowing that
he knows nothing; but he does not think knowledge unobtainable. On
the contrary, he thinks the search for knowledge of the utmost
importance. He maintains that no man sins wittingly, and therefore
only knowledge is needed to make all men perfectly virtuous.</p>
<p>The close connection between virtue and knowledge is characteristic
of Socrates and Plato. To some degree, it exists in all Greek
thought, as opposed to that of Christianity. In Christian ethics, a
pure heart is the essential, and is at least as likely to be found
among the ignorant as among the learned. This difference between
Greek and Christian ethics has persisted down to the present day.
(pages 91-92)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It has always been correct to praise Plato, but not to understand
him. This is the common fate of great men. (page 105)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It seems to us unwise to have insisted on teaching geometry to the
younger Dionysius, tyrant of Syracuse, in order to make him a good
king, but from Plato's point of view it was essential. He was
sufficiently Pythagorean to think that without mathematics no true
wisdom is possible. This view implies oligarchy.</p>
<p>... Plato, in common with most Greek philosophers, took the view
that leisure is essential to wisdom, which will therefore not be
found among those who have to work for their living, but only among
those who have independent means, or who are relieved by the state
from anxieties as to their subsistence. This point of view is
essentially aristocratic. (page 106)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It might be suggested that men could be given political wisdom by a
suitable training. But the question would arise: what is a suitable
training? And this would turn out to be a party question.</p>
<p>The problem of finding a collection of “wise” men and leaving the
government to them is thus an insoluble one. That is the ultimate
reason for democracy. (page 107)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Although all the rulers are to be philosophers, there are to be no
innovations: a philosopher is to be, for all time, a man who
understands and agrees with Plato. (page 115, on Plato's Utopia)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... the fundamental question of ethics and politics, namely: Is
there any standard of “good” and “bad,” except what the man using
these words desires? (page 117)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... any one who agrees with Thrasymachus will say: “There is no
question of proving or disproving; the only question is whether you
<em>like</em> the kind of State that Plato desires.” ... This is one of the
issues in philosophy that are still open; on each side there are men
who command respect. ... This problem is a difficult one, and I do
not profess to be able to solve it. (page 118)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>We may continue, if we like, to say that numbers are eternal,
immutable, and so on, but we must add that they are logical
fictions. (page 157)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Scepticism, as a doctrine of the schools, was first proclaimed by
Pyrrho, ... (page 233)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The manner in which Arcesilaus taught would have had much to commend
it, if the young men who learnt from him had been able to avoid
being paralysed by it. He maintained no thesis, but would refute any
thesis set up by a pupil. Sometimes he would himself advance two
contradictory propositions on successive occasions, showing how to
argue convincingly in favour of either. ... So great was the
influence of Arcesilaus that the Academy remained sceptical for
about two hundred years. (pages 235-236)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In the middle of this sceptical period, an amusing incident
occurred. Carneades, a worthy successor of Arcesilaus as head of the
Academy, was one of three philosophers sent by Athens on a
diplomatic mission to Rome in the year 156 B.C. He saw no reason why
his ambassadorial dignity should interfere with the main chance, so
he announced a course of lectures in Rome. The young men, who, at
that time, were anxious to ape Greek manners and acquire Greek
culture, flocked to hear him. His first lecture expounded the views
of Aristotle and Plato on justice, and was thoroughly edifying. His
second, however, was concerned in refuting all that he had said in
his first, not with a view of establishing opposite conclusions, but
merely to show that every conclusion is unwarranted. (page 236)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Without answering the arguments of the Sceptics, the ancient world
turned aside from them. (page 239)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Another doctrine of theirs [the Stoics] in theory of knowledge was
more influential, though more questionable. This was their belief in
innate ideas and principles. Greek logic was wholly deductive, and
this raised the question of first premises. First premises had to
be, at least in part, general, and no method existed of proving
them. The Stoics held that there are certain principles, which are
luminously obvious, and are admitted by all men; these could be
made, as in Euclid's <em>Elements,</em> the basis of deduction. Innate
ideas, similarly, could be used as the starting-point of
definitions. This point of view was accepted throughout the Middle
Ages, and even by Descartes. (page 269)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... the most effective men of action are often intellectually
second-rate. (page 381)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Damian was the author of a treatise <em>On Divine Omnipotence,</em> which
maintained that God can do things contrary to the law of
contradiction, and can undo the past. (page 413)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It seems Russell has this one wrong; Damian <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/peter-damian/#GodRestVirg" title="Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy: Peter Damian">didn't say</a> quite that.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In Hume, the empiricist philosophy culminated in a scepticism which
none could refute and none could accept. (page 494)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The ancient world found an end to anarchy in the Roman Empire, but
the Roman Empire was a brute fact, not an idea. The Catholic world
sought an end to anarchy in the Church, which was an idea, but was
never adequately embodied in fact. Neither the ancient nor the
medieval solution was satisfactory—the one because it could not be
idealized, the other because it could not be actualized. The modern
world, at present, seems to be moving towards a solution like that
of antiquity: a social order imposed by force, representing the will
of the powerful rather than the hopes of common men. The problem of
a durable and satisfactory social order can only be solved by
combining the solidity of the Roman Empire with the idealism of
Saint Augustine's City of God. To achieve this a new philosophy will
be needed. (pages 494-495)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The political conditions of the Renaissance favoured individual
development, but were unstable; the instability and the
individualism were closely connected, as in ancient Greece. A stable
social system is necessary, but every stable system hitherto devised
has hampered the development of exceptional artistic or intellectual
merit. How much murder and anarchy are we prepared to endure for the
sake of great achievements such as those of the Renaissance? In the
past, a great deal; in our own time, much less. No solution of this
problem has hitherto been found, although increase of social
organization is making it continually more important. (page 503)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There are some respects in which the concepts of modern theoretical
physics differ from those of the Newtonian system. To begin with,
the conception of “force,” which is prominent in the seventeenth
centurey, has been found to be superfluous. “Force,” in Newton, is
the cause of change of motion, whether in magnitude or direction. To
notion of cause is regarded as important, and force is conceived
imaginatively as the sort of thing that we experience when we push
or pull. For this reason it was considered an objection to
gravitation that it acted at a distance, and Newton himself conceded
that there must be some medium by which is was transmitted.
Gradually it was found that all the equations could be written down
without bringing in forces. What was observable was a certain
relation between acceleration and configuration; to say that this
relationship was brought about by the intermediacy of “force” was to
add nothing to our knowledge. Observation shows that the planets
have at all times an acceleration towards the sun, which varies
inversely as the square of their distance from it. To say that this
is due to the “force” of gravitation is merely verbal, like saying
that opium makes people sleep because it has a dormitive virtue. The
modern physicist, therefore, merely states formulæ which determine
accelerations, and avoids the word “force” altogether. “Force” was
the faint ghost of the vitalist view as to the causes of motions,
and gradually the ghost has been exorcized. (page 539)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>After five years spent in retirement, he [Francis Bacon] died of a
chill caught while experimenting on refrigeration by stuffing a
chicken full of snow. (page 542)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>One of the most famous parts of Bacon's philosophy is his
enumeration of what he calls “idols,” by which he means bad habits
of mind that cause people to fall into error. Of these he enumerates
five kinds. “Idos of the tribe” are those that are inherent in human
nature; he mentions in particular the habit of expecting more order
in natural phenomena than is actually to be found. “Idols of the
cave” are personal prejudices, characteristic of the particular
investigator. “Idols of the market-place” are those that have to do
with the tyranny of words and the difficulty of escaping from their
influence over our minds. “Idols of the theatre” are those that have
to do with received systems of thought; of these, naturally
Aristotle and the scholastics afforded him the most noteworthy
instances. Lastly there are “idols of the schools,” which consist in
thinking that some blind rule (such as the syllogism) can take the
place of judgement in investigation. (page 544)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think this is interesting as compared to modern collections of
logical fallacies, like Almossawi's cute <a href="/20201012-bad_arguments_by_almossawi/">Bad Arguments</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Bacon's inductive method is faulty through insufficient emphasis on
hypothesis. He hoped that mere orderly arrangement of data would
make the right hypothesis obvious, but this is seldom the case. As a
rule, the framing of a hypothesis is the most difficult part of
scientific work, and the part where great ability is indispensable.
So far, no method has been found which would make it possible to
invent hypotheses by rule. Usually some hypothesis is a necessary
preliminary to the collection of facts, since the selection of facts
demands some way of determining relevance. Without something of this
kind, the mere multiplicity of facts is baffling. (pages 544-545)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is related to modern thought around data science, data mining,
etc.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>So long as national States exist and fight each other, only
inefficiency can preserve the human race. (page 557)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is in relation to Hobbes's Leviathan...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Therefore corporeal nature in general, involving such matters as
extension, magnitude, and number, is less easy to question than
beliefs about particular things. Arithmetic and geometry, which are
not concerned with particular things, are therefore more certain
than physics and astronomy; they are true even of dream objects,
which do not differ from real ones as regards number and extension.
Even in regard to arithmetic and geometry, however, doubt is
possible. It may be that God causes me to make mistakes whenever I
try to count the sides of a square or add 2 to 3. Perhaps it is
wrong, even in imagination, to attribute such unkindness to God, but
there might be an evil demon, no less cunning and deceitful than
powerful, employing all his industry in misleading me. If there be
such a demon, it may be that all the things I see are only illusions
of which he makes use as traps for my credulity. (pages 563-564)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>But these considerations have not disposed of the sceptical
arguments which threw doubt on the existence of the external world.
This can only be done by first proving the existence of God. (page
566)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Spinoza (1634-77) is the noblest and most lovable of the great
philosophers. Intellectually, some others have surpassed him, but
ethically he is supreme. (page 569)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>[Arnauld had a negative opinion of some of the ideas Spinoza had
related in letters to Arnauld.] This hostile opinion no doubt led
Leibniz, thenceforth, to adopt a policy of secrecy as to his real
thoughts on philosophical subject. (page 591)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I wonder how often this kind of thing has happened through history.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There is a general belief (which I have never understood) that it is
better to exist than not to exist; on this ground children are
exhorted to be grateful to their parents. (page 594)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“For where is the man that has uncontestable evidence of the truth
of all that he holds, or of the falsehood of all he condemns; or can
say, that he has examined to the bottom all his own or other men's
opinions? The necessity of believing without knowledge, nay, often
upon very slight grounds, in this fleeting state of action and
blindness we are in, should make us more busy and careful to inform
ourselves than to restrain others. ... There is reason to think,
that if men were better instructed themselves, they would be less
imposing on others.” (page 609, quoting Locke)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Locke may be regarded as the founder of empiricism, which is the
doctrine that all our knowledge (with the possible exception of
logic and mathematics) is derived from experience. Accordingly the
first book of the <em>Essay</em> is concerned in arguing, as against Plato,
Descartes, and the scholastics, that there are no innate ideas or
principles. (page 609)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Empiricism and idealism alike are faced with a problem to which, so
far, philosophy has found no satisfactory solution. This is the
problem of showing how we have knowledge of other things than
ourself and the operations of our own mind. (page 611)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>No one has yet succeeded in inventing a philosophy at once credible
and self-consistent. (page 613)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Belief in the harmony between private and public interests is
characteristic of liberalism, and long survived the theological
foundation that it had in Locke.</p>
<p>Locke states that liberty depends upon the necessity of pursuing
true happiness and upon the government of our passions. This opinion
he derives from his doctrine that private and public interests are
identical in the long run, though not necessarily over short
periods.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I feel like there's a prisoner's dilemma in here.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The hereditary principle has almost vanished from politics. During
my lifetime, the emperors of Brazil, China, Russia, Germany, and
Austria have disappeared, to be replaced by dictators who do not aim
at the foundation of a hereditary dynasty. Aristocracy has lost its
privileges throughout Europe, except in England, where they have
become little more than a historical form. All this, in most
countries, is very recent, and has much to do with the rise of
dictatorships, since the traditional basis of power has been swept
away, and the habits of mind required for the successful practice of
democracy have not had time to grow up. There is one great
institution that has never had any hereditary element, namely, the
Catholic Church. We may expect the dictatorships, if they survive,
to develop gradually a form of government analogous to that of the
Church. This has already happened in the case of the great
corporations in America, which have, or had until Pearl Harbor,
powers almost equal to those of the government. (pages 621-622)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In Locke's theory of government, I repeat, there is little that is
original. In this Locke resembles most of the men who have won fame
for their ideas. As a rule, the man who first thinks of a new idea
is so much ahead of his time that every one thinks him silly, so
that he remains obscure and is soon forgotten. Then, gradually, the
world becomes ready for the idea, and the man who proclaims it at
the fortunate moment gets all the credit. So it was, for example,
with Darwin; poor Lord Monboddo was a laughing-stock. (page 624)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Monboddo was also a nudist, <a href="https://www.scottishlegal.com/articles/our-legal-heritage-lord-monboddo-the-nudist-judge-who-pre-empted-darwin-s-theory-of-evolution" title="Our Legal Heritage: Lord Monboddo – the nudist judge who pre-empted Darwin’s theory of evolution">apparently</a>?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>[One view on the origin of government] maintained that God had
bestowed power on certain persons, and that these persons, or their
heirs, constituted the legitimate government, rebellion against
which is not only treason, but impiety. This view was sanctioned by
sentiments of immemorial antiquity: in almost all early
civilizations, the king is a sacred person. Kings, naturally,
considered it an admirable theory. Aristocracies had motives for
supporting it and motives for opposing it. In its favour was the
fact that it emphasized the hereditary principle, and that gave
august support to resistance against the upstart merchant class.
Where the middle class was more feared or hated by the aristocracy
than the king was, these motives prevailed. Where the contrary was
the case, and especially where the aristocracy had a chance of
obtaining supreme power itself, it tended to oppose the king, and
therefore to reject theories of divine right. (page 629)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is just a really good example of Russell's pragmatic, realpolitik
explanations: he frequently points out that people tend to believe
whatever tends to advantage them.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The question of the rights of the individual as against the
government is a very difficult one. It is too readily assumed by
democrats that, when the government represents the majority, it has
a right to coerce the minority. Up to a point, this must be true,
since coercion is of the essence of government. But the divine right
of majorities, if pressed too far, may become almost as tyrannical
as the divine right of kings. (page 633)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Berkeley (Chapter XVI, starting page 647) is interesting for his focus
on perception. “<a href="https://www.britannica.com/topic/esse-est-percipi-doctrine" title="esse est percipi doctrine">esse est percipi</a>” It seems too strong to say that
we can know that things <em>don't</em> exist without being perceived though.
On what basis?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It remains to be asked whether any meaning can be attached to the
words “mind” and “matter.” Every one knows that “mind” is what an
idealist thinks there is nothing else but, and “matter” is what a
materialist thinks the same about. The reader knows also, I hope,
that idealists are virtuous and materialists are wicked. But perhaps
there may be more than this to be said.</p>
<p>My own definition of “matter” may seem unsatisfactory; I should
define it as what satisfies the equations of physics. There may be
nothing satisfying these equations; in that case either physics of
the concept “matter” is a mistake. If we reject substance, “matter”
will have to be a logical construction. Whether it can be any
construction composed of events—which may be partly inferred—is a
difficult question, but by no means an insoluble one.</p>
<p>As for “mind,” when substance has been rejected a mind must be some
group or structure of events. The grouping must be effected by some
relation which is characteristic of the sort of phenomena we wish to
call “mental.” We may take memory as typical. We might—though this
would be rather unduly simple—define a “mental” event as one which
remembers or is remembered. Then the “mind” to which a given mental
event belongs is the group of events connected with the given event
by memory-chains, backwards or forwards.</p>
<p>It will be seen that, according to the above definition, a mind and
a piece of matter are, each of them, a group of events. There is no
reason why every event should belong to a group of one kind or the
other, and there is no reason why some events should not belong to
both groups; therefore some events may be neither mental nor
material, and other events may be both. As to this, only detailed
empirical considerations can decide. (pages 658-659)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is about as nearly as Russell gives his own metaphysics. He has
some idea that “events” are fundamental. I don't see any clear reason
to think that his ideas here are good.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In the Cartesian philosophy, as in that of the Scholastics, the
connection of cause and effect was supposed to be necessary, as
logical connections are necessary. The first really serious
challenge to this view came from Hume, with whom the modern
philosophy of causation begins. (page 664)</p>
<p>“We have no other notion of cause and effect, but that of certain
objects, which have been <em>always conjoined</em> together... We canot
penetrate into the reason of the conjunction.” (page 665, quoting
Hume)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“All probable reasoning is nothing but a species of sensation. 'Tis
not solely in poetry and music, we must follow our taste and
sentiment, but likewise in philosophy. When I am convinced of any
principle, 'tis only an idea, which strikes more strongly upon me.
When I give the preference to one set of arguments above another, I
do nothing but decide from my feeling concerning the superiority of
their influence. Objects have no discoverable connexion together;
nor is it from any other principle but custom operating upon the
imagination, that we can draw any inference from the appearance of
one to the existence of another.” (page 670, quoting Hume)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The growth of unreason throughout the nineteenth century and what
has passed of the twentieth is a natural sequel to Hume's
destruction of empiricism. (page 673)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>What these arguments [against induction] prove—and I do not think
the proof can be controverted—is that induction is an independent
logical principle, incapable of being inferred either from
experience or from other logical principles, and that without this
principle science is impossible. (page 674)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Man is not a solitary animal, and so long as social life survives,
self-realization cannot be the supreme principle of ethics. (page
684)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>After satisfying himself that there is a God, the Vicar [Rousseau]
goes on to consider rules of conduct. “I do not deduce these rules,”
he says, “from the principles of a high philosophy, but I find them
in the depths of my heart, written by Nature in ineffaceable
characters.” From this he goes on to develop the view that
conscience is in all circumstances an infallible guide to right
action. “Thanks be to Heaven,” he concludes this part of his
argument, “we are thus freed from all this terrifying apparatus of
philosophy; we can be men without being learned; dispensed from
wasting our life in the study of morals, we have at less cost a more
assured guide in this immense labyrinth of human opinions.” Our
natural feelings, he contends, lead us to serve the common interest,
while our reason urges selfishness. We have therefore only to follow
feeling rather than reason in order to be virtuous. (page 693)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Rouseau is a dork.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“categorical imperative” ... <em>“Act only according to a maxim by
which you can at the same time will that it shall become a general
law.”</em> (pages 710-711)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Kant...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>To frame a philosophy capable of coping with men intoxicated with
the prospect of almost unlimited power and also with the apathy of
the powerless is the most pressing task of our time. (page 729)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>This may seem odd, but that is not my fault. (page 760)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Russell is saying this of his comparison between Nietzsche's superman
and Siegfried as in Wagner's <em>Ring</em> cycle, but it is also a fair
summary of Russell's attitude toward most ideas of most philosophers.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>One of the bad effects of an anti-intellectual philosophy, such as
that of Bergson, is that it thrives upon the errors and confusions
of the intellect. Hence it is led to prefer bad thinking to good, to
declare every momentary difficulty insoluble, and to regard every
foolish mistake as revealing the bankruptcy of intellect and the
triumph of intuition. (page 803)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>[William] James's doctrine of radical empiricism was first published
in 1904, in an <a href="http://fair-use.org/william-james/essays-in-radical-empiricism/does-consciousness-exist" title="Does Consciousness Exist? (1904)">essay</a> called “Does ‘Consciousness’ Exist?” The
main purpose of this essay was to deny that the subject-object
relation is fundamental. It had, until then, been taken for granted
by philosophers that there is a kind of occurrence called “knowing,”
in which one entity, the knower or subject, is aware of another, the
thing known or the object. The knower was regarded as a mind or
soul; the object known might be a material object, an eternal
essence, another mind, or, in self-consciousness, identical with the
knower. Almost everything in accepted philosophy was bound up with
the dualism of subject and object. The distinction of mind and
matter, the contemplative ideal, and the traditional notion of
“truth,” all need to be radically reconsidered if the distinction of
subject and object is not accepted as fundamental.</p>
<p>For my part, I am convinced that James was right on this matter, and
would, on this ground alone, deserve a high place among
philosophers. I had thought otherwise until he, and those who agreed
with him, persuaded me of the truth of his doctrine. But let us
proceed to his arguments. (page 812)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>By the form of the words, radical empiricism's focus on pure
experience seems like it could be something I agree with. If
experience is central, and James is denying a material existence of
consciousness but not denying the state of being conscious, then maybe
it's just linguistic weirdness, and just my preference to say instead
that perhaps <em>only</em> consciousness exists. But the weirdness runs much
deeper.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>My thesis is that if we start with the supposition that there is
only one primal stuff or material in the world, a stuff of which
everything is composed, and if we call that stuff pure experience,
then knowing can easily be explained as a particular sort of
relation towards one another into which portions of pure experience
may enter. (James's <a href="http://fair-use.org/william-james/essays-in-radical-empiricism/does-consciousness-exist" title="Does Consciousness Exist? (1904)">essay</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is as ridiculous as Leibniz's monads. What a jump! To claim you
can say what the whole universe is made of! To give it such a name!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>That entity [consciousness] is fictitious, while thoughts in the
concrete are fully real. But thoughts in the concrete are made of
the same stuff as things are. (James's <a href="http://fair-use.org/william-james/essays-in-radical-empiricism/does-consciousness-exist" title="Does Consciousness Exist? (1904)">essay</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>An underlying bad idea throughout, here, is that the physical world is
in a deep sense identical to our mental perception and ideas of the
physical world. I think this comes from the sense we have of directly
knowing the world around us, as when we see a cup, reach out and touch
it, and are assured of its existence as we expected. I would like to
get James a VR headset.</p>
<p>I guess this is where Russell gets his ideas about “events” that can
be combinations of mental and physical.</p>
<p>At least James doesn't deny conscious experience. Why he needs to go
all the way to a weird monism is beyond me.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>He defines “pure experience” as “the immediate flux of life which
furnishes the material to our later reflection.” (page 813, quoting
James's <em>Essays in Radical Empiricism</em>)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The concept of “truth” as something dependent upon facts largely
outside human control has been one of the ways in which philosophy
hitherto has inculcated the necessary element of humility. When this
check upon pride is removed, a further step is taken on the road
towards a certain kind of madness—the intoxication of power which
invaded philosophy with Fichte, and to which modern men, whether
philosophers or not, are prone. I am persuaded that this
intoxication is the greatest danger of our time, and that any
philosophy which, however unintentionally, contributes to it is
increasing the danger of vast social disaster. (page 828)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Modern analytical empirical, of which I have been giving an outline,
differs from that of Locke, Berkeley, and Hume by its incorporation
of mathematics and its development of a powerful logical technique.
It is thus able, in regard to certain problems, to achieve definite
answers, which have the quality of science rather than of
philosophy. It has the advantage, as compared with the philosophies
of the system-builders, of being able to tackle its problems one at
a time, instead of having to invent at one stroke a block theory of
the whole universe. Its methods, in this respect, resemble those of
science. I have no doubt that, in so far as philosophical knowledge
is possible, it is by such methods that it must be sought; I have
also no doubt that, by these methods, many ancient problems are
completely soluble.</p>
<p>There remains, however, a vast field, traditionally included in
philosophy, where scientific methods are inadequate. This field
includes ultimate questions of value; science alone, for example,
cannot prove that it is bad to enjoy the infliction of cruelty.
Whatever can be known, can be known by means of science; but things
which are legitimately matters of feeling lie outside its province.</p>
<p>Philosophy, throughout its history, has consisted of two parts
inharmoniously blended: on the one hand a theory as to the nature of
the world, on the other an ethical or political doctrine as to the
best way of living. The failure to separate these two with
sufficient clarity has been a source of much confused thinking.
(page 834)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is in the last chapter of the book, <em>The Philosophy of Logical
Analysis</em>.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230707-russell_history_of_western_philosophy/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230707-russell_history_of_western_philosophy/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Regression standard errors scale by all residuals</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Even in cases where it seems like it shouldn't matter whether you run
individual regressions or a combined regression, it does matter to the
standard errors, because the standard errors all scale by a factor
that includes all the residuals for the model.</p>
<p>Here's a simple data set in <a href="https://www.r-project.org/">R</a>:</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">set.seed(42)
x = rnorm(10)
df_a = data.frame(group='a', x=x, y=2*x + 5 + rnorm(10))
x = rnorm(10)
df_b = data.frame(group='b', x=x, y=3*x + 7 + rnorm(10))
df = rbind(df_a, df_b)
df
##     group           x          y
##  1      a  1.37095845  9.0467865
##  2      a -0.56469817  6.1572490
##  3      a  0.36312841  4.3373961
##  4      a  0.63286260  5.9869364
##  5      a  0.40426832  5.6752153
##  6      a -0.10612452  5.4237014
##  7      a  1.51152200  7.7387911
##  8      a -0.09465904  2.1542265
##  9      a  2.01842371  6.5963805
##  10     a -0.06271410  6.1946851
##  11     b -0.30663859  6.5355343
##  12     b -1.78130843  2.3609120
##  13     b -0.17191736  7.5193515
##  14     b  1.21467470 10.0350977
##  15     b  1.89519346 13.1905355
##  16     b -0.43046913  3.9915839
##  17     b -0.25726938  5.4437328
##  18     b -1.76316309  0.8596032
##  19     b  0.46009735  5.9660844
##  20     b -0.63999488  5.1161380</code></pre>

<p>If we're trying to recover the slopes and intercepts, we can run
separate regressions for group <em>a</em> and group <em>b</em>, or we can run a
combined regression for both at the same time.</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">summary(lm(y ~ x, data=df_a))
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  (Intercept)   5.2370     0.6162   8.500 2.82e-05 ***
##  x             1.2682     0.6397   1.983   0.0827 .
summary(lm(y ~ x, data=df_b))
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  (Intercept)   6.6258     0.3783  17.515 1.15e-07 ***
##  x             2.9421     0.3405   8.641 2.50e-05 ***
summary(lm(y ~ group:x + group - 1, data=df))
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##     groupa     5.2370     0.5411   9.679 4.32e-08 ***
##     groupb     6.6258     0.4511  14.689 1.05e-10 ***
##     groupa:x   1.2682     0.5618   2.258   0.0383 *
##     groupb:x   2.9421     0.4060   7.247 1.95e-06 ***</code></pre>

<p>The estimated coefficients are the same between the two methods
(good!) but the standard errors are different. Why? We know that the
data for group <em>a</em> doesn't really interact with the data for group <em>b</em>
at all, so it shouldn't affect the standard errors, right?</p>
<p>Indeed, adding extra independent data shouldn't affect the standard
errors, but regression doesn't know about the independence. (Run the
independent regressions, not the combined one, in cases like this if
you want correct standard errors.)</p>
<p>With \( X \) the design matrix and \( \sigma^2 \) the sum of
squared residuals divided by degrees of freedom, the standard errors
are \( \sqrt{ \sigma^2 ( X^TX )^{-1} } \). (Thanks to <a href="https://stats.stackexchange.com/a/44841/122282" title="How are the standard errors of coefficients calculated in a regression?">ocram</a>.)</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">model = lm(y ~ group:x + group - 1, data=df)
matrix = model.matrix(y ~ group:x + group - 1, data=df)
sqrt(diag((sum(model$residuals^2) / 16) * solve(t(matrix) %*% matrix)))
##     groupa    groupb  groupa:x  groupb:x
##  0.5410892 0.4510810 0.5617751 0.4059782</code></pre>

<p>In the example here, the group <em>a</em> coefficient on <em>x</em> isn't
significant (at 0.05) with the individual regression, but it appears
to be when the combined regression is done. And this is a modest
example, with the same scale normal noise in both data sets; data
won't be so homoscedastic in general so results could be even worse
for combined regressions.</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230706-regression_standard_errors_scale_by_all_residuals/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230706-regression_standard_errors_scale_by_all_residuals/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The useful lesson of Carneades</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
<p>“According to tradition, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carneades">Carneades</a> also delivered a pair of
lectures while in Rome, speaking in defense of justice on one day
and, in rebuttal of his own arguments of the previous day, against
it on the following day.” (<a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2020/entries/carneades/#LifeWork">Allen</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Carneades is sometimes interpreted as demonstrating only “that every
conclusion is unwarranted.” (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_History_of_Western_Philosophy" title="A History of Western Philosophy">Russell</a>, p. 236) The skeptic is
correct as such, but has not yet offered useful advice. The useful
lesson of Carneades is that rhetoric should be wielded responsibly to
create the world we want. In expelling Carneades from Rome,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cato_the_Elder" title="Cato the Elder">Cato the Censor</a> may or may not have acted wisely, but it seems he
understood the lesson.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230608-useful_lesson_of_carneades/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230608-useful_lesson_of_carneades/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fieller intervals in Python</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fieller%27s_theorem">Fieller's theorem</a> provides a way to get a confidence interval for
a ratio, which is hard in general. An alternative is to
<a href="/20211230-getting_var_ratio_can_be_hard/" title="Getting var(X/Y) can be hard">use the delta method</a> to estimate the variance of the ratio and use
that, but should your estimate of the ratio really be the middle of
the interval?</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">import scipy.stats

def fieller_interval(mean_x, var_x, mean_y, var_y, alpha=0.05):
   """Confidence interval for X/Y; see arxiv.org/pdf/0710.2024.pdf"""
   z = scipy.stats.norm().ppf(1 - alpha / 2)
   t = z  # Uses z instead of t (assumes large n)
   divisor = mean_y**2 - (t**2 * var_y)
   center = (mean_y * mean_x) / divisor
   spread = (((mean_y * mean_x)**2 -
              ((mean_y**2 - (t**2 * var_y)) *
               (mean_x**2 - (t**2 * var_x))) )**0.5 /
             divisor)
   return center - spread, center + spread</code></pre>

<p>Fieller's method uses its own center, which makes sense because the
distribution of a ratio is skewed in general.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">x = scipy.stats.norm(loc=110, scale=25).rvs(size=1000, random_state=110)
y = scipy.stats.norm(loc=100, scale=25).rvs(size=1000, random_state=100)</code></pre>

<!--
import matplotlib.pyplot as plt

plt.figure(figsize=(10, 4))
plt.hist(x/y, bins=40)
plt.xlabel('x/y')
plt.show()
-->

<p><img alt="histogram" src="hist.png"></p>
<p>The estimate <code>x.mean() / y.mean()</code> is 1.1, which is good, but the
Fieller center is 1.5, which is a better center for the interval
because of the skewness. You can check that about the right fraction
of values are in the tails. (<a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/blob/master/20230603-fieller_intervals_in_python/fieller.ipynb">Jupyter notebook</a>)</p>
<p>(Be sure to use the variances you care about—more likely to be
variances of sample means in practice.)</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230603-fieller_intervals_in_python/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230603-fieller_intervals_in_python/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How to stay productive when the world is ending</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>In the conclusion (“Congrats, you completed a book!”) the authors
clarify that <a href="https://shop.reductress.com/products/how-to-stay-productive-when-the-world-is-ending">this</a> is “a satirical book of essays about how the
double-bind of our need to work in order to have safety, security, and
predictability is making us powerless in an increasingly unsafe,
insecure, and unpredictable world.” They thank the Nap Bishop,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tricia_Hersey">Tricia Hersey</a>.</p>
<p>The cover is a pretty good indication of the contents, especially if
you notice it's from <a href="https://reductress.com/">Reductress</a>, which is a sort of like a feminist
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Onion">Onion</a> satirizing women's magazines.</p>
<p>An illustrative piece is titled “What is emotional labor?” and
includes this example:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When you have to ask for your salad dressing “light, medium, or
heavy” even though you know these are subjective terms, and no
answer guarantees you will receive your desired amount of salad
dressing</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This kind of poking fun at privilege is easy to laugh along with. The
whole book is in turns funny and depressing, as they spend time with
more serious challenges as well. The satire sneaks in as a coffee
table book, and leaves the reader to fix modern capitalism.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230602-how_to_stay_productive_when_the_world_is_ending/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230602-how_to_stay_productive_when_the_world_is_ending/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Black Holes, by Cox and Forshaw</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>When I was in elementary school, I found a book about black holes in
the school library. It was wonderful, and it covered approximately the
first chapter of this year's very British <a href="https://www.harpercollins.com/products/black-holes-brian-coxjeff-forshaw">book</a> from Cox and
Forshaw. I don't recall <a href="https://guide.wisc.edu/courses/physics/">Physics 247</a> (2001) having much more than
that either. It's good to see that science has continued!</p>
<p>Hearing about black holes feels like exploring weird edge case
trade-offs in the design of the universe. Quantum mechanics gets
involved, multiplying the disregard for everyday experience. The
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spacetime#Spacetime_interval">spacetime interval</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrose_diagram">Penrose diagrams</a> increase clarity, and
the Principle of Maximal Ageing is nice. But then we also get
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_hole_complementarity">Black hole complementarity</a> (you both fall across the event horizon
<em>and</em> get burned up at the event horizon) and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holographic_principle">the holographic principle</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ER_%3D_EPR">ER = EPR</a>. Wild! Keep it up,
science!</p>
<p>The subtitle is "The key to understanding the universe." It's a
compelling hook, and extremes do highlight interesting questions, but
the authors eventually admit that explaining natural phenomena is also
meaningfully distinct from some kinds of understanding, and they
"leave questions of ultimate truth to others" (page 237).</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>A singularity, a moment rather than a place when our knowledge of
the laws of Nature breaks down. According to general relativity, the
singularity lies at the end of time. There is also a singularity in
our past, which marks the beginning of time: the Big Bang. (page 2)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Georges Lemaître, a Catholic priest and one of the founders of
modern cosmology, described the Big Bang singularity at the origin
of our Universe as a day without a yesterday. A singularity formed
by gravitational collapse is a moment with no tomorrow. (page 5)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Sir Roger Penrose’s Nobel Prize-winning <a href="https://journals.aps.org/prl/pdf/10.1103/PhysRevLett.14.57">paper</a> ‘Gravitational
Collapse and Space-Time Singularities’, a three-page tour-de-force
in which Penrose proves that, in Wheeler’s words, ‘for just about
any description of matter that anyone has imagined, a singularity
must sit at the centre of a black hole’. (page 16)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>in science, unlike modern-day politics, principles matter. (page 18)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Thought this was funny, but also true?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Space and time may be emergent entities that do not exist in the
deepest description of Nature. Instead, they are synthesised out of
entangled quantum bits of information in a way that resembles a
cleverly constructed computer code. If the Universe is designed, it
seems, the designer is a programmer. (page 20)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I feel like they never really came back to this and really pay it off
completely, later in the book...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The Large Hadron Collider at CERN is the world’s most powerful
particle accelerator. The giant machine’s job is to make protons
travel around its underground tunnel at 99.999999 per cent the speed
of light, before smashing them together. The purpose is to explore
the structure of matter and the forces of Nature that animate our
world. The LHC is 27 kilometres in circumference from the point of
view of someone standing on the ground in Geneva, marvelling at this
great engineering achievement. From the point of view of the protons
orbiting around the ring, the circumference is 4 metres. (page 25)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>That night down the pub. (page 30)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is this British grammar? Can I be "down the" other things? "That day
down the library"?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>An entirely reasonable first response to that last paragraph is to
ask what on earth are we talking about. (page 41)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes indeed.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The point is that, in relativity theory, it is very important to say
exactly how time differences are being determined. Seeing things
(with instruments like eyes) can be very different from measuring
the passage of time using a network of clocks and rulers. The effect
we just discussed is known as the relativistic Doppler effect and it
is sensitive to the location of the light detector (i.e. where the
eyes are). (page 61)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>From the perspective of someone in freefall across the shell at the
Schwarzschild radius the Equivalence Principle informs us that
nothing untoward happens. (page 89)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>for a typical stellar mass black hole you’d be spaghettified before
you even reached the horizon. (page 103)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But not a really big black hole! Then you get spaghettified well after
crossing the horizon.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In particular, the idea that microscopic wormholes could be part of
the structure of spacetime is part of the ER = EPR hypothesis we’ll
meet in the final chapters. (page 130)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Both the maximally extended Schwarzschild and Kerr solutions are
vacuum solutions to Einstein’s equations–eternal black holes–and as
far as we know, no such black holes exist. (page 141)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Nature is not obliged to make physicists’ lives easier. (page 144)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emmy_Noether" title="Emmy Noether">Noether</a> discovered that the law of conservation of energy is a
direct consequence of time translational invariance, which when the
jargon is stripped away means that the result of an experiment does
not depend on what day of the week it is performed (all other things
being equal). Likewise, the law of momentum conservation is a
consequence of translational invariance in space, which means the
result does not depend on where the experiment is performed (all
other things being equal). (page 146)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>David L. Goodstein begins his textbook States of Matter with the
following paragraph: ‘Ludwig Boltzmann, who spent much of his life
studying statistical mechanics, died in 1906, by his own hand. Paul
Ehrenfest, carrying on the work, died similarly in 1933. Now it is
our turn to study Statistical Mechanics.’ (page 172)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Now here is writing that takes bold risks!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The remainder of the book is about the quest to understand the deep
origins of black hole thermodynamics; a quest that is edging us ever
closer to a new theory of space and time. (page 187)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Hawking’s discovery that black holes emit particles is of profound
importance, not least because it suggests that the origin of the law
of gravity is statistical. (page 190)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It is now understood that vacuum fluctuations cause the electrons
[in fluorescent lights] to fall back down to the lower energy levels
inside the atom. They ‘tickle’ the atom and trigger the emission of
light. (page 194)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There is one logical possibility that could explain the results
without resorting to quantum theory: every event in the Universe is
predetermined, freewill does not exist and the results were baked in
at the beginning of time. Putting that aside, we are left with
quantum mechanics. (page 215)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superdeterminism">Superdeterminism</a>!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>the remarkable <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reeh%E2%80%93Schlieder_theorem">Reeh–Schlieder theorem</a>, which states that it is
possible to operate on some small region of the vacuum in such a way
that anything can be created anywhere in the Universe. This
phenomenal conjuring trick is theoretically possible because the
vacuum is inexorably entangled. The outlandish nature of the theorem
is diminished ever-so-slightly by the fact that the local operation
required is not something that we could ever perform, which is a
shame. (page 218)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>From the perspective of someone freely falling through the horizon,
they feel nothing and are oblivious to this magical encoding.
Moreover, their fate is to be both spaghettified in the singularity
(from their own perspective) and burnt up on the horizon (from an
outsider’s perspective). But that is no problem for the laws of
Nature because no observer can be present at both events. This is
the essence of the black hole complementarity resolution to the
black hole information paradox. Is it nonsense? (page 226)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The inside of a black hole, in other words, is somehow ‘the same’ as
the outside. This idea has become known as the holographic
principle. (page 227)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Gravity thus emerges as a result of the quantum mechanics of a
system on the boundary. (page 237)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>We might ask which of these two descriptions is the real one. Is
there really a black hole or is it just a hologram of the boundary
physics? Or maybe the opposite is true, and the boundary physics is
not real and is just a clever way to describe the black hole. Maybe
trying to figure out what is ‘really’ true is to fall into a trap
that has long plagued physicists because it leads to navel gazing
without revealing deeper insight. There are plenty of people in the
world who can perform that function, and too few physicists, so
perhaps we should restrict ourselves to explaining natural phenomena
and leave questions of ultimate truth to others. Rather, the
holographic principle can be viewed as a realisation of
complementarity. There are two equivalent descriptions of the world,
and because they are equivalent there will be no contradictions:
What is true in one will be true in the other. This is the power of
the holographic principle, and Maldacena discovered a precise,
mathematical realisation of it. (page 237)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The wormhole appears when we allow the two quantum theories to
become entangled. In other words, entanglement builds the wormhole
connecting the two universes together: quantum entanglement and
wormholes go hand in hand. This is a profoundly important connection
between quantum theory and gravity. (page 240)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230601-black_holes_by_cox_and_forshaw/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230601-black_holes_by_cox_and_forshaw/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Conversion of Guelph energy to mass (p=0.049)</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><em>This is a short story I wrote in the second half of 2022. The image is from <a href="https://dezgo.com/">Dezgo</a>.</em></p>
<p><img alt="a tiny old wooden waterwheel moves gently with the water in a slow creak passing through a verdant forest" src="image.png"></p>
<p>“Are you sure you really want to know?” Verona asked, looking up from
her book. The wind off the ocean had slowed but the beach was still
cooling as evening approached. The sky was all pinks and purples now.
It was a pleasant, easy day.</p>
<p>“Maybe it doesn't even mean anything…” Adam finished pulling his
fingers through the sand one last time before turning with a smile.
“Are you hungry?”</p>
<p>They had both recently detected a faint smell of grilling nearby. Soon
they would go to dinner at one of the resort's restaurants, before
retiring to their room. This required very little coordination. They
enjoyed being in sync.</p>
<p>Verona grinned as she got up and began to shake out her towel. “Are
you going to say it doesn't mean anything in your dissertation?” Adam
was picking up the vanilla sun lotion and a few empty bottles.</p>
<p>“If I come out and say it, will there be any subtext left?” They were
both happy. “Besides, I need space for all the null results and
extended caveats.”</p>
<hr>
<p>It had been a surprise when brain-scan research led to a breakthrough
in understanding dark matter.</p>
<p>A new type of live brain scanner was designed with a calibration point
that was expected to read zero. This zero-point check worked fine for
some people. But for others, there was something there, where there
should have been nothing. The research team at the University of
Guelph initially called it strangely-interacting energy.</p>
<p>Particle physicists took an interest in this new zero-point
measurement and before long showed, to everyone's surprise, that it
was detecting one end of a spectrum that was somehow perpendicular to
everything that had been measured before. At one end was the
strangely-interacting energy. At the other end was
strangely-interacting mass: dark matter. The whole phenomenon came to
be called Guelph field.</p>
<p>The way Guelph energy interacts with regular matter is like a
paddle-wheel in water, if it's always impossible to tell whether the
water is pushing the wheel or the wheel is pushing the water. It
doesn't matter whether you see just one or the other or both; the
motion is the same.</p>
<p>The apparatus that makes it possible to observe Guelph energy is
called a McKinsey device. Zero-point measurement was sufficiently
paradigm-shifting that physicists sometimes almost forget that
McKinsey brain scanners are state of the art for their intended task
as well. As for Guelph mass, it is only observable by its gravity.</p>
<p>McKinsey scanners are expensive, but they're a good deal cheaper than
particle accelerators.</p>
<hr>
<p>“When I was a kid, she would take me canoeing sometimes, just for
fun.” Adam stood near the yellow wall of the funeral home while
unfamiliar extended family milled about slowly.</p>
<p>Verona had met Adam's great-grandmother only a handful of times in the
last few years. “Will she be speaking?”</p>
<p>A tiny smile flickered across Adam's face. “She was old-fashioned. She
said her family was better than any copy of her would be.” Adam
sighed.</p>
<p>“Do you think she was Guelph positive?” Verona was trying to bring
Adam to a friendly and familiar topic. She was surprised when he
looked away into the distance for a while before replying.</p>
<p>“Sorry; I feel like I don't have a lot of room to think right now.”
Adam paused again.</p>
<p>Verona answered for him. “I bet she was. I know everybody always says
so. She was so special to you all. She must have been, right? Just
like I feel like I must be, and you must be.” Verona squeezed Adam's
hand.</p>
<p>“I don't know. I didn't expect to feel like this.” Adam continued to
search for what to say. “I'm almost glad there isn't a copy; I think
it would be harder with one here.”</p>
<hr>
<p>At first, Guelph energy wasn't found anywhere outside biological human
brains. It has never been observed in dog brains, or dolphin brains,
or cuttlefish brains. It has never been observed in fruit trees, or
vacuum, or radioactive materials.</p>
<p>It would be a perfect answer to the question of what makes humans
different from all other creatures, except that not all humans are
Guelph positive. Measurements are, however, consistently binary:
either it's there or it isn't.</p>
<p>Guelph energy is detected in about half of people. When it is
detected, the signal is strongest in the cerebral cortex and fades
quickly at the brain stem. Repeated zero-point measurements are
consistent across the life span, until death.</p>
<p>Guelph energy has never been observed in a dead brain. There are two
main theories for why this is. The dissipation theory holds that the
energy is no longer attached to the brain and radiates outward to
unobservable levels. The conversion theory holds that the Guelph
energy changes state, becoming undetectable amounts of dark matter.</p>
<p>It isn't clear why Guelph energy should have an affinity for human
brains in the first place, or why this should change at death. No
experiment has been devised to resolve the debate between the
dissipation and conversion theories, or any of the many less plausible
alternative theories.</p>
<hr>
<p>“I think the least realistic part was just that so many labs would let
him use their gear.” Adam and Verona didn't always like the same
content, but they had found a movie called “Check Again” in which a
man becomes obsessed with getting McKinsey zero-point tests, until he
finds love in Greenland.</p>
<p>“It's more fun if you suspend your disbelief, you know,” Verona
replied. It was a familiar conversation. “Or, if you want to nitpick,
just think of the expense!”</p>
<p>“You're okay with the core concept?” asked Adam, relaxing back into
the couch expansively.</p>
<p>“People have all sorts of beliefs about Guelph. It's easy to forget
how many people really take it so seriously. But that's not what the
movie was about! It didn't matter what the tests said; it's the same
old story of a lonely guy who thinks proving himself will fill that
empty space.”</p>
<p>Adam leaned over with a smile to kiss her.</p>
<hr>
<p>In a Turing identity test, an examiner converses with two entities,
one human and one computer. As in a traditional Turing test, the
examiner seeks to determine which is human. The additional wrinkle is
that the human and computer are both claiming to be the same person.
The examiner must make a choice, so if the human and computer are
exactly equivalent, the examiners will be right in about half of
tests.</p>
<p>There are many types of brain scanners. They vary in fidelity, but
they all produce digital versions of a mind. Most techniques in
current use make copies that reliably pass Turing identity tests with
loved ones. All have no effect on Guelph field, except for McKinsey
scanners.</p>
<p>For years it was only known that if an individual who had tested
Guelph positive was subsequently copied using a McKinsey scanner, that
person's brain would afterward test negative.</p>
<p>A particularly well-funded professor decided to have her lab
demonstrate that a computer running a copy was as Guelph-free as every
other non-brain thing. The demonstration did not go as expected, and
turned instead into a series of revolutionary papers.</p>
<p>Work on explaining the mobility of Guelph energy led to
reconsideration of Kantor's development of information mechanics. That
field had moved for a while fruitlessly in the direction of digital
physics, but was revitalized by the problem of brains, computers, and
Guelph field.</p>
<p>The stability of computer-linked Guelph energy is not well
characterized but seems to depend on particulars of operating system
and low-level hardware implementations. In particular, copying a copy
has never led to observing two distinct Guelph loci. This has led some
to speculate that there should be a “McKinsey computer,” but no
concrete proposal for what this would mean in practice has yet
surfaced.</p>
<hr>
<p>“Will I ever get to meet Professor Loi?” Verona joined Adam at a small
white table in the community cafeteria that they liked. They sat with
steaming bowls of phở between them.</p>
<p>“It's getting harder for me to get even my usual scheduled time with
him. He's been insisting on talking to himself more recently, spawning
more copies and then keeping them all around, for analysis, he says.”</p>
<p>“I thought you said he was already way over budget?”</p>
<p>“He is, but he won't work with any of his PhD students unless he gets
to work on his own research. All the copies talk to each other; he's
like a union unto himself and none of the universities he's at can
afford to lose him.”</p>
<p>“Weird! Do you know what he's working on?”</p>
<p>“I can barely get him to explain what I'm working on. But hey,” Adam
raised his water glass, “this morning he said the hardware simulation
tests look good and we should be able to start recruiting subjects
soon.”</p>
<hr>
<p>Guelph field has an obvious connection to gravity, via dark matter,
but as with general relativity, the relationship between Guelph field
and quantum mechanics is unresolved. The “zero-point” of Guelph
detection is not related to zero-point quantum energy. This hasn't
stopped all manner of popular misconceptions from flourishing, despite
typically having as much grounding as saying Guelph field is elf
energy because of the rhyme.</p>
<p>Among the most persistent misinformation is that there is no Guelph
energy. The allegedly quantum basis for this claim hinges on the
mistaken belief that readings from McKinsey devices are quantum
observer effects based on nothing more than stochastic noise. These
theories generally try to explain the persistent patterns observed
with some appeal to entanglement over time or even more incoherent
ideas about beliefs influencing observations.</p>
<p>Contributing to distrust of Guelph theory is the subject-observer
isolation that is an intrinsic part of all McKinsey procedures. The
person inside a McKinsey device gets no indication that it's working.
More than that: After a procedure, the person who leaves a McKinsey
device has no memory of what happened inside. The effect is analogous
to some forms of anesthesia, or having a concussion, and is absolutely
essential for the safety of the subject's brain.</p>
<hr>
<p>“Come back! I see a blue blaze down this way,” Verona called out to
Adam. He turned and walked through the same dappled light again,
stepping on the same dry pine needles.</p>
<p>“This is why you should lead,” said Adam. “You're so good at finding
things! Maybe you can help find participants for the study too?”</p>
<p>“Are you really so surprised that people don't want to get
de-Guelphed?” Verona stopped to look at a patch of tiny white flowers
at the side of the trail.</p>
<p>“Who's to say mass isn't just as good as energy? Anyway nobody would
know the difference if we didn't tell them their initial test
results.” He looked up into the trees. “We'll get the subjects. People
are curious. It's really the regulations that slow everything down.”
Adam paused for a moment. “I got approval to run the protocol on
myself too.”</p>
<p>“Oh! You'll finally find out your status. Won't that be weird for
you?”</p>
<p>“In the end I know rationally it doesn't make a difference one way or
another.” Adam stopped to get something out of his boot, found
nothing, and put his boot back on. “I know you said you don't want to
be in the study, but if you want we can get you in for just the
initial test. We'll have the equipment for the day.”</p>
<p>“You want me there for moral support, huh? Sure. I wonder if people’s
eyes will look different, before and after.” The two walked on, up
stone steps that could have been natural or could have been put in,
matching the pace of the slowly shifting air.</p>
<hr>
<p>It is often repeated that a brain is a quantum computer that simulates
a brain. This is true in the same sense that a hammer is a quantum
computer that simulates a hammer. All matter is quantum, but this
doesn't imply that anything in particular is endowed with mysterious
properties on that basis.</p>
<p>Grover's search algorithm, number-theoretic results, uncomputation:
none of the uniquely quantum aspects of quantum computation are
particularly relevant to brain mechanics. Apart from some aspects of
parallelism, most components of brain simulation are more efficiently
implemented with traditional computers.</p>
<p>A quantum computer capable of running even a low-fidelity copy of a
human mind may never be technically feasible, but there is no reason
to expect that it would behave differently from a conventional
computer. A quantum computer is no more like a McKinsey device than a
regular digital computer.</p>
<hr>
<p>“It's darker with my eyes open!” When Verona spoke, their synchronized
breathing was no longer the dominant sound.</p>
<p>“And my senses were just starting to experience deprivation,” Adam
replied, with just a hint of a chuckle.</p>
<p>“What's the point of us being in here at the same time if we aren't
going to interact?”</p>
<p>“When I was booking this, the guy said that half the time there's only
one person using these two-person tanks. That's why it's such a good
deal when two people use one at the same time.”</p>
<p>“Oh.” Verona began to imagine all the kinds of lives that would
include floating naked in isolation.</p>
<p>“But yeah,” Adam replied again, “the dark is wild. I can almost forget
whether my eyes are open or closed. Some people say they get
hallucinations.”</p>
<p>Another topic came to Verona. “You really set it up so that we'll see
our results at the same time?”</p>
<p>“Hmm? Oh, right. Yeah, it's all my code. No problem. We'll find out
together.”</p>
<hr>
<p>In popular culture, Guelph theory has stirred the pot but not improved
the flavor, according to most. The problem of inclusion dominates
discussion.</p>
<p>The binary status of Guelph energy, combined with the relative
inaccessibility of legitimate testing, is taken by bigots for the
elaboration of hateful theories. The formula is that their preferred
group is Guelph positive while those they despise are negative (or,
more rarely, the reverse) and this can justify all manner of
atrocities.</p>
<p>The inclusion problem immediately confronts most philosophical
appropriations of Guelph theory. If Guelph energy is a mechanism for
free will, then why do only some people have it? Certainly this does
not resolve any problems in ethics.</p>
<p>To philosophers in the tradition of Dennett, Guelph energy is a red
herring, a distraction from anything that matters. The positive and
negative (unfortunate terms, really) can only be discriminated by
McKinsey device, not by introspection or any other behavior. Having a
second kind of thing in the brain changes nothing.</p>
<p>And since Guelph energy is still a phenomenon within the domain of
science, deterministic and described by equations, some look further
to a “third kind” that might finally explain everything that Guelph
theory does not.</p>
<p>For most, Guelph energy is just another mysterious part of the world,
like aurora and dreams and microwaves.</p>
<hr>
<p>“I love you,” said Adam into a microphone. They saw each other through
video monitors. Verona couldn't move her head, but every emotion
pulsed through her expression with the saccades of her eyes.</p>
<p>“Not like this,” she said. “I want to remember. Stop the experiment
and we can talk face to face.” Energy reflected off her eyes, into a
camera, through wires, off a screen, into Adam's eyes.</p>
<p>“It's already started,” said Adam. True to his word, he had programmed
the system to run without showing results, and it was running now.
Nobody used the emergency stop. What had been intended would be done.</p>
<p>Adam wasn't usually a gambler. But to ensure his experiment had
sufficient power to demonstrate the stimulated conversion of Guelph
energy to mass, he needed every Guelph positive participant he could
get. Between Adam and Verona, in expectation there was one subject.
The decision was already made in code. If he wasn't positive and she
was, she would join him in his doctoral experiment after all. Surely
she’d be okay with it. She knew how important this was. Professor Loi
was sure it was the right decision.</p>
<p>Whatever was happening in there now, he would tell her everything
afterward. The code was honest. There were no secrets between them.</p>
<hr>
<p>The largest religions have not changed policies regarding science and
have as much to say about Guelph theory as they do about electrolysis.
This does not prevent the religious from having their own beliefs on
the subject.</p>
<p>A few small religions, mostly for the super rich, admit only those who
have tested positive. Some claim a connection to Calvinism, and that
Guelph energy is evidence of predestined salvation.</p>
<p>Much more common, relatively, are religions that will certify Guelph
positive status without testing. These religions hold that their
certifications are more reliable than tests with a McKinsey device, so
they have no trouble resolving the odd contradictory result. Several
of these also claim a connection to Calvinism.</p>
<p>Neither religions that test before admittance nor those that certify
after joining seem to turn many people away, and data on Guelph energy
from any of them is generally not considered reliable by the
scientific community.</p>
<hr>
<p>“The phở tastes the same as always.” This is what Adam would have said
he was thinking, had anyone asked. He sat alone at the same small
white table. Phở had been their favorite.</p>
<p>The phở was hot. The noodles were chewy. The broth was salty. Sauce
added sweetness and a touch of sour. Umami-flavored protein floated at
the top.</p>
<p>Adam had never felt more alone.</p>
<p>As usual, he was surrounded by community here. So many people he
didn't know. He overheard but didn't understand snippets of Chinese at
a nearby table. He could turn on translation and join them, some day,
but for now it was a relief that the sounds died at his ears.</p>
<p>The lights were always so bright here, like an examination room. Like
the inside of a McKinsey chamber.</p>
<p>Adam tried to remember everything about Verona. What had it been that
made her so special? What was it that was gone, without her?</p>
<p>Had anyone asked, Adam would have said he was thinking that he'd never
know anyone like her again.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230325-conversion_of_guelph_energy_to_mass/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230325-conversion_of_guelph_energy_to_mass/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Solving a matching problem with OR-Tools CP-SAT</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Optimizing matching for preference satisfaction often focuses on
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stable_marriage_problem" title="Wikipedia: Stable marriage problem">stability</a>, which prioritizes individual interests. When maximizing
resource utilization is more important, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constraint_programming" title="Wikipedia: Constraint programming">Constraint Programming</a>
(CP) can be used to find good matches. Google's <a href="https://developers.google.com/optimization" title="OR-Tools | Google Developers">OR-Tools</a> package
includes the <a href="https://developers.google.com/optimization/cp/cp_solver" title="CP-SAT Solver | OR-Tools | Google Developers">CP-SAT</a> solver, which is one way to implement this.</p>
<p>For example, we may be assigning a pool of interns to specific roles.
Managers for each role have ranked some of the candidates, and a
candidate can only be matched to a role for which they have been
ranked. Roles often have one spot to be filled, but some have more.
Candidates have been ranked for multiple roles, but can only be
assigned one.</p>
<p>This problem is similar to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Resident_Matching_Program" title="Wikipedia: National Resident Matching Program">medical residency matching</a> problem,
which famously applies the Nobel-prize-winning
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gale%E2%80%93Shapley_algorithm" title="Wikipedia: Gale–Shapley algorithm">Gale–Shapley algorithm</a>. One difference is that the present example
only has preferences from one side. Sometimes random preferences are
created in order to still allow the application of algorithms like
Gale–Shapley, but this will not be necessary here because there is a
bigger issue.</p>
<p>The salient difference between what Gale–Shapley does and the goal of
the example here is that we really want to fill every available role,
even if it means the match isn't perfectly stable. Gale–Shapley will
create a match that leaves some roles unfilled if this is necessary to
ensure that no trade would better satisfy the preferences of the
individuals involved. In general, Gale–Shapley will leave some roles
unfilled.</p>
<p>To begin a solution with the OR-Tools (OR for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operations_research" title="Wikipedia: Operations research">Operations Research</a>)
package, we start by converting the rankings to scores, where 1 is the
best and 0 is the worst: <a href="rankings.csv"><code>rankings.csv</code></a> (There are
different ways of doing this, like percentiles; here we assume we have
scores.)</p>
<pre><code>role,person,score
Role 23,Person 11,0.5238095238095238
Role 23,Person 109,0.7619047619047619
Role 23,Person 111,0.6190476190476191
...</code></pre>

<p>Each role has some maximum number of spots to fill: <a href="spots.csv"><code>spots.csv</code></a></p>
<pre><code>Role 23,4
Role 31,1
Role 8,1
...</code></pre>

<p>We can start reading in data using Python.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">import csv

spots = {role: int(n) for role, n in csv.reader(open('spots.csv'))}
all_rankings = [ranking for ranking in csv.DictReader(open('rankings.csv'))]</code></pre>

<p>It will be convenient to have quick access to all the people ranked
for a role, and all the roles a person is ranked for.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">by_role, by_person = {}, {}

for ranking in all_rankings:
    by_role.setdefault(ranking['role'], []).append(ranking)
    by_person.setdefault(ranking['person'], []).append(ranking)</code></pre>

<p>Now we can start using OR-Tools.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">from ortools.sat.python import cp_model

model = cp_model.CpModel()
solver = cp_model.CpSolver()</code></pre>

<p>The matching will be represented via a Boolean variable for each
ranking that is true to select that match and false otherwise.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">for ranking in all_rankings:
    ranking['selected'] = model.NewBoolVar('')</code></pre>

<p>OR-Tools lets us use natural Python expressions to express
constraints. First, we dictate that each role should have no more than
the allowed number of people.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">for role, rankings in by_role.items():
    total = sum(ranking['selected'] for ranking in rankings)
    model.Add(total &lt;= spots[role])</code></pre>

<p>Similarly, we require that each person is matched with at most one
role.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">for person, rankings in by_person.items():
    total = sum(ranking['selected'] for ranking in rankings)
    model.Add(total &lt;= 1)</code></pre>

<p>The objective will be to maximize the total score of selected matches.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">total_score = 0
for ranking in all_rankings:
    score = float(ranking['score']) * ranking['selected']
    total_score += score</code></pre>

<p>At this point, we need only ask for the solution.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">model.Maximize(total_score)
status = solver.Solve(model)
print(solver.Value(total_score), solver.StatusName(status))
# 82.87644300144302 OPTIMAL</code></pre>

<p>You can check that every role has its maximal number of people, and
every person has one role (or zero; this example has more people than
spots). The CP-SAT solver has done the heavy lifting of finding a
solution and even guaranteeing that it is optimal.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">with open('results.csv', 'w') as f:
    writer = csv.DictWriter(f, all_rankings[0].keys())
    writer.writeheader()
    for ranking in all_rankings:
        ranking['selected'] = solver.Value(ranking['selected'])
        writer.writerow(ranking)</code></pre>

<p>Code is also available in a <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/blob/master/20230316-solving_a_matching_problem_with_ortools_cpsat/matching.ipynb">notebook</a>. Writing out results
produces: <a href="results.csv"><code>results.csv</code></a></p>
<pre><code>role,person,score,selected
Role 23,Person 11,0.5238095238095238,0
...
Role 23,Person 41,0.5714285714285714,1
...</code></pre>

<p>The approach here is general enough that with modifications it can be
applied to a wide range of more or less related problems. There is
always a question of whether the chosen metric is the right one to
optimize, but making some choice can get you pretty far toward a good
solution, with a solver that makes optimization easy. Indeed, what
other problems might be formulated in a manner amenable to solving in
this way? OR-Tools are handy!</p>
<hr>
<p>Thanks to Maxime Labonne, whose Linear Programming <a href="https://github.com/mlabonne/Linear-Programming-Course" title="Hands-on course about linear programming and mathematical optimization.">course</a> was very
helpful as I started to use OR-Tools.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230316-solving_a_matching_problem_with_ortools_cpsat/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230316-solving_a_matching_problem_with_ortools_cpsat/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Pity the Reader, by McConnell</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Vonnegut is the headline, and there are a lot of quotes, but it's
McConnell's book: elegy, eulogy, paean. I was down on the man a little
after I read about his affair in a biography years ago, but this
reminded me of his quality.</p>
<p>Vonnegut was an activist author, which I think is good. He was also an
entertainer and technician. Too much writing might as well come from
ChatGPT: predictable word after word. "Don’t be predictable. End your
sentences with something unexpected. Keep me awake." (page 195) A good
sentence delights you with pleasant thrills like a fresh ski run. On
writing with style: keep the entropy low.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<p>In the following quotes, I make no attempt to clarify whether they
come from Vonnegut or McConnell or a character etc.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"fiction is melody, and journalism, new or old, is noise." (page 44)</p>
<p>"Vonnegut earned no degree in anthropology." (page 52)</p>
<p>"Commitment invites Fate to be your Fairy Godmother Collaborator, to
close and open just the doors you need." (page 76)</p>
<p>"I once read an interview with John Barth and Kurt Vonnegut and
others in which Vonnegut stated that the reason all writers write,
of course, is that they want to change the world. Whereupon Barth
objected. No, he said. That wasn’t why he wrote. As I recall, Barth
said, in effect, that he just liked to horse around with words."
(page 84)</p>
<p>"Our awareness is all that is alive and maybe sacred in any of us."
(page 93)</p>
<p>"Writing is a generosity, even to yourself." (page 94)</p>
<p>"Vonnegut considered Galápagos his best book, by the way. Because
his canary-in-the-coal-mine is on urgent tweet." (page 119)</p>
<p>"Writers who are swoopers, it seems to me, find it wonderful that
people are funny or tragic or whatever, worth reporting, without
wondering why or how people are alive in the first place. Bashers,
while ostensibly making sentence after sentence as efficient as
possible, may actually be breaking down seeming doors and fences,
cutting their ways through seeming barbed-wire entanglements, under
fire and in an atmosphere of mustard gas, in search of answers to
these eternal questions: “What in heck should we be doing? What in
heck is really going on?”" (page 171)</p>
<p>"The young man did not appear to be listening to his own radio. He
may not even have understood English. The newscaster spoke with a
barking sort of hilarity, as though life were a comical
steeplechase, with unconventional steeds and hazards and vehicles
involved. He made me feel that even I was a contestant—in a bathtub
drawn by three aardvarks, perhaps. I had as good a chance as anybody
to win." (page 176)</p>
<p>"You have to play by the rules of the game of fiction well enough so
that you can get across what is in the rag-and-bone shop of your
heart. You have to be like a magician or pickpocket, distracting the
audience by entertaining, while you are really saying those things
you most want to say." (page 189)</p>
<p>"I don’t praise plots as accurate representations of life, but as
ways to keep readers reading." (page 202)</p>
<p>"“The thing Kurt seemed to want most in a story,” his student Ronni
Sandroff recalls, “was to be surprised. He once challenged us to
pause before we turned to the next page in a book and try to guess
how the sentence we were in the middle of would end. “You’ll almost
always get it right,” he said." (page 212)</p>
<p>"He warned against tiresomeness. He urged originality, freshness."
(page 212)</p>
<p>"Nothing in real life ends. “Millicent at last understands.” Nobody
ever understands." (page 215)</p>
<p>"it strikes me as gruesome and comical that in our culture we have
an expectation that a man can always solve his problems. There is
that implication that if you just have a little more energy, a
little more fight, the problem can always be solved. This is so
untrue that it makes me want to cry—or laugh." (page 270)</p>
<p>"“Since I took up carpentry,” Mark the pediatrician avows, “I
measure children much more carefully, sometimes to 1/32 of an
inch.”" (page 351)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230307-pity_the_reader_by_mcconnell/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230307-pity_the_reader_by_mcconnell/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Voltage Effect, by List</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The subtitle is "How to make good ideas great and great ideas scale,"
but a lot of it is about how to avoid bad ideas. The "Five Vital
Signs" are really five kinds of problems:</p>
<ol>
<li>Reliability: Thinking a test is promising when it's not: "Dupers
   and false positives"</li>
<li>Validity of a test sample: "Know your audience" or "overestimating
   how big a slice of the pie your idea can capture" or
   "representativeness of population"</li>
<li>Scalability of the treatment: "situational validity" or "unscalable
   ingredients" and "program drift" and "noncompliance"</li>
<li>Unintended consequences: "Spillovers"</li>
<li>Just too expensive: "The cost trap"</li>
</ol>
<p>Problems 4 and 5 could be special cases of 3.</p>
<p>Then there are four chapters that have some more positive
recommendations:</p>
<ol>
<li>"using behavioral-economic incentives"</li>
<li>"exploiting easily missed opportunities on the margins of your operation"</li>
<li>"knowing when to quit in the short term in order to win in the long term"</li>
<li>"culture that is sustainable at scale"</li>
</ol>
<p>It's a pop economics book. Marginal revolution, comparative advantage,
anecdotes from academia and Uber and Lyft and government. It's not
awful, but I didn't feel like it delivered quite what it promised.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Through my research and time working with policymakers, my personal
credo had become that the only ideas worth pursuing are the ones
with the potential to make a significant impact on human lives."
(page 6)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... the one thing all great ideas have in common is that they are
not guaranteed to succeed. ... the path from early promise to
widespread impact requires one thing and one thing only:
<em>scalability</em>—the capacity to grow and expand in a robust and
sustainable way." (page 9)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is this a contradiction? Great ideas may or may not be scalable? But
wouldn't a good idea be better if it was scalable?</p>
<p>Bad scalable ideas seem clearly allowed.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"(a charity will attract more donations in the short run <em>and</em> long
run if they attract initial donors by promising to never bother them
again rather than with the traditional strategy of constant
follow-ups)" (page 10)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The reference is <a href="https://spihub.org/site/resource_files/publications/spi_wp_025_list.pdf" title="Once and Done: Leveraging Behavioral Economicsto Increase Charitable Contributions">Once and Done</a> and I wonder whether it's been
replicated. The effect they find is strong, but their experiment is
with Smile Train, whose mailers include prominent photos of children
with cleft palates. The authors offered mechanism includes that "a
solicitation by a charity imposes a cost on the recipient," and in the
case of Smile Train that cost may be particularly high and not due
only to social pressure.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The book calls upon policy-makers to move their attention from
evidence-based policy to policy-based evidence." (page 15)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>List seems to want to make this his catch-phrase. It's repeated on (at
least) pages 15, 63, 87, and 233. I don't think it works as a slogan
because, for one, it isn't terribly clear. I <em>think</em> he's advocating
for program evaluation?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conjoint_analysis">conjoint analysis</a>" (page 53)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Logan believed that the extra perks combined with the 15% discount
on rides (rather than the 7.5 percent discount we'd initially
calculated) would motivate more JoGoods to join." (page 53)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This seems like an interesting story of data vs. executive
decision-making, but List doesn't elaborate further.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backward_induction">backward induction</a>" (page 87)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The spillover effect falls under a larger umbrella category
popularly known as the law of unintended consequences." (page 91)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Based on my experience with the baseball fundraising, one would
expect that making salaries transparent could drive resentful
demoralization if people saw peers making more. But that is not the
full story." (page 99)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He found that when he randomly paid some people less (for an identical
job) and they found out by talking to others, those paid less worked
less hard.</p>
<p>The more to the story he references is a study where when people
learned their managers made more than they thought, they worked
harder.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230226-voltage_effect_by_list/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230226-voltage_effect_by_list/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Ten Equations that Rule the World, by Sumpter</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://www.david-sumpter.com/" title="David Sumpter">Sumpter</a> has Bill Nye applied math energy. His central gimmick—a
secret society of people who know math—is a bit much. He's most
interesting when connecting equations and philosophy, but he likes
logical positivism more than his hero Ayers <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Language,_Truth,_and_Logic#Ayer's_later_rejection_of_logical_positivism" title="Wikipedia: Ayer's later rejection of logical positivism">did</a>, and his ultimate
appeal to ethical intuitionism is unsatisfying. Still very interesting
in places, and I'm generally with him.</p>
<p>I like the core idea of trying to distill a lot of understanding into
a few core concepts. I think Sumpter's book highlights both the
promise and challenge of attempting this.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<p>Here are the names Sumpter uses for his equations (and more
conventional names):</p>
<ol>
<li>The Judgment Equation (Bayes' theorem)</li>
<li>The Betting Equation (Logistic regression)</li>
<li>The Confidence Equation (Normal confidence intervals)</li>
<li>The Skill Equation (Markov property; memorylessness)</li>
<li>The Influencer Equation (Stationary distribution; PageRank)</li>
<li>The Market Equation (A sort of autoregressive differential model?)</li>
<li>The Advertising Equation (Correlation coefficient)</li>
<li>The Reward Equation (Exponential moving average; Q-learning)</li>
<li>The Learning Equation (Derivative of quadratic loss; gradient
   descent)</li>
<li>The Universal Equation (If-then; trying to get from "is" to
    "ought")</li>
</ol>
<p>With the exception of #6, I was reasonably familiar with all of these.
My failure to feel connected to the literature (or even what a common
name might be) for #6 makes me feel that this book might not be the
best way to encounter these ideas for the first time.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The first lesson to draw from Bayes's rule, the judgment equation,
is that we should be slow to draw definitive conclusions." (page 15)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Many people think of math as being all about objectivity; it's not.
It is a way of representing and arguing about the world, and
sometimes the things we argue about are known only to us." (page 24)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He's a professor of applied math, after all.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Much of mathematical modeling is about dividing the world into
understandable component parts, ..." (page 63)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"What I hadn't understood when I started working with sports
statistics was just how much time I would have to sit listening to
men telling me why they believed they were the special one." (page
85)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When Andrey Markov first wrote down his equation, he wasn't
interested in modeling sporting excellence. He was interested in
great literature. In 1913, he presented, at the Russian Royal
Academy of Sciences, an analysis of the first chapter and parts of
the second chapter of Pushkin's novel <em>Eugene Onegin.</em> In his
analysis of these twenty thousand Russian letters, he determined the
probability of sequences of vowels and consonants. He constructed a
model that predicted, based on the letter that had just occurred in
a text, whether a vowel or a consonant was more likely to occur as
the next character. In doing so, Markov had created a model for
creating new Pushkin works, one character at a time." (page 92)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Neat! I think I hadn't heard this story before.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Accurate reporting of assumptions is just as important as accurate
reporting of results." (page 99)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The salaries offered by tech giants were enough to lure even the
purest of mathematicians." (page 113)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The division of the world into models, data, and nonsense gave the
members of TEN a sense of certainty." (page 122)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I had researched Cambridge Analytica's algorithm in detail during
2017, the year before the scandal broke, and reached a conclusion
that contradicted both Nix and Wylie's versions of events. I doubted
that the company could have influenced the US presidential election.
They had certainly tried, but the methods they claimed to have used
to target voters were flawed." (page 146)</p>
<p>"Working on the inside, he [<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aleksandr_Kogan_(scientist)" title="Wikipedia: Aleksandr Kogan (scientist)">Alex Kogan</a>] had reached the same
conclusion about Cambridge Analytica as I had. He phrased it
politely at the Senate hearing. To me, he said, “That shit doesn't
work.”" (page 164)</p>
<p>"Instead of looking for the real reasons for the rise of
nationalistic sentiment that had brought Donald Trump to power, that
had caused Brexit, that was responsible for the Five Star movement
in Italy, Viktor Orbán in Hungary, and Jair Bolsonaro in Brazil,
everyone seemed to be rushing to find a James Bond-type villain, an
evil individual who had poisoned the political waters. Their Dr. No
came in the form of Alexander Nix and his company, Cambridge
Analytica. Somehow this man, with only a basic understanding of
models and data, was seen to have manipulated the whole of modern
democracy." (page 168)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I had some wonderings like this while reading <a href="https://planspace.org/20221029-mindf*ck_by_wylie/" title="Mindf*ck, by Wylie">Mindf*ck</a>...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The organization Tristan Harris cofounded, the
<a href="https://www.humanetech.com/">Center for Humane Technology</a>, has advice about how to take
control and move your own mind away from the tipping point." (page
186)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Page 187 mentions lazy ants, but is apparently unaware of follow-up
research. (<a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2017/09/170908205356.htm" title="Lazy ants make themselves useful in unexpected ways">coverage</a>)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Price believed, building on the philosophy of Plato, that
mathematics provided a truth that was independent of our physical
reality and that this truth told us the ethical thing to do. But A.
J. Ayer seemed to overwrite this view in the mid-twentieth century,
arguing with his principle of verifiability that we can't expect to
find any answers to moral questions in math. A mathematics that is
independent of physical reality, he demonstrated, is impossible to
verify." (page 209)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The sheer number of mathematical theorems that have proved to be
true led French mathematician Henri Poincaré to reflect in his 1902
book, <em>Science and Hypothesis,</em> that “if all the assertions which
mathematics puts forward can be derived from one another by formal
logic, mathematics cannot amount to anything more than an immense
tautology. Logical inference can teach us nothing essentially new
... But can we really allow that these theorems which fill so many
books serve no other purpose than to say in a roundabout fashion
that ‘A = A’?”" (page 214)</p>
<p>"In response to the rhetorical tone used by Poincaré, Ayer wrote,
“The power of logic and mathematics to surprise us depends, like
their usefulness, on the limitations of our reason.”" (page 216)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I have come to believe that there is a very simple answer to these
dilemmas: we should learn to trust and use our own ethical
intuitions." (page 222)</p>
<p>"I don't have any conclusive proof, but I believe that after logical
positivism strips away the idea of a universal utilitarianism, we
are left with moral intuition to guide us. It is this soft way of
thinking that tells us which problems to solve." (page 223)</p>
<p>"We need to be soft when we define our problems and brutally hard
when we solve them." (page 223)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230116-ten_equations_that_rule_the_world/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230116-ten_equations_that_rule_the_world/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
