<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>Everybody Lies, by Stephens-Davidowitz</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I finally read my copy of this <a href="http://sethsd.com/everybodylies">book</a>, which is a final form of the
author's collected <a href="http://sethsd.com/research">research</a> using "non-traditional" data, chiefly
Google search data. The contribution of <a href="https://twitter.com/natesilver538/status/703975062500732932">racism</a> to Trump's election
is a headline claim. I don't know that I'm as optimistic as the author
that these techniques all yield uniformly stronger claims than
"conventional" research.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As if the tradeoff between tractability and richness weren't bad
enough, scientists of human nature are vexed by the Law of Small
Numbers&#8211;Amos Tversky and Daniel Kahneman's name for the fallacy of
thinking that the traits of a population will be reflected in any
sample, no matter how small." (page x, in the foreword by Steven
Pinker)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The true divide [of racism in the US], Google search data
suggested, was not South versus North; it was East versus West. You
don't get this sort of thing much west of the Mississippi." (pages
7-8)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I am now convinced that Google searches are the most important
dataset ever collected on the human psyche." (page 14)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"At Google, major decisions are based on only a tiny sampling of all
their data." (page 21)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is citing Hal Varian's <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.28.2.3">Big Data: New Tricks for Econometrics</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Good data science is less complicated than people think. The best
data science is, in fact, surprisingly intuitive." (page 26)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"If you can't understand a study, the problem is probably with the
study, not with you." (page 27)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>"Offering up new types of data is the first power of Big Data."</li>
<li>"Providing honest data is the second power of Big Data."</li>
<li>"Allowing us to zoom in on small subsets of people is the third
   power of Big Data."</li>
<li>"Allowing us to do many causal experiments is the fourth power of
   Big Data." (pages 53-54)</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>On page 57 he mentions "<a href="https://research.google/pubs/pub41695/">Google Correlate</a>," which seems neat
("Google Trends in reverse") and was publicly available from 2011 to
2019.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The Big Data revolution is less about collecting more and more
data. It is about collecting the right data." (page 62)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"First, and perhaps most important, if you are going to try to use
new data to revolutionize a field, it is best to go into a field
where old methods are lousy."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He's going through a sort of "Moneyball for X" survey of people:</p>
<ul>
<li>Horse racing: Jeff Seder</li>
<li>Wine: Orley Ashenfelter</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>"The second lesson is that, when trying to make predictions, you
needn't worry too much about why your models work."</p>
<p>"The final lesson to be learned from Seder's successful attempt to
predict a potential Triple Crown winner is that you have to be open
and flexible in determining what counts as data." (pages 71-74)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>On page 91, he references a <a href="https://epjdatascience.springeropen.com/articles/10.1140/epjds/s13688-016-0093-1" title="The emotional arcs of stories are dominated by six basic shapes">study</a> that provides quantitative
evidence for Vonnegut's <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oP3c1h8v2ZQ&amp;ab_channel=DavidComberg">Shapes of Stories</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>""About one-third of the time, people lie in real life," he
suggests. "The habits carry over to surveys."" (page 107, quoting
Roger Tourangeau)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Another reason for lying is simply to mess with surveys. This is a
huge problem for any research regarding teenagers, fundamentally
complicating our ability to understand this age group. Researchers
originally found a correlation between a teenager's being adopted
and a variety of negative behaviors, such as using drugs, drinking
alcohol, and skipping school. In subsequent research, they found
this correlation was entirely explained by the 19 percent of
self-reported adopted teenagers who weren't actually adopted.
Follow-up research has found that a meaningful percent of teenagers
tell surveys they are more than seven feet tall, weigh more than
four hundred pounds, or have three children. One survey found 99
percent of students who reported having an artificial limb to
academic researchers were kidding." (page 108)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"He has always known he was attracted to men, he says, but thought
that this was universal and something that all men just hid." (page
119)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This kind of thing is fascinating to me&#8211;private conspiracy theories
that are self-protecting and secretly mislead those who form them. I
imagine that many racist people, "proud boys," etc. believe that most
people agree with them but hide their belief. See also expressions
like "He's saying what we're all thinking," which is a statement that is difficult to verify.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"One thing that does not seem to matter
[for explaining Trump support]: economics." (page 139)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Around page 144, he's talking about how the internet is less
segregated than you might think, in terms of people of all political
persuasions reading the most popular news sites and so on. He points
out also that "a surprising amount of the information people get on
Facebook comes from people with opposing views." This makes me wonder
how much the perception/reality of increased polarization is <em>caused
by</em> more communication and exposure to different views. If I never
hear about my aunt's crazy beliefs, I'm less likely to get upset about
them and feel like I need to advocate against them. Maybe hearing
about anti-racism makes some people more racist? Hmm.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I think it's safe to say that the Great Recession did make child
abuse worse, although the traditional measures did not show it."
(page 147)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We can't blindly trust government data. The government may tell us
that child abuse or abortion has fallen and politicians may
celebrate this achievement. But the results we think we're seeing
may be an artifact of flaws in the methods of collection. The truth
may be different&#8211;and sometimes, far darker." (pages 149-150)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is not a critique that is specific to government data...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Digital truth serum has revealed an abiding interest in judging
people based on their looks; the continued existence of millions of
closeted gay men; a meaningful percentage of women fantasizing about
rape; widespread animus against African-Americans; a hidden child
abuse and self-induced abortion crisis; and an outbreak of violent
Islamophobic rage that only got worse when the president appealed
for tolerance." (page 158)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"First, there can be comfort in knowing that you are not alone in
your insecurities and embarrassing behavior."</p>
<p>"The second benefit of digital truth serum is that it alerts us to
people who are suffering."</p>
<p>"The final&#8211;and, I think, most powerful&#8211;value in this digital truth
serum is indeed its ability to lead us from problems to solutions."
(pages 158-162)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Recall that Chetty's team was trying to figure out what areas are
good at allowing people to reach the upper middle class. My study
was trying to figure out what areas are good at allowing people to
reach fame. The results are strikingly different." (page 184)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is sort of an interesting look at success for the masses versus
success for the few, or at least at different levels/types of
"success"... A possible hypothesis might be that the two should go
together (more general success, more peak success) but that doesn't
seem to be the case. The ideas of success may be too different?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"On a given day in some schools in rural India, more than 40 percent
of teachers are absent." (page 209)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That's referencing <a href="https://economics.mit.edu/files/5582">Incentives Work: Getting Teachers to Come to School</a>, which has this abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"We use a randomized experiment and a structural model to test
whether monitoring and financial incentives can reduce teacher
absence and increase learning in India. In treatment schools,
teachers&#8217; attendance was monitored daily using cameras, and their
salaries were made a nonlinear function of attendance. Teacher
absenteeism in the treatment group fell by 21 percentage points
relative to the control group, and the children&#8217;s test scores
increased by 0.17 standard deviations. We estimate a structural
dynamic labor supply model and find that teachers respond strongly
to financial incentives. Our model is used to compute
cost-minimizing compensation policies."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Many economists previously leaned toward the view that leaders
largely were impotent figureheads pushed around by external forces.
Not so, according to Jones and Olken's analysis of nature's
experiment." (page 228)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That's referencing <a href="https://economics.mit.edu/files/3055">Hit or Miss? The Effect of Assassinations on Institutions and War</a>, which has this abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Assassinations are a persistent feature of the political landscape.
Using a new dataset of assassination attempts on all world leaders
from 1875 to 2004, we exploit inherent randomness in the success or
failure of assassination attempts to identify the effects of
assassination. We find that, on average, successful assassinations
of autocrats produce sustained moves toward democracy. We also find
that assassinations affect the intensity of small-scale conflicts.
The results document a contemporary source of institutional change,
inform theories of conflict, and show that small sources of
randomness can have a pronounced effect on history."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Kind of an interesting analysis for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_man_theory">the great man theory</a>...</p>
<hr>
<p>Some discussion around page 238 of the (non-)benefit of going to
Harvard etc... It's more useful to be the kind of person who <em>could</em>
go to Harvard (get in, etc.) - the perceived incremental benefit of
going to Harvard vs. some other school may not be real.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Generally, if someone tells you he will pay you back, he will not
pay you back." (page 259)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is about people writing on microfinance sites. Sounds about
right; interesting to see quantitative support for this kind of thing.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"social science is becoming a real science."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He says this is the "big point" of his book...</p>
<hr>
<p>Strong praise for Jawbone on page 277, which turned out to be bad
timing as the company went under the year the book came out (2017)...</p>
<hr>
<p>On page 283 there's a reference to Ellenberg's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawking_Index">Hawking Index</a>,
which was amusing to me because I've enjoyed following Ellenberg a
little bit since reading his <a href="/20200925-how_not_to_be_wrong_by_ellenberg/">How Not to Be Wrong</a>.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210314-everybody_lies_by_stephens-davidowitz/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210314-everybody_lies_by_stephens-davidowitz/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Intuition, action, and luck (and Harry Potter)</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>When work is going well, it feels good. It feels playful. Not like
following a plan or map, but exploring freely with only the loosest
sense of a destination in mind, until you find you've solved your
problem. It feels <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sn72qYmsWco">like</a> the <a href="https://harrypotter.fandom.com/wiki/Felix_Felicis">luck potion</a> from the Harry Potter
world:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&#8220;What does it feel like?&#8221; whispered Hermione.</p>
<p>Harry did not answer for a moment. Then, slowly but surely, an
exhilarating sense of infinite opportunity stole through him; he
felt as though he could have done anything, anything at all . . .
and getting the memory from Slughorn seemed suddenly not only
possible, but positively easy. . . .</p>
<p>He got to his feet, smiling, brimming with confidence.</p>
<p>&#8220;Excellent,&#8221; he said. &#8220;Really excellent. Right . . . I&#8217;m going down
to Hagrid&#8217;s.&#8221;</p>
<p>...</p>
<p>Why he knew that going to Hagrid&#8217;s was the right thing to do, he had
no idea. It was as though the potion was illuminating a few steps of
the path at a time: He could not see the final destination, he could
not see where Slughorn came in, but he knew that he was going the
right way to get that memory. When he reached the entrance hall he
saw that Filch had forgotten to lock the front door. Beaming, Harry
threw it open and breathed in the smell of clean air and grass for a
moment before walking down the steps into the dusk.</p>
<p>It was when he reached the bottom step that it occurred to him how
very pleasant it would be to pass the vegetable patch on his walk to
Hagrid&#8217;s. It was not strictly on the way, but it seemed clear to
Harry that this was a whim on which he should act, so he directed
his feet immediately toward the vegetable patch, where he was
pleased, but not altogether surprised, to find Professor Slughorn in
conversation with Professor Sprout. Harry lurked behind a low stone
wall, feeling at peace with the world and listening to their
conversation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's good to have this sense of "feeling at peace with the world" and
trying things even when you don't know for sure, consciously, how
they'll help. It's following your intuition in the sense of
<a href="/20210116-pragmatic_thinking_and_learning/">Pragmatic Thinking and Learning</a>.</p>
<p>It's also doing things because of "how very pleasant" they could be.
It's a bias toward action&#8211;playful action&#8211;and trying things that are
<a href="/20181204-worth_doing_even_if_it_fails/">worth doing even if they fail</a>.</p>
<p>There aren't any luck potions, but <a href="https://www.instituteforgiving.org/resources-for-fundraisers/fundraising-verities/item/313-verities-65-luck-favors-the-prepared-mind">luck favors the prepared mind</a>.
This kind of intuition-guided flow state isn't a consistent method,
but it's nice when it happens.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210227-intuition_action_and_luck_and_harry_potter/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210227-intuition_action_and_luck_and_harry_potter/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Vision and Mission</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<h3>Increasing the awareness of the universe</h3>
<p>I build and share understanding of the world to improve life for the
people I love most, and for everyone. I learn from others and from the
world, communicating and educating in turn to engage growth. I build
systems that contribute to these processes. I make improvements every
day to myself, my relationships, and the world around me.</p>
<hr>
<p>I was <a href="https://smile.amazon.com/gp/product/1642500267/">inspired</a> to "refine" my personal <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mission_statement">mission</a> statement, but
I had to make one first. I like brief <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vision_statement">vision</a> statements so I came
up with one of those as well.</p>
<p>I particularly like the vision, which can include lots of things I'm
interested in, including research, data science, and education.
There's a connection to <a href="https://westcoastword.wordpress.com/2013/04/22/chapter-7-the-purpose-of-life-from-breakfast-of-champions-by-kurt-vonnegut/">Vonnegut</a> as well:</p>
<pre>
What is the purpose of life?

To be
the eyes
and ears
and conscience
of the Creator of the Universe,
you fool.
</pre>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210226-vision_and_mission/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210226-vision_and_mission/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Elementary Presidents of the US Nations</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>There are 10 two-letter codes that correspond to both <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_U.S._state_and_territory_abbreviations">US states</a>
and ISO 3166 <a href="https://www.iso.org/iso-3166-country-codes.html">country codes</a> and (lowercasing the second letter) an
element from the <a href="https://ptable.com/">periodic table</a> with atomic number corresponding
to a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_presidents_of_the_United_States">US president</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1iv8Wdui64jiDkrM3fo5UFzhYFaXdvrl-O1vbJ8nEgYk/edit?usp=sharing"><img alt="table" src="table.png"></a></p>
<p>See all 324 data rows <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1iv8Wdui64jiDkrM3fo5UFzhYFaXdvrl-O1vbJ8nEgYk/edit?usp=sharing">as a Google Sheet</a>, or sources and processing
in the <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/tree/master/20210225-elementary_presidents_of_the_us_nations">README</a>.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210225-elementary_presidents_of_the_us_nations/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210225-elementary_presidents_of_the_us_nations/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Microphones matter</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<table>
<tr>

<td>
MacBook Air built-in mic
<audio controls src="computer_mic.mp3"></audio>
</td>

<td>
Apple wired headphone mic
<audio controls src="wired_apple_headphone_mic.mp3"></audio>
</td>

</tr>
<tr>

<td>
Bose QC35 II wireless headphone mic
<audio controls src="wireless_headphone_mic.mp3"></audio>
</td>

<td>
Blue Yeti USB mic
<audio controls src="new_mic.mp3"></audio>
</td>

</tr>
</table>

<p>These sound different! The laptop mic has <em>tons</em> of room noise. I
think the Bose headphones are trying hard to do clever signal
processing which reduces background noise but also makes my voice more
muted and a little robotic in places. The Yeti is pretty good but
still picks up some unintended nearby sounds despite being in
directional mode.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210218-microphones_matter/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210218-microphones_matter/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Big Con, by Maurer</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Published in 1940, WWI was "the War" (page 28), WWII was "the present
European War" (page 311), there were thousand-dollar <a href="https://www.investopedia.com/6-famous-discontinued-and-uncommon-u-s-currency-denominations-4773302#1000-bill">G-notes</a>, and
there was quite a lot of sexism and racism (throughout). Instead of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advance-fee_scam">emails from Nigerian princes</a>, you might see a classified ad in the
paper "For an honest, reliable businessman with $20,000 to invest for
a large return." (page 115) There were elaborate plots! Would you
really not fall for anything like that? What are people falling for
these days? Quite a lot! What a world, what a world.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"After all, a look around present-day American institutions should
suffice to demonstrate that the character in question has now fully
emerged from the underworld and entered the mainstream, where he may
be far less colorful and imaginative, but no less on the grift."
(page xv, from the introduction by Luc Sante)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Their methods differ more in degree than in kind from those
employed by more legitimate forms of business." (page 3)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The three big-con games, the <em>wire</em>, the <em>rag</em>, and the <em>pay-off</em>."
(page 3)</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><em>the wire</em>: "A big-con game in which the insideman (passing as a
   Western Union official) convinces the mark that he can delay the
   race results going to the book-makers long enough for the mark to
   place a bet after the race is run. The roper makes a mistake and
   the mark loses."</li>
<li><em>the rag</em>: "An intricate big-con game very similar to the pay-off,
   except that stocks are used instead of races. The insideman poses
   as an agent for a broker's syndicate which is trying to break the
   bucket-shops. The mark profits on several investments, is sent for
   a large sum of money, and is fleeced."</li>
<li><em>the pay-off</em>: "The most lucrative of all big-con games, with
   touches running from $10,000 up, with those of $100,000 being
   common. It operates on the principle that a wealthy mark is induced
   to believe that he has been taken into a deal whereby a large
   racing syndicate is to be swindled. At first he pays with money
   furnished him by the confidence men, then is put on the send for
   all the cash he can raise, fleeced, and blown off. The pay-off
   (invented in 1906) evolved from the short-pay at the track and was
   fully developed by 1910, when the big stores appeared in many of
   the larger cities."</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Most marks come from the upper strata of society, which, in
America, means that they have made, married, or inherited money.
Because of this, they acquire status which in time they come to
attribute to some inherent superiority, especially as regards
matters of sound judgment in finance and investment. Friends and
associates, themselves social climbers and sycophants, help to
maintain this illusion of superiority. Eventually, the mark comes to
regard himself as a person of vision and even of genius. Thus a
Babbitt who has cleared half a million in a real-estate development
easily forgets the part which luck and chicanery have played in his
financial rise; he accepts his mantle of respectability without
question; he na&#239;vely attributes his success to sound business
judgment. And any confidence man will testify that a real-estate man
is the fattest and juiciest of suckers." (page 104)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Religious scruples often seem to fail a mark at the crucial
moment." (page 105)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>""Larceny," or thieves' blood, runs not only in the veins of
professional thieves; it would appear that humanity at large has
just a dash of it&#8211;and sometimes more." (page 117)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Many con men feel that marks have one characteristic in common&#8211;they
are all liars." (page 118)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Such institutions [schools for grifters] have long been the delight
of fictioneers, but there is no reliable evidence to indicate that
they ever functioned in the American underworld." (page 160)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>The author references on page 164 "Dan the Dude's place at 28 W. 28th
St." as being a hangout for con men. It has been otherwise known as
well, <a href="https://ephemeralnewyork.wordpress.com/tag/28-west-28th-street/">it seems</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When we think of cheese, it's Wisconsin; when we speak of oil, it's
Pennsylvania; but with grifters, it's Indiana." (page 173)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"If fifty of them [con men] were selected and mixed indiscriminately
with a group of successful business and professional men, all the
correlations and statistics of a Hooton or a Lombroso would not set
them apart; and, if a census of opinions upon politics, ethics,
religion, or what-not were taken from the entire group, not even a
Solomon could separate the sheep from the goats on the basis of
their social views. If confidence men operate outside the law, it
must be remembered that they are not much further outside than many
of our pillars of society who go under names less sinister. They
only carry to an ultimate and very logical conclusion certain trends
which are often inherent in various forms of legitimate business."
(pages 178-179)</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earnest_Hooton">Earnest Hooton</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cesare_Lombroso">Cesare Lombroso</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The <em>short deck</em>. A short-con game operated by a man who drops one
card out of a deck he has offered to sell a mark very cheaply. They
argue over whether or not it is a full deck, then bet. The mark
thinks the deck is short one card, but the operator produces a full
deck." (page 304)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... a booming campaign of propaganda designed to rob the criminal
of the sympathetic public opinion he has for so long enjoyed." (page
312, with "federal operatives" behind this campaign)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3>Just words</h3>
<ul>
<li><em>appurtenance</em>: an accessory or other item associated with a
   particular activity or style of living</li>
<li><em>blackjack</em>: a short, leather-covered, typically lead-filled club
   with a flexible handle, used as a weapon</li>
<li><em>cackle-bladder</em>: a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cackle-bladder">means</a> of faking someone's death through the
   use of a rubber bladder filled with fake blood</li>
<li><em>chary</em>: cautiously or suspiciously reluctant to do something</li>
<li><em>charwoman</em>: a woman employed to clean houses or offices</li>
<li><em>chestnut</em>: a joke or story that has become tedious because of its
   age and constant repetition</li>
<li><em>chicane</em>: (from context) down on one's luck, broke, from (in card
   games) a hand without cards of one particular suit; a void</li>
<li><em>chicanery</em>: the use of trickery to achieve a political, financial,
   or legal purpose</li>
<li><em>connivance</em>: willingness to secretly allow or be involved in
   wrongdoing, especially an immoral or illegal act (as "with the
   connivance of officials")</li>
<li><em>crotchet</em>: a perverse or unfounded belief or notion</li>
<li><em>cupidity</em>: greed for money or possessions</li>
<li><em>demimonde</em>: (in 19th-century France) the class of women considered
   to be of doubtful morality and social standing; a group of people
   considered to be on the fringes of respectable society</li>
<li><em>depredation</em>: an act of attacking or plundering</li>
<li><em>diddle</em>: cheat or swindle (someone) so as to deprive them of
   something; deliberately falsify (something)</li>
<li><em>dissimulation</em>: concealment of one's thoughts, feelings, or
   character; pretense</li>
<li><em>doggerel</em>: comic verse composed in irregular rhythm; verse or
   words that are badly written or expressed</li>
<li><em>entomology</em>: the branch of zoology concerned with the study of
   insects</li>
<li><em>Faro</em>: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Faro_(card_game)">a specific old card game</a></li>
<li><em>fourflusher</em>: (a person who does this) (in poker) bluff when
   holding a weak hand, particularly a four flush; keep up a pretense;
   bluff</li>
<li><em>Gesamtkunstwerk</em>: a work of art that makes use of all or many art
   forms or strives to do so</li>
<li><em>hare-lip</em>: another term for cleft lip/palate</li>
<li><em>hep</em>: archaic or dialect term for "hip" in the sense of "wise"</li>
<li><em>inveigh</em>: speak or write about (something) with great hostility</li>
<li><em>larceny</em>: theft of personal property</li>
<li><em>much lost motion</em>: inefficiency, wasted busywork</li>
<li><em>obdurate</em>: stubbornly refusing to change one's opinion or course
   of action</li>
<li><em>obstreperous</em>: noisy and difficult to control</li>
<li><em>picaresque</em>: relating to an episodic style of fiction dealing with
   the adventures of a rough and dishonest but appealing hero</li>
<li><em>piker</em>: a gambler who makes only small bets; a stingy or cautious
   person</li>
<li><em>plunger</em>: a person who gambles or spends money recklessly</li>
<li><em>Pullman</em>: (car, couch, case) associated with a railroad car
   affording special comfort, especially one with sleeping berths</li>
<li><em>q.v.</em>: "quod vide&#257;s" (Latin) "which see" after something to refer
   to additional information for</li>
<li><em>ribald</em>: referring to sexual matters in an amusingly coarse or
   irreverent way</li>
<li><em>roister</em>: enjoy oneself or celebrate in a noisy or boisterous way</li>
<li><em>scapegrace</em>: a mischievous or wayward person, especially a young
   person or child; a rascal</li>
<li><em>shill</em>: an accomplice of a hawker, gambler, or swindler who acts
   as an enthusiastic customer to entice or encourage others (also
   "shillaber")</li>
<li><em>tout</em>: a person soliciting custom or business, typically in an
   aggressive or bold manner; a person who offers racing tips for a
   share of any resulting winnings</li>
<li><em>venire</em>: an entire panel from which a jury is drawn</li>
<li><em>winchell</em>: a confidence trickster&#8217;s victim, a sucker (from the
   image of gossip writer Walter Winchell as &#8216;swallowing&#8217; any story)</li>
</ul>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210214-the_big_con_by_maurer/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210214-the_big_con_by_maurer/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>High Concept Pitch Generator</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p></p><center>
<h3>We had a three-day retreat and came up with a new startup concept:</h3>
<h1><div id="concept"></div></h1>

<h5>(reload for a new billion-dollar idea) (royalties to <a href="https://twitter.com/planarrowspace">@planarrowspace</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/chris_whong">@chris_whong</a>)</h5>

<p></p></center>
<hr>
<p>This is a re-hosting of the <a href="http://bl.ocks.org/ajschumacher/raw/5511522/">original</a> Chris and I made in 2013. We
were reminded of it by <a href="http://pitchdeck.business/">Pitch Deck</a>, which turns this idea into a
party game (with better <a href="https://gist.github.com/ajschumacher/5511522">lists</a>, I think).</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210213-high_concept_pitch_generator/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210213-high_concept_pitch_generator/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>101 things to learn in art school, by Kit White</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I picked up this little coffee table <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/101-things-learn-art-school">book</a> at the
<a href="https://bookshop.org/shop/themitpressbookstore">MIT Press Bookstore</a> a while ago. It's cute. Some good stuff in
there. I'm a sucker for this kind of format recently.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<h3>My four favorite items from the book:</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>"16. Words are images. The power of the visual belongs to all things
received visually. The written word is both symbol and cognitive
catalyst; image and thought embodied. But words also conjure the
image that lives only as a thought or non-embodied object. Some
ideas are most potent when not embodied and exist as ephemeral,
fleeting experiences. Concept has form."</p>
<p>"25. Style is the consequence of something being described in the
way most appropriate to its content. It is not a hemline height or a
gratuitous decorative flourish added to modify or embellish an
image. Style is the by-product of saying what has to be said in the
most appropriate way a maker can say it. Meaningful style emerges
from the necessity of description; it is not a product of
self-conscious selection."</p>
<p>"29. "Conception cannot precede execution." (Maurice Merleau-Ponty,
<em>Sense and Non-Sense</em>) Art is a process of discovery through making,
and our ability to discover is generally greater than our ability to
invent. Think of your work process as a form of travel. Look for the
things you don't know, the things that are revealed or inadvertently
uncovered. It is easier to find a world than to make one."</p>
<p>"45. Work from your intuition, analyze with your intellect. To keep
your work spontaneous and inventive, try to draw upon what lies
beneath normal cognition in an uninhibited way. Intuition is not
hocus-pocus. It is simply a judgment system that operates without
immediately available conscious evidence. Intuition draws upon
subliminal knowledge and allows the unfiltered, unfamiliar, and
unknown to enter your work. Once there, you can apply your powers of
rational analysis to discover what you have done. At this stage, you
can always edit, but don't edit or preclude what does not yet
exist."</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210131-101_things_to_learn_in_art_school_by_white/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210131-101_things_to_learn_in_art_school_by_white/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Let's share books!</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Books on shelves are sad. They should be read! Please read my books.</p>
<p>You can browse over 500 of our household's books in two ways:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.librarycat.org/lib/ajschumacher">a modern-ish search-based interface</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.librarything.com/catalog/ajschumacher">an old-looking list interface where you can see everything</a></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="/aaron/">Contact me</a> if something catches your eye!</p>
<p>If you'd like, you can join <a href="https://www.librarything.com/">LibraryThing</a> too. You can search there
through all your friends' books (add <a href="https://www.librarything.com/profile/ajschumacher">me</a>!) which is pretty neat.
You can add your books too! The LibraryThing phone app is pretty good
for easily adding books.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210122-lets_share_books/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210122-lets_share_books/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Entangled Life, by Sheldrake</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Would you like to simulate a night at the bar with your smart friend
who's just <em>really</em> into 'shrooms? Then <a href="https://www.merlinsheldrake.com/entangled-life">Entangled Life</a> is for you!
Explore lots of symbioses and ask questions like "Is nature
fundamentally competitive or cooperative?" (page 210) It's a good
time!</p>
<ul>
<li>Introduction: What is it like to be a fungus? (the author takes LSD)</li>
<li>Chapter 1: A lure (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truffle">truffles</a>)</li>
<li>Chapter 2: Living labyrinths (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mycelium">mycelium</a>;
   <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DlYzIUXlpQE">women gathering mushrooms song</a>)</li>
<li>Chapter 3: The intimacy of strangers (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lichen">lichens</a>;
   <a href="https://www.waysofenlichenment.net/">Ways of Enlichenment</a>; <a href="https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/235683163.pdf">Queer theory for lichens</a>;
   <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynn_Margulis">Lynn Margulis</a> and mitochondria)</li>
<li>Chapter 4: Mycelial minds (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Girl_with_All_the_Gifts_(film)">The Girl with All the Gifts</a> but
   really; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psilocybin_mushroom">magic mushrooms</a>)</li>
<li>Chapter 5: Before roots (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mycorrhiza">mycorrhizae</a>;
   <a href="https://www.diaart.org/visit/visit-our-locations-sites/walter-de-maria-the-vertical-earth-kilometer-kassel-germany">The Vertical Earth Kilometer</a>)</li>
<li>Chapter 6: Wood Wide Webs (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mycorrhizal_network">mycorrhizal networks</a>)</li>
<li>Chapter 7: Radical mycology (using fungi for stuff; <a href="https://ecovativedesign.com/">Ecovative</a>)</li>
<li>Chapter 8: Making sense of fungi (fermentation etc.)</li>
<li>Epilogue: This compost (<a href="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/5decd1106597cc7e187b46cc/1590402213148-9Y7AUCTU4N6BQ4JXTGFJ/US-entangled-life-cover-34_DARK_compressed.jpg">the book itself</a>)</li>
</ul>
<p>Sheldrake spins a charming tale, but may be taking some liberties. For
example, he claims on page 129 that "Miycorrhizal fungi soon found
their way into <em>The Lord of the Rings</em>." The quotes he follows this
with do not clearly support that claim, and there's no further
evidence to be found in the text or endnotes.</p>
<p>The author at one point addresses concerns about anthropomorphism,
especially relevant to considerations of "intelligent" behaviors, but
has few reservations about using metaphor freely. This isn't all bad.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is well-established in the sciences that metaphors can help to
generate new ways of thinking. The biochemist Joseph Needham
described a working analogy as a "net of coordinates" that could be
used to arrange an otherwise formless mass of information, much as a
sculptor might use a wire frame to provide support for wet clay. The
evolutionary biologist Richard Lewontin pointed out that it is
impossible to "do the work of science" without using metaphors,
given that almost "the entire body of science is an attempt to
explain phenomena that cannot be experienced directly by human
beings." Metaphors and analogies, in turn, come laced with human
stories and values, meaning that no discussion of scientific
ideas&#8211;this one included&#8211;can be free of cultural bias." (page 211)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Together with frequent stories, it makes for engaging reading. I
generally prefer the viewpoint he gives a paragraph to on page 174,
when he quotes Toby Spibille: "I try just to look at the system and
let the lichen be a lichen."</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<h3>Fun words</h3>
<ul>
<li>anastomose: cross-connect between adjacent channels, tubes, fibers,
   or other parts of a network</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brocade">brocade</a>: a kind of fancy cloth</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cannula">cannula</a>: a thin tube inserted into a vein or body cavity to
   administer medicine, drain off fluid, or insert a surgical
   instrument</li>
<li>deliquesce: become liquid, typically during decomposition</li>
<li>esculent: fit to be eaten; edible (or: a thing that is)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holobiont">holobiont</a>: entity composed of multiple symbiotic members</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liana">liana</a>: a long-stemmed, woody vine that climbs up trees</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loupe">loupe</a>: a hand-lens; a magnifying glass with no handle</li>
<li>molder: slowly decay or disintegrate, especially because of neglect</li>
<li>nostrum: a medicine, especially one that is not considered
   effective, prepared by an unqualified person</li>
<li>torpor: a state of physical or mental inactivity; lethargy</li>
</ul>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210121-entangled_life_by_sheldrake/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210121-entangled_life_by_sheldrake/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Pragmatic Thinking and Learning, by Andy Hunt</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This 2008 <a href="https://pragprog.com/titles/ahptl/pragmatic-thinking-and-learning/">book</a> contained things both familiar and novel to me,
with a focus on creativity. One thing it describes is the
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Weinberg-Writing-Fieldstone-Gerald-M/dp/093263365X">fieldstone method</a>, which I think is close to my recent style of
collecting ideas. I'm trying the <a href="https://juliacameronlive.com/basic-tools/morning-pages/">morning pages</a> technique the book
also describes, and I think the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timothy_Gallwey#Inner_game">inner game</a> idea of teaching
awareness could be good. The book is an artifact of Hunt's experience,
drawing together and organizing ideas he'd encountered. Good stuff!</p>
<ul>
<li>Chapter 1: <a href="#intro">Introduction</a></li>
<li>Chapter 2: <a href="#journey">Journey from novice to expert</a></li>
<li>Chapter 3: <a href="#brain">This is your brain</a></li>
<li>Chapter 4: <a href="#right">Get in your right mind</a></li>
<li>Chapter 5: <a href="#debug">Debug your mind</a></li>
<li>Chapter 6: <a href="#learn">Learn deliberately</a></li>
<li>Chapter 7: <a href="#gain">Gain experience</a></li>
<li>Chapter 8: <a href="#focus">Manage focus</a></li>
<li>Chapter 9: <a href="#beyond">Beyond expertise</a></li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<h3>Chapter 1: <a href="#intro" name="intro">Introduction</a></h3>
<hr>
<p>On page 2:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Because of this complex interaction of many interested parties and
forces and the constant evolution of change, it seems to me that the
two most important modern skills are these:</p>
<ul>
<li>Communication skills</li>
<li>Learning and thinking skills"</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The learning is always up to you." (page 3)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3>Chapter 2: <a href="#journey" name="journey">Journey from novice to expert</a></h3>
<hr>
<p>Event theories vs. construct theories is kind of an interesting
division... See e.g. <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF03395570">Events and Constructs</a>. (Seems like
psychologists think about this distinction.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... consider the case of the developer who claims ten years of
experience, but in reality it was one year of experience repeated
nine times. That doesn't count as <em>experience</em>." (page 15)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The expert is very good at targeted, focused pattern matching."
(page 21)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's interesting how the focus on experts using intuition makes it
seem like experts are less "interpretable" than non-experts, in the
same way that neural networks are less interpretable than simpler
models.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... the reality that there is anywhere from a 20:1 and 40:1
difference in productivity among developers, depending on whose
study you believe" (page 23, with footnote as follows) "In 1968, a
difference of 10:1 in productivity among programmers was noted in
<em>Exploratory experimental studies comparing online and offline
programming performance</em>. The gulf seems to have widened since
then."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Sadly, studies seem to indicate that most people, for most skills,
for most of their lives, never get any higher than the second stage
[of five], advanced beginner, "performing the tasks they need and
learning new tasks as the need arises but never acquiring a more
broad-based, conceptual understanding of the task environment.""
(page 25)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Beware decontextualized objectivity." (page 36)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3>Chapter 3: <a href="#brain" name="brain">This is your brain</a></h3>
<hr>
<p>Interesting box on page 42 about PKMzeta in the brain being important
for memory (<a href="https://science.sciencemag.org/content/313/5790/1141.abstract" title="Storage of Spatial Information by the Maintenance Mechanism of LTP">ref</a>).</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Everyone&#8211;no matter their education, economic status, day job, or
age&#8211;has good ideas. But of this large number of people with good
ideas, far fewer bother to keep track of them. Of those, even fewer
bother to act on those ideas. Fewer still then have the resources to
make a good idea a success." (page 46)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>"Linear" L-mode and "Rich" R-mode as alternatives to "left brain" and
"right brain." He also calls it CPU #1 and CPU #2.</p>
<p>He references Guy Claxton's "Hare Brain, Tortoise Mind" which uses
"deliberate" d-mode and "undermind," Dan Pink's l-directed and
r-directed, and Betty Edwards' L mode and R mode. (page 50)</p>
<hr>
<h3>Chapter 4: <a href="#right" name="right">Get in your right mind</a></h3>
<hr>
<p>Emphasis on multi-sensory (even seemingly pointless multi-sensory,
like fiddling with a paperclip).</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>""Drawing" is really about seeing."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Write Drunk, Revise Sober"</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Page 72 references <a href="/20190128-bird_by_bird_by_anne_lamott/">Bird by Bird</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Metaphor, a common ground for both verbalizations and images, is a
way to voyage back and forth between the subconscious and conscious,
between right and left hemispheres." (from Conscious/Unconscious
Interaction in a creative act, Gordon and Poze)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<em>Metaphor</em> comes from the Greek meaning "to transfer," with the
idea that you are transferring the properties of one object to
another in a way that is not literally possible." (page 75)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Ways to try to get ideas (etc.) from your subconscious:</p>
<ul>
<li>"Image streaming" (close your eyes and describe out loud what you
   see)</li>
<li>Free-form journaling (blogging, letter-writing, etc.)</li>
<li>"Morning pages" (write three pages first thing in the morning)</li>
<li>Just write (mentions Weinberg's <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Weinberg-Writing-Fieldstone-Gerald-M/dp/093263365X">fieldstone method</a>, which is
   close to what I try to do, I think)</li>
<li>Walking</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Instead, you want to cultivate a style of non-goal-directed
thinking."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Once you get used to seeing very small methods, with only a few
lines of code, very long methods jump out at you as <em>wrong</em>."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The only difference between a rut and a grave is the dimensions."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When faced with a thorny problem, Dave Thomas will often say, "Turn
that on its head." That's one <em>mental wack</em>: a way to knock you out
of your rut to make you look at a problem from a different point of
view.</p>
<p>"For instance, audio engineers use a well-known technique when
mixing a recording. To make the sound as good as possible, they
first go through and make each instrument sound <em>as bad</em> as
possible."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The [mental] locks include assuming there's only one right answer,
thinking that a given solution is not logical, or dismissing <em>play</em>
as frivolous."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Page 92 mentions the Brian Eno and Peter Schmidt
<a href="http://www.rtqe.net/ObliqueStrategies/">Oblique Strategies</a>, which is quite out of print as a deck of
cards, and broken CGI apps on their site.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.thraeryn.org/strategies/deck.txt">The original hundred</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.rtqe.net/ObliqueStrategies/acutedeck.txt">Submitted "Acute" strategies</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3>Chapter 5: <a href="#debug" name="debug">Debug your mind</a></h3>
<hr>
<p>Partial list of cognitive biases:</p>
<ul>
<li>Anchoring</li>
<li>Fundamental attribution error</li>
<li>Self-serving bias</li>
<li>Need for closure</li>
<li>Confirmation bias</li>
<li>Exposure effect</li>
<li>Hawthorne effect</li>
<li>False memory</li>
<li>Symbolic reduction fallacy</li>
<li>Nominal fallacy</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>On debate about the future, in retrospect:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"pages and pages of analysis and speculation, forecasting and
fretting, almost always over the wrong question." (page 102)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Stuff on "generational affinity"</p>
<ul>
<li>GI generation, 1901-1924</li>
<li>Silent generation, 1925-1942</li>
<li>Boom generation, 1943-1960</li>
<li>Generation X, 1961-1981</li>
<li>Millenial generation, 1982-2005</li>
<li>Homeland generation, 2005-???</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Ideas about four repeating generation "archetypes" (hero, artist,
prophet, nomad) from Howe and Strauss, in e.g. the 2007
<a href="https://hbr.org/2007/07/the-next-20-years-how-customer-and-workforce-attitudes-will-evolve">The Next 20 Years: How Customer and Workforce Attitudes Will Evolve</a>,
which says:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Three of those generations will still be vital forces in American
society 20 years from now: Boomers, Generation X, and Millennials.
Their attitudes and behaviors will have profound effects on the
economy, the workplace, and social institutions in general. For
example, as aging Boomers eschew high-tech medicine in favor of
holistic self-care, natural foods, and mind-body healing techniques,
some hospitals are opening new wings featuring alternative medicine
and spiritual counseling. Gen Xers, having grown up in an era of
failing schools and marriages, will remain alienated, disaffected,
and pragmatic as they enter midlife. Already the greatest
entrepreneurial generation in U.S. history, they will be highly
effective at pushing innovation, efficiency, and mass customization.
In contrast, young adult Millennials will favor teamwork, close
family relationships, job security, and a bland popular culture.
Their unprecedented digital empowerment and talent for organizing
will create a political powerhouse and may even revitalize the union
movement."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"If you think you've defined something, try to also define its
opposite." (page 122)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is by logic we prove; it is by intuition we discover." (Henri
Poincar&#233;, quoted page 123)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3>Chapter 6: <a href="#learn" name="learn">Learn deliberately</a></h3>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheep_dip">Sheep dip</a> training doesn't work." (page 127)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In addition, and perhaps surprisingly, simply mastering a syllabus
of knowledge doesn't increase professional effectiveness. ...
Mastery of the knowledge alone isn't sufficient." (page 128)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Recommends SMART goals:</p>
<ul>
<li>Specific</li>
<li>Measurable</li>
<li>Achievable</li>
<li>Relevant</li>
<li>Time-boxed</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Create a Pragmatic Investment Plan" (page 133)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(This refers to investing in <em>learning</em>.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Unfortunately, relegating learning activities to your "free time"
is a recipe for failure." (page 133)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>On page 139 Hunt talks about Sternberg's
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triarchic_theory_of_intelligence">Triarchic theory of intelligence</a>, but his description is different
from what Wikipedia says... Wikipedia says it's these three:</p>
<ul>
<li>Componential &#8211; analytical</li>
<li>Experiential &#8211; creative</li>
<li>Practical - contextual</li>
</ul>
<p>But Hunt says "Sternberg sees a three-part mind, composed of a
meta-level component that manages thought processes overall;
performance-based components that do tasks, make associations, and so
on; and, finally, knowledge-acquisition components that handle
assimilating new information."</p>
<p>Maybe these line up somehow, but I don't see it from here.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Reading groups are nontoxic." (page 141)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Strong praise!</p>
<hr>
<p>Describes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQ3R">SQ3R</a> (Survey, Question, Read, Recite, Review).</p>
<hr>
<p>On page 146, the "Test-Driven Learning" box (a play on Test-Driven
Development) talks about spaced repetition. It mentions <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SuperMemo">SuperMemo</a>
and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mnemosyne_(software)">Mnemosyne</a>, and references
<a href="https://web.mit.edu/jbelcher/www/learner/retrieval.pdf">The Critical Importance of Retrieval for Learning</a>, which is a
pretty great ref.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As you go to add a new piece of information, a new thought, or an
insight to the mind map, you are faced with the question, where does
this belong? You have to evaluate the <em>relationships</em> between ideas,
not just the ideas themselves, and that can be a very revealing
activity." (page 149)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The most value, I find, is to take the raw notes while listening
(which helps you stay focused as you extract salient points from the
lecture) and then transcribe these raw notes into "official notes."
Even if I never read these notes again, the act of transcribing the
raw notes is the most valuable portion of this exercise. You can do
the same thing with mind maps-start with a rough messy one, and
redraw it as needed. The redrawing helps form more associations in
your brain." (page 150)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is very much like <a href="/20201124-take_notes_like_paul_halmos/">the method of Paul Halmos</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Use a mind map to help clarify." (page 152)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Page 154 has an interesting reference to <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Damon_Navandi/publication/268871823_Prepared_Mind_insight/links/547a09dd0cf205d1687fab98/Prepared-Mind-insight.pdf">The Prepared Mind</a>: Neural
Activity Prior to Problem Presentation Predicts Subsequent Solution by
Sudden Insight:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"A recent study suggests that mental preparation <em>that involves an
inward focus of attention</em> can promote flashes of insight, even if
the preparation occurs well in advance of facing any particular
problem."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This reference isn't really applicable to the book's topic there
(documentation). It isn't super clear how to get the mental focus the
researchers identify, or whether we really care because it seems like
it didn't help people solve more problems, but only to be more likely
to report that they solved via a flash of insight. And the problems in
question are like "pine, crab, sauce" ("apple") so it isn't clear how
useful this is anyway.</p>
<p>I think Hunt is right that "it might be that <em>documenting</em> is more
important than <em>documentation</em>" but his reference doesn't support that
claim.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Chapter 7: <a href="#gain" name="gain">Gain experience</a></h3>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"we build to learn, not learn to build." (page 160)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"You need to unlearn just as much as you need to learn." (page 164)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This reminds me of what Dijkstra said in
<a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/EWD/transcriptions/EWD10xx/EWD1036.html">On the cruelty of really teaching computing science</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>""I don't know" is a fine answer, but don't let it end there." (page
165)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Hunt riffs on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timothy_Gallwey#Inner_game">inner game</a> to talk about increasing your
awareness to increase your feedback and improve your improvement.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"the idea is to teach the student awareness and to use that
awareness to correct their performance." (page 170)</p>
<p>"This is a key aspect to playing the inner game: don't focus on
correcting individual details, but just be aware. Accept <em>what is</em>
as a first step, and just be aware of it. Don't judge, don't rush in
with a solution, don't criticize." (page 170)</p>
<p>"Don't just do something; stand there." (page 171)</p>
<p>"The Inner Game series sums up this idea with the phrase, "Trying
fails, awareness cures.""</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Page 173 references <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/51559/6-myths-creativity">The 6 Myths Of Creativity</a>, which are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Creativity comes from creative types</li>
<li>Money is a creativity motivator</li>
<li>Time pressure fuels creativity</li>
<li>Fear forces breakthroughs</li>
<li>Competition beats collaboration</li>
<li>A streamlined organization is a creative organization</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"You don't actually need to make errors, as long as it's OK if you
did." (page 174)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Perception is based on prediction." (page 177)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Reference here to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On_Intelligence">On Intelligence</a> by Jeff Hawkins.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Legendary jazz guitarist Pat Metheny takes this idea
[of surrounding yourself with inspiration] one step further and
offers this advice: "Always be the worst guy in every band you're
in. If you're the best guy there, you need to be in a different
band. And I think that works for almost everything that's out there
as well."" (page 177)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3>Chapter 8: <a href="#focus" name="focus">Manage focus</a></h3>
<hr>
<p>Hunt recommends <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vipassan%C4%81">meditation</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>In "Defocus to Focus" (page 187) on thinking about problems
creatively:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"it's not the idea of not doing <em>anything</em>, it's the idea of not
doing <em>something</em>."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Hunt advances Dennett's ideas from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consciousness_Explained">Consciousness Explained</a>, saying
"Multiple drafts form consciousness."</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"That makes consciousness a bottom-up, self-organizing, perhaps even
emergent property." (page 189)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Have you heard of the consultant's Rule of Three? In general, if
you can't think of three ways a plan can go wrong or think of three
different solutions to a problem, then you haven't thought it
through enough." (page 189)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A footnote attributes this to Jerry Weinberg's <em>The Secrets of
Consulting</em>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Thomas Jeffereson owned somewhere in the neighborhood of 10,000
books in his lifetime. And donated nearly 7,000 of them to form the
core of the Library of Congress in 1815. (page 191)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Hunt advocates using a personal wiki.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The real beauty of this approach is that once you have a place to
put a specific bit of information, you'll notice that new, relevant
bits of data suddenly start to show up out of nowhere. It's a
similar phenomenon to <em>sense tuning</em>."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He doesn't quite manage to say Baader-Meinhof.</p>
<p>The idea also aligns with the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Weinberg-Writing-Fieldstone-Gerald-M/dp/093263365X">fieldstone method</a>, I think.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Multitasking takes a heavy toll on productivity. One study found
that in general, multitasking can cost you 20 to 40 percent of your
productivity."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The "study" is footnoted as
http://www.umich.edu/~bcalab/multitasking.html, which is a collection
of links to papers... Not sure what it's referencing in particular.</p>
<hr>
<p>He recommends using one of those focus apps that blocks out the
internet etc. He references "Think!" and DeskTopple. Current options
seem to be <a href="https://zapier.com/blog/stay-focused-avoid-distractions/">different</a>.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Chapter 9: <a href="#beyond" name="beyond">Beyond expertise</a></h3>
<p>This is a brief conclusion, and I mostly liked that the <a href="https://twitter.com/PragmaticAndy">author</a>
wrapped up by giving his email address and inviting feedback.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210116-pragmatic_thinking_and_learning/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210116-pragmatic_thinking_and_learning/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Enchiridion in 52 sentences</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enchiridion_of_Epictetus">Enchiridion</a> isn't long, but it also doesn't have chapter
names, so I thought I'd write <a href="/20200715-communicate_immediately/#line">one-line summaries</a>. I referred to
the <a href="https://smile.amazon.com/Enchiridion-Epictetus/dp/B08BG7536P/">Long</a>, <a href="http://classics.mit.edu/Epictetus/epicench.html">Carter</a>, and (most preferred) <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1cDbKtlPBxvWJdkDMXWkSAbOeYCHHg8Fj/view">Eliot</a> translations.</p>
<ol>
<li>Only your actions and perceptions are under your exclusive control.</li>
<li>Limit your desires and fears to things you have control over.</li>
<li>Don't be upset by things outside your control.</li>
<li>Have realistic expectations and you will be less likely to be
   disturbed.</li>
<li>Fools blame others, and students blame themselves, but the wise
   blame no one.</li>
<li>Take pride only in what you do.</li>
<li>Live so that you are never unprepared for death.</li>
<li>Align your hopes with reality.</li>
<li>Physical impediments need not disadvantage your mind.</li>
<li>All challenges are opportunities to exercise your many virtues.</li>
<li>Everything is borrowed; nothing is lost, but only returned.</li>
<li>Don't let external things poison your mental state.</li>
<li>To learn effectively, devote no energy to appearing to know.</li>
<li>Do not hope to control other people, but only yourself.</li>
<li>Take what has come comfortably within reach, undistracted by
    distant desires.</li>
<li>It is not events that cause distress, but our reactions to them.</li>
<li>In whatever situation you find yourself, do your best.</li>
<li>Whatever the future holds can be turned to your advantage.</li>
<li>Judge yourself and others only by how well the controllable is
    controlled.</li>
<li>Insults and praise do not change who you are, and are not your
    concern or goal.</li>
<li>You could die at any moment; keep things in perspective.</li>
<li>Ignore invalid criticism, maintaining a humble focus on what's
    important.</li>
<li>However you wish to be seen by others, act so that you know this
    is how you are.</li>
<li>Do not let worldly goals distract you from living virtuously.</li>
<li>Every benefit has a cost; it is not helpful to covet what you will
    not pursue.</li>
<li>Also maintain an outsider's perspective on the events of your own
    life.</li>
<li>Nothing is intrinsically evil.</li>
<li>Do not let other people control your mind and emotions.</li>
<li>Before doing anything, consider what is entailed and whether you
    can commit fully.</li>
<li>Regardless of the behavior of those around you, behave virtuously
    toward them.</li>
<li>Do not assign blame, or even call things good or bad, except for
    your own actions.</li>
<li>Information is neither good nor bad; do not fear it, avoid it, or
    ignore it.</li>
<li>Be modest and reserved in speech and other involvements with the
    world.</li>
<li>Do not rush into hedonism, but consider also the satisfaction of
    self control.</li>
<li>Don't be afraid to be seen doing what you think is good to do.</li>
<li>Moderate your desires and share with others.</li>
<li>You can't be something else by pretending, and in pretending you
    also fail to be you.</li>
<li>As you protect your hand from being burned, take care to protect
    your state of mind.</li>
<li>Judge things by how well they fulfill their function; you don't
    need fancy things.</li>
<li>Honor people for their substantive contributions (regardless of
    gender, for example).</li>
<li>Don't let food, drink, exercise, sleep, or sex rule your mind.</li>
<li>Remember everyone is doing their best, given what they know and
    believe.</li>
<li>All things are handled better in a spirit of cooperation than
    confrontation.</li>
<li>No person is better or worse than any other, though their
    attributes may differ.</li>
<li>Avoid value judgements; strive to perceive and communicate
    factually.</li>
<li>Let wisdom inform all your actions, and reduce the amount you
    talk.</li>
<li>Do not seek admiration for doing what is admirable.</li>
<li>Maintain an internal locus of control, and control yourself.</li>
<li>Seek wisdom to guide your actions, not as academic posturing.</li>
<li>Do what is best, without delay, unapologetically, always striving
    to improve.</li>
<li>Be guided by your principles.</li>
<li>Accept reality freely&#8211;especially the reality of your mind's
    freedom.</li>
</ol>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210107-enchiridion_in_52_sentences/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210107-enchiridion_in_52_sentences/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Predicting the future from 2021</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Second year of doing <a href="/20200112-predicting_the_future_from_2020/">these</a>! Let's make some predictions for 1, 5,
10, and 20 years out!</p>
<h3>By 2022</h3>
<ul>
<li>Vaccine effective in controlling all strains of COVID-19.</li>
<li>No additional pandemic on the scale of COVID-19.</li>
<li>Donald Trump indicted.</li>
<li>S&amp;P 500 closes above 4,000.</li>
</ul>
<h3>By 2026</h3>
<ul>
<li>At least one of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facebook,_Apple,_Amazon,_Netflix_and_Google">FAANG</a> split up by government intervention.</li>
<li>Joe Biden is dead.</li>
<li>Democratic presidential ticket of Harris and Buttigieg loses.
   [<a href="#1">1</a>]</li>
<li>Intelligent extraterrestrials clearly real and communicating with
   humans. [<a href="#2">2</a>]</li>
<li>S&amp;P 500 closes above 6,000.
 <!-- * My grandparents are dead. --></li>
</ul>
<h3>By 2031</h3>
<ul>
<li>S&amp;P 500 closes above 8,000.</li>
</ul>
<h3>By 2041</h3>
<ul>
<li>S&amp;P 500 closes above 12,000.</li>
</ul>
<p>[<a name="1" href="#1">1</a>] What odds would you give me?</p>
<p>[<a name="2" href="#2">2</a>] I've included one low-probability, never
occurred before, possibly impossible prediction, at the recommendation
of my sister. There were <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haim_Eshed">Haim Eshed</a>'s claims, after all, and those
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentagon_UFO_videos">videos</a>. And wouldn't it be fun? I'll give aliens an optimistic 2%
for the next five years and reevaluate then as needed.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Reviewing predictions from 2020</h3>
<p>All my one-year <a href="/20200112-predicting_the_future_from_2020/">predictions</a> were correct, at least if you interpret my
"S&amp;P under 3,000" as meaning any time during the year, not just at the
end of the year.</p>
<p>I'm feeling more optimistic about the stock market now than I was last
year. Maybe that's a sign that it'll do more poorly now?</p>
<p>I had Justice Ginsberg dead by 2025, so my timing was sadly not
maximally precise.</p>
<p>Most of my predictions from last year were very conservative.
Understanding the present is a good method for predicting the near
future, but it isn't very interesting.</p>
<p>I have less to say about the farther future. It's harder to predict,
and I already <a href="/20200112-predicting_the_future_from_2020/">predicted</a> some things in the range of 10-20 years
out last year. No changing them now! I'm also just thinking more about
personal plans/goals; this stuff is just for fun.</p>
<h3>Probabilistic predictions?</h3>
<p><a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2020/04/29/predictions-for-2020/">Some people</a> assign probabilities to all their predictions, and I
think this isn't very interesting, because it's easy to nod along with
probabilities. Predictions are interesting when they're surprising,
and certainty can increase surprise.</p>
<p>It would be possible to compare probabilities between people and see
where they're most different. I could imagine making a little web
survey/app for this, which might be fun and good to do in a class
learning about <a href="/20201221-ulysses_compass/">cross-entropy</a>, for example.</p>
<p>A possible taxonomy of predictions by probability:</p>
<ul>
<li>Very likely based on the present. (More hurricanes.)</li>
<li>Coin flip. (Old person dies in some period.)</li>
<li>Slightly unlikely. (Underdog wins something.)</li>
<li>Very rare but known possible. (Pandemic.)</li>
<li>Possibly impossible. (Aliens visit Earth for wine and cheese party.)</li>
</ul>
<p>It's the very likely ones that make the most sense to think about most
of the time, I think, both because they don't require hedging and
because there's less uncertainty <em>in the estimate of the probability
itself</em>.</p>
<h3>COVID-19 and the right questions</h3>
<p>COVID-19 is the big thing that wasn't predicted for 2020: very rare
but known possible. I'm not going to predict any other things in this
category this year either, because that's easier and usually right.</p>
<p>When I wrote my 2020 predictions, there was already some news about
COVID-19. Is there something like that right now that I'm missing? I
googled "early signs" but didn't find anything likely to make me seem
perspicacious.</p>
<p>The things that turn out to be important are hard to predict because
you have to ask the right questions to even consider them. What aren't
we considering now that will turn out to be important?</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210102-predicting_the_future_from_2021/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210102-predicting_the_future_from_2021/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The weather outside is frightening</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Based on ten years of daily GHCN data, it is too cold, too hot, and
too wet out there. Best chances for livable weather: parts of the
Mexican plateau, California, and maybe Hawaii.</p>
<p><img src="chance_of_freezing.png" width="49%">
<img src="chance_of_heat.png" width="49%">
<img src="chance_of_precipitation.png" width="49%">
<img src="most_habitable.png" width="49%"></p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="temp" href="#temp">Temperature</a></h3>
<p>Lots of land is up north where it gets cold, and everything around the
equator gets too hot. Is there a Goldilocks region in between that's
"just right" year-round? No. Your best hope is Stockholm syndrome: "I
love the seasons!"</p>
<p><img src="chance_of_freezing.png" width="49%">
<img src="chance_of_heat.png" width="49%"></p>
<p>To get a moderate temperature all year, you have to rely on oceans, or
mountainous elevations, or both. Thanks a lot, solar system.</p>
<h3><a name="prcp" href="#prcp">Precipitation</a></h3>
<p>Even with over 15 thousand stations and ten years of <a href="https://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/data-access/land-based-station-data/land-based-datasets/global-historical-climatology-network-ghcn">GHCN</a> data,
there's spotty coverage for Africa, South America, and Asia. It also
looks like the US precipitation data may be systematically different
from Canadian and Mexican data. Thanks a lot, humans.</p>
<p><img alt="Chance of precipitation" src="chance_of_precipitation.png"></p>
<p>Precipitation: Can't live with it, can't have nice plants without it.
Thanks a lot, water cycle. Let's say once every six to nine days is
acceptable to avoid deserts.</p>
<h3><a name="habitable" href="#habitable">Habitable areas</a></h3>
<p><img alt="Even slightly habitable" src="even_slightly_habitable.png"></p>
<p>Mexico! With ocean on two sides and a high plateau to cut the
temperature and humidity, Mexico ought to be where everybody lives.
<a href="https://weather-and-climate.com/average-monthly-Rainfall-Temperature-Sunshine,zacatecas-zacatecas-mx,Mexico">Zacatecas</a> seems particularly good.</p>
<p>California has some okay spots, like San Diego and Monterey. Look out
for forest fires.</p>
<p>Hawaii isn't out of bounds, but even the lows are high, so if you
aren't at the beach it might not be ideal. Avoid the volcanoes.</p>
<p>Then there are survivable places, including lots of the west coast of
the Americas, New Zealand, and the southern coast of Australia. The
tip of South Africa and large parts of Europe could be okay. I think
that's roughly Japan and Korea seeming not quite deadly.</p>
<h3><a name="methods" href="#methods">Methods</a></h3>
<p>This slapdash analysis <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/blob/master/20201230-weather_outside_is_frightening/prepare_data.sh">gathers some data</a> and visualizes it with a
Python <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/blob/master/20201230-weather_outside_is_frightening/visualize.ipynb">notebook</a>, which has all the details and a few more fun
maps.</p>
<p>The chances of cold, heat, and precipitation are fractions of days
with low temperature under 0&#176; C (32&#176; F), high temperature over 30&#176; C
(86&#176; F), and precipitation over one millimeter, respectively. The
precipitation score may have issues. The scales on these maps go all
the way from 0% to 100%, using the plasma color scale. Legends are
ugly.</p>
<p>A location's score is the sum of the cold score, hot score, and
distance of the precipitation score from the range 1/6 to 1/9. It's
not quite a rate any more, just a badness score. The "Most habitable"
map colors scores less than 1/4, and the "Even slightly habitable" map
colors scores less than 3/5. <em>Do you really want to live somewhere
with a score over 60%?</em></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20201230-weather_outside_is_frightening/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20201230-weather_outside_is_frightening/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Estimate manifold dimensionality with LID</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Local Intrinsic Dimensionality (LID) is based on assuming locally
uniform density and using the geometric idea that in \( D \)
dimensions the volume of a ball with radius \( r \) goes as \( r^D
\). With an outer radius \( r_{\text{bound}} \) from some point and
a distance \( r \lt r_{\text{bound}} \) to a neighboring point, the
maximum likelihood estimator of LID is \( 1 / \log{\left(
r_{\text{bound}}/r \right)} \), and multiple estimates are averaged
with the harmonic mean.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/200688576_Non-linear_scaling_techniques_for_uncovering_the_perceptual_dimensions_of_timbre/figures"><img src="swiss_roll.jpg" style="float: right; margin-left: 1em;" title="Image from: Non-linear scaling techniques for uncovering the perceptual dimensions of timbre"></a></p>
<p>For example, Swiss roll data curves through three dimensions but only
on a two-dimensional manifold. LID for the three-dimensional Swiss
roll data is about two, which is informative.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#calculating">Calculating LID with Python</a><ul>
<li><a href="#cloud">In a cloud of points</a></li>
<li><a href="#roll">For a Swiss roll dataset</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#derivation">Mathematical derivation of LID</a><ul>
<li><a href="#cdf">Cumulative Distribution Function (CDF) of radius</a></li>
<li><a href="#pdf">Probability Density Function (PDF) of radius</a></li>
<li><a href="#ev">Expected Value of radius</a></li>
<li><a href="#mle">Maximum Likelihood Estimate of dimension</a></li>
<li><a href="#harmonic">Harmonic mean for dimensionality</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#caveats">Caveats</a></li>
<li><a href="#literature">LID in the literature</a></li>
<li><a href="#topological">Topological extensions</a></li>
</ul>
<h3><a name="calculating" href="#calculating">Calculating LID with Python</a></h3>
<p>The maximum likelihood estimator of Local Intrinsic Dimensionality is
\( 1 / \log{\left( r_{\text{bound}}/r \right)} \).</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">import math

def lid(radius, radius_bound):
    return 1 / math.log(radius_bound / radius)</code></pre>

<p>The radii will be distances measured from data using
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euclidean_distance">Euclidean distance</a>.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">def euclidean(xs, ys):  # Euclidean distance
    return math.sqrt(sum((x - y)**2 for x, y in zip(xs, ys)))</code></pre>

<p>To average multiple estimates of dimensionality, use the
<a href="#harmonic">harmonic mean</a>.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">def harmonic_mean(numbers):
    return len(numbers) / sum(1 / number for number in numbers)</code></pre>

<p>Filter out zeros (such as the distance from a point to itself).</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">def positive(numbers):
    return [number for number in numbers if number &gt; 0]</code></pre>

<p>For a point in some data, find the distances to its \( k+1 \)
nearest neighbors. The greatest of these is \( r_{\text{bound}} \),
and the estimates based on the \( k \) nearest neighbors are
averaged.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">def neighbors_lid(origin, points, k=1, distance=euclidean):
    radii = sorted(positive([distance(origin, point) for point in points]))
    return harmonic_mean([lid(radius, radii[k]) for radius in radii[:k]])</code></pre>

<h4><a name="cloud" href="#cloud">In a cloud of points</a></h4>
<p>A uniformly random cloud of points in \( D \) dimensions has
dimensionality equal to \( D \).</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">import random

def cloud(dimensions, count=100, bounds=(-1, 1)):
    return [[random.uniform(*bounds) for _ in range(dimensions)]
            for _ in range(count)]</code></pre>

<p>LID can be calculated from anywhere in the cloud, such as the origin,
as in this seven-dimensional example.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">neighbors_lid([0]*7, cloud(7))
## 6.851551579378687</code></pre>

<p>These estimates are very noisy, depending on the particular random
points in the cloud; it's very likely that a given run won't be so
close to seven. Repeating the experiment many times is more
reassuring.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">harmonic_mean([neighbors_lid([0]*7, cloud(7)) for _ in range(1000)])
## 7.006859728132216</code></pre>

<h4><a name="roll" href="#roll">For a Swiss roll dataset</a></h4>
<p>To estimate a dataset's dimensionality, average LID from each point in
the dataset.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">def data_lid(points, k=1, distance=euclidean):
    return harmonic_mean([neighbors_lid(point, points, k=k, distance=distance)
                          for point in points])</code></pre>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swiss_roll">Swiss roll</a> data, first introduced in the <a href="https://web.mit.edu/cocosci/Papers/sci_reprint.pdf" title="A Global Geometric Framework for Nonlinear Dimensionality Reduction">Isomap paper</a>, is a
two-dimensional <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manifold">manifold</a> embedded in three dimensions. It's not
terribly hard to make from scratch, but the
<a href="https://github.com/scikit-learn/scikit-learn/blob/42aff4e2e/sklearn/datasets/_samples_generator.py#L1402">scikit-learn implementation</a> is convenient.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/200688576_Non-linear_scaling_techniques_for_uncovering_the_perceptual_dimensions_of_timbre" title="Image from: Non-linear scaling techniques for uncovering the perceptual dimensions of timbre"><img alt="swiss roll" src="swiss_roll.jpg"></a></p>
<pre><code class="language-python">import sklearn.datasets

roll, _ = sklearn.datasets.make_swiss_roll()
data_lid(roll)
## 2.0706005383894444</code></pre>

<p>The code here is also available in a <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/blob/master/20201227-estimate_manifold_dimensionality_with_lid/lid.ipynb">notebook</a> with slightly more
technical commentary.</p>
<h3><a name="derivation" href="#derivation">Mathematical derivation of LID</a></h3>
<p>Local Intrinsic Dimensionality arises from considering radius from a
given point to another point nearer than \( r_{\text{bound}} \) as a
random variable \( R \) which takes a specific value \( r \).</p>
<h4><a name="cdf" href="#cdf">Cumulative Distribution Function (CDF) of radius</a></h4>
<p>With uniform density, the probability of encountering a point is
proportional to volume, and the volume of a radius \( r \) ball in
\( D \) dimensions is proportional to \( r^D \), giving the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cumulative_distribution_function">CDF</a>.</p>
<p>\[ P(R&lt;r) = \frac{r^D}{r_{\text{bound}}^D} = \left(\frac{r}{r_{\text{bound}}}\right)^D \]</p>
<h4><a name="pdf" href="#pdf">Probability Density Function (PDF) of radius</a></h4>
<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Probability_density_function">PDF</a> is the derivative of the CDF with respect to \( r \).</p>
<p>\[ P(R=r) = D \left( \frac{r}{r_{\text{bound}}} \right)^{D-1} \]</p>
<h4><a name="ev" href="#ev">Expected Value of radius</a></h4>
<p>Integrating the PDF times \( r \) from 0 to \( r_{\text{bound}} \)
gives the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expected_value">expected value</a> of \( R \), which is \( \frac{D}{D+1}
r_{\text{bound}} \). This isn't terribly important to the derivation
here, but it shows that as dimensionality increases, points are likely
to be closer and closer to the outer radius. This is an aspect of the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curse_of_dimensionality">curse of dimensionality</a> and the phenomenon that LID is based on.</p>
<h4><a name="mle" href="#mle">Maximum Likelihood Estimate of dimension</a></h4>
<p>For a given measured \( r \) within \( r_{\text{bound}} \), some
dimensionality \( D \) maximizes the likelihood of that observation.
The probability density function is a likelihood, and the log of that
function has the same maximum where both derivatives are zero. Setting
the derivative with respect to \( D \) of the natural log likelihood
equal to zero gives a simple solution.</p>
<p>\[ \log{\left( \frac{r}{r_{\text{bound}}} \right)} + \frac{1}{D} = 0 \]</p>
<p>\[ D = \frac{1}{\log{ \left( \frac{r_{\text{bound}}}{r} \right)}} \]</p>
<p>This choice of natural log is not arbitrary, because a derivative is
taken; using a different log base would introduce an additional
constant factor.</p>
<h4><a name="harmonic" href="#harmonic">Harmonic mean for dimensionality</a></h4>
<p>With two observed radii \( r_1 \) and \( r_2 \), the joint
probability is two (PDF) likelihoods multiplied together, and the log
likelihood sums. Maximizing gives the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harmonic_mean">harmonic mean</a> of two
individual estimates.</p>
<p>\[ \log{\left( \frac{r_1}{r_{\text{bound}}} \right)} + \frac{1}{D} + \log{\left( \frac{r_2}{r_{\text{bound}}} \right)} + \frac{1}{D} = 0 \]</p>
<p>\[ D = \frac{2}{\log{\left( \frac{r_{\text{bound}}}{r_1} \right)} + \log{\left( \frac{r_{\text{bound}}}{r_2} \right)}} \]</p>
<p>The same thing happens for any number of measurements; the harmonic
mean is the appropriate way to average estimates of dimensionality.</p>
<p>The harmonic mean is typically appropriate for averaging <em>rates</em>, so
its appearance here suggests thinking of <em>dimension</em> as a <em>rate</em>.
Perhaps dimension is the rate at which "space" becomes available, or
entropy becomes possible, per distance traveled.</p>
<h3><a name="caveats" href="#caveats">Caveats</a></h3>
<p>It's very common for distance to not really make sense in a dataset.
Scaling of variables can be very important, for example (not to
mention categorical variables).</p>
<p>Even with a meaningful distance, in high dimensions, "nearest
neighbors" <a href="https://members.loria.fr/MOBerger/Enseignement/Master2/Exposes/beyer.pdf" title="When Is &#8220;Nearest Neighbor&#8221; Meaningful?">may not be meaningful</a>.</p>
<p>Euclidean distance is assumed here, but <a href="https://bib.dbvis.de/uploadedFiles/155.pdf" title="On the Surprising Behavior of Distance Metrics in High Dimensional Space">other distances</a> may also
be worth considering. There is also an <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.12880" title="ABID: Angle Based Intrinsic Dimensionality">angle-based approach</a> to
estimating LID.</p>
<h3><a name="literature" href="#literature">LID in the literature</a></h3>
<p>A common reference is <a href="https://www.stat.berkeley.edu/~bickel/mldim.pdf" title="Maximum Likelihood Estimation of Intrinsic Dimension">Levina and Bickel</a>, "Maximum Likelihood
Estimation of Intrinsic Dimension." Their derivation is slightly
different, but the result is the same: their Equation 8 is
<a href="#mle">the MLE above</a> in different notation.</p>
<p>Levina and Bickel suggest an adjustment to the harmonic mean when \(
k \rightarrow \infty \). In practice it may be better to keep \( k
\) small in the interest of maintaining locality and not adjust.</p>
<p>Another form of the MLE sometimes appears (e.g. <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1801.02613" title="Characterizing Adversarial Subspaces Using Local Intrinsic Dimensionality">1</a>, <a href="https://epubs.siam.org/doi/abs/10.1137/1.9781611975673.21" title="Intrinsic Dimensionality Estimation within Tight Localities">2</a>) but is
not recommended.</p>
<p>\[ \widehat{LID}(x) = -\left( \frac{1}{k} \sum_{i=1}^k{ \log{ \frac{r_i(x)}{r_k(x)} } } \right)^{-1} \]</p>
<p>In this form, \( r_i(x) \) is the distance to the \( i\text{-th}
\) nearest neighbor of the point \( x \), and \( r_k(x) \) is the
maximum of these distances. Here the \( k \) neighbors include the
farthest one, defining \( r_k(x) \), which is elsewhere called \(
r_{\text{bound}} \). The effect of this inclusion is to add a \(
\log(1) = 0 \) term to the sum (which would not be meaningful as an
individual estimate) or equivalently to average \( k-1 \) estimates
as if there were \( k \). With two nearest neighbors, this will
incorrectly double the estimate, and it will always inflate it to some
degree.</p>
<p>In addition to the arithmetic mean, sometimes a regression approach is
used to combine estimates of dimensionality. <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-017-11873-y.pdf" title="Estimating the intrinsic dimension of datasets by a minimal neighborhood information">Facco et al.</a> apply
such an approach, noting and dropping large outliers in order to get
more robust estimates. The <a href="#harmonic">harmonic mean</a> (itself
<a href="https://stats.stackexchange.com/questions/264368/harmonic-mean-minimizes-sum-of-squared-relative-errors" title="Harmonic mean minimizes sum of squared relative errors">a kind of robust regression</a>) is more appropriate.</p>
<h3><a name="topological" href="#topological">Topological extensions</a></h3>
<p>Topological approaches use nearest neighbors to turn point-like data
into <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graph_(discrete_mathematics)">graph</a>-like data (okay, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simplicial_complex">simplicial complexes</a>). <a href="https://umap-learn.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">UMAP</a> is
a popular modern technique based on this idea.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://web.mit.edu/cocosci/Papers/sci_reprint.pdf" title="A Global Geometric Framework for Nonlinear Dimensionality Reduction">Isomap</a>, a graph enforces geodesic distances, staying on the
manifold via neighbors connected in the graph. For estimating
dimensionality, a graph lets you avoid polluting the set of nearest
neighbors with points from actually distant parts of the manifold
(imagine jumping between sheets in Swiss roll data, for example). Some
work on dimensionality (e.g. <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/srep31377" title="Accurate Estimation of the Intrinsic Dimension Using Graph Distances: Unraveling the Geometric Complexity of Datasets">A</a>, <a href="http://hal.cse.msu.edu/assets/pdfs/papers/2019-cvpr-intrinsic-dimensionality.pdf" title="On the Intrinsic Dimensionality of Image Representations">B</a>) involves this approach.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Wolfram">Stephen Wolfram</a> has some <a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2020/04/finally-we-may-have-a-path-to-the-fundamental-theory-of-physics-and-its-beautiful/">topological ideas about physics</a>,
including a very literal <a href="https://www.wolframphysics.org/technical-introduction/limiting-behavior-and-emergent-geometry/the-notion-of-dimension/">interpretation of dimensionality</a> being
the rate at which traveling a distance gives you access to more space.</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20201227-estimate_manifold_dimensionality_with_lid/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20201227-estimate_manifold_dimensionality_with_lid/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Ulysses' compass</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>These are some <a href="big.html">slides</a> for a book club discussion of
Chapter 7 from McElreath's <a href="https://xcelab.net/rm/statistical-rethinking/">Statistical Rethinking</a>. See also
McElreath's own <a href="https://github.com/rmcelreath/statrethinking_winter2019">slides and video presentations</a>.</p>
<hr>
<pre><code>&#128009; Scylla of overfitting
  &#9973; Ulysses' compass &#129517;
&#127786; Charybdis of underfitting</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>The title of the chapter is "Ulysses' Compass." McElreath loves to
give his chapters cute names that don't necessarily mean anything to
you until you've read the chapter.</p>
<p>What do we value: simplicity or accuracy? The chapter is about
navigating between overfitting and underfitting, which McElreath notes
briefly (page 201) is related to but distinct from the bias variance
trade-off. I think the difference he's alluding to is about what a
model is <em>capable</em> of representing (bias/variance) vs. what it <em>does</em>
represent (under/overfitting).</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="overfitting" src="overfitting.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>In section 7.1, "The problem with parameters" is that too many can
make it easy to overfit. It's a fairly standard presentation of
overfitting via polynomial regression and hating on R<sup>2</sup> (or
any naive score on the training data).</p>
<hr>
<pre><code class="language-python">from math import log

# Truth (as in Problem 7E1)
p = [0.7, 0.3]  # heads, tails</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>So now it's time to do <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information_theory">information theory</a>. Here we go!</p>
<p>This section was the most interesting to me, so I'm going to spend
some time on it here. I felt like his explanations were helpful, and
I've encountered the material in less cogent ways previously, so I
appreciated the chance to think things through all together a bit.</p>
<p>I'll do a running example where the true probabilities of heads and
tails for a coin (say) are 0.7 and 0.3. (We never really know the true
probabilities.)</p>
<hr>
<pre><code class="language-python"># Entropy, H(p)
H = lambda p: -sum(p_i * log(p_i) for p_i in p)
H(p)  # 0.6108643020548935</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>So we get entropy, which measures how uncertain things are. (He gives
some motivating criteria and implies it could be derived.)</p>
<hr>
<pre><code class="language-python"># Candidate "models"
q = [0.5, 0.5]
r = [0.9, 0.1]</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>So say we have these two "models" for that coin.</p>
<p>(These are just point estimates, not whole posterior distributions.)</p>
<hr>
<pre><code class="language-python"># Cross-Entropy, H(p, q), xH here because Python
xH = lambda p, q: -sum(p_i * log(q_i) for p_i, q_i in zip(p, q))
xH(p, q)  # 0.6931471805599453
xH(p, r)  # 0.764527888858692</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>Cross-entropy tells us something about how well a model goes with the
truth. (Well; how un-well: lower scores are better.)</p>
<p>The best score is what you get using the true model, which is the
entropy of the true model.</p>
<p>In lots of my models, we use cross-entropy loss, and we generally just
implicitly round all the "true" probabilities to one or zero, or do
something nearly as unjustified.</p>
<hr>
<pre><code class="language-python"># KL Divergence, D(p, q)
D = lambda p, q: sum(p_i * log(p_i/q_i) for p_i, q_i in zip(p, q))
D(p, q)  # 0.08228287850505178
D(p, r)  # 0.15366358680379852</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>Divergence then is just cross-entropy with the entropy subtracted off,
so that the best you can do is zero.</p>
<hr>
<pre><code class="language-python"># D(p, q) = H(p, q) - H(p)
D(p, q) == xH(p, q) - H(p)  # True</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>The other one doesn't happen to come out exactly due to floating point
math; what luck that the first one does!</p>
<p>So we wish we could use divergence to evaluate models, but we can't
because we never really know the true underlying model <code>p</code>. All we get
are data.</p>
<p>(If instead we're assuming that all the data is really 100% likely,
then H(p) is 0 and there's nothing to subtract off.)</p>
<p>The key insight in general is that even if we don't know <code>p</code>, when we
compare two models' scores by subtracting them, the <code>p</code> goes away, so
we can still get relative scores even without <code>p</code>.</p>
<hr>
<pre><code class="language-python"># Data
d = [0, 0, 1]  # heads, heads, tails</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>So here are some data.</p>
<hr>
<pre><code class="language-python"># Log probability (likelihood) score
S = lambda d, p: sum(log(p[d_i]) for d_i in d)
S(d, q)  # -2.0794415416798357
S(d, r)  # -2.513306124309698</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>So we switch now to just using the sum of log likelihoods of the data
given the model as the model's score.</p>
<p>This score is the same as the "cross-entropy" I often use, which is
the same also as divergence, when we're saying all the true
probabilities are zero or one.</p>
<p>Higher scores are better here.</p>
<hr>
<p>Positive log likelihoods happen!</p>
<hr>
<p>Positive log likelihoods caused me a little bit of consternation,
because I'd been thinking in terms of probabilities rather than
probability distributions. But really when you have a distribution,
you're using a density, which can be greater than one. So the log
could be positive.</p>
<hr>
<pre><code class="language-python"># True vs. predictive
S(d, p)  # -1.917322692203401
S(d, [2/3, 1/3])
         # -1.9095425048844388</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>The true model isn't necessarily the one that scores best on a given
sample of data.</p>
<hr>
<pre><code class="language-python"># Deviance
deviance = lambda d, p: -2 * S(d, p)
S(d, p)         # -1.917322692203401
deviance(d, p)  #  3.834645384406802</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>Then it's also common to switch to deviance, to make something nice
happen with chi-squared distributions or something. Now smaller scores
are better.</p>
<hr>
<p><em>Regular</em>ization!</p>
<hr>
<p>From the information theory stuff, he really wants to develop
information criteria, but first he talks about regularization.</p>
<p>He points out that it's sort of about pulling out the "regular"
patterns in the data, rather than overfitting to chance patterns. Nice
little mnemonic.</p>
<p>Bayesians are pretty smug about regularization, because they get it
essentially for free by adjusting their priors.</p>
<p>The chapter also has some material on robust regression, which
Bayesian's are also pretty smug about because it's relatively easy for
them to just swap out the normal distribution for something with
fatter tails.</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="silly meme" src="silly_meme.png"></p>
<hr>
<p>Next it's on to "Predicting predictive accuracy." McElreath talks a
little bit about cross-validation, but it's pretty clear his true love
is information criteria.</p>
<p>I generally prefer (read: "actually use") cross-validation.</p>
<hr>
<ul>
<li>AIC: Akaike Information Criterion</li>
<li>BIC: Bayesian Information Criterion (aka Schwarz criterion)</li>
<li>CV: Cross-Validation</li>
<li>DIC: Deviance Information Criterion</li>
<li>lppd: Log Pointwise Predictive Density</li>
<li>PSIS: Pareto-smoothed importance sampling cross-validation</li>
<li>R^2: "variance explained" or "coefficient of determination"</li>
<li>WAIC: [Widely Applicable | Watanabe-Akaike] Information Criterion</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>So he talks about his favorites, PSIS and WAIC. They seem fine.</p>
<hr>
<p>compare but don't select</p>
<hr>
<p>Then he says not to do model selection, in the sense of throwing out
models and what you learned from them in the process.</p>
<hr>
<pre><code># Mine (Python)
def sum_log_prob(a, b):
    return max(a, b) + math.log1p(math.exp(0 - abs(a - b)))

# McElreath's (R)
log_sum_exp &lt;- function( x ) {
    xmax &lt;- max(x)
    xsum &lt;- sum( exp( x - xmax ) )
    xmax + log(xsum)
}</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>Little sidebar (as also McElreath had one): Multiplying probabilities
that you have the logs of is easy, because you just add the logs.
Adding log probabilities is more annoying. But you can be a little
clever about it and it works out! I needed this recently while playing
with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Petersburg_paradox">St. Petersburg paradox</a>.</p>
<p>Mine is based on a <a href="https://gasstationwithoutpumps.wordpress.com/2014/05/06/sum-of-probabilities-in-log-prob-space/">post from Kevin Karplus</a>. I found McElreath's on
a <a href="https://rdrr.io/github/rmcelreath/rethinking/src/R/distributions.r">post on rdrr</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Ulysses' compass</p>
<ul>
<li>Don't overfit</li>
<li>Use log likelihood</li>
<li>Use CV and/or IC</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>So that about wraps it up!</p>
<p>See also my <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/issues/216#issuecomment-748518338">notes and quotes</a> from the chapter.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20201221-ulysses_compass/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20201221-ulysses_compass/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Pragmatic Programmer</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I read the original <a href="https://pragprog.com/titles/tpp20/the-pragmatic-programmer-20th-anniversary-edition/">Pragmatic Programmer</a> years ago, and now read
the 20th anniversary edition with some of my colleagues. It was an
important book to me early in my career, and still has lots of useful
reminders and updates with the new edition.</p>
<p>I wish the whole book was available as pages on the public web. It's
"written as a series of self-contained sections" in a way that would
work really well with hyperlinks.</p>
<h3>Quotes and notes by chapter</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="#ch1">Chapter 1: A Pragmatic Philosophy</a></li>
<li><a href="#ch2">Chapter 2: A Pragmatic Approach</a></li>
<li><a href="#ch3">Chapter 3: The Basic Tools</a></li>
<li><a href="#ch4">Chapter 4: Pragmatic Paranoia</a></li>
<li><a href="#ch5">Chapter 5: Bend, or Break</a></li>
<li><a href="#ch6">Chapter 6: Concurrency</a></li>
<li><a href="#ch7">Chapter 7: While You Are Coding</a></li>
<li><a href="#ch8">Chapter 8: Before the Project</a></li>
<li><a href="#ch9">Chapter 9: Pragmatic Projects</a></li>
<li><a href="#ch10">Chapter 10: Postface</a></li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="cover" src="pragprog.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="ch1"></a>Chapter 1: A Pragmatic Philosophy</h3>
<hr>
<p>The "broken windows" terminology hasn't aged terribly well because of
the controversy around <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broken_windows_theory">broken windows policing</a>; I agree broadly
with the software development message, but the term has some unwanted
connotations.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Tip 9: Invest Regularly in Your Knowledge Portfolio" (page 15)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The "Knowledge Portfolio" metaphor is pretty good. I also want people
to be life-long knowledge investors.</p>
<p>They list five items in managing a knowledge portfolio:</p>
<ul>
<li>Invest regularly</li>
<li>Diversify</li>
<li>Manage risk</li>
<li>Buy low, sell high</li>
<li>Review and rebalance</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"While there's a glut of short-form essays and occasionally reliable
answers on the web, for deep understanding you need long-form
books." (page 16)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"A favorite consulting trick: ask "why?" at least five times." (page
18)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In <a href="https://hbr.org/2018/09/curiosity">Why Curiosity Matters</a> they reference "Toyota&#8217;s 5 Whys approach."</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"One of the Neuro Linguistic Programming suppositions is "The
meaning of your communication is the response you get."" (page 20)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3><a name="ch2"></a>Chapter 2: A Pragmatic Approach</h3>
<hr>
<p>They note "Meyer's <em>Uniform Access principle</em>," which <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_access_principle">states</a> that
"All services offered by a module should be available through a
uniform notation, which does not betray whether they are implemented
through storage or through computation."</p>
<p>In Python this doesn't have to mean exposing getters and setters;
using <a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/functions.html#property">@property</a> is a good solution.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<em>If it isn't easy, people won't do it.</em>" (page 38)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In fact, this book is written in Markdown, and typeset directly
from the Markdown source." (page 45)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>How? How do they do footnotes, etc.? Sounds like ConTeXt can do some
part... But presumably they have their own custom stuff. Lots of
details, I imagine.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Model building can be both creative and useful in the long term.
Often, the process of building the model leads to discoveries of
underlying patterns and processes that weren't apparent on the
surface." (page 67)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"During the calculation phase, you get answers that seem strange.
Don't be too quick to dismiss them. If your arithmetic is correct,
your understanding of the problem or your model is probably wrong.
This is valuable information." (page 68)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3><a name="ch3"></a>Chapter 3: The Basic Tools</h3>
<hr>
<p>The footnote on page 100 cites <a href="http://pignottia.faculty.mjc.edu/math134/homework/doodlingCaseStudy.pdf">What Does Doodling do?</a>, which seems
kind of neat. I don't completely trust the result in the paper though,
or at least the interpretation. Here's the abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Doodling is a way of passing the time when bored by a lecture or
telephone call. Does it improve or hinder attention to the primary
task? To answer this question, 40 participants monitored a
monotonous mock telephone message for the names of people coming to
a party. Half of the group was randomly assigned to a &#8216;doodling&#8217;
condition where they shaded printed shapes while listening to the
telephone call. The doodling group performed better on the
monitoring task and recalled 29% more information on a surprise
memory test. Unlike many dual task situations, doodling while
working can be beneficial. Future research could test whether
doodling aids cognitive performance by reducing daydreaming</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3><a name="ch4"></a>Chapter 4: Pragmatic Paranoia</h3>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"DBC [Design By Contract] is more efficient (and DRY-er) than
defensive programming, where <em>everyone</em> has to validate data in case
no one else does." (page 108)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"By expressing the domain of the square root function in the
precondition of the <code>sqrt</code> routine, you shift the burden of
correctness to the caller&#8211;where it belongs." (page 110)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And other "fail fast" kinds of things... "crashing early" etc...</p>
<hr>
<p>In Python, <code>with open</code> blocks help implement "Finish What You Start"
(page 118).</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="ch5"></a>Chapter 5: Bend, or Break</h3>
<p>This chapter is <em>very substantially</em> different from the original
version, and in interesting ways. Here's a quick summary of the
content:</p>
<ul>
<li>Decoupling</li>
<li>Events<ul>
<li>Finite State Machines</li>
<li>The Observer Pattern</li>
<li>Publish/Subscribe</li>
<li>Reactive Programming and Streams</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Functional programming</li>
<li>Don't use inheritance<ul>
<li>Interfaces and protocols</li>
<li>Delegation</li>
<li>Mixins and traits</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Configuration (as a service)</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When we try to pick out anything by itself, we find it hitched to
everything else in the Universe." (page 130, quoting John Muir, My
First Summer in the Sierra)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>On page 148, they list files such as <code>dry.pml</code> which I guess means
they write using "Pragmatic Markup Language" as their custom
Markdown...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Do you program in an object-oriented language? Do you use
inheritance?</p>
<p>"If so, stop! It probably isn't what you want to do." (page 158)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3><a name="ch6"></a>Chapter 6: Concurrency</h3>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"[Concurrency] is often implemented using things such as fibers,
threads, and processes." (page 169)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I wasn't familiar with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fiber_(computer_science)">fibers</a>. Cute name. Connected to coroutines
(cooperative multitasking). Seems like fibers is common terminology in
Ruby.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... messaging systems (such as Kafka and NATS)" (page 189)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I wasn't familiar with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NATS_Messaging">NATS</a>. It's a messaging system. According
the <a href="https://docs.nats.io/faq">FAQ</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"NATS stands for Neural Autonomic Transport System. Derek Collison
conceived NATS as a messaging platform that functions like a central
nervous system."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3><a name="ch7"></a>Chapter 7: While You Are Coding</h3>
<hr>
<p>"Testing is not about finding bugs, it&#8217;s about getting feedback on
your code: aspects of design, the API, coupling, and so on. That means
that the major benefits of testing happen when you think about and
write the tests, not just when you run them." (page 325)</p>
<hr>
<p>"If you&#8217;re not sure why it works, you won&#8217;t know why it fails." (page
339)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Tip 68: Build End-to-End, Not Top-Down or Bottom Up" (page 366)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Testing, design, coding&#8212;it&#8217;s all programming." (page 374)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Property-based testing seems like fuzzing...</p>
<hr>
<p>That NIST thing on having reasonable password rules:
https://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/SpecialPublications/NIST.SP.800-63b.pdf</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="ch8"></a>Chapter 8: Before the Project</h3>
<p>This is good stuff, but I didn't pull out specific notes. It's on
working in tight feedback loops rather than trying to "collect
requirements" all at the beginning.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="ch9"></a>Chapter 9: Pragmatic Projects</h3>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Programmers are a bit like cats: intelligent, strong willed,
opinionated, independent, and often worshiped by the net." (page
437)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Tip 85: Schedule It to Make It Happen" (page 441)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/324959836_Mythical_Unit_Test_Coverage">Mythical Unit Test Coverage</a>
is neat. Abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is a continuous struggle to understand how much a product should
be tested before its delivery to the market. Ericsson, as a global
software development company, decided to evaluate the adequacy of
the unit-test-coverage criterion that it had employed for years as a
guide for sufficiency of testing. Naturally, one can think that if
increasing coverage decreases the number of defects significantly,
then coverage can be considered a criterion for test sufficiency. To
test this hypothesis in practice, we investigated the relationship
of unit-test-coverage measures and post-unit-test defects in a large
commercial product of Ericsson. The results indicate that high
unit-test coverage did not seem to be any tangible help in producing
defect-free software."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Even though your title might be some variation of &#8220;Software
Developer&#8221; or &#8220;Software Engineer,&#8221; in truth it should be &#8220;Problem
Solver.&#8221; That&#8217;s what we do, and that&#8217;s the essence of a Pragmatic
Programmer. We solve problems." (page 464)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Anonymity, especially on large projects, can provide a breeding
ground for sloppiness, mistakes, sloth, and bad code." (page 466)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3><a name="ch10"></a>Chapter 10: Postface</h3>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Tip 99: Don&#8217;t Enable Scumbags" (page 472)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20201210-pragmatic_programmer/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20201210-pragmatic_programmer/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Thinking Cards</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Inspired by <a href="/2013/09/28/polyas-how-to-solve-it-quotes-and-comments/">How to Solve It</a>, <a href="/20200716-lateral_thinking_creativity_step_by_step/">Lateral Thinking</a>, and others,
I've started to collect tactics for problem-solving. The shuffling
stuff is so that you can easily choose a random tactic to try.</p>
<p>I might do more with this and I'd love feedback/suggestions;
<a href="#contact">comment or message me</a>!</p>
<p></p><center>
  <input id="shuffle" type="submit" value="Shuffle" style="width: 49%">
  <input id="order" type="submit" value="Put in order" style="width: 49%">
</center>
<!-- Copy in cards.html below here -->

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#1" name="1">1</a>. Embrace problems</h3>
<p>The word "problem" has a negative connotation, and some problems are
hard to love. But in general, problems make life more interesting and
give us opportunities to learn, grow, and improve. Keep your problems
close.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#2" name="2">2</a>. Take care of yourself</h3>
<p>Are you hungry? Tired? Stressed? Eat well, sleep well, and look after
your mental health. Try to do something right now to make your body
and mind more effective, like stretching.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#3" name="3">3</a>. Take the pressure off</h3>
<p>What can you do to approach the problem calmly? Should you ask for
help or otherwise communicate with others? Should you make a back-up
plan or adjust your goal?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#4" name="4">4</a>. Reinforce the positive</h3>
<p>You have an opportunity for growth. You're learning. Celebrate all
progress, even small progress. Feel good about what you're doing. You
can do this.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#5" name="5">5</a>. Remove distractions</h3>
<p>Turn off the TV. Turn off your phone. Turn off notifications. Don't
check the news. Multitasking is a lie. If other thoughts come, jot
them down elsewhere to return to later.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#6" name="6">6</a>. Get inspired</h3>
<p>Why are you working on this? What's the larger goal? What are the
larger benefits? What other problems or people have done work you
admire? Appreciate and aspire to greatness.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#7" name="7">7</a>. Make a plan</h3>
<p>If you know how to attack the problem, make a plan to do that. Even if
you don't, make a plan to spend time on the problem, not all at once,
but consistently over a longer period.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#8" name="8">8</a>. Do other things</h3>
<p>Don't forget to eat and sleep, but also, spend time on complementary
and even unrelated tasks. Read a book. Tutor a student. Revisit other
things. Take a walk.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#9" name="9">9</a>. Work hard</h3>
<p>You need to focus. You need to put in time and effort. Sometimes you
have to stop looking for shortcuts and do the work. There is no royal
road. Work harder than anyone else.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#10" name="10">10</a>. Relax</h3>
<p>Take some time to change the nature of your focus on the problem. Pull
back from single-minded concentration. Don't focus on anything else
either. Relax. Don't micromanage your brain. What comes to you?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#11" name="11">11</a>. Work smart</h3>
<p>Even if you're already making progress, is there something you could
do more effectively? Can you find a better process if you reconsider?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#12" name="12">12</a>. Find support</h3>
<p>What would help you to be effective? Is there a group or team you can
join or form? What people or other resources can you engage with?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#13" name="13">13</a>. Understand the problem</h3>
<p>Do you completely understand what you're working on? Are all the
definitions clear? Does everyone involved agree on the problem
statement and objective?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#14" name="14">14</a>. Find roots</h3>
<p>What is the root cause (or causes) of the problem? Is the problem as
stated the real problem? How did the problem come to be? Keep asking
why.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#15" name="15">15</a>. Know what you know</h3>
<p>What do you know, and how do you know it? Are you sure? Could you
explain it to someone else? What do you not know, and how could you
come to know it? What else might be relevant?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#16" name="16">16</a>. Question assumptions</h3>
<p>What are you taking for granted? What is so obvius that you haven't
thought about it? What biases might be affecting your thinking? Are
there alternatives that seem "out there"?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#17" name="17">17</a>. Find similar problems</h3>
<p>Do you know a related problem? What have others done in similar
situations? How is a similar problem solved in nature, or in another
field? Can you build on work you or others have done before?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#18" name="18">18</a>. Consider quitting</h3>
<p>Is this a problem that shouldn't be solved? Is this problem the right
use of your time, right now? What if you didn't solve this particular
problem?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#19" name="19">19</a>. Get an easy win</h3>
<p>Find a task that you can succeed at in the next two minutes. It could
be getting out a pen, or opening a book. Do it, then praise yourself
for that victory. It may be easier to keep making progress afterward.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#20" name="20">20</a>. Start things cooking</h3>
<p>Many tasks involve some waiting after you initiate them, like waiting
for food to marinate, or waiting for responses to an email. Make a
point to get these things started as soon as you can.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#21" name="21">21</a>. Take a step</h3>
<p>Even if you're not sure of your whole plan, do something now. You can
always reevaluate afterward. Choose some goal that you can accomplish,
and do it now.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#22" name="22">22</a>. Do an experiment</h3>
<p>You don't have to only do things that you know will work. Try
something and see what happens. Be prepared to throw it away. You'll
learn from it and it will help you to make progress.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#23" name="23">23</a>. Guess and check</h3>
<p>A particular kind of experiment is to choose a next step, even if you
don't know that it's right, and see what happens next. Follow the
consequences forward. Even if you guessed wrong, you'll learn
something.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#24" name="24">24</a>. Write down what you&#8217;ve done</h3>
<p>Keep some log of what you've been doing, what you've tried, and what
the results have been. If you haven't been doing this, try to remember
and write down what you've done so far.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#25" name="25">25</a>. Try again</h3>
<p>Sometimes when you try something and it doesn't work, it isn't that
the approach was bad, it's that something didn't align that time. It
could be worth trying again, especially with things you tried when you
knew less.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#26" name="26">26</a>. Zoom in</h3>
<p>How close can you get to the tiniest pieces? What happens for exactly
one component? For a global problem, how does a single individual play
a part on a daily basis?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#27" name="27">27</a>. Zoom out</h3>
<p>What's the big picture? How does the problem fit into larger systems?
What's the global view? What's the long term view?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#28" name="28">28</a>. Draw a picture</h3>
<p>Make a graphical representation. It could be a sketch, a plot, a
diagram, a mind map, a flow chart. Make something you can see.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#29" name="29">29</a>. Change representations</h3>
<p>What's another way to conceptualize the problem? In math, you might
switch between numeric, geometric, and algebraic forms. You might
change domains, or phrase the problem as a story.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#30" name="30">30</a>. Use a different tool</h3>
<p>Try saying it out loud. Try typing, or writing longhand, or recording
a video. Try post-it notes or index cards. Try paper and pencil, or a
calculator, a diagramming tool, or a programming language.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#31" name="31">31</a>. Use analogy</h3>
<p>What else is this like? Can you compare to something else, even if
it's a stretch? What do the similarities and differences tell you?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#32" name="32">32</a>. Change viewpoints</h3>
<p>How does this look from different perspectives? How do different
people, pieces, places see the problem? Can you imagine yourself in
different positions?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#33" name="33">33</a>. Organize concepts</h3>
<p>What's the deep structure of this problem? Can you model the problem?
Are there axes or other ways of representing the ideas of your
problem?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#34" name="34">34</a>. Add randomness</h3>
<p>Consider something you wouldn't otherwise: a random word, WikiPedia
article, or the concept of randomness itself. Go to a museum, or a
store. Whatever you find, relate it to your problem. What could it
mean?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#35" name="35">35</a>. Talk it through</h3>
<p>Have a conversation with someone. Or imagine a conversation with
someone. Or have a conversation with yourself. Explain everything
you're thinking about.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#36" name="36">36</a>. Decompose/Recompose</h3>
<p>What are the words and ideas that you're using? Are they clich&#233;? Are
they appropriate? What if you broke down the way you're understanding
the problem and rebuilt it? Can you articulate the problem and
solution spaces?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#37" name="37">37</a>. Get feedback</h3>
<p>Get an outside view on your problem and your work on it. Try to
solicit feedback that helps you see things you aren't otherwise
seeing.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#38" name="38">38</a>. Learn more</h3>
<p>You may not know enough to solve your problem, and you may not even
know what it is that you don't know. Keep learning! Be curious about
topics near and far. Read and study for pleasure.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#39" name="39">39</a>. Ask for help</h3>
<p>Other people can help you a lot. Put effort into finding the right
place and way to ask, and others will often put effort into helping
you.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#40" name="40">40</a>. Break it up</h3>
<p>Sometimes you can break big problems into many more manageable steps.
It may even be possible for multiple people to work on separate parts.
Regardless, pursue and celebrate partial progress.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#41" name="41">41</a>. Use inversion</h3>
<p>How might you achieve the opposite of your goal? Are there other
reversals or inversions that might be illuminating? What's the worst
case outcome? Can you avoid it?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#42" name="42">42</a>. Make a list</h3>
<p>Generate lots of ideas. What are all the options? Consider more
possibilities. What else could you make a list of?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#43" name="43">43</a>. Eliminate possibilities</h3>
<p>What can you rule out? What hasn't worked already? What's impossible?
What has to be wrong? Why is that? What are the constraints? What can
you learn from what doesn't work?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#44" name="44">44</a>. Work backward</h3>
<p>Assume you have a solution. How would it come to be? What would
immediately lead to it? Can you follow steps backward from the end?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#45" name="45">45</a>. Consider special cases</h3>
<p>Are there some specific forms of the problem that are more tractable
or help with understanding? Can you extend a method based on these?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#46" name="46">46</a>. Consider extremes</h3>
<p>What if something in your problem disappeared, or was huge? What if
the problem itself was much worse, or more minor?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#47" name="47">47</a>. Add a constraint</h3>
<p>Add a deadline for something. Can you come up with ten ideas in ten
minutes? What if you have to be done today? What if your techniques or
resources were limited? What if you couldn't use a tool you're
currently using?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#48" name="48">48</a>. Simplify</h3>
<p>In what ways could a complicated problem be made less so? What does
simplifying it mean? Can you solve the simpler problem? If so, is that
good enough, or is there a way to build on the solution?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#49" name="49">49</a>. Generalize</h3>
<p>Can you make your problem a special case of some other problem? Can
you solve that problem? Maybe a general-purpose tool or approach can
be used or adapted for your problem.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#50" name="50">50</a>. Change the goal</h3>
<p>Maybe you don't need to solve exactly the problem you started with.
What's most important? Can you focus on that? Can you compromise to
find something that you can make progress on?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#51" name="51">51</a>. Imagine the end</h3>
<p>"Begin with the end in mind." What would a solution look like? Would
it necessarily have certain properties? What properties?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#52" name="52">52</a>. Find checks</h3>
<p>If you had a solution, how would you know that it's a good solution?
What would be the "check" in a "guess and check" approach? What can
you learn from your checks?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#53" name="53">53</a>. Think beyond the end</h3>
<p>If you had a solution, what would you do next? How does this step fit
into your ideas for where you want to go? Would you be happy, once you
had a solution? Why?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#54" name="54">54</a>. Choose the right tactic</h3>
<p>Which tactic is the one that will help you the most right now?
Choosing them should be natural as you work on problems all the time.
Think about your problem and what would be best.</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#55" name="55">55</a>. Make your own tactic</h3>
<p>Add a new tactic that works for you. What fits with how you think, and
the problems that you care about? Have you learned something that
works for you? Do you need something specific to your current problem?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#56" name="56">56</a>. Implement an existing solution</h3>
<p>Try applying an approach that's worked for you or someone else in the
past, even if it came from a slightly different problem. What do you
learn from trying this? Can you adapt the solution?</p>
</div>

<div class="card">
<hr>
<h3><a href="#57" name="57">57</a>. Quantify your progress</h3>
<p>Can you measure how much you've done, and how much is left to to?
Finding a metric can help you better understand your goal and what's
working to get you there.</p>
</div>

<!-- Don't remove this stuff down here... -->


    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20201206-thinking_cards/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20201206-thinking_cards/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Add variance to achieve a given correlation</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>If you have data <em>x</em> and you want some data <em>y</em> that has a given
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pearson_correlation_coefficient">correlation</a> <em>r</em> with <em>x</em>, multiply <em>x</em> by the sign of <em>r</em> and then
add random noise with variance equal to the original variance over the
square of the desired correlation, minus the original variance.</p>
<p>You can do this in <a href="https://www.r-project.org/">R</a>, for example:</p>
<!-- set.seed(27)  -->

<pre><code class="language-r">correlated &lt;- function(x, r) {
  return(x * sign(r) + rnorm(length(x), sd=sqrt(var(x)/r^2 - var(x))))
}

x &lt;- rnorm(100)
cor(x, correlated(x, 0.75))
## [1] 0.7537228</code></pre>

<p>The resulting correlation is only equal to the desired value in
expectation; you can tweak a value in the result to make it more exact
if you like, or use a <a href="https://stat.ethz.ch/pipermail/r-help/2007-April/128925.html">more sophisticated method</a>.</p>
<p>The method here works because of the relationship between correlation
and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coefficient_of_determination">coefficient of determination</a> which holds here, and of course
the <a href="/20201030-the_variance_sum_law_is_interesting/">variance sum law</a>.</p>
<p>\[ r^2 = R^2 = 1 - \frac{ \sigma^2_\text{noise} }{ \sigma^2_{x + \text{noise}} } = \frac{ \sigma^2_x }{ \sigma^2_x + \sigma^2_\text{noise} } \]</p>
<p>\[ \sigma^2_\text{noise} = \frac{\sigma^2_x}{r^2} - \sigma^2_x \]</p>
<p>The question of how to do this came up years ago at an old job I had.
I don't recall anybody coming up with a solution, back then. Live and
learn!</p>
<p>If you're generating all the data yourself, it's easier to use a
multi-dimensional random generator. The <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/MASS/index.html">MASS</a> package's <a href="https://www.rdocumentation.org/packages/MASS/versions/7.3-53/topics/mvrnorm">mvrnorm</a>
function has an <code>empirical</code> flag which can even make things work out
exactly (rather than just in expectation). And if you need more new
variables that relate to existing data, you probably want a
<a href="https://stat.ethz.ch/pipermail/r-help/2007-April/128925.html">more sophisticated method</a>.</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20201128-add_variance_to_achieve_a_given_correlation/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20201128-add_variance_to_achieve_a_given_correlation/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Correlation can be confounder determination</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>In a situation of pure confounding (<em>x</em>&#8592;<em>z</em>&#8594;<em>y</em>) with equivariant
noise, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pearson_correlation_coefficient">correlation</a> between <em>x</em> and <em>y</em> is the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coefficient_of_determination">coefficient of determination</a> between <em>z</em> and either <em>x</em> or <em>y</em>:
\( r = R^2 \).</p>
<p>I got to thinking about this because of <a href="/20200917-book_of_why/">The Book of Why</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"[<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbara_Stoddard_Burks">Burks</a>] computed the direct effect of parental IQ on children's
IQ and found that only 35 percent, or about one-third, of IQ
variation is inherited. In other words, parents with an IQ fifteen
points above average would typically have children five points above
average." (page 306)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That works out if we have a simple data-generating model like this in
<a href="https://www.r-project.org/">R</a>:</p>
<!-- set.seed(10)  -->

<pre><code class="language-r">z &lt;- rnorm(1000000, sd=1)            # genetics,            variance=1
x &lt;- z + rnorm(1000000, sd=sqrt(2))  # IQ of parents,  adds variance=2 noise
y &lt;- z + rnorm(1000000, sd=sqrt(2))  # IQ of children, adds variance=2 noise
mean(y[0.9 &lt; x &amp; x &lt; 1.1])
## [1] 0.334556</code></pre>

<p>One third of <em>x</em> and <em>y</em> variance is due to <em>z</em>, and when <em>x</em> values
are around 1, average corresponding <em>y</em> value is around 1/3, so that
checks out: regression to the mean.</p>
<p>The genetic contribution <em>z</em> isn't really observable, though. All we
see are <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>. So how do we get the contribution of <em>z</em>?</p>
<p>Both <em>x</em> and <em>y</em> <a href="/20201030-the_variance_sum_law_is_interesting/">have</a> variance 3. If we had a twin study in this
world, we could recover that variance is 2 when genetics is fixed, and
that would let us find that genetics explains 1/3 of variance. But we
don't generally have a twin study.</p>
<p>The common thing to do would be a regression.</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">summary(lm(y ~ x))  # (Pulling out one line of output...)
## Multiple R-squared:  0.1114,     Adjusted R-squared:  0.1114</code></pre>

<p>This is usually interpreted as saying that <em>x</em> explains 11% of the
variation of <em>y</em>. That's true enough, but it isn't how much is
explained by <em>z</em>.</p>
<p>The correlation between <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>, however, <em>is</em> how much variance
is explained by <em>z</em>.</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">cor(x, y)
## [1] 0.3338363</code></pre>

<p>More generally (for non-equivariant noise) the regression coefficient
gives the fraction of variance explained by <em>z</em>. (See also the earlier
estimate illustrating regression to the mean.)</p>
<p>So this is a way of estimating the effect of an unobserved confounder,
which seems to work in this very simple setting. Is this like what
Burks did? Probably her models were not so simple. Is this a special
case of some more general approach?</p>
<p>I don't think I've seen this kind of "method" before; I'd love to see
more elaboration of this kind of idea for estimating impacts of
unobserved variables.</p>
<p><img alt="confounding" src="common_cause.png"></p>
<p>The data-generating model above (and surrounding discussion) requires
suspension of disbelief; it represents some sort of asexual
reproduction, has additional influences on IQ that are entirely
uncorrelated between parents and children, and of course IQ is fraught
as a topic to begin with. Hopefully the statistical considerations are
still visible.</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20201127-correlation_can_be_confounder_determination/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20201127-correlation_can_be_confounder_determination/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
