<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>Communicate Immediately</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Discover what's important and present it early and concisely to refine
your ideas and engage with your audience. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverted_pyramid_(journalism)">Don't bury the lede</a>. Put
the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BLUF_(communication)">Bottom Line Up Front</a>. Communicate as if you may be
interrupted.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#message">Identify your message</a></li>
<li><a href="#line">Give a one-line version</a></li>
<li><a href="#paragraph">Give a one-paragraph version</a></li>
<li><a href="#detail">Add detail until complete</a></li>
<li><a href="#media">Use the best of text and other media</a></li>
</ul>
<h3><a name="message"></a>Identify your message</h3>
<p>What your audience needs most is your unique contribution: a result or
recommendation, a summary or synthesis. Help them to understand.
Prepare them to take action.</p>
<p>If you don't know what your message is, you have little chance of
communicating it. Think beyond listing what you've done, what you've
read, what you've seen. Find a deeper conclusion. Even without an
audience, you should be doing this for yourself.</p>
<p>According to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Mathematical_Theory_of_Communication">Shannon</a>, information is related to surprise. One
heuristic is to identify the most central "surprise" you have to
communicate. What does your audience not know? Can you anticipate
questions they would ask, and answer them?</p>
<p>Don't force your audience to come to their own conclusions. Your
message won't prevent them from doing that anyway, if you are honest
and <a href="#detail">complete</a>. Your message isn't the final word. It should
be a generous starting point.</p>
<p>Regardless of audience, the practice of articulating a message into
short concrete forms can help you to clarify and improve your ideas,
possibly through several iterations.</p>
<h3><a name="line"></a>Give a one-line version</h3>
<p>Start with a title, or subject line, or initial answer to a question.
A one-line version should be complete enough that the audience can
choose whether to continue.</p>
<p>Good newspaper headlines, like "Truman wins presidency," are tiny
versions of their articles. Clickbait titles illustrate what not to
do, as in "You won't believe what Truman did." Emulate good headlines.</p>
<!-- https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dewey_Defeats_Truman -->

<p>Good one-line versions are usually complete sentences, not just noun
phrases. Don't convey just the subject you're talking about, include
what you're saying about it.</p>
<p>Feel free to use the specialized language of your field.
<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.10029v1">Big Self-Supervised Models are Strong Semi-Supervised Learners</a> is
a great title for a Machine Learning paper, though it may seem opaque
to botanists.</p>
<p>Though the need for summarizing is real, there's value in retaining
important detail. For example, "Technique X Improves Results" is
likely not a better one-line version than "Technique X Improves Metric
Y by 3%." Include specifics as much as you can.</p>
<p>It may be challenging to distill your message into a faithful one-line
representation, but it can be done. In some cases, a one-line version
is all you need.</p>
<h3><a name="paragraph"></a>Give a one-paragraph version</h3>
<p>Whether it's labeled as an abstract or a summary or not, a first
paragraph should always be a complete version of your message, not an
introduction.</p>
<p>The one-line version of your message may be just a sketch, but a
well-crafted paragraph let's you convey, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle">Pareto</a>-style, a complete
core message, missing only detail.</p>
<p>The practice of skipping quickly to an article's conclusion is not a
natural part of reading, it is a defensive work-around for bad
writing. Present the conclusion at the beginning.</p>
<p>You shouldn't require your audience go all the way to the end. For
example, if the purpose of an email is to make a request, make the
request clear at the beginning.</p>
<p>The focus here is effective, purposeful, reality-oriented
communication. This is distinct from small talk, poetry, or fiction,
where it may make sense to approach a topic obliquely over time, to
carefully build an effect.</p>
<p>With a useful one-paragraph version at the beginning, the audience can
determine what information is being communicated and what further
detail they're interested in. This is kind to your audience&#8212;and your
audience may be you.</p>
<h3><a name="detail"></a>Add detail until complete</h3>
<p>Including condensed versions at the beginning doesn't mean omitting
supporting detail, clarification, data, and other supplementary
material. Be very inclusive. The expectation is not that the audience
must review everything, but that they may.</p>
<p>Organize for the benefit of the audience. Make it easy to find things.
This should follow from the nature of what you're communicating, and
could also be responsive to the expectations of your audience.</p>
<p>The overall structure should often be fractal, in that further
sections are organized following the overall guidelines, starting with
short versions.</p>
<p>Generally, information density and polish should decrease gradually.
Content at the beginning is likely still elaborating the core message.
More related detail is added gradually, until toward the end one might
include a list of references, notes, logs of activities over time,
source data, audio or transcriptions from interviews, and the like.</p>
<p>Enough should be provided that the audience can replicate your
conclusions or form their own. Nothing should be hidden.</p>
<h3><a name="media"></a>Use the best of text and other media</h3>
<p>Text is a mighty tool, but it is not the only tool. Always use the
best available tool for communicating. Outside of conversation, text
and its variants together with two-dimensional graphics (especially
data visualizations) are most useful, with time-distributed media and
interactive artifacts only sometimes worthwhile.</p>
<p>Text can be used in many ways. Headings add structure. Numbered and
bulleted lists and tables can help organize and summarize. Fonts,
weights, sizes, and styles can assist in communication when used well.
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext">Hypertext</a> allows linking easily to related resources.</p>
<p>Numbers are data visualizations, as are quantitative tables. Carefully
presented numbers can be very communicative.</p>
<p>Graphics can help communicate ideas diagrammatically. Graphical data
visualizations (plots, graphs, charts) can convey quantitative
information exceptionally well; their effective use is an extended
topic. Images can also sometimes be useful.</p>
<p>Time-distributed media refers principally to audio and video. To date,
these are difficult to search or skim. They tend to require the
audience to sit through them. Similarly, interactive artifacts are
relatively oblique rather than communicating directly. There are
places for all of these, but they are not often the best choice for
direct communication.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200715-communicate_immediately/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200715-communicate_immediately/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Asimov's Foundation trilogy</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3Gdm40MPYnw">inspired</a> to read the core trilogy of Asimov's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foundation_series">Foundation</a>
series. Started in 1942, it's in many ways a relic, but it's
interesting for its <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foundation_series#Cultural_impact">influence</a> and explorations of how history
develops, what matters, what can be predicted, and what can be
controlled.</p>
<p>Hari Seldon comes up with a mathematical <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychohistory_(fictional)">psychohistory</a> for
predicting the future of society, obtaining predictions we are to take
as correct for up to 30,000 years in the future. As a kind of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statistical_mechanics">statistical mechanics</a> for humanity, it seems like
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/People%27s_history">history from below</a>. This conflicts with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_man_theory">Great Man Theory</a>&#8212;and
the author's desire to have characters drive developments (though the
main characters do once turn out to be totally irrelevant).</p>
<p>I usually think of the future as hard to <a href="/20200112-predicting_the_future_from_2020/">predict</a>, so just
imagining there could be such good predictions is kind of fun. Is it
just that we don't know how, or (as the book suggests) that it's only
possible on scales greater than one planet?</p>
<p>I've recently been <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_Revolutions_and_Financial_Capital">learning</a> about supposed economic cycles as long
as 50 to 60 years, but it isn't clear how truly predictive these are.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The current view of mainstream economics is that business cycles
are essentially the summation of purely random shocks to the economy
and thus are not, in fact, cycles, despite appearing to be so."
[<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_cycle">wiki</a>]</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also, if a prediction is widely known then it may no longer be valid,
which is then a possible incentive to secrecy. Regardless, it's fun to
think about how much can be predicted, how it might be done, and what
might invalidate predictions.</p>
<p><img alt="Foundation trilogy cover" src="foundation_cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200714-foundation_trilogy/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200714-foundation_trilogy/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Peopleware: Productive Projects and Teams</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
<p>"... the major issues of software development are human, not
technical."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peopleware:_Productive_Projects_and_Teams">1987 book</a> has wisdom still in rare supply. Humans are
non-modular. Solving problems relies on people more than technology.
The best management is something like an evolution of Montessori
teaching. The book is organized into six parts:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>"Managing the Human Resource" (introduction)</li>
<li>"The Office Environment" (literally, setting up a nice physical
   space)</li>
<li>"The Right People" (people are important, hire well, avoid
   turnover)</li>
<li>"Growing Productive Teams" (encourage teams to jell)</li>
<li>"Fertile Soil" (good practices for meetings, email, etc.)</li>
<li>"It's Supposed to Be Fun to Work Here" (conclusion)</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<h2>The book's recommendations</h2>
<p>Make it possible for people to work without interruption.</p>
<p>Everyone can be self-coordinating:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Each time you're inclined to send a coordinating e-mail to a
colleague or to anyone who works for you, think about what steps you
have to make to coach that person to self-coordinate. Don't expect
this to be easy. Telling someone what to do <em>is</em> easy, while
instilling self-coordinating abilities in that same person is much
more complicated. But it pays off in the long run." (page 202)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Process rules and strict methodologies are bad. Let people have good
<em>training</em>, <em>tools</em>, and <em>peer review</em> (page 180).</p>
<p>Every project should be trying exactly one really new thing. Apart
from escaping local maxima, this is based on an interesting
interpretation of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawthorne_effect">the Hawthorne Effect</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"... the <em>Hawthorne Effect</em>. Loosely stated, it says that people
perform better when they're trying something new." (page 181)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Consider "Open-Space meetings" which are informal "mingling" meetings
that allow small group conversations (pages 190-191).</p>
<p>They recommend brainstorming techniques &#224; la <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_de_Bono">de Bono</a> on page 228:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>"Analogy thinking (How does nature solve this or some similar
  problem?)"</li>
<li>"Inversion (How might we achieve the opposite of our goal?)"</li>
<li>"Immersion (How might you project yourself into the problem?)"</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>They encourage considering fallback plans, especially regarding
deadlines:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The risk we tend not to manage is the risk of our own failure."
(page 184)</p>
</blockquote>
<h2>Flipping attitudes</h2>
<p>The Netflix "<a href="https://igormroz.com/documents/netflix_culture.pdf">freedom and responsibility</a>" approach provides an
interesting contrast. Netflix wants to be "a pro sports team" with
coaches who "cut smartly, so we have stars".</p>
<p>The Peopleware authors note explicitly (page 158) that they dislike
the sports team comparison, because sports teams have internal
competition and individuals can succeed or fail independent of the
group.</p>
<p>The Netflix approach can sound exciting, but it's also why Netflix is
known for a <a href="https://qz.com/work/1439451/the-seven-ways-netflix-culture-sounds-like-your-worst-work-nightmare/">culture of fear</a>. Peopleware is much more like
<a href="/20151118-debugging_teams/">Debugging Teams</a>, with its focus on humility, respect, and trust.
"Above all, resist the urge to manage."</p>
<p>I hadn't known anything about TQM (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Total_quality_management">Total Quality Management</a>) but I
was interested to see that it's a real flip from what I'd expect from
such a bureaucratic-sounding name.</p>
<p><a href="https://asq.org/quality-resources/total-quality-management/deming-points">Deming&#8217;s 14 Points on Quality Management</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>"Create constancy of purpose for improving products and
   services."</li>
<li>"Adopt the new philosophy."</li>
<li>"Cease dependence on inspection to achieve quality."</li>
<li>"End the practice of awarding business on price alone; instead,
   minimize total cost by working with a single supplier."</li>
<li>"Improve constantly and forever every process for planning,
   production and service."</li>
<li>"Institute training on the job."</li>
<li>"Adopt and institute leadership."</li>
<li>"Drive out fear."</li>
<li>"Break down barriers between staff areas."</li>
<li>"Eliminate slogans, exhortations and targets for the workforce."</li>
<li>"Eliminate numerical quotas for the workforce and numerical
    goals for management."</li>
<li>"Remove barriers that rob people of pride of workmanship, and
    eliminate the annual rating or merit system."</li>
<li>"Institute a vigorous program of education and self-improvement
    for everyone."</li>
<li>"Put everybody in the company to work accomplishing the
    transformation."</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Some of those points seem opposed to <a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/">metrics</a>, which isn't always
the stance of the Peopleware authors:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Gilb's Law: <em>Anything you need to quantify can be measured in some
way that is superior to not measuring it at all.</em>" (page 58)</p>
</blockquote>
<h2>Hiring and development</h2>
<p>The authors seem generally capable of holding
<a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2020/01/05/intelligence/">two opposed ideas at the same time</a>, and this is especially true in
their takes on hiring and development of employees.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"... managers are unlikely to change their people in any meaningful
way. ... If they're not right for the job from the start, they never
will be." (page 94)</p>
<p>"At Southern California Edison some years ago, the person in charge
of all data processing began as a meter reader. At EG&amp;G, there was a
program of retraining administrative staff to become systems
analysts. At the Bureau of Labor Statistics, philosophy Ph.D.s are
hired to become software developers and the retraining starts with
their first day on the job. At Hitachi Software, the chief scientist
has as his principal function the training of new hires. At Pacific
Bell, a main source of new systems people is the retrained lineman
or operator." (page 123)</p>
<p>"If your staff isn't up to the job at hand, you will fail. Of
course, if the people are badly suited to the job, you should get
new people. But once you've decided to go with a given group, your
best tactic is to trust them. Any defensive measure taken to
guarantee success in spite of them will only make things worse."
(page 144)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is an interesting apparent tension.</p>
<h2>Signs of age, signs of prescience</h2>
<p>Peopleware was updated in 2013, but it isn't completely modern.
Innocuously, it refers to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_General#32-bit_Project_Eagle_-_the_Eagle_project">Eagle project</a> as if everyone knows
it. More unfortunately, it uses "<a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/o/open-kimono.asp">open kimono</a>" as if there's no
reason not to.</p>
<p>The authors rail against the interruptions of the telephone. At least
for me, this is dated. They're right, phones are awful, but everybody
knows this now and I can't remember the last time somebody called me
for work.</p>
<p>They emphasize the importance of uninterrupted work time and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)">flow</a>
in a way that is pretty well known now, I think. Paul Graham's 2009
<a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html">Maker's Schedule, Manager's Schedule</a> is one related
popularization.</p>
<p>The authors don't comment at all on remote work, which I think is
unfortunate.</p>
<h2>Two more quotes</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>"There is very little true teamwork required in most of our work."
(page 136)</p>
<p>"Managers are often not true members of their teams" (page 137)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img alt="cover" src="peopleware.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200523-peopleware_productive_projects_and_teams/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200523-peopleware_productive_projects_and_teams/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Looks like people don't die on weekends</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Like a lot of people, my hobby recently has been checking COVID-19
stats more often than is helpful. It can be hard to tell if a new
day's numbers are relatively good or bad, in part because of a
distinct weekly pattern.</p>
<p><img alt="Daily new COVID-19 deaths (USA)" src="data_and_trend.png"></p>
<p>If you take out the trend, it's clear that there are consistently
relatively fewer deaths reported on Sundays and Mondays. There's a
compensatory tendency for Tuesdays and Wednesdays to have higher
numbers of deaths reported.</p>
<p><img alt="Week day average COVID-19 deaths (USA) relative to trend" src="week_day_residuals.png"></p>
<p>This clearly shows that the way to fight COVID-19 is by instituting an
all-weekend policy.</p>
<p>But it really is an interesting phenomenon. What's causing this effect
in the data?</p>
<ul>
<li>Do people really avoid death on weekends? I could imagine a small
   effect in that direction, but I wouldn't think it would be anything
   like this big.</li>
<li>Is it purely a reporting effect? Lots of health professionals are
   working weekends these days, I suspect, but maybe clerical staff or
   others in the reporting chain take consistent weekends? I suspect
   this is the main explanation.</li>
<li>Why is it primarily Sunday and Monday rather than Saturday and
   Sunday? Do the daily numbers correspond more accurately to the
   prior day?</li>
</ul>
<p>In any event, it's a good idea to, for example, use a 7-day rolling
average (as <a href="https://www.ft.com/coronavirus-latest">in the Financial Times</a>) to avoid being mislead by this
weekly pattern.</p>
<hr>
<p>Update 2020-05-04: The plot above uses an average of numbers of
deaths, which feels raw and real, but isn't super meaningful against
the changing scale of the pandemic in the US over time. The version
below is by percent difference (weighted by the trend, to avoid undue
influence when the numbers were all small and the fit of the trend
isn't as good.)</p>
<p><img alt="Week day average COVID-19 deaths (USA) relative to trend (percentage)" src="week_day_residuals_percent.png"></p>
<p>The plot looks very similar, but these percentages can be used (with a
little math) to try to "seasonally adjust" daily US COVID-19 death
numbers. I'm not saying this has any particular statistical validity,
but it's one way to try to guess what a Sunday or Monday number really
means, for example.</p>
<hr>
<p>I used the New York Times' <a href="https://github.com/nytimes/covid-19-data">covid-19-data</a>. My code is all up
<a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/covid_weekend">on GitHub</a>.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200502-looks_like_people_dont_die_on_weekends/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200502-looks_like_people_dont_die_on_weekends/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Tyranny of Metrics, by Muller</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/hardcover/9780691174952/the-tyranny-of-metrics" title="The Tyranny of Metrics (Princeton University Press)">The Tyranny of Metrics</a> is the book version of the author's
<a href="https://www.the-american-interest.com/2015/08/03/the-costs-of-accountability/" title="The Costs of Accountability (The American Interest)">earlier article</a>. It's a pretty good <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2013/05/31/178263/the-dictatorship-of-data/" title="The Dictatorship of Data (MIT Technology Review)">collection</a> of <a href="https://www.amstat.org/asa/files/pdfs/POL-ASAVAM-Statement.pdf" title="ASA Statement on Using Value-Added Models for Educational Assessment">concerns</a>
around measurement, focused on <a href="https://fs.blog/2018/02/unintended-consequences/" title="The Law of Unintended Consequences: Shakespeare, Cobra Breeding, and a Tower in Pisa (Farnam Street)">unintended consequences</a>.</p>
<p>One thing that <a href="https://history.catholic.edu/faculty-and-research/faculty-profiles/muller-jerry/index.html">Muller</a>'s historical perspective brought out was the
development of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientific_management">scientific management</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Management_consulting">management consulting</a>
as practices distinct from particular fields or businesses. I think
there are parallels to the development of data science.</p>
<p>He also maintains that the main value of a metric can come from
looking at outliers rather than tracking averages or otherwise using
the metric over all cases. I think this is an often neglected focus.</p>
<p>There's a lot of interesting stuff. Here are some quotes that I
thought were particularly interesting:</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Accountability ought to mean being held responsible for one's
actions. But by a sort of linguistic sleight of hand, accountability
has come to mean demonstrating success through standardized
measurement, as if only that which can be counted really counts."
(page 4)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When proponents of metrics advocate "accountability," they tacitly
combine two meanings of the word. On the one hand, to be accountable
means to be responsible. But it can also mean "capable of being
counted."" (page 17)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This book is not about the evils of measuring. It is about the
unintended consequences of trying to substitute standardized
measures of performance for personal judgment based on experience.
The problem is not measurement, but excessive measurement and
inappropriate measurement&#8212;not metrics, but metric fixation." (page
4)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The key components of metric fixation are</p>
<ul>
<li>"the belief that it is possible and desirable to replace judgment,
  acquired by personal experience and talent, with numerical
  indicators of comparative performance based upon standardized data
  (metrics);</li>
<li>"the belief that making such metrics public (transparent) assures
  that institutions are actually carrying out their purposes
  (accountability);</li>
<li>"the belief that the best way to motivate people within these
  organizations is by attaching rewards and penalties to their
  measured performance, rewards that are either monetary
  (pay-for-performance) or reputational (rankings)." (page 18)</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>"Recurring Flaws" from Chapter 2:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>"Measuring the most easily measurable"</li>
<li>"measuring the simple when the desired outcome is complex"</li>
<li>"Measuring inputs rather than outcomes"</li>
<li>"Degrading information quality through standardization"</li>
<li>"Gaming through creaming"</li>
<li>"Improving numbers by lowering standards"</li>
<li>"Improving numbers through omission or distortion of data"</li>
<li>"Cheating"</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Under scientific management the managers assume ... the burden of
gathering together all of the traditional knowledge which in the
past has been possessed by the workmen and then of classifying,
tabulating, and reducing this knowledge to rules, laws, formulae...
Thus all of the planning which under the old system was done by the
workmen, must of necessity under the new system be done by
management in accordance with the law of science." (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_Winslow_Taylor">Taylor</a>
quoted pages 32-33)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is only through <em>enforced</em> standardization of methods,
<em>enforced</em> adoption of the best implements and working conditions,
and <em>enforced</em> cooperation that this faster work can be assured. And
the duty of enforcing the adoption of standards and enforcing this
cooperation rests with <em>management</em> alone." (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_Winslow_Taylor">Taylor</a> quoted page
33)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The calculative is the enemy of the imaginative." (page 61)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This lends a certain air of unreality to the explorations of what
one might call the unworldly economists, who combine hard measures
of statistical validity with weak interest in the validity of the
units of measurement." (page 72)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>The effect of valuing quantity over quality in academic publishing
leads to:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"a great stream of publications that are both uninteresting and
unread." (page 79)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This is an instance of <em>diagnostic</em> metrics. It provides data that
can be used by a practitioner (physician), or internally within an
institution (hospital), or shared among practitioners and
institutions to discover what is working and what is not, and to use
that information to improve performance." (page 110)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... the metrics matter because of the way they are embedded into a
larger institutional culture." (page 110)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Extrinsic rewards become an important determinant of job
satisfaction only among workers for whom intrinsic rewards are
relatively unavailable." (<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2778664" title="The Happy Worker: An Analysis of Educational and Occupational Differences in Determinants of Job Satisfaction">Gruenberg</a> quoted page 137)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The fact that allies spy on one another to a certain degree to
determine intentions, capacities, and vulnerabilities is well known
to practitioners of government. But it cannot be publicly
acknowledged, since it represents a threat to the amour propre of
other nations." (page 164)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Chapter 15 "Unintended but predictable negative consequences":</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>"Goal displacement through diversion of effort to what gets
  measured"</li>
<li>"Promoting short-termism"</li>
<li>"Costs in employee time"</li>
<li>"Diminishing utility"</li>
<li>"Rule cascades" (to prevent gaming the metrics, etc.)</li>
<li>"Rewarding luck"</li>
<li>"Discouraging risk-taking"</li>
<li>"Discouraging innovation"</li>
<li>"Discouraging cooperation and common purpose"</li>
<li>"Degradation of work" (the experience of working people)</li>
<li>"Costs to productivity"</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Chapter 16 "When and how to use metrics":</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>"What <em>kind</em> of information are you thinking of measuring?"</li>
<li>"How <em>useful</em> is the information?"</li>
<li>"How useful are <em>more</em> metrics?"</li>
<li>"What are the costs of <em>not</em> relying upon standardized
   measurement?"</li>
<li>"To what <em>purposes</em> will the measurement be put, or to put it
   another way, to <em>whom</em> will the information be made transparent?"</li>
<li>"What are the <em>costs</em> of acquiring the metrics?"</li>
<li>"Ask why the people at the top of the organization are demanding
   performance metrics."</li>
<li>"<em>How</em> and <em>by whom</em> are the measures of performance developed?"</li>
<li>"Remember that <em>even the best measures are subject to corruption
   or goal diversion.</em>"</li>
<li>"Remember that sometimes, recognizing the limits of the possible
    is the beginning of wisdom."</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Here Muller lists a factor outside the control of the American medical
system, citing page 84 of <em>In Excellent Health</em> by Atlas and a paper
on <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w14333" title="Socioeconomic Status and Health: Dimensions and Mechanisms">Socioeconomic Status and Health</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Moreover, the United States is an ethnically heterogeneous country,
and some ethnic groups (such as African Americans) have
disproportionately high rates of infant mortality, reflecting
social, cultural, and possibly genetic factors." (p. 106)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This strikes me as, at the very least, unfortunate phrasing. Here's
<a href="https://www.americanprogress.org/issues/early-childhood/reports/2018/02/01/445576/exploring-african-americans-high-maternal-infant-death-rates/" title="Exploring African Americans&#8217; High Maternal and Infant Death Rates">how some others talk</a> about African American infant mortality rates:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is racism, not race itself, that threatens the lives of African
American women and infants."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="tyranny.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Ultimate Question 2.0, by Reichheld</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I was interested in Net Promoter&#174; score, so I read <a href="https://www.netpromotersystem.com/books/the-ultimate-question-2.0/" title="The Ultimate Question 2.0">the book</a>, which
is a longer version of <a href="https://hbr.org/2003/12/the-one-number-you-need-to-grow" title="The One Number You Need to Grow">the original article</a>. NPS is an interesting
case study in simplicity, interpretability, paths to action,
unintended consequences, and data collection.</p>
<h3>Simplicity</h3>
<p>Net Promoter is built around one question, now common in many
variants, about whether you'd make a recommendation.</p>
<p><img alt="NPS summary" src="nps_summary.png"></p>
<p>The single-question approach may help with response rate, but that
isn't the only rationale.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Traditional satisfaction surveys ... ask too many questions and
inspire analysis instead of action." (pages ix-x)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Reichheld describes research supporting the use of a single question
as a correlate of growth, and clustering analysis supporting the three
response categories. Whether these are perfect is beside the point of
<em>focusing</em> on <em>some</em> data about customer experience.</p>
<h3>Interpretability</h3>
<p>The Net Promoter score is explained as the percentage of promoters
minus the percentage of detractors. This is equivalent to averaging a
remapping of the 0 to 10 scale, but better at maintaining a meaningful
interpretation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"[This] made sense to frontline managers, who could relate to the
goal of increasing the number of promoters and reducing the number
of detractors more readily than increasing the mean of their
satisfaction index by one standard deviation." (<a href="https://hbr.org/2003/12/the-one-number-you-need-to-grow" title="The One Number You Need to Grow">HBR</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This scoring method amounts to a kind of data visualization, focused
on communicating and understanding. Whether or not it generates the
best correlation coefficients with other quantities of interest,
there's little doubt that it's instantly understandable.</p>
<h3>Paths to Action</h3>
<p>The Net Promoter <em>score</em> is quantitative, but the <em>system</em> is always
supposed to include a second question: "What is the primary reason for
your score?" This is one of the ways that NPS becomes actionable.</p>
<p>The open-ended follow-up avoids "the preconceived response categories
of traditional customer-satisfaction questionnaires" (page 5) and
invites the power of anecdote.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Reading a comment from a customer promoter or detractor has far
more impact than looking at a statistic on a monthly report from
headquarters." (page 186)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The bottom-up application of NPS is intended to be non-anonymous and
closed-loop: An employee might call detractors shortly after their
responses come in to apologize and try to address issues immediately.</p>
<p>This kind of feedback helps to "Make NPS a tool to help people succeed
(not just an evaluation metric)" (page 254) independent of statistics.
The scores themselves can also be used more directly, but not without
risk.</p>
<h3>Unintended Consequences</h3>
<p>NPS generates scores can be compared, incentivized, and then gamed:
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodhart%27s_law">Goodhart's law</a>.</p>
<p>NPS can also be used to evaluate employee satisfaction: "employee Net
Promoter scores (eNPS)" (page 165). Like any data, it can be used for
questionable purposes.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"When JetBlue first began its eNPS surveys, it discovered pockets of
detractors. Upon deeper investigation, management learned that some
of these unhappy employees were preparing a union-organizing
campaign. Rapid intervention helped resolve the key issues before
things reached that point." (page 168)</p>
</blockquote>
<h3>Data Collection</h3>
<p>It's hard to get people to fill out surveys in the age of survey
fatigue.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Customers already receive too many survey requests, and as NPS
spreads, their tolerance will diminish." (page 238 of 2011 version
of 2006 book)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Reichheld recommends using phone surveys over register receipt surveys
or email surveys.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Phone surveys may not be the right long-term solution for your
firm, but beware of defaulting to the cheapest alternative." (page
237)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Even with the shortest possible surveys, people are just
<a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2016-05-04/tasty-taco-helpful-hygienist-are-all-those-surveys-of-any-use" title="The Inventor of Customer Satisfaction Surveys Is Sick of Them, Too">sick of them</a>, which is a challenge for getting good data.</p>
<hr>
<p>Reichheld is a consultant who focuses on customer loyalty. Cynically,
he wants to be known for "a full-fledged management system with an
ethos that rivals <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Six_Sigma">Six Sigma</a> in power" (front flap) and get his
metric on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balanced_scorecard">balanced scorecards</a>. Less cynically, he really wants
companies to treat everyone well and avoid "bad profits" created by
taking advantage of customers.</p>
<p><img alt="book cover" src="ultimate_cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>Otherwise unrelated quote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"A bounced check cost [Charles Schwab Corporation] 82 cents, but the
firm charged the client $40." (page 128)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200413-ultimate_question_by_reichheld/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200413-ultimate_question_by_reichheld/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Montessori Toddler, by Simone Davies</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>We saw <a href="https://www.workman.com/products/the-montessori-toddler">this book</a> at <a href="https://toddlersonthehill.org/">TOTH</a> and subsequently picked up a copy.
It's a very nice book with lots of good advice for living with
toddlers, and plenty of universally good advice.</p>
<p>I like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Montessori">Montessori</a> in general. I read <em>The Absorbent Mind</em> a long
time ago and recall it fondly. There's room for debate around exactly
how to operationalize it, but the underlying idea is that people are
good and will do well, on the basis of internal motivation, if they're
supported appropriately.</p>
<p>This comparison resonates with me:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"...the children in the [other] school always put up their
hands to ask the teacher if something was on the test. The
Montessori children were used to learning because they loved to do
so, not because they were being tested." (page 231)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The author also draws from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nonviolent_Communication">non-violent communication</a> and there's
an "Instead of This, Say That" section at the back, with
recommendations (like "Instead of blaming others, take
responsibility") that are good regardless of the age of the person
you're speaking with.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="montessori_toddler_cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200322-montessori_toddler/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200322-montessori_toddler/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Zombie Ideas</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<ul><a id="zombie"></a>
</ul>

<h3>What is this?</h3>
<p>Sometimes I put ideas in <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/issues">my blog's GitHub Issues</a> "for later"&#8212;but
then I don't look at them any more. It's an idea graveyard. So this
hits the GitHub API and randomly shows eight old ideas on every page
load. (View source to see code.) Maybe I'll be inspired?</p>
<p>New ideas seem exciting, and urgent things get done urgently. But I do
find myself sometimes looking for something to do (like finding a show
to watch) rather than realizing I could work on one of these old
ideas.</p>
<p>Some ideas got so little attention that I've even forgotten what my
note for the idea means. See also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spaced_repetition">spaced repetition</a>. There's also
some connection here to prioritization, to-do lists, deciding to say
no to an idea, etc...</p>
<p>Amusingly, I'd forgotten that this very idea was <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/issues/164">#164</a> "random idea
refresher" until it came up while I was testing this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"some way of showing you a sample of your own ideas, things to think
about, quotes, etc."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I still think this is a neat idea. For the time being, this page will
replace my usual new browser tab image.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200209-zombie_ideas/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200209-zombie_ideas/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>What If? by Randall Munroe</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I read this after enjoying <a href="/20200101-how_to_by_randall_munroe/">How To</a> by the same author. This one is
more directly from the <a href="https://what-if.xkcd.com/">blog</a>, which I had only read occasionally.
It's laugh-out-loud funny physics nerdery.</p>
<p>Even when it isn't funny, it explains things in ways that provide
quick understanding:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Chemotherapy drugs are blunt instruments. Some are more precisely
targeted than others, but many simply interrupt cell division in
general. The reason that this selectively kills cancer cells,
instead of harming the patient and the cancer equally, is that
cancer cells are dividing all the time, whereas most normal cells
divide only occasionally." (page 134)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>My only gripe is this apparent inconsistency:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Q. How hard would a puck have to be shot to be able to knock the
goalie himself backward into the net? A. This can't really happen."
(page 112)</p>
<p>"If it's going fast enough, a feather can <em>absolutely</em> knock you
over." page 177</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But in general the book seems basically correct in its wild
order-of-magnitude flights of fancy, and it's a darn good time.</p>
<p><img alt="What If? cover" src="what_if_cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200207-what_if_by_randall_munroe/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200207-what_if_by_randall_munroe/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Practical Statistics for Data Scientists, 2nd Edition</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I was happy to do a pre-publication technical review of the upcoming
<a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/practical-statistics-for/9781492072935/">second edition</a> of this fine book by three folks including the
founder of <a href="https://www.statistics.com/">statistics.com</a>. The book has a unique perspective
enlivened by examples and historical detail, which I enjoyed.</p>
<!--
 * Honorarium was $300
 * My notes are in:
     https://bitbucket.org/ajschumacher/vis_book/src/master/stat_for_ds[-personal].md
-->

<p><img alt="cover" src="prac_stat_cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200206-practical_statistics_for_data_scientists_2nd_ed/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200206-practical_statistics_for_data_scientists_2nd_ed/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Three Body Problem (Remembrance of Earth's Past)</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liu_Cixin">Liu Cixin</a>'s popular trilogy is a problematic page-turner. It's
hard sci-fi fascinated with society but culturally backward and
exceptionally pessimistic. It's kind of fun to play what-if with the
author, but these books feel like artifacts of a bad old world.</p>
<p><img alt="trilogy covers" src="trilogy_covers.png"></p>
<p>The main concept of the books' universe is that there's tons of
intelligent life, but life always decides to preemptively annihilate
any other life it can find, and therefore also to hide. This
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Dark_Forest">Dark Forest</a> idea resolves the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fermi_paradox">Fermi paradox</a>. Stephen Hawking
even <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/apr/26/stephen-hawking-issues-warning-on-aliens">co-signs</a>.</p>
<p>Annihilation is typically done by wrecking stars, but also sometimes
by locally reducing the number of spatial dimensions. The universe is
11-dimensional, but war has effectively reduced it to 3D, and most
humans get killed when the solar system is reduced to 2D.</p>
<p>There's a surprising amount of smoking. Two hundred years in the
future, the big advance is that cigarettes are self-lighting. Bad
communication between a father and son is held up as somehow noble.
The character Fraisse is arguably a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magical_Negro">Magical Negro</a>.</p>
<p>The books have a problematic relationship with women. The trilogy
opens with a wife betraying her husband as he's murdered by young
girls in a public display. This couple's daughter goes on to invite
aliens to conquer Earth, like Eve with a backstory.</p>
<p>We meet the protagonist of book two while he's trying to remember the
name of the woman he just slept with. She's immediately killed by an
assassination attempt meant for him. This important man falls in love
with an imaginary woman, until later he describes her and has people
go find a real woman like his imaginary lover, who is brought to live
with him and then marries him and bears him a child.</p>
<p>An initially competent woman is introduced in the third book. She goes
on to allow aliens to conquer Earth because of her "maternal
instinct," and then yet again to doom the Earth further because she
wouldn't let a man do what he wanted.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Twice, she had been placed in a position of authority second only
to God, and both times she had pushed the world into the abyss in
the name of love." (Death's End, page 641)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The books are deeply pessimistic. There's a lot of suicide, including
humanity-wide:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The most surprising aspect of the Earth-Trisolaris Movement was
that so many people had abandoned all hope in human civilization,
hated and were willing to betray their own species, and even
cherished as their highest ideal the elimination of the entire human
race, including themselves and their children." (The Three Body
Problem, page 317)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(There actually is a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voluntary_Human_Extinction_Movement">Voluntary Human Extinction Movement</a>. It is
not very popular.)</p>
<p>When people do want to keep living they very quickly turn on one
another. The zero-sum nature of the universe is an axiom of these
books. A little bit of fun comes out of the explorations of deception
in the face of full-information competition, but it's a sad world.</p>
<p>The first book <a href="http://peterbutler.blog/the-shooter-and-the-farmer/">teases</a> that it might explore fun ideas around
foundations or philosophy, but there's no real payoff to these plot
directions. It feels like something from an earlier draft that never
got edited out.</p>
<p>The first book is a long introduction to the trilogy. The backdrop of
the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cultural_Revolution">Cultural Revolution</a> is interesting for the unfamiliar, but
what I most enjoyed hearing from Liu was his sci-fi speculation, and
that really only gets rolling in book two.</p>
<p>I like science and all, but I didn't need all the pro-STEM pandering,
much less the anti-environmentalism. (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silent_Spring">Silent Spring</a> helps inspire
a desire to kill all humans, for example.)</p>
<p>I liked Ken Liu's translation of the first and third books, and his
brief notes. He says that translation shouldn't read as if it was
originally written in the target language, which I thought was
interesting. The second book's translator may have taken Ken's advice
too far, stilting the dialogue and having people refer to one another
as "doctor" far too much.</p>
<p>The Remembrance of Earth's Past is unique to me in that while I found
it engrossing, I can't really recommend it. Read <a href="/20180723-broken_earth_trilogy/">The Broken Earth</a>
instead.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The era for humanity's degenerate freedom is over. If you want to
survive here, you must relearn collectivism and retrieve the dignity
of your race!" (Death's End, page 235)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200124-three_body_problem_remembrance_of_earths_past/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200124-three_body_problem_remembrance_of_earths_past/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Predicting the Future from 2020</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>What's going to happen in the future? I will tell you. The future will
be basically like now, but some things will be slightly better, and
some things will be slightly worse.</p>
<h3>By 2021</h3>
<ul>
<li>Joe Biden becomes Democratic candidate for US presidency.</li>
<li>Democratic candidate wins US presidency.</li>
<li>At least one hurricane leads to visit by US president.</li>
<li>Foreign powers seek to influence US citizens via the internet, but
   this is hard to verify.</li>
<li>None of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facebook,_Apple,_Amazon,_Netflix_and_Google">FAANG</a> are split up by government intervention.</li>
<li>S&amp;P 500 closes below 3,000.</li>
</ul>
<h3>By 2025</h3>
<ul>
<li>Ruth Bader Ginsberg is dead.</li>
<li>At least one merger of streaming TV offerings.</li>
<li>Chinese Communist Party represented in Hong Kong government.</li>
<li>The "transformer" family of neural network architectures is
   generalized for arbitrary inputs (not just sequences) and continues
   to be interesting.</li>
<li>There is no car that I can buy and have drive itself curb-to-curb
   across town.</li>
<li>S&amp;P 500 closes above 3,500.</li>
</ul>
<h3>By 2030</h3>
<ul>
<li>Donald Trump is dead.</li>
<li>Russia is bigger (by territory).</li>
<li>There is at least one new US law with ID requirements for posting
   online.</li>
<li>US minimum wage at least 15 USD/hour.</li>
<li>AI development has a clearer split between research and
   application: The forefronts of research are not immediately
   applicable to industry.</li>
<li>S&amp;P 500 closes above 4,000.</li>
</ul>
<h3>By 2040</h3>
<ul>
<li>At least one of DC and Puerto Rico have at least one full voting US
   senator.</li>
<li>Inflation found to be related to minimum wage: raising minimum wage
   does not increase purchasing power of minimum-wage workers.</li>
<li>The majority of new cars sold are electric.</li>
<li>Product delivery to homes (like Amazon) as a utility, like
   electricity.</li>
<li>US government-subsidized program to encourage people to move to
   inland cities.</li>
<li>S&amp;P 500 closes above 8,000.</li>
</ul>
<p>General trends: Climate continues to change. Unemployment gets worse
not because companies don't want to hire but because they can't find
employees with positive marginal value. Rich continue to get richer
while the poor are largely left behind. Some governments sell the poor
totalitarianism as populism while others move toward socialism.
Warfare is as targeted as possible; assassinations become more common.
International psyops are generally opposed to wealth redistribution.</p>
<hr>
<p>In thinking about these predictions, it's striking how much more
significant my personal choices generally are (for me) than things
that happen in the world. I'm very fortunate that even the biggest
things in the news don't affect me very much. I've never been forced
to migrate anywhere, for example, and I don't expect to be.</p>
<p>Most big changes in my life are independent of the news. Ten years ago
I lived in Korea, five years ago I lived in New York, now I live in
DC. For most of the last ten years I was a childless single renter,
and now I'm a married homeowner with a daughter.</p>
<p>Most technology doesn't change terribly much. Ten years ago, I had an
iPhone, I searched on Google, I translated things with Google
Translate, and I programmed with Python. I drive a hybrid gas/electric
car that's over ten years old. All these technologies are better today
than they used to be, but they aren't fundamentally new.</p>
<p>One technology that has seen dramatic change over the last ten years
is deep learning. It's been really neat to be a small part of that. I
wonder what technology might be the equivalent in the next decade. I
suspect it isn't going to be any of the buzz words (VR, AR, crypto,
etc.). Maybe something biological?</p>
<hr>
<p>I'm curious to hear predictions from others, and I look forward to
reflecting on all these predictions in the future!</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200112-predicting_the_future_from_2020/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200112-predicting_the_future_from_2020/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How To, by Randall Munroe</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>"<a href="https://xkcd.com/how-to/">How To</a>" is essentially more "What If?" (<a href="https://what-if.xkcd.com/">blog</a>/<a href="https://store.xkcd.com/pages/if-you-re-looking-for-the-what-if-book">book</a>). It's an excuse for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Randall_Munroe">Munroe</a> to talk about interesting things, and it's great. Here are some things I thought were neat:</p>
<p>In "How to Keep Your House from Moving," I learned that you really can't, because of tectonic plates. Keeping track of where things are is surprisingly hard! If you use latitude and longitude, your location will become incorrect as plates move. This is part of why different localities use their own local coordinate systems, which has frustrated me in the past in part because I didn't see any reason for them to do that.</p>
<p>In "How to Play Tag," I learned that Usain Bolt's agent told The New Yorker that Bolt has never run a mile. That's Munroe's careful phrasing, which I appreciate, but it's also just interesting to think about that level of specialization. I tend to value generalization, or cross-training, but it may not always be necessary.</p>
<p>In "How to Power Your House (On Earth)," I learned that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panicum_virgatum">switchgrass</a> is a really cool plant, and that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Betz%27s_law">Betz's law</a> says that wind turbines can't capture more than 16/27 of wind energy because the wind has to keep moving or the turbine won't keep working.</p>
<p>On page 274 it says that UTC is "from its French acronym," which isn't quite right, and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coordinated_Universal_Time#Etymology">real story</a> is much more fun. But in general the book seems basically correct in its wild order-of-magnitude flights of fancy, and it's a darn good time.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="how_to_cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200101-how_to_by_randall_munroe/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200101-how_to_by_randall_munroe/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Look Look Look, by Callista Buchen</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This short <a href="https://www.blacklawrence.com/look-look-look/">book</a> of prose poems is an intensely personal,
frequently painful look at the author's experiences of motherhood. I'm
no expert in poetry, but it seems like a success.</p>
<p>There are five untitled parts, the first three of which correspond to
periods around the birth of a first child, then the loss before birth
of a child, and then the birth of a second child. The last two parts
might be less obviously demarcated subsequent periods or aspects. None
of the parts seem to have been particularly easy for the author.</p>
<p>One short sentence, "We do the research," stuck out to me as
emblematic of the modern experience of educated people approaching the
enigmatic corporeal realities of fertility.</p>
<p>The author and her husband and I were high school classmates, which
adds something. Reading the poem "Sadness" on page 49, there's the
abstract author, there are the people I went to school with, and
there's the recasting with my family and others. It's also interesting
to see the language change, becoming more direct, at the beginning of
the third part&#8212;a deliberate device, or the unconscious development of
the author over time?</p>
<p>It's like reading a diary, but everyone has been invited to look,
look, look.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="look_look_look.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20191229-look_look_look_by_callista_buchen/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20191229-look_look_look_by_callista_buchen/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Open Borders, by Caplan and Weinersmith</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I'd heard about some of <a href="http://www.bcaplan.com/">Caplan</a>'s books, but I hadn't read any
until the guy who does <a href="http://smbc-comics.com/">SMBC</a> advertised the one he worked with
Caplan on. It's a comic book that reads in an evening. I'm glad it's
out there, but I'm not sure the book will change many minds.</p>
<p>The first chapter is called "Global Apartheid," which seems to be
typical of Caplan's flare for the provocative. I don't think the
current system of national borders is quite the same as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apartheid">apartheid</a>.
I didn't think it was a good choice to start the book with this
heading, which risks destroying the appearance of arguing in good
faith.</p>
<p>The comic medium can probably be persuasive, but this book sometimes
prioritizes cartoon over argument. For example, on page 34 a central
result from <a href="https://pubs.aeaweb.org/doi/pdfplus/10.1257/jep.25.3.83">a paper by Clemens</a> is mentioned, and the next four
pages illustrate the largeness of an amount of money, while I still
wasn't convinced about how the result was obtained.</p>
<p>It sometimes seems that Caplan isn't aware of how he might sound to
readers. On page 36:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Open borders isn't 'trickle-down economics.' It's Niagara Falls
economics!"</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Caplan is pictured going over Niagara Falls in an open barrel. Is this
supposed to be a good thing? If you think trickle-down economics is a
fraud, is this larger version a bigger fraud? The comparison and
imagery are not effective.</p>
<p>On page 39, Caplan jokes (?) that if not for borders being relatively
open for academics, he would work at Harvard rather than George Mason
University. This suggests a "yes, some people won't get their
preferred jobs" discussion, which isn't addressed.</p>
<p>I was hoping to find a compelling book that argues strongly for open
borders. This one does introduce a lot of arguments, and it may even
be correct throughout, but the overall effect is not as coherent and
convincing as I had hoped it would be.</p>
<p><img alt="Open Borders (cover)" src="open_borders.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20191109-open_borders_by_caplan_and_weinersmith/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20191109-open_borders_by_caplan_and_weinersmith/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2019 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Accelerando, by Stross</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accelerando">Accelerando</a> was referenced in <a href="https://jack-clark.net/2019/10/21/import-ai-169-multi-task-testing-for-vision-floating-drones-could-build-communications-networks-in-the-future-medical-tech-gets-fda-approval/">Issue 169</a> of the <a href="https://jack-clark.net/about/">Import AI</a>
newsletter. The Accelerando ebook is available <a href="https://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/fiction/accelerando/accelerando-intro.html">for free</a>, along
with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Stross">the author</a>'s charming story of how the book came to be.
Accelerando is a reasonably fun, wacky romp through the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_singularity">technological singularity</a>.</p>
<p>Bits of the story, such as the space lobster AI, have an absurdist
element along the lines of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hitchhiker%27s_Guide_to_the_Galaxy">Hitchhiker's Guide</a>. A difference is
that Accelerando has more connections to actual science and
technology: different kinds of reminders of how strange reality can
be.</p>
<p>The book was born in the late 90s, published as short stories, and
finally released as a novel in 2005. Now, after the rise and
(arguable) fall of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_Glass">Google Glass</a>, among other things, it's
interesting to consider how progress toward this imagining of the
singularity is going.</p>
<p>The likes of <a href="https://deepmind.com/">DeepMind</a> and <a href="https://openai.com/">OpenAI</a> keep announcing new results,
but the last 5% of the driverless car problem still seems hard.
Language models are good enough to <a href="https://www.blog.google/products/search/search-language-understanding-bert/">improve Google search</a>, but
don't really seem to be moving toward <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_general_intelligence">AGI</a>. Some kind of progress
is being made, but it isn't always clear how much any particular
advance moves us toward specific long-term goals.</p>
<p>Is technology making people more productive? In the rich world, it
sometimes feels like it might be doing the opposite, on average.
Fiction loves a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_man_theory">great personality</a>, but I can't really see
canonizing folks who are automating content farms, for example.</p>
<p>The book has dystopian elements, perhaps from the over-association of
tech startup culture and singularity theorizing. Corporate structures
become sentient. Legal battles and financial concerns still command a
surprising amount of attention in the post-scarcity future of
Accelerando.</p>
<p>Also typical of fiction, the book keeps you wondering what's going to
happen. Somewhat atypically, the premise is that the world changes so
much that humans can't understand it any more, so by definition the
book can't deliver a satisfying conclusion, in some respects.</p>
<p>The characters have more sexuality than personality, but if you can
ignore that and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nQHBAdShgYI">the transporter problem</a> you get to upload your
brain to a tiny <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solar_sail">light sail</a> starship and watch a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dyson_sphere">Dyson sphere</a>
get built. Could be worse.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="accelerando_cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20191108-accelerando_by_stross/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20191108-accelerando_by_stross/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2019 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Q-Learning Tic-Tac-Toe, Briefly</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tic-tac-toe">Tic-tac-toe</a> doesn't call for <a href="/20171114-deep_rl/">reinforcement learning</a>, except as
an exercise or illustration. Recently, I saw several examples
implementing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Q-learning">Q-learning</a>, all of which were rather long. I thought
I'd give tic-tac-toe with Q-learning a <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/blob/master/20191103-q_learning_tic_tac_toe_briefly/q_learning_tic_tac_toe.ipynb">try</a> myself, using Python
and TensorFlow, aiming for brevity.</p>
<p>The board is represented with a matrix, where zero means empty.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">def new_board(size):
    return np.zeros(shape=(size, size))</code></pre>

<p>Moves are represented by their coordinates, like <code>[0, 0]</code> for the
upper left.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">def available_moves(board):
    return np.argwhere(board == 0)</code></pre>

<p>The first player is <code>+1</code> and the second player is <code>-1</code>, so having
three in a row means getting a row, column, or diagonal to sum to <code>+3</code>
or <code>-3</code>, respectively.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">def check_game_end(board):
    best = max(list(board.sum(axis=0)) +    # columns
               list(board.sum(axis=1)) +    # rows
               [board.trace()] +            # main diagonal
               [np.fliplr(board).trace()],  # other diagonal
               key=abs)
    if abs(best) == board.shape[0]:  # assumes square board
        return np.sign(best)  # winning player, +1 or -1
    if available_moves(board).size == 0:
        return 0  # a draw (otherwise, return None by default)</code></pre>

<p>Q-learning will require some state, so a player will be an object with
a <code>move</code> method that takes a board and returns the coordinates of the
chosen move. Here's a random player:</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">class RandomPlayer(Player):
    def move(self, board):
        return random.choice(available_moves(board))</code></pre>

<p>This is sufficient for the game loop, starting from any initial board:</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">def play(board, player_objs):
    player = +1
    game_end = check_game_end(board)
    while game_end is None:
        move = player_objs[player].move(board)
        board[tuple(move)] = player
        game_end = check_game_end(board)
        player *= -1  # switch players
    return game_end</code></pre>

<p>So this plays out a game between two random players and gives the
result:</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">play(new_board(3), {+1: RandomPlayer(), -1: RandomPlayer()})</code></pre>

<p>Playing out 10,000 games, it's clear that the first random player is
more likely to win, and also that results can vary a good deal even
when averaging over 500 games.</p>
<p><img alt="3x3 tic-tac-toe, two random players" src="img/3x3random-random.png"></p>
<p>Here's a boring player that chooses the first available move from left
to right, top to bottom:</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">class BoringPlayer(Player):
    def move(self, board):
        return available_moves(board)[0]</code></pre>

<p>Games between boring players always end the same way. The comparison
with the random player is more interesting. This table give results
for 10,000 games per row:</p>
<pre><code>| Size | First Player | Second Player | Draw |
|------|--------------|---------------|------|
| 3x3  | Random: 59%  | Random: 29%   | 12%  |
| 3x3  | Boring: 78%  | Random: 18%   |  4%  |
| 3x3  | Random: 52%  | Boring: 44%   |  4%  |</code></pre>

<p>The boring player does better than a random player whether it plays
first or second. Now we have multiple "baselines." A learning agent
should do better than the baselines.</p>
<p>The Q-learning player starts with a neural network that takes a board
as input and produces an estimate of how good each move is from that
position: Q-values.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">class Agent(Player):
    def __init__(self, size):
        self.size = size
        self.model = tf.keras.Sequential()
        self.model.add(tf.keras.layers.Dense(size**2))
        self.model.compile(optimizer='sgd', loss='mean_squared_error')</code></pre>

<p>A couple helper methods make the interface nicer for using and
training the neural net. (There may be a better way of achieving
this.)</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">    def predict_q(self, board):
        return self.model.predict(
            np.array([board.ravel()])).reshape(self.size, self.size)

    def fit_q(self, board, q_values):
        self.model.fit(
            np.array([board.ravel()]), np.array([q_values.ravel()]), verbose=0)</code></pre>

<p>The Q-learning agent preserves some history, which is reset when a new
game starts.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">    def new_game(self):
        self.last_move = None
        self.board_history = []
        self.q_history = []</code></pre>

<p>The <code>move</code> method uses the Q-network to choose the best available move
and then calls the <code>reward</code> method to operationalize Q-learning's
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bellman_equation#The_Bellman_equation">Bellman equation</a>.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">    def move(self, board):
        q_values = self.predict_q(board)
        temp_q = q_values.copy()
        temp_q[board != 0] = temp_q.min() - 1  # no illegal moves
        move = np.unravel_index(np.argmax(temp_q), board.shape)
        value = temp_q.max()
        if self.last_move is not None:
            self.reward(value)
        self.board_history.append(board.copy())
        self.q_history.append(q_values)
        self.last_move = move
        return move</code></pre>

<p>The <code>reward</code> method trains the Q-network, updating a previous estimate
of Q-values with a new estimate for the last chosen move.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">    def reward(self, reward_value):
        new_q = self.q_history[-1].copy()
        new_q[self.last_move] = reward_value
        self.fit_q(self.board_history[-1], new_q)</code></pre>

<p>Using a <code>play</code> function that resets games and delivers a reward of
<code>+1</code> for wins and <code>-1</code> for losses and draws (see the full
<a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/blob/master/20191103-q_learning_tic_tac_toe_briefly/q_learning_tic_tac_toe.ipynb">notebook</a>), a Q-learning agent plays a random agent:</p>
<p><img alt="3x3 tic-tac-toe, q-learning vs. random player" src="img/3x3qlearn-random.png"></p>
<p>The Q-learning player quickly achieves much stronger play than the
baselines.</p>
<pre><code>| Size | First Player | Second Player | Draw |
|------|--------------|---------------|------|
| 3x3  | Random:  59% | Random:  29%  | 12%  |
| 3x3  | Boring:  78% | Random:  18%  |  4%  |
| 3x3  | Random:  52% | Boring:  44%  |  4%  |
| 3x3  | Q-Learn: 93% | Random:   6%  |  1%  |
| 3x3  | Random:  21% | Q-Learn: 78%  |  1%  |</code></pre>

<p>(For Q-learning players, they play 10,000 games while learning and
then another 10,000 games while frozen to evaluate their performance
level after learning, which is what's shown in the table.)</p>
<p>And that's it! Tic-tac-toe with a Q-learning agent, comfortably under
100 lines of code.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Ideas for doing more</h3>
<ul>
<li>The Q-learning player didn't achieve a "perfect" strategy in which
   it never loses. Why not? Can you fix it? Further ideas below may
   contribute to a solution.</li>
<li>You can write your own perfect tic-tac-toe player, or use a package
   like <a href="https://github.com/dwayne/xo-python">xo</a>. How does the Q-learning player do against a perfect
   player?</li>
<li>For tic-tac-toe, it's also possible to implement tabular
   Q-learning: a table keeps track of the estimated Q-value for every
   board state/action combination. How does this compare to the neural
   net approach here, in terms of game performance, sample efficiency,
   and space/time/compute complexity? The network architecture here
   has just 90 parameters, which is a good deal less space than is
   needed for a full table. What are the trade-offs? (Thanks to Chris
   Marciniak for suggesting this topic.)</li>
<li>The initialization of the network and the play of the random
   opponent vary from run to run. How consistent are results? How do
   they vary? What source of randomness matters more?</li>
<li>How can you analyze and describe the "strategies" that the system
   learns? How much do these vary from run to run, or when varying
   other things?</li>
<li>Draws require nine moves, but it's possible to win in five. How
   does game length vary by player strategy and over the course of
   training the Q-learning player?</li>
<li>The Q-learning algorithm here is simplified, with no reward decay,
   for example. Can you re-complicate the algorithm and perhaps
   achieve shorter game lengths?</li>
<li>There is no explicit exploration mechanism in the Q-learning
   algorithm here. Can you add one and improve performance?</li>
<li>What happens when the Q-learning player plays against the boring
   player, and what does this suggest?</li>
<li>What happens when a Q-learning player plays against one type of
   player, and then faces a different player? How can this vary and
   what does it suggest?</li>
<li>None of the players in these implementations are ever told which
   player they are, and none of them explicitly work it out for
   themselves, though this is possible. How does a Q-learning player
   that has played as first player do when made to play as second
   player instead? Can you improve this?</li>
<li>How effective is self-play (Q-learning player vs. another
   Q-learning player)?</li>
<li>Can you quantify the sample efficiency of the Q-learning algorithm,
   which should capture how many games or moves the algorithm needs to
   learn a good strategy?</li>
<li>There are lots of enhancements to Q-learning, for example
   <a href="https://www.cs.toronto.edu/~vmnih/docs/dqn.PDF">experience replay</a>. Can you improve sample efficiency using such
   a mechanism?</li>
<li>There are symmetries in the tic-tac-toe board; can you take
   advantage of these?</li>
<li>The neural network used here is very simple. It is not at all
   "deep," for example. Does a more sophisticated network architecture
   give better results?<ul>
<li>Convolutional filters are useful in neural networks for
   computer vision. Can this kind of domain-specific approach
   inform an architecture design specialized for tic-tac-toe?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The form of the input to the neural network here has only nine
   elements, which can each be positive or negative. Especially with a
   simple network architecture, this may not be ideal. (For example,
   consider how the current setup manifests the
   <a href="http://www.ece.utep.edu/research/webfuzzy/docs/kk-thesis/kk-thesis-html/node19.html">exclusive or (XOR) problem</a>.) What other board representations
   can you use as input to the neural net? Do some work better than
   others?</li>
<li>Lots of defaults are used in the implementation here, for example
   for the neural network's learning rate. Can you find better values?</li>
<li>The rewards for a loss and a tie are both <code>-1</code> in the
   implementation here. What happens when ties aren't as bad as
   losses? Is zero a good reward for a tie?</li>
<li>The code shown here aims to be brief. Is this good or bad for
   readability, maintainability, and extensibility? Are other
   characteristics also important? How can you improve the code?</li>
<li>Experiment with different board sizes:</li>
</ul>
<pre><code>| Size | First Player | Second Player | Draw |
|------|--------------|---------------|------|
| 3x3  | Random: 59%  | Random: 29%   | 12%  |
| 4x4  | Random: 31%  | Random: 27%   | 42%  |
| 5x5  | Random: 25%  | Random: 15%   | 60%  |</code></pre>

<p>As the board gets bigger, the advantage of going first decreases and
the probability of a draw goes up considerably.</p>
<p>It also takes a good deal more games to learn a good strategy:</p>
<p><img alt="3x3 tic-tac-toe, q-learning vs. random player" src="img/5x5qlearn-random.png"></p>
<p>For the implementations here, some results are as follows:</p>
<pre><code>| Size | First Player | Second Player | Draw |
|------|--------------|---------------|------|
| 4x4  | Random:  31% | Random:  27%  | 42%  |
| 4x4  | Q-Learn: 83% | Random:  10%  |  7%  |
| 4x4  | Random:  11% | Q-Learn: 80%  |  9%  |
| 5x5  | Random:  25% | Random:  15%  | 60%  |
| 5x5  | Q-Learn: 79% | Random:   5%  | 16%  |
| 5x5  | Random:  18% | Q-Learn: 53%  | 29%  |</code></pre>

<p>What is optimal for these larger boards? How well can you do? At what
point is a Q-learning approach more effective (considering the trade
with compute time) than exhaustive minimax search, if ever?</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20191103-q_learning_tic_tac_toe_briefly/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20191103-q_learning_tic_tac_toe_briefly/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Influence, by Cialdini</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Influence:_Science_and_Practice">Influence: Science and Practice</a> is a sort of cross between <a href="/2011/03/05/how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people/">How to Win Friends and Influence People</a> and <a href="/2011/12/17/selections-from-and-thoughts-on/">Thinking, Fast and Slow</a>. Originally published well before Kahneman's popular book, it cites some of his earlier work. <em>Influence</em> describes six principles used by "compliance professionals," a category rather broader than "marketers."</p>
<ol>
<li>Reciprocation</li>
<li>Commitment/Consistency</li>
<li>Social proof</li>
<li>Liking</li>
<li>Authority</li>
<li>Scarcity</li>
</ol>
<p>I believe it was this book that popularized the term "social proof"&#8212;<em>Influence</em> has been influential. I heard about the book in <a href="/20190824-100_startup/">The $100 Startup</a>.</p>
<p>The tone can be militant. The principles are called "weapons of influence" and the examples include the Jonestown Massacre and techniques used on American prisoners during the Korean War. Referring to "boycott, threat, confrontation, censure, tirade, nearly anything to retaliate," Cialdini says "I don't consider myself pugnacious by nature, but I actively advocate such beligerent actions because in a way I am at war with the exploiters."</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I have recently become impressed by evidence suggesting that the
form and pace of modern life is not allowing us to make fully
thoughtful decisions, even on many personally relevant topics. That
is, sometimes the issues may be so complicated, the time so tight,
the distractions so intrusive, the emotional arousal so strong, or
the mental fatigue so deep that we are in no cognitive condition to
operate mindfully.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Largely a collection of anecdotes and research results presented as stories, <em>Influence</em> plays hard into the tendency of readers to reason from the specific to the general. This includes at least one example I know to be at least partially debunked in connection with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murder_of_Kitty_Genovese">the bystander effect</a>.</p>
<p>In connection with the "Liking" principle, I was interested to learn something I hadn't been aware of previously about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jigsaw_(teaching_technique)">jigsaw</a> teaching technique: that it was designed "to help weaken racial cliques in forcibly integrated schools." I feel like I should have known that earlier!</p>
<p>One other fun connection was to the machine learning idea of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overfitting">overfitting</a>. Kahneman's automatic "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow#Two_systems">system one</a>" thinking is helpful but can lead to errors, often because it focuses on just one feature of a situation. Biological intelligence is sometimes held up as not having any drawbacks of ML, but it's interesting to draw this parallel.</p>
<p>This book was first published in 1984. I read the fifth edition, which has been updated so that on page 219 there's a picture of an Apple store with a caption about "the china department of Harrod's." <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Cialdini">Cialdini</a> is 74 now. His book has been successful.</p>
<p><img alt="Influence cover" src="influence.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20191009-influence_by_cialdini/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20191009-influence_by_cialdini/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2019 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>How to be Miserable, by Paterson</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>CGP Grey recommended this <a href="https://www.newharbinger.com/how-be-miserable">book</a> in his <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LO1mTELoj6o">video</a> highlighting seven
of its "40 strategies you already use" to increase misery. It's a fun,
quick read, during which occasionally some things may hit close to
home and force you to remind yourself that the advice is deliberately
bad. I especially liked "Lesson 20: Work Endlessly on Your
Self-Esteem."</p>
<hr>
<h3>Lesson 20: Work Endlessly on Your Self-Esteem</h3>
<p>Do you have a cat? If so, does it seem to think well of itself, or
does it appear to slink around in deep shame at being an inferior sort
of feline?</p>
<p>Most people sense that the cats they know have perfectly high
self-esteem&#8288;&#8212;despite never having had psychotherapy, attending no
esteem-building workshops, and reading very few self-help books. How
do they do it?</p>
<p>We live in a culture with a deep and abiding faith in the concept of
self-esteem. To follow this particular path downward, all you have to
do is go along with the crowd. Like them, view self-esteem as
something that you are born without and must build up, brick by brick,
into a tall and sturdy structure. Assume that self-esteem is something
separate from confidence in your ability to perform any particular
task, like juggling or changing the oil in your car. This makes it
vague and amorphous enough that constructing it becomes a futile&#8288;&#8212;and
thus misery-inducing&#8288;&#8212;effort.</p>
<p>But wait. Isn't self-esteem real? You've been taught about it since
birth. It can't possibly be just another Easter Bunny, can it?</p>
<p>Let's find out. Imagine a person with terrible self-esteem visiting
the bank and then walking to a caf&#233; for lunch. What's he thinking
about?</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>I probably looked like an idiot when I dropped my pen back there,
and the teller could see my bank balance&#8212;she probably thought I'm a
complete failure. Even now, these people on the sidewalk can see
what a loser I am, and my hair is sticking up everywhere. When I get
lunch, I'll probably spill it on myself and look even worse.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sound plausible?</p>
<p>Now imagine a person with great self-esteem doing the same thing.
What's he thinking about?</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Wow, I really impressed them all at the bank back there&#8212;when I bent
over to pick up my pen they could see how toned my rear end is,
after all that work at the gym, and my balance probably made the
teller drool. Look at all these lucky people sharing the sidewalk
with me, envying me for my great hair. And when I get to the caf&#233;,
they'll put me at the table in the front window to attract other
customers. Hey, I know: let me recite positive affirmations to
myself on the way.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>You think?</p>
<p>Or is he more likely to be wondering, <em>Do I want the soup or just a
chicken sandwich?</em></p>
<p>The truth is, people with good self-esteem are not constantly
evaluating themselves. It's the ones without it who do this. Our
culture teaches us that having self-esteem is an active process of
building ourselves up. It isn't. Cats, three-year-olds, and adults
with self-esteem aren't doing much of anything&#8212;they're just focused on
the task at hand.</p>
<p>The active process is to have <em>low</em> self-esteem, to be constantly
tearing ourselves down. When we wake up in the morning, before our
mind starts going, our self-esteem is fine. We only begin feeling
inadequate when we start rehearsing the negative story that we tell
ourselves. By focusing on self-esteem, we cleverly divert attention
from the real issue.</p>
<p>Self-esteem, in other words, <em>does not exist.</em> Self-loathing, however,
is very real.</p>
<p>In the classic French film <em>Jean de Florette,</em> townspeople in Provence
conspire to trick a man out of the property he has inherited by
capping the farm's only source of water, thus starving his crops and
ensuring his downfall. Jean strives mightily to haul water to the
farm, unaware that it already has an inexhaustible supply just
underground.</p>
<p>Similarly, believers in self-esteem strive to import a sense of
self-worth, neglecting the fact that no such efforts are really
necessary: all they need to do is remove the plug that prevents
self-worth from flowing. That plug is the relentless self-criticism in
which they engage.</p>
<p>Your mission, then, is to affirm your faith in the concept of
self-esteem. Strive to build it up within yourself. Attend workshop
after workshop, recite affirmations, invite friends and therapists to
exalt your achievements. In doing so, you will reinforce both the
hidden conviction that there is much to make up for and the
corresponding belief in your inherent faultiness.</p>
<p>Sisyphus found an ideal path to misery: endlessly rolling a stone up a
hill, only to have it repeatedly escape his grasp and tumble to the
bottom. Trying to create self-esteem is like trying to construct a
ladder out of water. Futility leads to unhappiness, and seeing
yourself as lacking something that does not actually exist is a
perfect example.</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="How to be Miserable (cover)" src="miserable_cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20191005-how_to_be_miserable/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20191005-how_to_be_miserable/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2019 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The AWK Programming Language</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The 1988 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_AWK_Programming_Language">book</a> on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AWK"><code>awk</code></a> by Aho, Weinberger, and Kernighan is as good as everyone says, and I will highly recommend it for programmers and data science folks.</p>
<p>Specialized tools <a href="/2013/05/21/command-line-data-manipulation/">like <code>cut</code> and <code>bc</code></a> handle many simple tasks, and general languages like Python can do pretty complicated things. For a long time I avoided properly learning <code>awk</code>, perhaps because I didn't understand that it fills such a useful space between those two extremes, and that the learning curve is really reasonable.</p>
<p>Awk is good at processing lines of delimited text quickly and easily, with defaults that are often convenient. For example, here's adding a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Body_mass_index">BMI</a> column to <a href="biostats.csv">this file</a> I <a href="https://people.sc.fsu.edu/~jburkardt/data/csv/csv.html">found</a>:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">cat biostats.csv | awk -F, 'NR == 1 {print $0, ",BMI"} \
                            NR &gt; 1 {print $0, "," ($5/2.205) / ($4/39.37)^2}'</code></pre>

<p>That would probably take more effort with most other tools.</p>
<p>Unfortunately <code>awk</code> doesn't make it very easy to deal with some complications that can show up in CSV (quoting, newlines inside fields, etc.). A Python project called <a href="https://github.com/alecthomas/pawk"><code>pawk</code></a> looks like it could be the answer, if you don't mind installing it and using Python syntax.</p>
<p>Here's the conclusion from the book:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Awk is not a solution to every programming problem, but it's an
indispensible part of a programmer's toolbox, especially on Unix,
where easy connection of tools is a way of life. Although the larger
examples in the book might give a different impression, most awk
programs are short and simple and do tasks the language was
originally meant for: counting things, converting data from one form
to another, adding up numbers, extracting information for reports.</p>
<p>For tasks like these, where program development time is more
important than run time, awk is hard to beat. The implicit input
loop and the pattern-action paradigm simplify and often entirely
eliminate control flow. Field splitting parses the most common forms
of input, while numbers and strings and the coercions between them
handle the most common data types. Associative arrays provide both
conventional array storage and the much richer possibilities of
arbitrary subscripts. Regular expressions are a uniform notation for
describing patterns of text. Default initialization and the absence
of declarations shorten programs.</p>
<p>What we did not anticipate were the less conventional applications.
For example, the transition from "not programming" to "programming"
is quite gradual: the absence of the syntactic baggage of
conventional languages like C or Pascal makes awk easy enough to
learn that it has been the first language for a surprising number of
people.</p>
<p>The features added in 1985, especially the ability to define
functions, have led to a variety of unexpected applications, like
small database systems and compilers for little languages. In many
cases, awk is used for a prototype, an experiment to demonstrate
feasibility and to play with features and user interfaces, although
sometimes the awk program remains the production version. Awk has
even been used for software engineering courses, because it's
possible to experiment with designs much more readily than with
larger languages.</p>
<p>Of course, one must be wary of going too far &#8212; any tool can be
pushed beyond its limits &#8212; but many people have found awk to be
valuable for a wide range of problems. We hope we have suggested
ways in which awk might be useful to you as well.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>They take <code>awk</code> pretty far in the book, and it's delightful to see, even if you only end up using <code>awk</code> for simpler things like my example above.</p>
<p><img alt="AWK book cover" src="awk_cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20190901-awk_programming_language/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20190901-awk_programming_language/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
