<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>Try HoloViz for Python plotting</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Yang <a href="https://sophiamyang.github.io/DS/visualization/holoviz/holoviz.html" title="Visualization and Interactive Dashboard in Python">inspired</a> me to check out <a href="https://holoviz.org/" title="High-level tools to simplify visualization in Python">HoloViz</a>, which makes it easy,
among other things, to do interactive scatterplots in Jupyter
Notebooks—and stick them in any HTML!</p>
<p><link rel="stylesheet" href="https://unpkg.com/@holoviz/panel@0.12.5/dist/css/alerts.css" type="text/css">
<link rel="stylesheet" href="https://unpkg.com/@holoviz/panel@0.12.5/dist/css/card.css" type="text/css">
<link rel="stylesheet" href="https://unpkg.com/@holoviz/panel@0.12.5/dist/css/widgets.css" type="text/css">
<link rel="stylesheet" href="https://unpkg.com/@holoviz/panel@0.12.5/dist/css/markdown.css" type="text/css">
<link rel="stylesheet" href="https://unpkg.com/@holoviz/panel@0.12.5/dist/css/json.css" type="text/css">
<link rel="stylesheet" href="https://unpkg.com/@holoviz/panel@0.12.5/dist/css/loading.css" type="text/css">
<link rel="stylesheet" href="https://unpkg.com/@holoviz/panel@0.12.5/dist/css/dataframe.css" type="text/css"></p>
<style>
                    .bk.pn-loading.arcs:before {
                      background-image: url("data:image/svg+xml;base64,PHN2ZyB4bWxucz0iaHR0cDovL3d3dy53My5vcmcvMjAwMC9zdmciIHhtbG5zOnhsaW5rPSJodHRwOi8vd3d3LnczLm9yZy8xOTk5L3hsaW5rIiBzdHlsZT0ibWFyZ2luOiBhdXRvOyBiYWNrZ3JvdW5kOiBub25lOyBkaXNwbGF5OiBibG9jazsgc2hhcGUtcmVuZGVyaW5nOiBhdXRvOyIgdmlld0JveD0iMCAwIDEwMCAxMDAiIHByZXNlcnZlQXNwZWN0UmF0aW89InhNaWRZTWlkIj4gIDxjaXJjbGUgY3g9IjUwIiBjeT0iNTAiIHI9IjMyIiBzdHJva2Utd2lkdGg9IjgiIHN0cm9rZT0iI2MzYzNjMyIgc3Ryb2tlLWRhc2hhcnJheT0iNTAuMjY1NDgyNDU3NDM2NjkgNTAuMjY1NDgyNDU3NDM2NjkiIGZpbGw9Im5vbmUiIHN0cm9rZS1saW5lY2FwPSJyb3VuZCI+ICAgIDxhbmltYXRlVHJhbnNmb3JtIGF0dHJpYnV0ZU5hbWU9InRyYW5zZm9ybSIgdHlwZT0icm90YXRlIiByZXBlYXRDb3VudD0iaW5kZWZpbml0ZSIgZHVyPSIxcyIga2V5VGltZXM9IjA7MSIgdmFsdWVzPSIwIDUwIDUwOzM2MCA1MCA1MCI+PC9hbmltYXRlVHJhbnNmb3JtPiAgPC9jaXJjbGU+PC9zdmc+");
                      max-height: 400px;
                    }
</style>

<div class="bk-root" id="7b0543dc-c84e-416d-896c-1741cbecf45a" data-root-id="3831"></div>

<p>I've wanted this to be standard functionality for a long time; six
years ago I briefly started a <a href="/20150119-gog_a_separate_layer_for_visualization/" title="gog: a separate layer for visualization">project</a> that included it in its
proof of concept, as in this screenshot:</p>
<p><img alt="gog screenshot" src="gogi_iris.png"></p>
<p>The interactive example above is the hvPlot <a href="https://hvplot.holoviz.org/reference/pandas/scatter.html" title="Scatter">Scatter example</a> saved
to HTML as in <a href="https://hvplot.holoviz.org/user_guide/Viewing.html#saving-plots" title="Saving plots">Saving plots</a> (code is <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/try_holoviz">on GitHub</a>) and then
copy-pasted into my blog Markdown file. The interactive plots
unfortunately don't show up in GitHub's Jupyter Notebook preview.</p>
<p><a href="https://hvplot.holoviz.org/">hvPlot</a> is just one corner of HoloViz and related packages, but the
interactive scatterplot functionality alone is enough for me to be a
big fan.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20211126-try_holoviz_for_python_plotting/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20211126-try_holoviz_for_python_plotting/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Essence of Progress and Poverty, by Henry George</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This is a 2020 version of the 1928 abridging (endorsed by
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Dewey" title="John Dewey (Wikipedia)">John Dewey</a>) of the 1879 original. It's enough to
<a href="https://www.henrygeorge.org/catsup.htm" title="“Seeing the Cat” has long been a slang term for achieving an understanding of Henry George's ideas.">“see the cat”</a>, I think, but I'm not yet convinced <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgism" title="Georgism (Wikipedia)">Georgism</a> is
<a href="/20211017-how_the_world_could_be_made_a_good_and_happy_place/" title="(a simple solution to solve all problems)">“how the world could be made a good and happy place”</a>. The single
tax on land seems like a decent idea, but I'm not sure it's sufficient
for Star Trek style post-scarcity utopia (<a href="/20210401-trekonomics_by_saadia/" title="Trekonomics, by Saadia">a</a>, <a href="/20201109-economics_of_star_trek_by_webb/" title="The Economics of Star Trek, by Webb">b</a>).</p>
<p>It's nice to encounter an idea that's <em>trying</em> to be a big solution. I
don't know a good reason not to try it, apart from that those who are
currently own land wouldn't like it.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It has always been to the newer countries—that is, to the countries
where material progress is yet in its earlier stages—that laborers
have emigrated in search of higher wages, and capital has flowed in
search of higher interest. It is in the older countries—that is to
say, the countries where material progress has reached later
stages—that widespread destitution is found in the midst of the
greatest abundance. Go into a new community where Anglo-Saxon vigor
is just beginning the race of progress; where the machinery of
production and exchange is yet rude and inefficient; where the
increment of wealth is not yet great enough to enable any class to
live in ease and luxury; where the best house is but a cabin of logs
or a cloth and paper shanty; and the richest man is forced to daily
work—and though you will find an absence of wealth and all its
concomitants, you will find no beggars." (page 4)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Couple things.</p>
<ul>
<li>"Anglo-Saxon vigor"? How deep is this racist-imperialist thinking?
   Does he think only white people are people?</li>
<li>Was this ever true, that net migration was from richer to poorer
   countries? Is it true now? Certainly the stereotype is that people
   prefer to move from poorer to richer countries "in search of higher
   wages".</li>
<li>Is it really true that the situation he describes is somehow a cure
   for poverty, or is it that George is wrong, or perhaps that people
   who would be poor cannot survive in such settings, so they aren't
   observed, or some combination?</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"To educate men who must be condemned to poverty, is but to make
them restive; to base on a state of most glaring social inequality
political institutions under which men are theoretically equal, is
to stand a pyramid on its apex." (page 7)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This makes me think of antagonism toward "elites"... Not a perfect
connection though.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The reason why, in spite of the increase of productive power, wages
constantly tend to a minimum which will give but a bare living, is
that, with increase in productive power, rent tends to even greater
increase, thus producing a constant tendency to the forcing down of
wages." (page 26)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But it also isn't that employers keep throwing more money at
employees, and then landlords respond by increasing rents. If rent was
suddenly free, wouldn't employers lower wages in response to the
changed cost of living? Currently we see employers adjusting salaries
of remote employees based on cost of living in various markets, which
is largely driven by cost of housing.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"To extirpate poverty, to make wages what justice demands they
should be, the full earnings of the laborer, we must therefore
substitute for the individual ownership of land a common ownership.</p>
<p>"The right of ownership that springs from labor excludes the
possibility of any other right of ownership." (page 32)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It [tax upon land values] is the taking by the community, for the
use of the community, of that value which is the creation of the
community." (page 37)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Every productive enterprise, besides its return to those who
undertake it, yields collateral advantages to others." (page 43)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is tautological or incorrect.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It seems to me that in a condition of society in which no one need
fear poverty, no one would desire great wealth—at least, no one
would take the trouble to strive and to strain for it as men do
now." (page 47)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Shortsighted is the philosophy which counts on selfishness as the
master motive of human action." (page 57)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20211121-essence_of_progress_and_poverty/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20211121-essence_of_progress_and_poverty/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Come work at Meta! (Facebook/Instagram/WhatsApp/etc.)</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>People have started asking me to refer them for jobs at <a href="https://meta.com/">Meta</a>,
which is great because Meta is <a href="https://www.facebookcareers.com/jobs">hiring</a>! I'd be happy to refer you;
send <a href="/aaron/">me</a> the following:</p>
<ol>
<li>Your full name</li>
<li>Your email address</li>
<li>Exactly one of:<ul>
<li>Your resume in PDF format</li>
<li>A link to your LinkedIn profile</li>
<li>Tell me to put in your email address and you'll be prompted to
  provide information yourself. (I've never tried this.)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>One to three job links from the <a href="https://www.facebookcareers.com/jobs">official jobs site</a><ul>
<li>Not from LinkedIn, not from Indeed, etc. They have to be from
  the official jobs site to work in the system.</li>
<li>Ensure you meet the minimum requirements listed for each, and
  that the locations listed (including remote if applicable) are
  aligned with your preferences.</li>
<li>If you're interested in working remotely, mention that to me.</li>
<li>If you're interested in a position based in an EU or UK office,
  mention that to me.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Are you either of: a current university student or graduated from
   university within the last nine months? (yes/no)</li>
<li>How many years of industry experience do you have (not counting
   internships)? (one number)</li>
<li>Do you live in either of: the EU or UK? (yes/no)</li>
<li>Optional things<ul>
<li>LinkedIn profile link</li>
<li>GitHub profile link</li>
<li>Portfolio website link</li>
<li>Brief note (one paragraph or less) on why you should be hired</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Once I have the above, I can put you into the system. After that, I
won't hear anything before you do. I can't guarantee any particular
next steps, but I wish you the best of luck and hope you do well!</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20211109-come_work_at_meta/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20211109-come_work_at_meta/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Parallel coordinate plots for visualizing functions</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>While thinking about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binomial_proportion_confidence_interval#Arcsine_transformation">arcsin transform</a> for <a href="/20211106-visualizing_cohens_h/">Cohen's <em>h</em></a>, I
described the function as “stretching” its inputs, and compared it to
the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logit">logit function</a>. I wondered whether a
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parallel_coordinates">parallel coordinates plot</a> could visualize the “stretching” more
clearly than the traditional Cartesian plot. I think it kind of works!</p>
<p><img alt="parallel coordinates plots" src="parallel.png"></p>
<p>This left-to-right function input-to-output view is pleasing in some
ways. I think it succeeds in showing how the function is “stretching”
the input, as desired. It's hard to show very many input/output pairs
though, and it would be hard to show non-monotonic functions well, or
show multiple functions on the same axes. For the logit, I think it's
less clear in implying the function is unbounded than with the
Cartesian version.</p>
<p><img alt="traditional cartesian plots" src="cartesian.png"></p>
<p>The usual way of plotting functions feels a little drier. “Stretching”
is greater where the plot is more vertical; I feel this less
immediately here than with the parallel coordinates version. Overall
this is still a great way to visualize functions, of course. I
wouldn't mind the occasional parallel coordinates plot as an
alternative visualization though!</p>
<hr>
<p>Code is <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/parallel_coordinate_functions">on GitHub</a>.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20211107-parallel_coordinate_plots_for_visualizing_functions/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20211107-parallel_coordinate_plots_for_visualizing_functions/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Visualizing Cohen's h</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cohen%27s_h">Cohen's <em>h</em></a> is an effect size for differences between two
proportions. It ranges from 0 to \( \pi \) (when nondirectional) and
adjusts for whether the proportions are “extreme” (near 0 or 1) so
that equal Cohen's <em>h</em> means equal statistical detectability (Cohen
1988).</p>
<p><img alt="Cohen's h" src="cohens_h.png"></p>
<p>The heuristic values of 0.2 for “small,” 0.5 for “medium,” and 0.8 for
“large” are analogous to the 0.05 confidence level: often taken more
seriously than they should be.</p>
<p>Cohen's <em>h</em> is the difference between the two proportions'
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binomial_proportion_confidence_interval#Arcsine_transformation">arcsin transforms</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="arcsin transformation" src="arcsin_transform.png"></p>
<p>The arcsin transform stretches out values near 0 and 1 more than
values around 0.5. It is bounded though, so for example if your
baseline proportion is 0.95, there is no proportion higher than that
which will register as a “medium” effect size.</p>
<p>You could replace the arcsin transform with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logit">log odds</a>; the logit
would allow any size difference anywhere, at least in principle. But I
don't think it would have any useful connection to variance, as the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binomial_proportion_confidence_interval#Arcsine_transformation">arcsin transformation</a> does.</p>
<hr>
<p>Code is <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/cohens_h">on GitHub</a>.</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20211106-visualizing_cohens_h/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20211106-visualizing_cohens_h/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Simple diff-in-diff</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Things are always changing. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Difference_in_differences">Difference in differences</a> tries to
identify how much of a change is due to some treatment by comparing to
a control that's also changing over time.</p>
<p><img alt="diff-in-diff diagram" src="diff_in_diff.jpg"></p>
<p>This is often presented graphically with response value against time.</p>
<p><img alt="diff-in-diff graph" src="diff_in_diff_graph.jpg"></p>
<p>A noiseless design matrix illustrates how this becomes a diff-in-diff
regression.</p>
<pre><code>| treatment base | control base | common diff | treatment diff | response |
|----------------|--------------|-------------|----------------|----------|
| 1              | 0            | 0           | 0              |  3       |
| 0              | 1            | 0           | 0              |  2       |
| 1              | 0            | 1           | 1              | 12       |
| 0              | 1            | 1           | 0              |  7       |
</code></pre>

<p>Real data will have noise; here's a simulation in <a href="https://www.r-project.org/">R</a>.</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">treatment_base = c(rep(1, 100), rep(0, 100), rep(1, 100), rep(0, 100))
control_base   = c(rep(0, 100), rep(1, 100), rep(0, 100), rep(1, 100))
common_diff    = c(rep(0, 100), rep(0, 100), rep(1, 100), rep(1, 100))
treatment_diff = c(rep(0, 100), rep(0, 100), rep(1, 100), rep(0, 100))
response = c(rnorm(100, mean=3),
             rnorm(100, mean=2),
             rnorm(100, mean=3) + rnorm(100, mean=5) + rnorm(100, mean=4),
             rnorm(100, mean=2) + rnorm(100, mean=5))
summary(lm(response ~ treatment_base + control_base + common_diff + treatment_diff + 0))
##                Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
## treatment_base   3.0747     0.1367   22.50   &lt;2e-16 ***
## control_base     1.9798     0.1367   14.49   &lt;2e-16 ***
## common_diff      5.0990     0.1933   26.38   &lt;2e-16 ***
## treatment_diff   3.9453     0.2733   14.44   &lt;2e-16 ***</code></pre>

<p>Diff-in-diff can get <a href="https://andrewcbaker.netlify.app/2019/09/25/difference-in-differences-methodology/">more complicated</a>, but the simple version
isn't too bad.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thanks to Dr. Erica Blom for valuable discussion and references on
this topic.</p>
<hr>
<h3>See also</h3>
<ul>
<li>Four “back door” regression situations:
   <a href="/20200912-what_should_be_in_your_regression/">What should be in your regression?</a></li>
<li><a href="/20210501-simple_front_door_regression/">Simple Front Door Regression</a></li>
<li><a href="/20210430-a_simple_instrumental_variable/">A simple Instrumental Variable</a></li>
</ul>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20211031-simple_diff_in_diff/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20211031-simple_diff_in_diff/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>My daily routine</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Especially since reading <a href="/2014/01/19/daily-rituals-is-sort-of-inspiring/" title="Daily Rituals is sort of inspiring">Daily Rituals</a>, I've thought about how
people structure their days. This year I've been working on my
routines, especially mornings. Here's how it's looking.</p>
<h3>6:00-6:30 — <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spaced_repetition" title="Spaced repetition on Wikipedia">Spaced repetition</a> review with <a href="https://apps.ankiweb.net/" title="Anki App">Anki</a></h3>
<p>I review about a hundred cards per day in the <a href="https://apps.ankiweb.net/" title="Anki App">Anki</a> app. I
<a href="/20201009-anki_is_easy/" title="Anki is easy">got into this</a> about a year ago, and I think I'm going to
<a href="/20210908-spaced_repetition_is_o_log_n_sustainable/" title="Spaced repetition is O(log n) sustainable">stick with it</a>. It's pretty common to recommend daily physical
exercise, and I think of this as being a similar practice for
knowledge and memory.</p>
<h3>6:30-7:00 — Writing in journal aka “<a href="https://juliacameronlive.com/basic-tools/morning-pages/" title="Morning Pages">Morning pages</a>”</h3>
<p>This is a <a href="https://juliacameronlive.com/basic-tools/morning-pages/" title="Morning Pages">Julia Cameron thing</a> I picked up from
<a href="/20210116-pragmatic_thinking_and_learning/" title="Pragmatic Thinking and Learning, by Andy Hunt">Andy Hunt's book</a>. It's pretty good. I don't always write a full
three pages, but I make a point to always write something.</p>
<h3>7:00-7:30 — Physical exercise</h3>
<p>I alternate running about three miles outside and doing a 21-minute
“Smart Workout” with the <a href="https://7minuteworkout.jnj.com/" title="The Johnson &amp; Johnson Official 7 Minute Workout® App">J&amp;J 7-Minute Workout app</a> in the basement.
Running allows podcast listening.</p>
<p>Then I try to shower and everything by eight.</p>
<h3>Food and drink</h3>
<p>During the week, my breakfast and lunch have gotten pretty consistent.</p>
<ul>
<li>Breakfast: Granola with a little whole milk Greek yogurt</li>
<li>Lunch: Turkey and Swiss sandwich on whole grain bread with mustard</li>
</ul>
<p>Also in a typical day I drink two to four 8.4-ounce cans of Red Bull
Sugar Free.</p>
<h3>“Dailies”</h3>
<p>There are a number of little things I try to do every day. They can
change, and aren't always super strict. Here are some examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>Read today's entry from Tolstoy's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Calendar_of_Wisdom">Calendar of Wisdom</a></li>
<li>Copy one of my old book posts into <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/34234019-aaron-schumacher">Goodreads</a> and Amazon reviews</li>
<li>Post a picture of my algae tank on Instagram</li>
<li>Greet someone I wasn't otherwise planning to talk to today</li>
<li>Do a lesson and reviews on <a href="https://www.executeprogram.com/">Execute Program</a></li>
<li>Come up with one new idea based on a random word</li>
</ul>
<p>Some of these I track in a spreadsheet.</p>
<h3>Evening — Read a book</h3>
<p>I try to read a chapter, or an hour, or at least <em>something</em> that
isn't screaming at me from a screen. This is usually a paper book
because I like them, but the main characteristic of this reading is
that it's deliberate rather than reactive. I record what I've read in
my journal.</p>
<hr>
<p>I'm not perfect in following all of this, but recently I've been
getting more consistent, and I like it. One way I think about this is
that it raises the floor for how much I do in a day. Even if I do
nothing else, if I do these things I've done something to be happy
about. And of course these things have benefits that help me do other
things too. Always room to learn and improve more too!</p>
<p>The routines here are the least important parts of my days; I hope
they support the things I value and don't conflict with them.</p>
<p>I'm very fortunate to be largely free to choose how I spend so much
time; I owe so much to Erica in particular for supporting me and
making our family's life better every day.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20211030-my_daily_routine/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20211030-my_daily_routine/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Core RAPPOR</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1407.6981">RAPPOR</a> (“Randomized Aggregatable Privacy-Preserving Ordinal
Response”) is really close to the classic coin-flip
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Differential_privacy#Randomized_response">randomized response</a> method, with one more layer of randomness.
It's “ordinal” in that it's every bit for itself: you can represent
histogram bins, but you can't really represent numbers in the usual
binary way. They additionally use Bloom filters to represent sets of
hashable things, which is neat too.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Differential_privacy#Randomized_response">Randomized response</a> works like this. Did you wash your hands?</p>
<ul>
<li>25% of the time, just say “yes” regardless</li>
<li>25% of the time, just say “no” regardless</li>
<li>50% of the time, answer truthfully</li>
</ul>
<p>Those percentages correspond to \( f = 0.5 \) in the RAPPOR
<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1407.6981.pdf">paper</a>'s notation. They call this the “permanent” step, because
it's done once per respondent.</p>
<!--
<pre><code class="language-python">import random</code></pre>
-->

<pre><code class="language-python">def permanent_randomized(response: bool, f=0.5):
    randomizer = random.random()  # uniform on [0, 1)
    if 0 &lt;= randomizer &lt; f/2:  # probability f/2
        return True
    elif f/2 &lt;= randomizer &lt; f:  # probability f/2
        return False
    elif f &lt;= randomizer &lt; 1:  # probability 1 - f
        return response</code></pre>

<p>If you get 59% positive responses with this method, 25% were just automatically saying “yes” and 34% were answering “yes” because they were being honest. Half of people were being honest, so double the 34% to find the overall true positive rate is 68%.</p>
<p>To let individuals report multiple times without losing privacy or being trackable, RAPPOR adds “instantaneous” randomness as well.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">def instantaneous_randomized(response: bool, q=0.75, p=0.5):
    randomizer = random.random()  # uniform on [0, 1)
    if response is True:
        return randomizer &lt; q  # probability q
    elif response is False:
        return randomizer &lt; p  # probability p</code></pre>

<p>With the complete method, recovering the true rate gets a little more complicated; see first equation in the <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1407.6981.pdf">paper</a>'s §4.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">def extract_rate(raw_rate: float, f=0.5, q=0.75, p=0.5):
    return (raw_rate - p - f*q/2 + f*p/2) / ((1 - f)*(q - p))</code></pre>

<p>And it works!</p>
<!--
<pre><code class="language-python">random.seed(0)</code></pre>
-->

<pre><code class="language-python">true_rate = 0.68
n = 1_000_000

raw_rate = sum(
    instantaneous_randomized(
        permanent_randomized(random.random() &lt; true_rate))
    for _ in range(n)) / n

extract_rate(raw_rate)
## 0.6807759999999998</code></pre>

<p>RAPPOR is just doing this for any number of bits per respondent. Each
bit can have a direct interpretation like “this thing yes for this
respondent.”</p>
<p>RAPPOR also introduces a way of having respondents hash strings (say)
into <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloom_filter">Bloom filters</a>, which is kind of neat. They show how to have
different groups of respondents use different hash functions and then
do some regression to try to overcome noise and false positives. As
far as I can tell, you have to already know the set of things you're
going to be hashing into the Bloom filter (you won't discover an
unknown unknown) but it is more efficient and flexible than defining a
separate bit for every candidate string.</p>
<p>RAPPOR is used <a href="https://www.chromium.org/developers/design-documents/rappor">in Chrome</a>, for example, and if you have really a
lot of respondents, it seems pretty good!</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20211019-core_rappor/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20211019-core_rappor/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>“how the world could be made a good and happy place”</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The opening of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hitchhiker%27s_Guide_to_the_Galaxy">The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy</a> goes like this
(italics in original, bold added):</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Far out in the uncharted backwaters of the unfashionable end of the
Western Spiral arm of the Galaxy lies a small unregarded yellow sun.
Orbiting this at a distance of roughly ninety-eight million miles is
an utterly insignificant little blue-green planet whose apedescended
life forms are so amazingly primitive that they still think digital
watches are a pretty neat idea.</em></p>
<p><em>This planet has—or rather had—a problem, which was this: most of
the people living on it were unhappy for pretty much of the time.
Many solutions were suggested for this problem, but most of these
were largely concerned with the movements of small green pieces of
paper, which is odd because on the whole it wasn’t the small green
pieces of paper that were unhappy.</em></p>
<p><em>And so the problem remained; lots of the people were mean, and most
of them were miserable, even the ones with digital watches.</em></p>
<p><em>Many were increasingly of the opinion that they’d all made a big
mistake in coming down from the trees in the first place. And some
said that even the trees had been a bad move, and that no one should
ever have left the oceans.</em></p>
<p><em>And then, one Thursday, nearly two thousand years after one man had
been nailed to a tree for saying how great it would be to be nice to
people for a change, <strong>a girl sitting on her own in a small café in
Rickmansworth suddenly realized what it was that had been going
wrong all this time, and she finally knew how the world could be
made a good and happy place. This time it was right, it would work,
and no one would have to get nailed to anything.</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Sadly, however, before she could get to a phone to tell anyone
about it, a terrible, stupid catastrophe occurred, and the idea was
lost for ever.</em></p>
<p><em>This is not her story.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think the joke is that there is no such idea (so let's have nihilist
sci-fi fun) but I still don't like it. I bet Douglas Adams would have
written her story if he could have.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20211017-how_the_world_could_be_made_a_good_and_happy_place/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20211017-how_the_world_could_be_made_a_good_and_happy_place/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 17 Oct 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Case Against Education, by Caplan</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Caplan thinks students aren't learning—“The vast majority are
philistines”—so we should stop trying to teach them. I agree with
Caplan on some of his premises, but I don't follow him all the way to
his libertarian recommendations.</p>
<p>Should everyone be pushed toward college as if it's the only
acceptable path? Probably not. More vocational education seems like a
fine idea. I agree there's a signaling component (possibly large) to
the personal benefit of education, and that many people don't learn as
much as it seems like they should.</p>
<p>Caplan turns his back on equality of opportunity when he recommends
letting the market decide on education. I'm not entirely comfortable
with how casually he cites <a href="https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/extremist-files/individual/arthur-jensen">Jensen</a> (page 60) or ignores that
effects vary substantially by race even in work he cites (page 150).</p>
<p>I think it's inconsistent to treat education as essentially daycare
but not include the provision of that service in the accounting of
economic benefits.</p>
<p>I think the interesting thing is to consider Caplan's critiques and
think about what really effective education could look like. What
really would build human capital? What would make people wiser,
happier, and more productive?</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Bryan Caplan, the foremost whistle-blower in the academy, argues
persuasively that learning about completely arbitrary subjects is
attractive to employers because it signals students' intelligence,
work ethic, desire to please, and conformity—even when such learning
conveys no cognitive advantage or increase in human capital." (cover
blurb from Stephen J. Ceci)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Learning doesn't have to be useful. Learning doesn't have to be
inspirational. When learning is neither useful nor inspirational,
though, how can we call it anything but wasteful." (page 2)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Few jobs require knowledge of higher mathematics, but over 80% of
high school grads suffer through geometry. Students study history
for years, but history teachers are almost the only people alive who
use history on the job." (pages 6-7)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Geometry is higher mathematics? But more importantly, isn't history
important, at least in theory, to having informed voters for
democracy? Caplan later points out that years of history don't usually
yield informed voters in the current system anyway, but it seems
inappropriate to completely neglect civic objectives for education.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"...statistics and econometrics courses at elite colleges emphasize
mathematical proofs, not hands-on statistical training." (page 11)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That cites <a href="https://ftp.iza.org/dp10535.pdf">Undergraduate Econometrics Instruction: Through Our Classes, Darkly</a>, which includes the following in its abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Questions of research design and causality still take a back seat
in the classroom, in spite of having risen to the top of the modern
empirical agenda. This essay traces the divergent development of
econometric teaching and empirical practice, arguing for a
pedagogical paradigm shift."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Higher education is the only product where the consumer tries to
get as little out of it as possible." (page 26, quoting Arnold
Kling, sort of)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The citation is <a href="https://www.econlib.org/archives/2006/08/college_custome.html">College Customers vs. Suppliers</a>, in which Kling writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"I recall seeing a quote somewhere else to the effect that higher
education is the only product where the consumer tries to get as
little out of it as possible."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So who knows where the quote comes from!</p>
<p>Kling proposes separating testing from teaching, to align students and
professors in the direction of rigor rather than easy A's. Maybe so?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Basic literacy and numeracy are virtually the <em>only</em> book learning
most American adults possess." (page 40)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Though college grads spend at least seventeen years in school,
under a third have the level of literacy and numeracy we assume of
every college freshman." (page 43)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Note: Statisticians routinely rely on the approximate equality
between logged variables and percentages. However, when coefficients
are large, this approximation breaks down, so I convert results to
percentages for clarity." (page 302, endnote 8 from page 73)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't think this is very clear. What it's getting at is that if
you're fitting a linear model, then a logged outcome variable makes
the additive model multiplicative in the original outcome, so a 0.02
change in the regression outcome is a 2% change in the original
outcome. Gelman has a decent <a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2019/08/21/you-should-usually-log-transform-your-positive-data/">intro</a>, maybe. Or <a href="https://people.duke.edu/~rnau/411log.htm">this</a>, which
notes that "small changes in the natural log of a variable are
directly interpretable as percentage changes, to a very close
approximation" and even a nice table showing how the approximation
breaks down.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Most strikingly, the standard measure of "fatalism," the Rotter
Internal-External Locus of Control Scale, is a four-question
personality test. (page 303, endnote 24 from page 75)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is misleading. The <a href="https://www.mccc.edu/~jenningh/Courses/documents/Rotter-locusofcontrolhandout.pdf" title="Rotter's Locus of Control Scale">Rotter</a> instrument has 29 questions. But
Caplan is citing <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w12006" title="The Effects of Cognitive and Noncognitive Abilities on Labor Market Outcomes and Social Behavior">a 2006 paper</a> that uses <a href="https://www.bls.gov/nls/nlsy79.htm" title="National Longitudinal Survey of Youth 1979">NLSY79</a> data, which
does indeed <a href="https://www.nlsinfo.org/content/cohorts/nlsy79/other-documentation/codebook-supplement/nlsy79-appendix-21-attitudinal-scales#rotter">include</a> a "four-item abbreviated version of the Rotter
Internal External Locus of Control Scale"—sort of.</p>
<p>NLSY79 included Rotter questions 28, 13, 15, and 25 (in that order)
and in addition to asking respondents to choose one of two statements
for each, also asked whether their choice was "much closer" or
"slightly closer" to their view. So it's an eight-question instrument
(or at least, it yields eight bits of information).</p>
<p>There are multiple tests for internal-external locus of control, some
<a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00223891.1974.10119987" title="An Abbreviated Measure of Internal-External Locus of Control">shorter</a> than 29 questions, some <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/1973-21097-001" title="A locus of control scale for children">longer</a>. If you do want a
four-question instrument, consider Kovaleva's <a href="https://www.ssoar.info/ssoar/bitstream/handle/document/37119/ssoar-2012-kovaleva-The_IE-4_Construction_and_Validation.pdf" title="The IE-4: Construction and Validation of a Short Scale for the Assessment of Locus of Control">IE-4</a> (four
five-point Likert scale questions; see Table 26 on page 81).</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Full-length intelligence tests have a very high reliability; the
reliability of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armed_Services_Vocational_Aptitude_Battery#Armed_Forces_Qualification_Test">AFQT</a>, for example, is .94 (ASVAB 2015). Short
intelligence tests, in contrast, have markedly lower reliability—.74
in the case of the General Social Survey's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wordsum">ten-word IQ test</a>
(Caplan and Miller 2010, p. 645)." (page 307, endnote 98 from page
93)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"You'll never apply most of what you study, but so what? Academic
success opens doors. A dysfunctional game, but if you refuse to
play, the labor market brands you a loser." (page 108)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<em>Signals can affect pay even after employers know the truth.</em>
Employer learning researchers speak as if the payoff for signaling
ends as soon as employers know a worker's true worth. They should be
more circumspect. For starters, firms often give new workers
valuable on-the-job training. As a result, signaling can indirectly
boost your productivity. Step 1: Signal in school. Step 2: Land a
good job. Step 3: Learn useful job skills on the job. Step 4:
Persistently profit. If your signal modestly overstates your skill,
your imployer may soon wish they'd hired someone else. By the time
they spot their mistake, however, your new marketable skills
permanently justify higher pay." (page 112)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Following the endnote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"While research on this story is sparse, Heisz and Oreopoulos 2006
report the payoff for high-ranked M.B.A. and law degrees <em>increases</em>
with experience, even correcting for individual ability, because
high-ranked degrees lead to good first jobs, which lead to even
better jobs down the line." (page 312)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The Higher Education Research Institute has questioned college
freshmen about their goals since the 1970s. The vast majority is
openly careerist and materialist. In 2012, almost 90% called "being
able to get a better job" a "very important" or "essential" reason
to go to college. Being "very well-off financially" (over 80%) and
"making more money" (about 75%) are almost as popular. Less than
half say the same about "developing a meaningful philosophy of
life." These results are especially striking because humans
exaggerate their idealism and downplay their selfishness. Students
probably prize worldly success even more than they admit." (page
126)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"A cynic isn't someone who puts a price on the sacred; a cynic is
someone who puts a <em>low</em> price on the sacred." (page 126)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The High School Survey of Student Engagement, probably the single
best study of how high school students feel about school, reports
that 66% of high school students say they're bored in class <em>every
day</em>. Seventeen percent say they're bored in <em>every</em> class <em>every</em>
day. Only 2% claim they're never bored in class. Why so bored?
Eighty-two percent say the material isn't interesting; 41% say the
material isn't relevant. Another research team gave beepers to
middle school students to capture their feelings in real time.
During schoolwork, students were bored 36% of the time, versus 17%
for all other activities. No wonder a major Gates Foundation study
ranked boredom the <em>most</em> important reason why kids drop out of high
school." (page 135)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"How much does your alma mater's rank matter? Research is oddly
mixed." (page 149)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The endnote points to <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.23.4.95">Hoxby 2009</a>, which is about college
selectivity, not how much it matters to student outcomes. It's
interesting though; here's the abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Over the past few decades, the average college has not become more
selective: the reverse is true, though not dramatically. People who
believe that college selectivity is increasing may be extrapolating
from the experience of a small number of colleges such as members of
the Ivy League, Stanford, Duke, and so on. These colleges have
experienced rising selectivity, but their experience turns out to be
the exception rather than the rule. Only the top 10 percent of
colleges are substantially more selective now than they were
in 1962. Moreover, at least 50 percent of colleges are substantially
less selective now than they were in 1962. To understand changing
selectivity, we must focus on how the market for college education
has re-sorted students among schools as the costs of distance and
information have fallen. In the past, students' choices were very
sensitive to the distance of a college from their home, but today,
students, especially high-aptitude students, are far more sensitive
to a college's resources and student body. It is the consequent
re-sorting of students among colleges that has, at once, caused
selectivity to rise in a small number of colleges while
simultaneously causing it to fall in other colleges. This has had
profound implications for colleges' resources, tuition, and
subsidies for students. I demonstrate that the stakes associated
with choosing a college are greater today than they were four
decades ago because very selective colleges are offering very large
per-student resources and per-student subsidies, enabling admitted
students to make massive human capital investments."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Their [Dale and Krueger's] most amazing discovery is that students
who <em>submit</em> lots of applications to high-quality schools enjoy
exceptional career success whether or not they attend such schools."
(page 150)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The citation is <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/23799087" title="Estimating the Effects of College Characteristics over the Career Using Administrative Earnings Data">Dale and Krueger 2014</a>, which has this abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"We estimate the labor market effect of attending a highly selective
college, using the College and Beyond Survey linked to Social
Security Administration data. We extend earlier work by estimating
effects for students that entered college in 1976 over a longer time
horizon (from 1983 through 2007) and for a more recent cohort
(1989). For both cohorts, the effects of college characteristics on
earnings are sizeable (and similar in magnitude) in standard
regression models. In selection-adjusted models, these effects
generally fall to close to zero; however, these effects remain large
for certain subgroups, such as for black and Hispanic students."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's the last sentence that matters. Caplan only read the first half
of that one, somehow, which I think is a substantial mistake.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As long as your state's best public school admits you, there's no
solid reason to pay more." (page 153)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you're white. I mean, <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/23799087" title="Estimating the Effects of College Characteristics over the Career Using Administrative Earnings Data">Dale and Krueger 2014</a> is <em>his</em>
citation—how can he ignore that?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"American marriage is a diploma-based caste system." (page 156)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Going to Harvard may not get you a better job but almost certainly
puts you in an exclusive dating pool for life." (page 157)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Most Ph.D. students have spent their entire lives at the top of the
class, yet half wander off before they defend their dissertations."
(pages 163-164)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Yet common sense insists the best way to discover useful ideas is
to search for useful ideas—not to search for whatever fascinates you
and pray it turns out to be useful." (page 175)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He cites Niskanen 1997 in this opposition to basic research. This is
the common sense of those who don't make the discoveries that enable
the useful ideas of the future.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The United States—and probably the rest of the world—is
overeducated." (page 199)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And yet, still so apparently in need of more/better education.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There really is no need for K-12 to teach history, social studies,
art, music, or foreign languages." (page 205)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Better retention efforts will not make Poor Students perform like
Fair Students, Fair Students like Good Students, or Good Students
like Excellent Students." (pages 211-212)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Instead of treating the human capital model as an accurate
description of education, they could treat it as a noble
<em>pre-_scription _for</em> education. Let's transform our schools from
time sinks to skill factories." (page 225)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Doing <em>any</em> job teaches you how to do a job. If this seems a low
bar, recall that almost half of dropouts and a third of high school
graduates these days aren't even <em>looking</em> for work. Acclimating
them to a any form of employment would be a step up." (page 232)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>On page 239, Caplan quotes at some length from Malcolm X describing
how he copied a dictionary in prison. It's a bit Hirsch-like, this
advocacy for content, for volume...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The straightforward story, though, is that high culture requires
extra mental effort to appreciate—and most humans resent mental
effort." (page 247)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Measuring effects issue by issue neatly explains education's
puzzlingly small impact on ideology and party. Since education
simultaneously increases social liberalism <em>and</em> economic
conservatism, its effect on "liberalism" is ambiguous. And while
their social liberalism makes the well-educated more Democratic,
their economic conservatism makes them more Republican, leaving
partisanship nearly untouched." (page 333, endnote 36 from page 249)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"If a world of historical ignorance is scary, you should be scared
already, because that's where we live." (page 250)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When you run out of ideas, assign a random Wikipedia article. ...
Start with the Bureau of Labor Statistics' figures on "employment by
major occupational group" and "occupations with the most job
growth." When you run out of ideas, have students check out an
unfamiliar job from the Bureau of Labor Statistics' <em>Occupational
Outlook Handbook</em>." (page 256)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I do kind of like some of this. In particular, I feel like I didn't
learn in school much of anything about what jobs exist or what people
really do in them.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I'm cynical about students. The vast majority are philistines. The
best teachers in the universe couldn't inspire them with sincere and
lasting love of ideas and culture. I'm cynical about teachers. The
vast majority are uninspiring; they can't convince even <em>themselves</em>
to love ideas and culture, much less their students. I'm cynical
about "deciders"—the school officials who control what students
study. The vast majority think they've done their job as long as
students obey." (page 259)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I don't hate education. Rather I love education too much to accept
our Orwellian substitute." (page 260)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As Stanford education professor David Labaree remarks, "Motivating
volunteers to engage in human improvement is very difficult, as any
psychotherapist can confirm, but motivating conscripts is quite
another thing altogether. And it is conscripts that teachers face
every day in the classroom."" (page 260)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Many idealists object that the Internet provides enlightenment only
for those who seek it. They're right, but petulant to ask for more."
(page 261)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Most humans intrigued by abstract ideas and high culture are
working adults. Instead of lamenting youthful apathy, passionate
educators should redirect their energy to humans who are <em>ready</em> for
enlightenment. There is little money in blogging, podcasting, or
uploading lectures to YouTube. But if, like me, you love education
to the depths of your soul, such efforts are their own reward."
(page 261)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And that's how the book ends, apart from the five dispensable
dialogues that follow.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20211006-case_against_education_by_caplan/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20211006-case_against_education_by_caplan/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>XGBoost/LightGBM/CatBoost (briefly)</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>There are many explainers of the popular gradient boosted tree models,
but this is short.</p>
<table width="100%" border="1">
  <tr>
    <th style="width:33%;">
      <a href="https://xgboost.readthedocs.io/">XGBoost</a></th>
    <th style="width:34%;">
      <a href="https://lightgbm.readthedocs.io/">LightGBM</a></th>
    <th style="width:33%;">
      <a href="https://catboost.ai/">CatBoost</a></th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>search missing high and low</td>
    <td>search, then assign missing</td>
    <td>specify missing high or low</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>"normal" balanced trees</td>
    <td>leaf-first tree growth</td>
    <td>oblivious trees (tables)</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>you handle categories</td>
    <td>smart categorical ordering</td>
    <td>permuted target coding</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>weighted quantile sketch</td>
    <td>sample high-grad examples</td>
    <td>permuted boosting</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>regularized objective</td>
    <td>exclusive feature bundling</td>
    <td>learns category interactions</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1603.02754">2016 paper</a></td>
    <td><a href="https://papers.nips.cc/paper/2017/hash/6449f44a102fde848669bdd9eb6b76fa-Abstract.html">2017 paper</a></td>
    <td><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.09516">2017 paper</a></td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>This is close to correct, I think. It probably won't help you
understand what's going on, but if you already know it might help jog
your memory. The models all work pretty well.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20211003-xgboost_lightgbm_catboost_briefly/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20211003-xgboost_lightgbm_catboost_briefly/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 03 Oct 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Staff Engineer, by Larson</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>It's all <a href="https://staffeng.com/">online for free too</a>, but I enjoyed reading a paper copy
of <a href="https://lethain.com/">Larson</a>'s <a href="https://staffeng.com/guides">Staff Engineer</a>. (Well: I skimmed some of the
interviews that pad out the page count.) I really liked the use of QR
codes with the endnote links. That could work well in Tufte-style
margins too.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There's a popular vision of heroic leadership that centers on
extraordinarily productive individuals whose decisions change their
company's future. Most of those narratives are intentionally
designed by public relations teams to create a good story. You're
far more likely to change your company's long-term trajectory by
growing the engineers around you than through personal heroics. The
best way to grow those around you is by creating an active practice
of mentorship and sponsorship." (page 22)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It might be addressing the sudden realization that your primary
database only has three months of remaining disk space, and you
can't upgrade to a larger size (in my experience, a surprisingly
frequent problem at fast-growing startups)." (page 24)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"For mentorship and sponsorship, spend some time with Lara Hogan's
<a href="https://larahogan.me/blog/what-sponsorship-looks-like/">What Does Sponsorship Look Like?</a>, and for being glue, spend time
with Tanya Reilly's piece that bore the phrase, <a href="https://noidea.dog/glue">Being Glue</a>."
(page 34)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The first place to look for work that matters is exploring whether
your company is experiencing an existential risk." (page 39)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Foster growth" (page 40)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Specific statements create alignment; generic statements create the
illusion of alignment." (page 47)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There's no such thing as winning, only learning and earning the
chance to keep playing." (page 52)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Reminds me of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finite_and_Infinite_Games">Finite and Infinite Games</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Premature processes add more friction than value and are quick to
expose themselves as ineffective." (page 43)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There's the old joke about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarbanes%E2%80%93Oxley_Act">Sarbannes-Oxley</a> [sic]: it doesn't
reduce risk; it just makes it clear to blame when things go wrong."
(page 54)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... adopting the "define errors out of existence" approach
described in A Philosophy of Software Design." (page 54)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At a quick look, it seems like this is something like "give your
functions defaults rather than exceptions" so if you ask for something
out of range, for example, you get the last thing rather than throwing.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Genuine best practice has to be supported by research, and the best
source of research on this topic is <a href="https://itrevolution.com/accelerate-book/">Accelerate</a>." (page 56)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When it comes to complex systems and interdependencies, moving
quickly is just optics. It's methodical movement that gets the job
done." (page 69)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I think this is the most important lesson I've learned over the
past few years: the most effective leaders spend more time following
than they do leading. This idea also comes up in the idea of the
"<a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/derek_sivers_how_to_start_a_movement">the first follower creates a leader</a>," but effective leaders
don't split the world into a leader and follower dichotomy, rather
they move in and out of the leadership and follower roles with the
folks around them." (page 76)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There's a well-worn model of genius encapsulated in
<a href="https://wiki.c2.com/?FeynmanAlgorithm">the Feynman algorithm</a>: "1) Write down a problem. 2) Think very
hard. 3) Write down the solution." This mystical view of genius is
both unapproachable and discouraging. It's also unrealistic, but
it's hard for folks to know it's unrealistic if we don't write down
our thinking process for others to follow. By writing down the
process of finding an answer, as well as the rationale for the
answer, folks around us can being to <em>learn from</em> our decisions
rather than simply being <em>directed</em> by them" (page 85)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Barbara Minto, whose The Pyramid Principle is the most influential
work on effective business communication, is also a big fan of
structure: "Controlling the sequence in which you present your ideas
is the single most important act necessary to clear writing. The
clearest sequence is always to give the summarizing idea before you
give the individual ideas being summarized. I cannot emphasize this
point too much."" (page 96)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<a href="https://jvns.ca/blog/brag-documents/">brag document</a>" (page 106)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Whether your company does ad-hoc promotions or uses a calibration
process, promotions are a team activity and as Julia Grace, then of
Slack, advised me once during a job search, "Don't play team games
along, you'll lose."" (page 110)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Share weekly notes of your work to your team and stakeholders in a
way that other folks can get access to your notes if they're
interested" (page 128)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The flying wedge pattern of one senior leader joining a company and
then bringing on their previous coworkers is a well-known and
justifiably-despised pattern that relies on this built-in
referrer-as-sponsor, but it doesn't have to be toxic if done
sparingly." (page 139)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There are some wonderful engineering leaders creating pockets of
equitable access to Staff-plus roles, but those pockets can quickly
turn into a <a href="https://lethain.com/values-oasis/">Values Oasis</a> that can't sustain itself once the
sponsoring leader departs the company or changes roles." (page 139)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Back in 2012, Patrick McKenzie wrote <a href="https://www.kalzumeus.com/2012/01/23/salary-negotiation/">Salary Negotiation</a>, which
has since become the defacto [sic] guide to negotiating salaries for
software engineers." (page 145)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Staff-plus is all about enabling other people to do better work -
to be a force multiplier." (page 184, from Bert Fan)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This is not a meritocracy and your professional network is
important." (page 186, from Bert Fan)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"To reach Staff Engineer, you have to know and do more than what you
currently know." (page 209, from Ritu Vincent)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"A quote I love from Seneca is <em>"Luck is what happens when
preparation meets opportunity."</em>" (page 267, from Damian
Schenkelman)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In the quest for efficiency over effectiveness, many companies trap
their managers in a staggering amount of coordination and
bureaucracy." (page 309)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When we talk about designing a Staff-plus engineer interview loop,
the first thing to talk about is that absolutely no one is confident
their Staff-plus interview loop works well." (page 312)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210919-staff_engineer_by_larson/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210919-staff_engineer_by_larson/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Sep 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Weight of Evidence is logistic coefficients</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>“Weight of Evidence” (WoE) is a <a href="https://www.endocrinescience.org/glossary/weight-of-evidence-woe/" title="Weight of evidence refers to a systematic approach that scientists use to evaluate the totality of scientific evidence to assess if the science supports a particular conclusion.">good idea</a> for decision-making,
but, especially in the financial risk modeling world, it's also a
specific feature processing <a href="https://contrib.scikit-learn.org/category_encoders/woe.html">method</a> based on <a href="http://helios.mm.di.uoa.gr/~rouvas/ssi/sigkdd/sigkdd.vol3.1/barreca.pdf">target statistics</a>.
Weight of Evidence changes a categorical variable into the log odds
coefficients corresponding to a logistic regression with intercept at
the overall rate.</p>
<p>Say you have a categorical predictor, or a continuous predictor that
you're going to bin into categories in order to make it easier to
model nonlinear relationships, and a binary outcome like “defaulted on
loan or not”. Then for each category, the WoE score is:</p>
<p>\[ \text{WoE} =
    \log \left( \frac{\text{count of positives for this category} /
                      \text{count of all positives}}
                     {\text{count of negatives for this category} /
                      \text{count of all negatives}} \right) \]</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">import numpy as np
import pandas as pd
import category_encoders as ce

X = pd.DataFrame({'x': ['a', 'a', 'a', 'a', 'b', 'b', 'b', 'b']})
y =                    [ 1 ,  1 ,  0 ,  0 ,  1 ,  0 ,  0 ,  0 ]

woe = ce.woe.WOEEncoder(regularization=0)
woe.fit(X, y)
woe.transform(pd.DataFrame({'x': ['a', 'b']}))
## (0.5108256237659906, -0.587786664902119)

np.log((2/3)/(2/5)), np.log((1/3)/(3/5))
## (0.5108256237659906, -0.587786664902119)</code></pre>

<p>It's usually written <a href="https://www.listendata.com/2015/03/weight-of-evidence-woe-and-information.html">like</a> <a href="https://docs.tibco.com/data-science/GUID-44739B00-E85F-4CE7-8404-24F9B775ADE8.html">that</a>, sometimes with additive
smoothing (add some small numbers to the counts) to avoid zeros and
reduce variance. To make it even clearer that this is just
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logit">log odds</a>, rearrange to:</p>
<p>\[ \text{WoE} =
    \log \left( \frac{\text{count of positives for this category}}
                     {\text{count of negatives for this category}} \right) -
    \log \left( \frac{\text{count of all positives}}
                     {\text{count of all negatives}} \right) \]</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">np.log(2/2) - np.log(3/5), np.log(1/3) - np.log(3/5)
## (0.5108256237659907, -0.5877866649021191)</code></pre>

<p>The WoE values are exactly the coefficients you'd get if you
<a href="https://pandas.pydata.org/docs/reference/api/pandas.get_dummies.html">made indicator columns</a> for your categorical variable, added an
intercept column, and did a logistic regression. That design matrix
isn't full rank, so there isn't a unique solution—unless you set the
intercept coefficient to represent the overall log odds (as in the
subtracted term above).</p>
<p>These WoE scores are monotonic with the category-specific percent
positive, for example, so if you're going to use a tree-based model
where spacing doesn't matter, the more immediately interpretable value
might be preferable. If you're doing a simple logistic regression with
a WoE predictor, the coefficient will be one. In combination with
other features, it isn't obvious to me that WoE will always be an
absolutely optimal transform, but it seems like a fine choice for
multiple logistic regression as well. Using WoE instead of a
categorical feature can prevent learning interactions with the
affected categories, etc., which could be a consideration.</p>
<p>Like other transforms based on target statistics, WoE can leak label
information into training data. Even in large datasets, if some
categories appear rarely, this may be a problem. Cranking up the
additive smoothing (<a href="https://contrib.scikit-learn.org/category_encoders/woe.html">"regularization"</a>) a bit might help, or
consider alternatives as in the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.09516">CatBoost paper</a> etc.</p>
<p>I think WoE is interesting in part because it's sort of on the
threshold between a simple pre-processing step and what might be
considered model stacking. It's a reminder that even “fancy” models
are just statistics with more steps; the mean is a model too.</p>
<hr>
<p>If you're working on credit scoring, maybe you'll also do feature
selection using “Information Value” (<a href="https://www.lexjansen.com/mwsug/2013/AA/MWSUG-2013-AA14.pdf">IV</a>). I don't know... It
reminds me a little bit of <a href="/2013/02/05/finding-the-mic-of-a-circle/">MIC</a>, almost? That's not quite right.
I'm not so interested in IV right now.</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210917-weight_of_evidence_is_logistic_coefficients/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210917-weight_of_evidence_is_logistic_coefficients/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>You can derive the formula for the determinant</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
<p><em>“Determinants are difficult, non-intuitive, and often defined
without motivation.” (Sheldon Axler, 1995)</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's <a href="https://smile.amazon.com/Linear-Algebra-Its-Applications-4th/dp/0030105676/">common</a> to talk about properties of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Determinant">determinant</a>, but
then treat its formula as almost coming from nowhere, focusing more on
<a href="https://www.mathsisfun.com/algebra/matrix-determinant.html">mnemonics</a> than meaning. I think it could be worth seeing that the
determinant's formula pops out easily in a common setting.</p>
<p>A matrix is a <a href="/20210915-flow_metaphor_for_matrix_multiplication/">transformation</a> that maps <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Origin_(mathematics)">origin</a> to origin. If a
matrix happens to map anything <em>else</em> to the origin, then that matrix
isn't invertible, because no inverse can map the origin back to two
different points. So we seek a solution to a system of equations.</p>
<p>\[ \begin{bmatrix} a &amp; b \\ c &amp; d \end{bmatrix}
    \begin{bmatrix} x \\ y \end{bmatrix} =
    \begin{bmatrix} 0 \\ 0 \end{bmatrix} \]</p>
<p>Eliminating \( x \) and \( y \) (<a href="#solution">example solution below</a>)
yields the familiar \( ad - bc = 0 \). That is, if \( ad - bc = 0
\), there's some \( x \) and \( y \) (not both zero) that the
matrix maps to the origin, and so the matrix is not invertible. The
determinant is \( ad - bc \).</p>
<p>I worked through this also for the three-by-three case and was
satisfied to recover the usual expression. There's probably a deeper
proof or other connection to more linear algebra, but I don't recall
ever being taught any rationale at all for the determinant taking the
form it does, so I was just pleased that it's as straightforward as
this to show at this level. It's slower, but if you happen to forget
the formula for the determinant, you can always work it out again this
way!</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="solution" href="#solution">Example solution</a></h3>
<p>The matrix equation above is equivalent to Equations 1 and 2.</p>
<p>\[ ax + by = 0 \tag{1} \]</p>
<p>\[ cx + dy = 0 \tag{2} \]</p>
<p>Solving Equation 1 for \( x \) produces Equation 3.</p>
<p>\[ x = - \frac{b}{a} y \tag{3} \]</p>
<p>Substituting Equation 3 into Equation 2 yields Equation 4.</p>
<p>\[ - \frac{cb}{a}y + dy = 0 \tag{4} \]</p>
<p>Multiplying by \( a \), dividing by \( y \), and reordering then
recovers the familiar form of the determinant in Equation 5.</p>
<p>\[ ad - bc = 0 \tag{5} \]</p>
<hr>
<p>If I was just sleeping through linear algebra, please let
<a href="/aaron/">me</a> know what I missed! Also let me know if there are any
problems with or alternatives to this method! Thanks!</p>
<p>The quote at top from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheldon_Axler">Axler</a> is from his 1995 paper,
<a href="https://www.axler.net/DwD.html">Down with Determinants!</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks to Erica for helpful feedback!</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210915-you_can_devive_the_formula_for_the_determinant/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210915-you_can_devive_the_formula_for_the_determinant/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The flow metaphor for matrix multiplication</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
<p><em>“I cannot believe that anything so ugly as multiplication of
matrices is an essential part of the scheme of nature.” (Arthur
Eddington, 1936)</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Even <a href="https://smile.amazon.com/Linear-Algebra-Its-Applications-4th/dp/0030105676/">Strang</a> introduces matrix multiplication by saying “there is
only one possible rule, and I am not sure who discovered it. It makes
everything work.” This is not satisfying or helpful for understanding.
The flow metaphor of graphical linear algebra makes matrix
multiplication seem natural and helps provide intuition for
understanding linear algebra.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#diagram">A simple diagram style</a></li>
<li><a href="#mult">Matrix multiplication</a></li>
<li><a href="#directions">Aligning directions</a></li>
<li><a href="#sources">Sources</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3><a name="diagram" href="#diagram">A simple diagram style</a></h3>
<p>The inputs <em>x</em> and <em>y</em> pass from left to right along the arrow
paths—getting multiplied by <em>a</em>, <em>b</em>, <em>c</em>, and <em>d</em>, respectively—and
then adding up to outputs <em>i</em> and <em>j</em>.</p>
<p><img alt="vector - matrix multiplication" src="vec_mat_mult.png"></p>
<p>The diagram is equivalent to the usual notation for a simple
vector-matrix multiplication.</p>
<p>\[ \begin{bmatrix} i \\ j \end{bmatrix} =
    \begin{bmatrix} a &amp; b \\ c &amp; d \end{bmatrix}
    \begin{bmatrix} x \\ y \end{bmatrix} =
    \begin{bmatrix} ax+by \\ cx+dy \end{bmatrix} \]</p>
<p>You can visualize inputs entering at the top and outputs going out the
side. For example, the <em>x</em> enters the 2-by-2 matrix over the <em>a</em>, and
then exits to the left to contribute <em>ax</em> to <em>i</em>. The <em>y</em> enters over
the <em>b</em> and exits to the left to contribute <em>by</em> to <em>i</em>.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="mult" href="#mult">Matrix multiplication</a></h3>
<p>To compose two matrix diagrams, follow the paths from inputs to
outputs. For example, to go from <em>x</em> to <em>u</em>, there's the <em>ae</em> path
that goes via <em>i</em>, and there's the <em>cf</em> path that goes via <em>j</em>, so the
simplified single path from <em>x</em> to <em>u</em> is <em>ae + cf</em>.</p>
<p><img alt="matrix - matrix multiplication" src="mat_mat_mult.png"></p>
<p>This is matrix multiplication that makes sense. After the input-output
behavior <a href="#diagram">above</a> is established, there's no other way for matrix
multiplication to come out.</p>
<p>\[ \begin{bmatrix} e &amp; f \\ g &amp; h \end{bmatrix}
    \begin{bmatrix} a &amp; b \\ c &amp; d \end{bmatrix} =
    \begin{bmatrix} ae+cf &amp; be+df \\ ag+ch &amp; bg+dh \end{bmatrix} \]</p>
<p>Why do the inner dimensions need to be the same for two matrices
you're multiplying? Because you have to match up outputs from one with
inputs for the other.</p>
<p>I find this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Where_Mathematics_Comes_From" title="Where Mathematics Comes From: How the Embodied Mind Brings Mathematics into Being">metaphor</a> really helpful, and I suspect it could help
people learning linear algebra for the first time as well. I think it
can be complementary with thinking about (and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLZHQObOWTQDPD3MizzM2xVFitgF8hE_ab" title="Essence of linear algebra, from 3Blue1Brown">visualizing</a>) vector
spaces. Exposition might proceed from introducing the idea of linear
combinations, to the diagram form, to the matrix notation, for
example.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="directions" href="#directions">Aligning directions</a></h3>
<p>I think it's a good thing that the diagrams make it obvious that order
matters. I'd rather have both the diagrams and matrix notation read
naturally from left to right, but I don't think everybody will change
how they write their linear algebra.</p>
<p>There's nothing special about the usual orientation. Both directions
are “on” by default. You can multiply a row vector and matrix, which
is like going right to left along the diagram for the matrix. You can
see the result isn't equivalent unless you transpose.</p>
<p>Transpose is the operation that swaps inputs with outputs For example,
\( (A B)^T = B^T A^T \). Visualize rotating two connected pieces of
pipe.</p>
<p>For a given order, sometimes it feels more natural to think about
going left to right rather than right to left. For example, in the \(
y = X \beta \) of linear regression, it feels better to me to think
of moving a row of the data matrix \( X \) through the coefficient
transformation \( \beta \), rather than thinking of the data \( X
\) as transforming the coefficients. Either way.</p>
<p>Note also that a column vector is not the same as a row vector, and
neither are the same as a vector. We probably shouldn't say a vector
<em>is</em> any particular matrix.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="sources" href="#sources">Sources</a></h3>
<p>I started thinking about this based on §3.2.2.4 in Spivak's <em>Category
Theory for the Sciences</em>. A complete, rigorous formulation as
Graphical Linear Algebra is nicely introduced in
<a href="https://graphicallinearalgebra.net/">Sobocinski's blog</a>. The best brief introduction I've seen is in a
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ptWK8ehQvyw&amp;t=3379s">presentation from Paixão</a>. (Thanks to Spivak and Sobocinski for
helpful pointers over email as well!)</p>
<p>The quote at top from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Eddington">Sir Eddington</a> about the ugliness of matrix
multiplication is from page 36 of his <em>Relativity Theory of Electrons
and Protons</em>, published in 1936 by Cambridge University Press, as
quoted in Macedo and Oliveira's <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1312.4818">Typing linear algebra</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“So the way we normally teach linear algebra to students is we write
down the formula for multiplying a matrix. Where does this formula
come from? I mean everyone learns it in first year, right, so we
don't question it, but it's actually very difficult to explain. I
mean I have to teach linear algebra to first-year students and, you
know, it takes them quite a bit of time to get it. And they learn
it, they get it by memorizing, you know, these kinds of algorithms
in their heads, but this is not the way we should teach maths. We
shouldn't teach maths, you know, by telling people to memorize
algorithms.” (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yHUp23AyF2A">Sobocinski</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210915-flow_metaphor_for_matrix_multiplication/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210915-flow_metaphor_for_matrix_multiplication/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Didau's 2019 book: Plagiarism and one main bad idea</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Former English teacher David Didau seems to have <a href="#plagiarism">plagiarised</a>
Wikipedia in his book called <em>Making kids cleverer</em>. At least it's
less into eugenics than his <a href="/20210914-david_didaus_2015_book_endorses_eugenics/" title="David Didau's 2015 book endorses eugenics">older book</a>. The main bad idea is a
central desire to shape curriculum so as to perpetuate existing
systems of power.</p>
<p>Didau's titular thesis is that the goal of schools is to make kids
cleverer, in the sense of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fluid_and_crystallized_intelligence">crystallized intelligence</a>, by teaching
knowledge, broadly construed. When it comes time to discuss <em>which</em>
knowledge, he pivots from arguing in support of cleverness to arguing
in support of dead white men on the grounds that this knowledge is
culturally valued—implicitly, valued by the culture he values.</p>
<p>I think it's <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2015/07/what-every-american-should-know/397334/">possible</a> to make an argument for some shared
knowledge, in the tradition of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E._D._Hirsch">Hirsch</a>, but I think it's a
different argument than arguing for knowledge that best helps students
think more effectively in the sense of moving toward a global maximum.
Similarly, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lindy_effect">Lindy effect</a> is about longevity, but not
necessarily quality. I think it would be much more interesting to look
at curriculum design by taking seriously the idea of giving students
the best mental toolkit possible. This is not what Didau does.</p>
<p>Didau discusses the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flynn_effect">Flynn effect</a>, and subscribes to the
"scientific spectacles" interpretation that general skills with
scientific abstraction explain increases in average IQ over time, but
at the same time argues one-sidedly for teaching concrete knowledge,
not general skills.</p>
<p>I do think that students can and probably should learn and remember
much more, generally, than they sometimes do, but Didau is a
problematic advocate, and I don't think his obsession with IQ is
useful.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cleverer_cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>While this is always the case, I feel like it's especially important
with a book like this for me to point out that selected quotes below
do not indicate my agreement with or support for any particular quote.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Over the course of this book, I will explain that, unlike many
other qualities we might value, intelligence has the advantages of
being malleable, measurable and meaningful." (page 7)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"By 'making cleverer' what I really mean, of course, is raising
intelligence—increasing children's intellectual capacity." (page 7)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Arthur Scargill, tub-thumping leader of the National Union of
Mineworkers, who led the opposition to Margaret Thatcher's struggle
to break the power of the trade unions, wrote, "My father still
reads the dictionary every day. He says your life depends on your
power to master words."" (page 9)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Trying to develop children's ability by teaching generic skills
directly is fundamentally unfair. Children with higher fluid
intelligence and those from more advantaged backgrounds will be
further privileged." (page 11)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This is the central thesis of the book: more knowledge equals more
intelligence." (page 11)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It's my view that '21st century skills' depend on knowing things
rather than on simply being able to look stuff up on the internet."
(page 12)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Developing children's character depends ont on attempting to
explicitly teach some ephemeral set of 'non-cognitive' skills but on
a combination of high expectations, accountability and modeling. As
Kalenze suggests, probably the best way to teach resilience is to
give children challenging work to do; the best way to teach respect
and politeness is to model it; and the best way to teach children
how to be functional, happy citizens is to set up systems which hold
them to account for their behaviour." (page 25)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"[Kevin] Laland points out that "Humanity's success is sometimes
attributed to our cleverness, but culture is actually what makes us
smart. Intelligence is not irrelevant of course, but what singles
out our species is an ability to pool our insights and knowledge and
build on each other's solutions."" (page 43)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Some children may be born with a greater capacity for solving
problems and thinking critically than others. These children are
lucky. At the same time, some children will possess more (and more
useful) knowledge of the world on which to apply these skills. These
children will tend to be from more privileged backgrounds. What
happens in school matters far less to both these groups of children
than it does to the less fortunate and the less advantaged. The
killer argument against a curriculum that focuses on 21st century
skills—or any other kind of generic competencies—is that it is
inherently iniquitous." (page 45)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The purpose of schools, as much as anything else, is to provide an
environment where children are made to attend to what they would
otherwise prefer to avoid." (page 53)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... the position I will advance in this book is that intelligence
is as much a product of what we know as it is a mechanism for
acquiring knowledge." (page 57)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Although we might perceive some children to be more 'able' than
others, this is unimportant because there's not really anything we
can do about it. We can, however, do an awful lot about developing
the quantity and quality of what children know." (page 60)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"While correlation is not proof that one thing causes another,
causation is implied." (page 65)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This follows shortly after a section called "Correlation ≠ causation"...</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://www.danielnettle.org.uk/download/023.pdf">Intelligence and class mobility in the British population</a> by
Nettle is cited on page 67.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Using the environment to increase crystallised intelligence is
central to making kids cleverer; fluid intelligence, and its
associated individual differences, is largely a distraction." (page
77)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://thepsychologist.bps.org.uk/volume-11/edition-2/can-iq-change">Can IQ change?</a> by Howe is cited on page 77.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The difference of natural talents in different men is, in reality,
much less than we are aware of ... The difference between the most
dissimilar characters, between a philosopher and a common street
porter, for example, seems to arise not so much from nature as from
habit, custom, and education." (page 85, quoting Adam Smith, The
Wealth of Nations)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://www.aft.org/periodical/american-educator/spring-2013/schooling-makes-you-smarter">Schooling Makes You Smarter: What Teachers Need to Know about IQ</a>
by Nisbett is cited on page 88. Decent?</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/14629696/">Socioeconomic status modifies heritability of IQ in young children</a>
by Turkheimer et al. is cited on page 89.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="http://www1.udel.edu/educ/gottfredson/reprints/1997mainstream.pdf">Mainstream Science on Intelligence: An Editorial With 52 Signatories, History, and Bibliography</a> by Gottfredson is cited on page 95.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17100793/">Black Americans reduce the racial IQ gap: evidence from standardization samples</a>
by Dickens and Flynn is cited on page 97.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The IQ score of the same person taking a test on different days
would produce a correlation of about 0.87." (pages 100-101)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And this is <em>good</em> reliability? Hmm.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Whether or not this [set of recommendations for schools] results in
a measurable increase in IQ is largely irrelevant. I think we can
all agree that intellectual curiosity and a lifelong love of
learning are things we want for all children, and these suggestions
seems like a reasonable bet for getting what we want." (page 111)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But the title of the book is "Making kids cleverer"... that was the
whole goal you were working on!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The rule seems to be that education raises crystallised
intelligence but not fluid intelligence." (page 118)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a href="http://www.iapsych.com/iqmr/fe/LinkedDocuments/wongupparaj2015.pdf">A Cross-Temporal Meta-Analysis of Raven's Progressive Matrices: Age groups and developing versus developed countries</a> by Wongupparaj et al. is cited on page 128.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/115/26/6674">Flynn effect and its reversal are both environmentally caused</a> by Bratsberg and Rogeberg is referenced on page 129.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It's much more likely that a growth mindset follows from
experiencing success." (page 131)</p>
<p>"As we've seen, motivation is a product of being successful." (page
267)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The earlier bit has no reference. The later cites <a href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.1056.1518&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf">The Relation of Academic Self-Concept to Motivation among University EFL Students</a>, but that paper is reporting correlation, not causation. The closest they get to causation is actually in the reverse direction:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"results support numerous research findings that academic
self-concept is an important determinant of students’ academic
performance"</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Beliefs about the malleability of basic ability appear to be
largely irrelevant: achievement is all about work." (page 135)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"However, if you want to, you can take an A level <a href="https://www.cambridgeinternational.org/images/164766-2016-syllabus.pdf">course</a> in
thinking skills." (140)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_acceleration">Cognitive Acceleration through Science Education (CASE)</a>"
(page 140)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The main reason children end up not learning what they're taught in
school isn't that they're not capable of remembering it; it's that
their teachers don't sufficiently value kids knowing stuff and don't
use the sorts of consolidation strategies which would help them to
remember." (page 157)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I have to show you how to use a comma in a wide variety of contexts
and then get you to practise writing correctly punctuated
sentences." (page 179)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So his focus on "knowledge" includes skills and application; not just
memorization.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The general rule is that expert knowledge always trumps raw
ability." (page 180)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Knowledge is most truly flexible when it is automatised." (page
183)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>On page 183, Didau references a student's test response as "empty and
worthless". His book doesn't include the question prompt visible in
<a href="https://i2.wp.com/www.learningspy.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Screen-Shot-2016-11-09-at-15.12.38.png">the original</a>. With that context, the answer doesn't seem so crazy
to me. Doesn't seem like a very good question, really.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"So what does it mean to be skilled at making inferences? Nothing:
it is indistinguishable from being knowledgeable." (page 186)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We are unable to think with anything that we are dependent on
looking up." (page 191)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It's only when people ask us to explain what we think we know that
we find out whether we know it." (page 197)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Many references to Michael Young's "powerful knowledge" idea. Here's
one <a href="https://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/EJ1085994.pdf">applied explainer</a> I found. I also stumbled on this
<a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/323587483_The_Weakness_of_Powerful_Knowledge">critique</a>, which includes in its abstract: "The first part of the
article focuses on the definitional connection that Young makes
between 'powerful knowledge' and systematic relationships between
concepts. It argues that most of the school subjects that Young sees
as providing 'powerful knowledge' fall short on this requirement."</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Being able to quote Shakespeare or knowing Pythagoras' theorem may
seem like trivia, but it enables us to access society in a way which
would be impossible if we didn't know any of this." (page 209)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"One much chewed bone of contention is who gets to decide what
knowledge children should learn. The assumption seems to be that
there's some shadowy elite inflicting their preferences on the rest
of us. This is nonsense. No one chooses; we all choose. No one
person knows enough to make this choice but collectively we have
access to the vast accumulation of human culture. The most important
things to know are those things that last and which most influence
other cultural developments; those things that inspire the most
'conversations' backwards and forwards through time and across
space; those things that allow us to trace our cultural inheritance
through threads of thought from the discoveries of modern science
and the synthesis of modern art back to their ancient origins."
(page 210)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is a mess on multiple levels. Leaving aside the most obvious
issues around who he means by "we", he's abandoned his original claim
of arguing for making children cleverer: lasting a long time and being
culturally popular does not imply useful for thought, and then we're
back to who he means when he says "our cultural inheritance".</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"On the face of it, building a curriculum around the thoughts and
deeds of historically marginalised groups looks like a really good
idea. Who wouldn't want children to know about the achievements of
women and people of colour? The trouble is, this isn't shared
knowledge. It doesn't allow access to the 'knowledge of power', and,
crucially, it doesn't provide much cultural capital." (page 211)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What happened to making children cleverer? Say, by giving them access
to the powerful idea that everyone can contribute to society, not just
historically dominant (not to say oppressive) people?</p>
<p>Maybe he's arguing against a curriculum based <em>only</em> on historically
marginalised groups, to the exclusion of his buddy Shakespeare, say?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Does it add to children's knowledge of what others in society
consider to be valuable?" (page 218)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is the <em>first</em> in Didau's list of desiderata for what to teach.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The epistemology of most sciences, for example, is often based upon
experimentation and discovery and, since this is so, experimentation
and discovery should be apart of any curriculum aimed at 'producing'
future scientists. But this does not mean that experimentation and
discovery should also be the basis for curriculum organization and
learning-environment designing." (quoting Paul Kirschner, page 223)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think the opposite (not teaching students <em>about</em> experimentation
and discovery, and letting them try it <em>at least a little</em>) is also a
mistake.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We've already seen that the best way to learn the solutions to
problems is not by solving problems. Problem solving is the means by
which new knowledge might be added to the domain; it is not an
effective means of learning the knowledge already within the
domain." (page 224)</p>
<p>"Solving problems is an inefficient way to get better at problem
solving." (page 236)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This sounds very strange from a math teacher's perspective, where the
goal is often to teach students <em>to solve problems</em>, and some even say
the only way to learn it is to solve problems. Here's Lockhart:
"Mental acuity of any kind comes from solving problems yourself, not
from being told how to solve them."</p>
<hr>
<p>Didau's second requirement for a curriculum is that it is "Culturally
rich. (Does the selected content conform to shared cultural agreements
of what is considered valuable to know?)" (page 224)</p>
<p>On page 225 he summarizes "Some knowledge is more culturally rich than
other knowledge — that is, more valued within society."</p>
<p>There is a separate case to be made, maybe, for knowing what other
people know so that you can communicate with them, walk the halls of
power, etc. But it is not, in my opinion, the same as a case for some
knowledge making you cleverer. The argument that historically dominant
knowledge is the best knowledge is problematic.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As experts, we often assume that others share the same background
knowledge as us and so it often goes unsaid. And where expert
knowledge is stated, all too often it isn't understood. Experts are
unaware of the extent of their knowledge and end up speaking in
maxims. As we saw in Chapter 7, such maxims are easily understood by
other experts but are meaningless to novices. Where a novice will be
confused and frustrated by gaps in explanation, an expert fills them
within even realising they're doing it. Such is the curse of
knowledge. This lack of insight into the source of expertise can
lead us into neglecting the teaching of the vital nuts and bolts on
which our expert performances depend." (page 234)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It's worth noting that we can't create mental representations just
through study — we have to get our hands dirty by trying to do the
thing we want to improve at." (page 240)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3><a name="plagiarism" href="#plagiarism">Plagiarism</a></h3>
<p>I happened to look up the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expertise_reversal_effect">expertise reversal effect</a> on Wikipedia.
I'll put in bold parts that correspond word for word.</p>
<p>Here's what Didau's book includes on page 245:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"<strong><em>The worked-example effect</em></strong> — <strong>worked examples</strong> (<strong>a problem
statement followed by a step-by-step demonstration of how to solve
it</strong>) <strong>are often contrasted with open-ended problem solving in
which the learner is responsible for providing the step-by-step
solution.</strong> Although novices <strong>benefit more from studying structured
worked examples than from solving problems on their own, as
knowledge increases, open-ended problem solving becomes more
effective.</strong>"</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here's Wikipedia:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Interactions between levels of knowledge and <strong>the worked-example
effect</strong>: <strong>Worked examples</strong> provide <strong>a problem statement followed
by a step-by-step demonstration of how to solve it</strong>. Worked
examples <strong>are often contrasted with open-ended problem solving in
which the learner is responsible for providing the step-by-step
solution.</strong> Low-knowledge learners <strong>benefit more from studying
structured worked</strong>-out <strong>examples than from solving problems on
their own</strong>. However, <strong>as knowledge increases, open-ended problem
solving becomes</strong> the <strong>more effective</strong> learning activity."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think a teacher grading a paper would have to call this plagiarism.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/43549795">Domain-Specific Knowledge and Why Teaching Generic Skills Does Not Work</a> by André Tricot and John Sweller is cited on page 245.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We should always remember that novices are not less intelligent,
they are less knowledgeable. Everyone gets cleverer the more they
know and the more they practise." (page 246)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The point of these desirable difficulties is to confront us with
the illusion of knowledge and reveal the true extent of our
ignorance." (page 254)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"If students simply struggle they will learn to hate school. If they
struggle too much, or too soon, this will also be undesirable.
Struggle is only desirable after success has been encoded." (page
254)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<em>The point is not that children should sink or swim, it's that they
should all swim.</em>" (page 255)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>"Encode success.</li>
<li>Promote internalisation.</li>
<li>Increase challenge.</li>
<li>Repeat." (page 255)</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Developing good explanations and accurate analogies is probably the
key area of subject specialist knowledge teachers most need to
develop." (page 257)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Attempting to follow along in their own copy of a text while
simultaneously having to listen as the text is read aloud is
impossible. Children are forced to task switch between the printed
material and the sound of the teacher's voice, meaning they lose
track of what it is they're supposed to be reading and remember far
less than if they had either read or listened without trying to do
both at once." (page 261)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is presented without citation. It would be interesting if it was
supported by some evidence. I feel like I remember plenty of following
along in texts while others read in my early education at least, and I
don't recall it being difficult. References welcome.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"And thinking about what we teach is enhanced by remembering that
our aim is to help children become more creative, be better problem
solvers, think more critically and be more collaborative." (page
269)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Some knowledge is both more powerful (allows for thinking more
thoughts) and more culturally rich (has a higher cultural value)
than other kinds of knowledge; as such, it results in more useful
schemas." (page 276)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here at least he recognizes a distinction.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210914-didaus_2019_book_plagiarism_and_one_main_bad_idea/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210914-didaus_2019_book_plagiarism_and_one_main_bad_idea/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>David Didau's 2015 book endorses eugenics</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The most salient thing about Didau's <em>What if everything you knew
about education was wrong?</em> turns out to be that it has an appendix by
<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2020/feb/17/andrew-sabisky-boris-johnsons-ex-adviser-in-his-own-words">Andrew Sabisky</a> which recommends as an "excellent and readable
introduction to behavior genetics" an <a href="https://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/ED023722.pdf">infamous article</a> by
eugenicist <a href="https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/extremist-files/individual/arthur-jensen">Arthur Jensen</a>, among other more and less explicitly
racist, backward things.</p>
<p>This harmful propaganda was not only published, but also hasn't been
corrected since. The book is still for sale. Didau's <a href="https://learningspy.co.uk/featured/have-you-read-the-wrongbook/">site</a> still
says "Andrew Sabisky has elegantly debunked a series of the most
enduring edu-myths about intelligence" in it. While in a
<a href="/20210914-didaus_2019_book_plagiarism_and_one_main_bad_idea/">later book</a> Didau describes eugenics as "an unpleasant and
inherently racist ideology" (page 96) he hasn't disavowed the contents
of his earlier book, including when asked directly (<a href="https://twitter.com/planarrowspace/status/1432060069961736204">1</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/planarrowspace/status/1433458397647708163">2</a>).</p>
<p>Didau's chapters themselves dog-whistle a little more subtly, as when
he smirks at political correctness by referencing an
<a href="https://metro.co.uk/2008/06/20/dont-brainstorm-take-a-thought-shower-204354/">obscure incident</a> (page 76) or (in his <a href="/20210914-didaus_2019_book_plagiarism_and_one_main_bad_idea/">later book</a>) disparages a
feminist paper without considering its contents (page 204).</p>
<p>The book otherwise advocates for explicit instruction and trying to
get kids to remember things via, for example, spaced repetition. Didau
supports a knowledge-rich curriculum like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E._D._Hirsch">Hirsch</a> and wants
everybody to stop hassling teachers so much. His thinking here reminds
me of a <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/iq-bell-curve-midwit">meme</a> from
<a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/F6ZTtBXn2cFLmWPdM/seven-years-of-spaced-repetition-software-in-the-classroom-1">Seven Years of Spaced Repetition Software in the Classroom</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="cartoon" src="just_show_em_stuff.jpg"></p>
<p>Approach with caution.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="eugenics_book_cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>While this is always the case, I feel like it's especially important
with a book like this for me to point out that selected quotes below
do not indicate my agreement with or support for any particular quote.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"To make things even more challenging for us as learners and/or
teachers, conditions of instruction or practice that appear to
result in rapid progress and learning can fail to produce good
long-term retention of skills and knowledge, or transfer of such
skills or knowledge to new situations where they are relevant,
whereas other conditions that pose challenges for the learner — and
appear to slow the learning process — can enhance such long-term
retention and transfer. Conditions of the latter type, which I have
labelled "desirable difficulties", include spacing, rather than
massing, repeated study opportunities; interleaving, rather than
blocking, instruction or practice on the separate components of a
given task; providing intermittent, rather than continuous, feedback
to learners; varying the conditions of learning, rather than keeping
them constant and predictable; and using tests, rather than
re-presentations, as learning opportunities." (pages iv-v)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"These are the <em>threshold concepts</em> of the book:</p>
<ul>
<li>Seeing shouldn't always result in believing (Chapter 1).</li>
<li>We are all victims of cognitive bias (Chapter 2).</li>
<li>Compromise doesn't always result in effective solutions (Chapter
    4).</li>
<li>Evidence is not the same as proof (Chapter 5).</li>
<li>Progress is a gradual, non-linear process (Chapters 6 and 7).</li>
<li>Learning is invisible (Chapter 8).</li>
<li>Current performance is not only a poor indication of learning, it
    actually seems to prevent it (Chapters 8 and 9).</li>
<li>Forgetting aids learning (Chapter 9).</li>
<li>Experts and novices learn diffferently (Chapter 10).</li>
<li>Making learning more difficult can make it more durable (Chapter
    11)." (page 2)</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Because curriculum time is always limited, we need to decide which
is more important: teaching or learning." (page 3)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This leads us to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Na%C3%AFve_realism_(psychology)">naive realism</a> — the belief that our senses
provide us with an objective and reliable awareness of the world."
(page 16)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"For the most part 'anecdotal evidence' is an oxymoron." (page 18)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The fusion of these beliefs is <em>enactivism</em>: there really is an
objective reality out there, but we cannot perceive it directly.
Instead we share in the generation of meaning; we don't just
exchange information and ideas, we change the world by our
participation in it. We take the evidence of our senses and
construct our own individual models of the world. But because we
start with the same objective reality, our individual constructed
realities have lots of points of contact." (page 21)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I'm not sure that's quite what others mean by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enactivism">enactivism</a>...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This is what Michael Shermer calls "patternicity": the tendency to
find meaningful patterns in random noise." (page 26)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is citing "The Believing Brain: From Ghosts and Gods to Politics
and Conspiracies—How We Construct Beliefs and Reinforce Them as
Truths".</p>
<p>See also: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apophenia">apophenia</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Our inability to think statistically causes us to routinely
misinterpret what data tells us. In a survey of school results in
Pennsylvania, many of the top performing schools were very small.
Intuitively this makes sense — in a small school teachers will
better know their students and will be able to give much more
tailored support. This finding encouraged the Bill and Melinda Gates
Foundation to make a $1.7 billion investment in founding a string of
small schools. Sadly the project was a failure. The finding that
smaller schools do better was a confound; the worst schools in the
Pennsylvania survey were also small schools. Statistically small
schools are not better. In fact, larger schools tend to produce
better results due to the diversity of curriculum options they can
offer. OUr desire to find patterns and explanations trips us up. We
ignore the statistical fact that small populations tend to yield
more extreme results than larger populations, and we focus instead
on causes and narratives." (page 27)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This cites "Evidence That Smaller Schools Do Not Improve Student
Achievement" by Wainer and Zwerling.</p>
<hr>
<p>On page 55 he talks about the British system of "target grades", which
is surprising and weird to me. Every student gets some explicit target
grade for their big exams at the end of high school. Wacky. He cites a
<a href="https://othmarstrombone.wordpress.com/2014/07/18/how-to-eat-50-hot-dogs-in-12-minutes-and-why-setting-targets-may-hold-back-progress/">blog post</a>.</p>
<p>After talking to Jay about this, it's possible having "target grades"
isn't so different from how things often play out in the US, when
student performance on standardized tests sorts them into tracked
classes... Not exactly the same thing, but maybe not <em>so</em> foreign.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Assigning numerical values to our preferences and biases gives them
the power of data, but they're still just made up." (page 58)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The philosopher Bertrand Russell pointed out, "in the modern world
the stupid are cocksure while the intelligent are full of doubt"."
(page 62)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The citation is Russell's "<a href="https://russell-j.com/0583TS.HTM">The Triumph of Stupidity</a>".</p>
<hr>
<p>I hadn't heard of "thought-showering" instead of "brain-storming"...
The phrase seems to have had a <a href="https://metro.co.uk/2008/06/20/dont-brainstorm-take-a-thought-shower-204354/">short history</a>. The citation of
<a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1207/s15324834basp1201_1">Productivity Loss in Brainstorming Groups: A Meta-Analytic Integration</a>
is more relevant. (page 76)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Rushing students into situations where they are expected to behave
like experts misses the fact that they don't yet know enough to do
so. Simply making students work in groups will not create better
workers." (page 77)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The point of collaboration is that it opens us up to the ideas of
others. But so does reading books." (page 77)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"If the evidence tells us that teacher led instruction is an
effective way to teach and discovery learning is an ineffective way
of teaching (and it does), why would you do a bit of both?" (101)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That highly opinionated bit contrasts with this nearby selection:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Teaching cannot be child centered and teacher led at the same time.
You have to make a choice. I'm not arguing that one position is
better than the other, just that they are mutually exclusive." (page
102)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He's trying to make an argument here, and it might even be right, but
he isn't making it very well.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"My own suspicion is that most teachers put on a child-centered show
when observed and then revert to teaching from the front when the
classroom door is closed. The only real effect that being told
teaching should be relevant, active and collaborative has had is to
make us feel guilty for teaching." (page 109)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is quite a claim.</p>
<hr>
<p>On page 111, I was interested to see the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edgar_Dale#Cone_of_Experience">Cone of Experience</a>/"Learning Pyramid" ("people remember X% of what
they Y") debunked. I remember seeing a poster version back in middle
school, and I never questioned it. Didau cites
<a href="https://www.cisco.com/c/dam/en_us/solutions/industries/docs/education/Multimodal-Learning-Through-Media.pdf">Multimodal Learning Through Media</a>, which opens with a good
critique of the "Learning Pyramid" thing.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Making it harder to learn is more effective than making it easy."
(page 115)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Instead of endlessly seeking to find out new things, we should
think more carefully about the things we've already found out."
(page 127)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I like this, but maybe it's not an "instead of" but "in addition
to"...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It's not clear whether 'direct instruction' refers to generic
teacher-led whole-class teaching or Siegfried Engelmann's
<a href="https://www.nifdi.org/">Direct Instruction</a>, in which lessons are scripted and which
outperformed all other teaching methods in the largest and most
expensive education study ever undertaken, Project Follow Through."
(page 131)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If scripted lessons are so great, why is video not so great?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Education researcher and author Geoff Petty <a href="https://geoffpetty.com/geoffs-books/evidence-based-teaching-ebt/">says</a>, "This
strategy of top-down diktat does not work, it has been carefully
evaluated and it fails. So if you are forced to do “evidence based
teaching”, you are not doing Evidence Based Teaching! You are being
bullied with an ineffective management strategy!"" (page 133)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Coe has <a href="https://img1.wsimg.com/blobby/go/ede177f2-5088-4fee-a850-d64ccdf72d47/downloads/Improving%20Education%20Coe%20Inaugural%20June%202013.pdf?ver=1621348419849">suggested</a> this axiom: "Learning happens when people
have to think hard.""</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Understanding and recognizing the most important conceptual areas
of our subjects upon which all else rests might help us to make
better decisions about both what and how to teach." (page 164)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The notion of ability is as much about how we see ourselves and how
others see us as it is about intelligence." (page 172)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We want our students to have an understanding of the deep structure
of a domain of knowledge, but we have to be patient. If we want
someone to have an insight, simply telling them what the insight is
'meant to be' robs them of seeing it for themselves. Instead, we can
tell them as much about the surface features of a problem as we can
and wait for them to join our dots. Mimicry is a necessary waiting
room in the chaos of liminal space. Feeling frustrated that children
know, say, their times tables, but are unable to do long division,
is silly. As they learn more facts, see more examples and get more
practice, they will slowly but surely move towards an expert's
understanding of the subject." (page 201)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>For someone who doesn't like discovery learning, this seems similar to
discovery learning...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The path to mastery isn't smooth, but it becomes a lot less bumpy
when we accept that it's hard and that we're supposed to struggle."
(page 209)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Testing can (and should) include some of the tricks and techniques
we've been misusing and misunderstanding as Formative Assessment. In
fact, it doesn't really matter how we test students as long as our
emphasis changes. Testing should not be used primarily to assess the
efficacy of your teaching and students' learning; it should be used
as a powerful tool in your pedagogical armory to <em>help</em> them learn."
(page 234)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Trying harder makes a big difference. Getting students to
understand what they should be doing is hard enough, but motivating
them to actually do it is the master skill." (page 256)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>For something that's "the master skill", this topic isn't given much
attention... There is some though...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The fourth reason
[for students to decide to invest effort, "To improve their performance"]
is the one we should seek to develop. How can we give feedback which
harnesses students' desire to improve their performance? ... What we
want is for students to see their success as being directly causes
by their effort. ... The point of all this, as William concludes, is
for students to believe that "It's up to me" (internal) and "I can
do something about it" (stable)." (pages 259-261)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Quoting Dylan William:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"So, as a general rule, I advise teachers not to give feedback
unless the first 10 to 15 minutes of the next lesson is allocated to
students responding to the feedback." (page 267)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"One of my favorite models for classroom observation is the one
taken by Doug Lemov and the Uncommon Schools network. The idea is
ridiculously simple: you look at the data to find out which teachers
have the best results and then you observe them to find out what
they're doing. Lemov's teaching manual, <em>Teach Like A Champion</em>, is
a compendium of some of the strategies common to these über-teachers
which can be practiced and replicated by us mere mortals." (page
302)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As we know, children are complex and classrooms more complex still.
We're probably interested in more than students 'merely' acquiring
new skills and knowledge within the domains of the subjects we
teach. We may also have an interest in fostering a 'love of
learning' and turning students into 'lifelong learners'. Whatever
the current trend might be, we want our students to somehow be
changed and improved by their experiences in school." (page 309)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Quoting <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/1948550610385872" title="Deliberate Practice Spells Success: Why Grittier Competitors Triumph at the National Spelling Bee">Duckworth et al.</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Grittier spellers engaged in deliberate practice more so than their
less gritty counterparts, and hours of deliberate practice fully
mediated the prospective association between grit and spelling
performance." (page 310)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Quoting <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Craftsman_(book)">Richard Sennett</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"We share in common and in roughly equal measure the raw abilities
that allow us to become good craftsmen: it is the motivation and
aspiration for quality that takes people along different paths in
their lives. Social conditions shape these motivations." (page 320)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>(From here on is from Appendix 2: "Five myths about intelligence" by
Andrew Sabisky, who seems to be <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2020/feb/17/andrew-sabisky-boris-johnsons-ex-adviser-in-his-own-words">a monster</a>.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Differential psychology — the science that investigates the nature
and causes of differences between individuals in their cognition
..." (page 391)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Throughout the 19th century, most commentators on mental abilities
assumed they were independent — a school of thought called 'faculty
psychology'. [in the sense of multiple intelligences] Such a model
remained untested until an English psychologist, Charles Spearman,
found that boys' grades in school subjects were highly correlated;
the boys who excelled at math were likely to be better than average
in English and Latin. Spearman developed a novel statistical
technique called factor analysis to analyze his data and proposed
that one common factor, <em>g</em>, explained most of the variance in a
battery of mental tests, but that each subtest also had its own
specific variance (Spearman called this non-shared variation <em>s</em>
factor). Spearman's original finding has since been modified by
later analyses and the factors derived from analyses of mental tests
are best thought to fit into a pyramidal structure, with <em>g</em> at the
top (see Figure A2.1). The finding that all mental tests positively
inter-correlate is probably the most replicated result in all of
psychology, and factor analyses is now an extremely popular
statistical tool used widely across the social and biological
sciences." (pages 392-393)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<em>G</em> does not appear to be a chimerical statistical artefact, as has
sometimes been alleged by Stephen J. Gould and others, but a
biological reality fundamental to cognition." (page 393)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Sabisky references, as an "excellent and readable introduction to
behavior genetics", the article
<a href="https://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/ED023722.pdf">How much can we boost IQ and scholastic achievement?</a> by
<a href="https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/extremist-files/individual/arthur-jensen">Arthur Jensen</a>. So while Sabisky is a little racist and eugenicist
in his appendix, he's citing (and recommending, even) very racist,
very eugenicist sources.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The assumption is taken for granted that all groups are exactly
equal in their ability and that any differences between them result
from biased tests." (page 402)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I'm not commenting everywhere, but this is so egregious a straw man I
couldn't skip it.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The tests that best predict job performance also discriminate the
most against non-Asian ethnic minorities, and especially blacks. The
dilemma this gives rise to is known in industrial-organizational
psychology as the <em>diversity-validity trade-off</em>." (page 403)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Do we want to assess the intellectual ability of our students? Such
tests are certainly of great value to universities and even more to
many employers. Or do we want to assess the competence of our
teachers by making sure that our students have in fact learned, with
some reasonable proficiency, a core stock of knowledge that we value
as a society?" (page 406)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>I didn't know quite what "<a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/education-34538222">grammar school</a>" means in the UK...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Large, permanent individual differences in talent are a fact of
life and are not going to go away for the foreseeable future." (page
408)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210914-david_didaus_2015_book_endorses_eugenics/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210914-david_didaus_2015_book_endorses_eugenics/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Simple short number notation</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Scientific notation is great, but "67B" is easier for most people than
"6.7e10". I whipped up a quick Python function that does this for
numbers up into the trillions. It always gives you back four
characters, like this:</p>
<pre><code>                   1.1 -&gt; '  1 '
                  98.2 -&gt; ' 98 '
                 111.7 -&gt; '112 '
               9_876   -&gt; '9.9K'
          12_345_678   -&gt; ' 12M'
     123_456_789_012   -&gt; '123B'
 999_123_456_789_012   -&gt; '999T'</code></pre>

<p>Thousands as "K" might be a little unfamiliar for some audiences, but
overall I think this is pretty good, for example for labeling axes.
Here's the code:</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">def tdn(number):
    """Short (Three-Digit Number) string representation"""
    assert 0 &lt;= number &lt; 9.995e14, 'outside range of defined behavior'
    if number &lt; 1000:
        return f'{round(number):3d} '
    number /= 1000
    for symbol in 'KMBT':
        if number &gt;= 1000:
            number /= 1000
            continue
        if number &gt;= 10:
            return f'{number:3.0f}{symbol}'
        return f'{number:1.1f}{symbol}'
    return result</code></pre>

<p>There's probably a nicer way to do it; feedback (and pull requests
<a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/three_digit_numbers">on GitHub</a>) welcome!</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210908-simple_short_number_notation/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210908-simple_short_number_notation/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Spaced repetition is O(log n) sustainable</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>If you use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spaced_repetition">spaced repetition</a> software like <a href="https://apps.ankiweb.net/">Anki</a> for a long
time, will you have to spend more and more time studying every day?
Yes, but the increase is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_complexity#Logarithmic_time">logarithmic</a> with time, which is a very
slow increase. If you add ten cards a day, then after a year you do 85
reviews per day. After ten years, that goes to 118 reviews per day,
and even after 100 years, it's 152 reviews per day—still only half an
hour or so each day.</p>
<p>The major simplifying assumption here is that review delays double, so
that after <em>n</em> days, the number of days that are contributing their
cards to today's review is <em>log<sub>2</sub>(n)</em>.</p>
<p>Your review delays won't be exactly that, and you won't add cards
evenly across days. For me, the estimate is close but slightly high
after 336 days of using Anki.</p>
<p>The average number of cards added per day is an important
multiplicative factor; my average is currently 11.3 cards per day and
trending lower. It might be higher for full-time students, but I'd be
surprised if many people stayed much above ten cards per day over
multiple years. When you stop adding so many cards, daily reviews
decrease rapidly.</p>
<p>I think spaced repetition study could reasonably be a lifelong
practice, like daily exercise.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210908-spaced_repetition_is_o_log_n_sustainable/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210908-spaced_repetition_is_o_log_n_sustainable/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Try a table instead of a Pareto chart</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I thought <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_chart">Pareto charts</a> might be fine if they didn't use multiple
vertical axes, but I was wrong. Pareto charts have lots of problems,
especially with many items and long labels. Pareto chart information
is better presented horizontally, as in a table.</p>
<div style="display: flex; align-items: start;">
<img src="pareto_budget.png" width="49%">
<img src="table_budget.png" width="49%">
</div>

<p>The Pareto chart image at left is the same width as the table image
shown at right.</p>
<hr>
<ul>
<li><a href="#multi_vert">Multiple vertical axes?</a></li>
<li><a href="#cumulative_bad">The cumulative percentage line is bad</a></li>
<li><a href="#labeling_pie">Pie charts are also bad for labeling</a></li>
<li><a href="#labeling_bar">Stacked bar charts are also hard to label</a></li>
<li><a href="#label_bar">Bar charts: Hard to label</a></li>
<li><a href="#table">Just make a table</a></li>
<li><a href="#categories">Categories are problematic</a></li>
<li><a href="#change">Change over time?</a></li>
<li><a href="#data">Data for this example</a></li>
<li><a href="#code">Code for this example</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3><a name="multi_vert" href="#multi_vert">Multiple vertical axes?</a></h3>
<p>Here's an example I <a href="https://medium.com/swlh/pareto-chart-with-python-5200459ee65c">found</a> of a Pareto chart where both the
individual bars and cumulative line use all the vertical space, which
looks nice visually.</p>
<p><img alt="Pareto chart with two different vertical axes" src="multi_vertical_pareto_chart.png"></p>
<p>In my opinion the confusion introduced by having two different
vertical axes is unacceptable.</p>
<p>This particular example is especially egregious because the right hand
cumulative percentage scale starts at 20% rather than 0%, which makes
it look like the leftmost category somehow accounts for almost none of
the cumulative total.</p>
<p>This example also shows how text on visualizations can become a
disaster by getting tiny. Don't make people squint.</p>
<p>The problem of having two vertical scales isn't necessary; the same
scale can be used, and presented as both raw value and percent of
total. But often, this introduces a lot of whitespace.</p>
<p><img alt="Pareto chart with lots of whitespace" src="pareto_whitespace.png"></p>
<p>The vertical axis labels could be improved here, but the main visual
effect is to foreground the cumulative percentage line, squishing the
bars. Is the cumulative percentage line worth it?</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="cumulative_bad" href="#cumulative_bad">The cumulative percentage line is bad</a></h3>
<p>Ordering things by size is interesting and useful for understanding
what components are largest, but it isn't really a natural ordering.
It could change, for example. So while there is a cumulative value in
the sense of "the top 5 items account for X% of the total", these
values aren't cumulative in the sense of summing over a natural order
the way you might to get the probability of rolling a 3 or lower, for
example.</p>
<p>There's also no meaning to the cumulative value "between" two
categories, generally. Using a line to connect the cumulative sums
suggests a smoothness of transition which is misleading.</p>
<p>The main use you might put the cumulative line to is identifying the
number of categories that add up to some percentage of the total, like
50% or 80%. This leads immediately to trying to do this using the
figure's axes, which is clumsy. Better to include the values, and if
you do this via direct labeling, your figure is becoming a table with
awkward alignment.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="labeling_pie" href="#labeling_pie">Pie charts are also bad for labeling</a></h3>
<p>The main thing people love to hate about pie charts is the difficulty
we have interpreting relative sizes of pieces of pie, and this is
valid. But it's also a huge pain to label those slices.</p>
<p>If you take the easy way out with a separate legend, as in this
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Fy2010_spending_by_category.jpg">extreme example</a>, you create a miserable game of hide and seek for
the viewer.</p>
<p><img alt="horrible pie chart" src="horrible_pie.jpg"></p>
<p>This example struggles even to label the percentages of the tiny
slices, and matching labels to slices is very difficult.</p>
<p>Attempting direct labeling with a pie chart is better, as in this
<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Military_Expenditures_by_Country_2019.svg">example</a> comparing military spending.</p>
<p><img alt="labeled war pie" src="labeled_war_pie.png"></p>
<p>There are two reasons direct labeling is possible here: country names
tend to be short, and most countries get tossed into "Rest of World".
In general, pie chart labeling won't work as well as this.</p>
<p>And of course the problems with using a circular representation remain
as well.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="labeling_bar" href="#labeling_bar">Stacked bar charts are also hard to label</a></h3>
<p>A stacked bar chart should be better than a pie chart in that it
allows viewers to compare linear distances, but it's still hard to
label. I tried a couple different ways.</p>
<p>I tried mocking up direct labeling on a stacked bar, but I gave up
before I finished adding all the lines because it was just a
nightmare. Too many lines, too close together.</p>
<p><img alt="directly labeled stacked bar" src="direct_bar.png"></p>
<p>The alternative then is to use proximity. But what do you do with the
labels that won't fit?</p>
<p>Here's one clumsy answer, just stacking the labels once there isn't
space to put them in the right places. It starts to just look like a
table with wasted space.</p>
<p><img alt="some direct labeling on a bar" src="list_bar.png"></p>
<p>A variation puts all the unlabelable categories into a catch-all,
which I don't really love either.</p>
<p><img alt="catch-all on a bar" src="glom_bar.png"></p>
<p>The horizontal text is at least readable, and it isn't a pie chart,
but it's also still not really so easy to compare lengths between
segments at the top and the bottom of the stacked bar.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="label_bar" href="#label_bar">Bar charts: Hard to label</a></h3>
<p>With languages that write left-to-right or right-to-left, it's
difficult to label a bunch of vertical bars. Especially with longer
labels, it can get ridiculous.</p>
<p><img alt="as a Pareto chart" src="pareto_budget.png"></p>
<p>Arguably, a big part of the value of a Pareto chart <em>is the labels</em>
because they've been put in order so that the biggest factors come
first. Readability is important. The Pareto chart generally fails to
have highly readable labeling.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="table" href="#table">Just make a table</a></h3>
<p>A horizontal bar chart with the cumulative line dropped could make for
a better Pareto chart. You could adjust orientation and add numeric
labeling so that viewers can read off useful values. At this point
what you have is really a table with one column of <a href="https://support.google.com/docs/answer/3093289">SPARKLINE</a> bars.</p>
<p><img alt="as a table" src="table_budget.png"></p>
<p>Using a table lets you easily align data in columns for easy reference
and scanning, increasing information density without making an
irregular Where's Waldo of numbers.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="categories" href="#categories">Categories are problematic</a></h3>
<p>Categories are generally epiphenomena of human perception.</p>
<p>In this example, why is "Medicare" separate from "Health"? Why use the
divisions here and not others? Sometimes big categories here are
omitted by others as non-discretionary; why not do that?</p>
<p>Questions of this kind are probably a bigger deal than the
visualization you choose, but are outside scope here.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="change" href="#change">Change over time?</a></h3>
<p>Data is shown for a single year here, but changes over time are super
interesting. "Income security" is the top category for 2020, but
that's because of COVID-19: it was fifth for 2019. "National defense"
was second in 2019. I'm not sure what the best way to show these
changes over time; the <a href="https://datalab.usaspending.gov/americas-finance-guide/spending/trends/">trends</a> page from the data provider isn't
bad.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="data" href="#data">Data for this example</a></h3>
<p>The data is from <a href="https://www.usaspending.gov/">USAspending.gov</a>'s Data Lab
<a href="https://datalab.usaspending.gov/americas-finance-guide/spending/categories/">Federal Spending by Category and Agency</a>. I dropped "Offsetting
Revenue Collected But Not Attributed to Functions" on the grounds that
I don't understand how it's spending. Really I think their displays
are pretty good.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="code" href="#code">Code for this example</a></h3>
<p>A brief Python notebook is <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/pareto_chart">on GitHub</a>. I mocked some stuff up in a
<a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1hpaWIa7o0OvJkJZUQPotfGkvMxM548Gc6n5ruEZ8rTE/edit?usp=sharing">Google Slides deck</a>, and the main table is in a <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1o6fo5obvkJAUW-r12EAzqvmoNnEhd-Q05RUFMlq1xuw/edit?usp=sharing">Google Sheet</a>.
All of these are fairly clumsy and I'd love to find better ways of
doing this kind of thing.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20210907-try_a_table_instead_of_a_pareto_chart/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20210907-try_a_table_instead_of_a_pareto_chart/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
