<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>What should be in your regression?</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>If you're fitting a model in the hopes of better understanding the
effect of <em>x</em> on <em>y</em>, then including another predictor variable <em>z</em>
could be necessary, or could be harmful. Deciding whether to control
for <em>z</em> depends on identifying how the variables are causally related.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#direct">Simple direct causation</a></li>
<li><a href="#mediated">Mediated causation</a>: don't control for <em>z</em></li>
<li><a href="#common_cause">Common cause (confounding)</a>: control for <em>z</em></li>
<li><a href="#common_effect">Common effect (collider)</a>: don't control for <em>z</em></li>
<li><a href="#complicated">More complicated cases</a></li>
</ul>
<p>These examples vary the data generating process (which isn't possible
in practice) in order to illustrate what happens in each case when you
do or don't control for <em>z</em>.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.r-project.org/about.html">R</a> code uses random <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Normal_distribution">normal</a> data, additive relationships,
and linear regression. With real data and processes, other modeling
methods may be more appropriate.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="direct"></a>Simple direct causation</h3>
<p><img alt="x -&gt; y" src="direct.png"></p>
<p>Say the reality is that <em>x</em> influences <em>y</em> (not the reverse) and no
other variables are involved.</p>
<!-- set.seed(99) -->

<pre><code class="language-r">x = rnorm(100)
y = x + rnorm(100)
summary(lm(y ~ x))
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  x            1.07747    0.11931   9.031 1.53e-14 ***</code></pre>

<p>The estimate of 1.077 is close to the true value of 1. The very low
p-value (with three stars) indicates confidence that there is a
non-random relationship between <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="mediated"></a>Mediated causation</h3>
<p><img alt="x -&gt; z -&gt; y" src="mediated.png"></p>
<p>Here, the reality is that <em>x</em> influences <em>z</em>, which then influences
<em>y</em>.</p>
<p>In this case, <em>x</em> really does influence <em>y</em>, so you're right to look
for the relationship. And it might be tempting to control for <em>z</em>,
perhaps because of a desire to &#8220;isolate&#8221; the effect of <em>x</em>.</p>
<p>If you include <em>z</em> in your regression, the desired estimate of the
effect of <em>x</em> will disappear.</p>
<!-- set.seed(101) -->

<pre><code class="language-r">x = rnorm(100)
z = x + rnorm(100)
y = z + rnorm(100)
summary(lm(y ~ x + z))
##               Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  x           -0.146874   0.135695  -1.082    0.282
##  z            1.127586   0.087819  12.840   &lt;2e-16 ***</code></pre>

<p>Including <em>z</em> makes it appear that <em>x</em> has no significant influence on
<em>y</em>, which is incorrect.</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">summary(lm(y ~ x))
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  x            1.11140    0.15343   7.244    1e-10 ***</code></pre>

<p>Leaving <em>z</em> out gives a good estimate of the effect of <em>x</em>.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="common_cause"></a>Common cause (confounding)</h3>
<p><img alt="x &lt;- z -&gt; y" src="common_cause.png"></p>
<p>In this case, the reality is that <em>z</em> influences both <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>,
which are otherwise unrelated.</p>
<p>This is an extreme example, in the sense that you'd be totally wrong
to look for an effect of <em>x</em> on <em>y</em> in this case. The case where
there's also a direct connection between <em>x</em> and <em>y</em> is similar, but
for simplicity this example doesn't have one.</p>
<p>If you don't include <em>z</em> in your regression, the relationship between
<em>x</em> and <em>y</em> could be misleading.</p>
<!-- set.seed(103) -->

<pre><code class="language-r">z = rnorm(100)
x = z + rnorm(100)
y = z + rnorm(100)
summary(lm(y ~ x))
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  x            0.56257    0.10365   5.428 4.14e-07 ***</code></pre>

<p>There is a relationship between <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>, but it's because of <em>z</em>,
not because of <em>x</em>. The regression result ignoring <em>z</em> could easily be
misinterpreted.</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">summary(lm(y ~ x + z))
##             Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
## x            0.03608    0.10590   0.341    0.734
## z            1.05814    0.13556   7.806 6.93e-12 ***</code></pre>

<p>With <em>z</em> in the model, the result correctly indicates that <em>z</em> is the
influencing factor.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="common_effect"></a>Common effect (collider)</h3>
<p><img alt="x -&gt; z &lt;- y" src="collider.png"></p>
<p>Here, the reality is that <em>x</em> and <em>y</em> are completely unrelated, but
they both influence <em>z</em>.</p>
<p>As with <a href="#common_cause">common cause</a>, it's more interesting when
there's also a direct connection between <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>, but the behavior
is similar and this example keeps things simpler.</p>
<p>Somewhat surprisingly, if you include <em>z</em> in your regression, you'll
see evidence that both <em>z</em> and <em>x</em> influence <em>y</em>.</p>
<!-- set.seed(105) -->

<pre><code class="language-r">x = rnorm(100)
y = rnorm(100)
z = x + y + rnorm(100)
summary(lm(y ~ x + z))
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  x           -0.46951    0.08831  -5.317 6.76e-07 ***
##  z            0.44439    0.04971   8.939 2.62e-14 ***</code></pre>

<p>This is a case of &#8220;<a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/3192123_Explaining_explaining_away%27">explaining away</a>.&#8221;</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">summary(lm(y ~ x))
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&gt;|t|)
##  x           -0.11308    0.10586  -1.068    0.288</code></pre>

<p>Without <em>z</em> in the regression, the result correctly indicates no
relationship between <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="complicated"></a>More complicated cases</h3>
<p>With a more complex causal graph, it may not be obvious what you need
to control for, or it may be that conventional methods of control
aren't sufficient. Methods like Judea Pearl's do-calculus might be
helpful.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thanks to Erica Blom, Ben Klemens, and Jonathan Robinson for providing
helpful feedback.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200912-what_should_be_in_your_regression/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200912-what_should_be_in_your_regression/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>GPU environment variables</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><code>CUDA_DEVICE_ORDER</code> can default to <code>FASTEST_FIRST</code>, which may not
match the order you see in <code>nvidia-smi</code> output. Use
<code>CUDA_DEVICE_ORDER=PCI_BUS_ID</code>.</p>
<p>Set <code>CUDA_VISIBLE_DEVICES=2</code> to only run on GPU 2. That GPU will then
be accessed as GPU 0, not GPU 2.</p>
<p>When using TensorFlow, you <a href="https://www.tensorflow.org/guide/gpu#limiting_gpu_memory_growth">can</a> set
<code>TF_FORCE_GPU_ALLOW_GROWTH=true</code> to keep TF from preemptively claiming
all the GPU memory. However, in my tests (with the older version 1.14)
TF still allocates way more memory than it really needs, so this
setting doesn't help much in practice.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200910-gpu_environment_variables/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200910-gpu_environment_variables/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>A Mathematician's Lament, by Lockhart</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://www.maa.org/external_archive/devlin/LockhartsLament.pdf">Lockhart&#8217;s Lament</a> (and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Mathematician%27s_Lament">Exultation</a>!) is <a href="https://smile.amazon.com/Mathematicians-Lament-School-Fascinating-Imaginative/dp/1934137170/">available</a> as a
beautiful little book. It&#8217;s in the familiar territory of balancing
doing original things versus learning what others have done, but he&#8217;s
probably right that many people don&#8217;t really know what <em>doing</em> math
is. I particularly identify with his emphasis on understanding and
good explanations.</p>
<p>Lockhart&#8217;s recommendation to do math for the pleasure of it reminds me
of McCullough&#8217;s similar thought on history:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"It should be taught for pleasure: The pleasure of history, like art
or music or literature, consists of an expansion of the experience
of being alive, which is what education is largely about."
(<a href="https://imprimis.hillsdale.edu/knowing-history-and-knowing-who-we-are/">McCullough</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is important to remember: People don&#8217;t really do things they
don&#8217;t enjoy. Pleasure can be found in most things, but it can be more
or less difficult to find. Finding it is important.</p>
<p>Lockhart correctly identifies the epistemology of math, in my opinion.
He points out that most people don&#8217;t need or use the math that&#8217;s
currently taught in schools, so losing it wouldn't be a great loss.
Carpenters don&#8217;t use trigonometry. Have you ever used the quadratic
formula?</p>
<p>I&#8217;m not sure Lockhart wrote to change anyone&#8217;s mind, and he doesn&#8217;t
include many approachable recommendations. On page 82 he says, "There
should be no standards, and no curriculum." He recommends <a href="https://www.usgo.org/news/2016/07/paul-lockhart-named-teacher-of-the-year/">games</a>,
which is something, at least. He also teaches at a K-12 school where
students interview for a chance to pay $50k <a href="https://saintannsny.org/divisions-and-offices/finance/parents/tuition-financial-aid/tuition/">tuition</a>. I like his
ideas, but is there an accessible implementation?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"By concentrating on <em>what</em>, and leaving out <em>why</em>, mathematics is
reduced to an empty shell. The art is not in the &#8220;truth&#8221; but in the
explanation, the argument. It is the argument itself that gives the
truth its context, and determines what is really being said and
meant. Mathematics is <em>the art of explanation</em>." (page 29)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Mental acuity of any kind comes from solving problems yourself, not
from being told how to solve them." (pages 53-54)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"[Accepting the standard math curriculum as being synonymous with math itself]
is intimately connected to what I call the &#8220;ladder myth&#8221;&#8212;the idea
that mathematics can be arranged as a sequence of &#8220;subjects&#8221; each
being in some way more advanced, or &#8220;higher,&#8221; than the previous. The
effect is to make school mathematics into a race&#8212;some students are
&#8220;ahead&#8221; of others, and parents worry that their child is &#8220;falling
behind.&#8221;" (page 56)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"High school students must learn to use the secant function, &#8216;sec
<em>x</em>,&#8217; as an abbreviation for the reciprocal of the cosine function,
&#8216;1 / cos <em>x</em>,&#8217; a definition with as much intellectual weight as the
decision to use &#8216;&amp;&#8217; in place of &#8220;and.&#8221; That this particular
shorthand, a holdover from fifteenth-century nautical tables, is
still with us (whereas others, such as &#8220;versine,&#8221; have died out) is
mere historical accident, and is of utterly no value in an era when
rapid and precise shipboard computation is no longer an issue. Thus
we clutter our math classes with pointless nomenclature for its own
sake." (pages 58-59)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Mathematics is about problems, and problems must be made the focus
of a student&#8217;s mathematical life." (pages 60-61)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I was made to learn by heart: &#8220;The square of the sum of two numbers
is equal to the sum of their squares increased by twice their
product.&#8221; I had not the vaguest idea what this meant and when I
could not remember the words, my tutor threw the book at my head,
which did not stimulate my intellect in any way." (quoting Bertrand
Russell, pages 61-62)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There should be no standards, and no curriculum." (page 82)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Ultimately you have to face the fact that people are different, and
that&#8217;s just fine." (page 82)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="A_Mathematician's_Lament.png"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200909-mathematicians_lament_by_lockhart/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200909-mathematicians_lament_by_lockhart/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Share a tmux session</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Multiple people can connect to the same <a href="https://github.com/tmux/tmux/wiki">tmux</a> session, with all
participants able to control the session. Combined with a voice
connection (phone, etc.) this can be used for remote pair programming
in an editor like <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/">Emacs</a>, for example.</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash"># originating:
tmux -S /tmp/party_socket new -s party_session
chgrp shared_group /tmp/party_socket
# joining:
tmux -S /tmp/party_socket attach -t party_session</code></pre>

<hr>
<p>All participants need to be logged in to the same machine, likely
using <a href="https://www.ssh.com/ssh/">ssh</a>. If everyone's logged in as the same user, you're
already done: just make a session and have everyone join it. If people
have separate user accounts, you need to think about sockets.</p>
<p>tmux uses a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix_domain_socket">socket</a> for communication. Joining will require access
to that socket.</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">tmux -S /tmp/party_socket new -s party_session</code></pre>

<p>That line names the socket and the session explicitly, which is
convenient. In an existing tmux session, you can find your current
socket with "<code>echo $TMUX</code>", and you can check your session name with
"<code>tmux display-message -p '#S'</code>".</p>
<p>Let's grant access at the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Group_identifier">group</a> level, assuming everyone is in a
group called <code>shared_group</code>. You can check using <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/coreutils/manual/html_node/groups-invocation.html#groups-invocation">groups</a> and use an
existing shared group (<code>user</code> is common) which is convenient but will
allow anyone in that group to join. Or you could create a new group
for the purpose and add only the intended participants.</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">chgrp shared_group /tmp/party_socket</code></pre>

<p>Now the group has access to the socket, and can join the tmux session.</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">tmux -S /tmp/party_socket attach -t party_session</code></pre>

<p>If people don't need to control the session, they can add "<code>-r</code>" to
that line to join read-only.</p>
<p>This is a simple way to check who's connected to the session:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">ps -eo user:16,cmd | grep party_session</code></pre>

<p>That could be made fancier (as in <a href="https://github.com/zolrath/wemux">wemux</a>, for example) but should
generally do the job.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://www.howtoforge.com/sharing-terminal-sessions-with-tmux-and-screen">HowtoForge</a>, from which I adapted the core of this.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200902-share_a_tmux_session/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200902-share_a_tmux_session/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>e: The Story of a Number (and more)</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eli_Maor">Eli Maor</a> gives a great <a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/paperback/9780691168487/e-the-story-of-a-number">history</a> of <a href="https://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/E_(mathematical_constant)"><em>e</em></a>, full of
personalities and math concepts that I found very enjoyable. I was
reminded of the difference between historical development and modern
understanding, which led me to revisit
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Where_Mathematics_Comes_From">Where Mathematics Comes From</a>, which has in its part VI perhaps a
better presentation of the latter way of knowing about <em>e</em>.</p>
<p>The historical perspective reminds me that math didn't start as formal
as it is now. Like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas_Bourbaki">Bourbaki</a> leading to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Math">New Math</a>, modern
formalism may not be the best way to teach concepts. Being able to
prove something and understanding it are not the same thing. I'm not
sure I agree completely with the idea of what math is in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Where_Mathematics_Comes_From">WMCF</a>, but
I do agree that humans do better when they understand things as
something more than just a game of symbol manipulation. In a similar
spirit to the <a href="https://tauday.com/tau-manifesto">tau movement</a>, I think mathematical notation, proof,
and especially education should focus on communicating <em>meaning</em>.</p>
<p>More broadly, I think there ought to be <a href="https://fs.blog/2012/04/feynman-technique/">Feynman explanations</a> for
more topics.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#is_e_so_natural">Is <em>e</em> so "natural?"</a></li>
<li><a href="#a_quick_trip">A quick trip to \( e^{\pi i} -1 = 0\)</a></li>
<li><a href="#a_few_quotes">A few quotes from <em>e</em>: The Story of a Number</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3><a name="is_e_so_natural"></a>Is <em>e</em> so "natural?"</h3>
<p>I think <em>e</em> is not always the best choice of base, despite being the
"natural" log base. The advantages of <em>e</em> are largely to do with
calculus, and may not help in a particular application.</p>
<p>In the math for radioactive decay, often <em>e</em> is used even though
things are mostly otherwise in terms of half-life. This <a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/science/physics/quantum-physics/in-in-nuclei/v/exponential-decay-formula-proof-can-skip-involves-calculus">introduces</a>
complexity that just isn't necessary. It would be more convenient to
use 1/2 as the base. (I wonder whether <em>e</em> is used just because that's
the button people have on their calculators.)</p>
<p>In finance, interest is usually based on some finite period, like 1/12
of a year in the case of my savings account and mortgage. I did find,
<a href="https://twitter.com/planarrowspace/status/1293999229363458051">with help</a>, <a href="https://www.myfreeholdbank.com/savings.aspx">one bank</a> that compounds continuously for some
products. But usually \( e^x \) will be an approximation, not what
is really going on, for finance.</p>
<p>When scaling data with a log, changing the base is the same as
multiplying the scaled data by some constant. Especially if you're
already going to normalize that data (with a z-score, for example) or
use scale invariant techniques on the transformed data, it doesn't
matter what log base you use.</p>
<p>For <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Softmax_function">softmax</a>, we do care about the derivative, but not really about
whether it's <em>exactly</em> equal to the function's value. When training a
neural net, the constant factor is "neutralized" by the constant
factor we introduce in the learning rate. At inference, using a
different base is the same thing as changing the softmax temperature,
which people already do for various reasons.</p>
<p>The number \( e \) is very cool, no doubt, but that doesn't mean it
has to be used for every application.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="a_quick_trip"></a>A quick trip to \( e^{\pi i} -1 = 0\)</h3>
<p>What function is always equal to its own derivative?</p>
<p>\[ f(x) = f'(x) \tag{1} \]</p>
<p>The constant function \( f(x) = 0 \) has that property, but is dull,
so leave it out.</p>
<p>The function can't ever touch the x-axis: the closer it gets, the
slower it approaches.</p>
<!-- Then the function can't ever touch the x-axis, because of
something like Zeno's paradox." -->

<p>The function can't be moved up or down, because that would break
equality with its derivative. It can be moved left or right, and it
can be flipped over the x-axis, so to pick a unique function, set the
y-intercept to be 1.</p>
<p>\[ f(0) = 1 \tag{2} \]</p>
<p>Equations (1) and (2) are enough to write out the function as a
polynomial.</p>
<p>Equation (2) says the constant term is 1. Equation (1) says the
polynomial must include a term whose derivative is 1, so the linear
term is \( \int{1} = x \). By the same reasoning, the next term is
\( \int{x} = \frac{1}{2} x^2 \), and the next is \( \frac{1}{3}
\cdot \frac{1}{2} x^3 \), and so on. This gives equation (3).</p>
<p>\[ f(x) =
    1 + x + \frac{x^2}{2} + \frac{x^3}{3!} + \dots =
    \sum_{n=0}^{\infty} \frac{x^n}{n!}
    \tag{3} \]</p>
<p>The functions with derivatives proportional to their values are the
exponential functions, \( f(x) = b^x \). Equation (2) is aligned
with \( b^0 = 1 \). Using \( b^1 = b \) identifies the base for
equation (3).</p>
<p>\[ f(1) =
    \frac{1}{0!} + \frac{1}{1!} + \frac{1}{2!} + \frac{1}{3!} + \dots =
    2.718281828
    \tag{4} \]</p>
<p>This is \( e \), and it's \( e \) not by numerical equality but
because this is the essence of \( e \): the base of the exponential
whose derivative equals its value.</p>
<p>\[ e^x = \sum_{n=0}^{\infty} \frac{x^n}{n!} \tag{5} \]</p>
<p>This relates exponentiation using arbitrary powers with using only
integer powers. It already supports complex exponents if you don't
mind doing some calculating.</p>
<pre><code class="language-python">import math

def approx_exp(x, terms=20):
    return sum(x**n / math.factorial(n) for n in range(terms))

approx_exp(math.pi * 1j)
## (-1.0000000035290801-5.289182672965142e-10j)</code></pre>

<p>\[ e^{\pi i} + 1 = 0 \tag{6} \]</p>
<p>To understand why that should be, consider that exponentiation
connects addition and multiplication, as \( b^{m + n} = b^m \cdot b^n
\). Imaginary numbers add as usual, but their multiplication amounts
to rotation. The base \( e \) has the property that rotation is
given in radians, so \( \pi i \) means one half turn, taking the
result to -1.</p>
<p>This can also be seen by discovering that \( e^{xi} = \cos{x} + i
\sin{x} \), for example by checking that their values at 0 and all
their derivatives are equal.</p>
<p>Negative bases have the funny property that their even exponents give
positive results, but odd exponents give negative results. What should
the result be for an exponent like 1.2, then? Thinking of rotation, it
makes sense that results sweep through complex values to get from the
positive real axis to the negative real axis and so on. This is a fine
way to draw a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logarithmic_spiral">logarithmic spiral</a>. It can be connected to equation
(6).</p>
<p>\[ (-b)^x = b^x (-1)^x = b^x (e^{\pi i})^x = b^x e^{x \pi i} \tag{7} \]</p>
<p>The rotation comes from the negative base <em>already</em> being rotated to
begin with. In fact it's only the boring positive real numbers that
don't rotate when exponentiated.</p>
<hr>
<p>Forgive me for using \( \pi \) despite mentioning \( \tau \)
above; \( \pi \) is so familiar in this context that I didn't want
to introduce a separate new thing, even though \( \tau \) is
arguably better <em>especially</em> in this setting.</p>
<hr>
<h3><a name="a_few_quotes"></a>A few quotes from <em>e</em>: The Story of a Number</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>"Though [William] Oughtred held no official university position, his
contributions to mathematics were substantial. In his most
influential work, the <em>Clavis mathematicae</em> (1631), a book on
arithmetic and algebra, he introduced many new mathematical symbols,
some of which are still in use today. (Among them is the symbol &#215;
for multiplication, to which Leibniz later objected because of its
similarity to the letter <em>x</em>; two other symbols that can still be
seen occasionally are :: to denote a proportion and ~ for "the
difference between.")" (page 15)</p>
<p>"The Pythagoreans believed that numbers are the prime cause behind
everything in the world, from the laws of musical harmony to the
motion of the planets. "Number rules the universe" was their motto,
and by "number" they meant natural numbers and their ratios;
everything else&#8212;negative numbers, irrational numbers, and even
zero&#8212;was excluded." (page 51)</p>
<p>"[William Rowan] Hamilton's rigorous approach marked the beginning
of axiomatic algebra: ..." (page 167)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/wmkarney">Will Karnasiewicz</a> for pointing me to a continuously
compounding bank, and Mervin Chen for pointing me to Khan's gratuitous
calculus.</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="e: The Story of a Number" src="e_cover.jpg"></p>
<p><img alt="Where Mathematics Comes From" src="Where_Mathematics_Comes_From.jpg"></p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200816-e_the_story_of_a_number_and_more/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200816-e_the_story_of_a_number_and_more/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Green Eggs and Ham uses 50 words</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I recently heard that Dr. Seuss wrote Green Eggs and Ham using
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green_Eggs_and_Ham#Background">just 50 words</a> to win a bet. Naturally, I had to check. Counting
"Sam-I-am" as three distinct words, it is indeed exactly 50 unique
words, used 802 total times, with no use of the letters J, P, Q, V, or
Z.</p>
<hr>
<p>Dr. Seuss introduces no more than 7 new words on any one of the book's
62 pages, and indeed eight pages introduce just one new word.</p>
<p><img alt="Introduction of words by page in Green Eggs and Ham" src="new_words_by_page.png"></p>
<p>I used only the words that appear printed as text in the book, which
ignores the "I am Sam" sign carried by Sam in the illustration on page
three (and similar sign on page seven). If those are included, word
counts change slightly and the maximum new words on a page is just
five.</p>
<hr>
<p>Green Eggs and Ham doesn't seem to follow <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zipf%27s_law">Zipf's Law</a> very well. If
it did, the log-log plot here should show a straight line rather than
being concave. The repetitive nature of the text means more words
appear more often than a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_law">power law</a> would suggest.</p>
<p><img alt="Word frequencies in Green Eggs and Ham" src="frequencies_log_log.png"></p>
<p>Of course this is a small sample of text, so
<a href="https://xkcd.com/2268/">draw conclusions accordingly</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Here's a list showing numbers of occurrences and each word that
appears with that frequency (there are 25 unique frequencies):</p>
<ul>
<li>84: not</li>
<li>82: I</li>
<li>61: them</li>
<li>59: a</li>
<li>44: like</li>
<li>40: in</li>
<li>37: do</li>
<li>33: you</li>
<li>26: would</li>
<li>25: and, eat</li>
<li>21: will</li>
<li>19: with</li>
<li>16: Sam</li>
<li>14: could</li>
<li>13: am</li>
<li>11: green, eggs, ham, here, the</li>
<li>9: there, train</li>
<li>8: or, anywhere, house, mouse</li>
<li>7: box, fox, car, on, dark</li>
<li>6: tree</li>
<li>5: say, so</li>
<li>4: may, see, let, me, be, rain, goat, try</li>
<li>3: that, boat</li>
<li>2: they, are, good, thank</li>
<li>1: if</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Data and code is <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/green_eggs_and_ham">on GitHub</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200815-green_eggs_and_ham_uses_50_words/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200815-green_eggs_and_ham_uses_50_words/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Life expectancy is historically misleading</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The modern distribution of age at death is substantially novel. In
today's wealthiest countries most people die at an age near their life
expectancy, but historically a third of people died as young children
and the remainder died over a wide range of ages.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Life_expectancy">Life expectancy</a> at birth, an average of possible ages at death, is
now a measure of central tendency, but even just 100 years ago the
distribution of age at death didn't really <em>have</em> a central tendency.
Interpreting it as if it did gives a misleading impression of past
cultures.</p>
<p><img alt="Life Expectancy and Distribution of Age at Death Over Time in Sweden" src="lifetimes_in_sweden.png"></p>
<p>Inspired by <a href="/20200805-factfulness_by_rosling/">Hans Rosling</a>, I went looking for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Life_table">life tables</a>.
Appropriately enough, his native Sweden birthed the first National
Statistical Office, with 270 years of life tables <a href="https://www.mortality.org/cgi-bin/hmd/country.php?cntr=SWE&amp;level=1">available</a>.
That's enough history to show how the world used to be, and as a rich
country Sweden also shows us where the whole world is (hopefully)
heading.</p>
<p>Back when life expectancy was mid-thirties, you were more likely to
die in your seventies than in your thirties. If you interpret a life
expectancy of 36 to mean "most people died around age 36" you might
incorrectly imagine a world with very few people over 50.</p>
<p>Or, as Rosling explains it:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Back in 1800, when Swedes starved to death and British children
worked in coal mines, life expectancy was roughly 30 years
everywhere in the world. That was what it had been throughout
history. Among all babies who were ever born, roughly half died
during their childhood. Most of the other half died between the ages
of 50 and 70. So the average was around 30. It doesn't mean most
people lived to be 30. It's just an average, and with averages we
must always remember that there's a spread." (<a href="/20200805-factfulness_by_rosling/">Factfulness</a>, page
54)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This doesn't mean that life expectancy isn't a useful statistic for
tracking development! It can be both limited and useful.</p>
<p>I like the visualization I made (above) because it shows enough
information to see distributional changes over time.</p>
<p>The question of whether life expectancy will <em>continue</em> to go up is an
interesting one. I'm not sure this data has much to say. The length of
past lives has an <a href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20181002-how-long-did-ancient-people-live-life-span-versus-longevity">uncertain</a> relationship with theoretical/possible
lifespan. Are people living longer, or just not dying earlier? There's
also a possible question about quality of life at extreme ages which
might be complicating.</p>
<hr>
<p>Source for the visualization above is <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/life_expectancy">on github</a>.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200806-life_expectancy_is_historically_misleading/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200806-life_expectancy_is_historically_misleading/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Factfulness, by Rosling</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://www.gapminder.org/factfulness-book/">Factfulness</a> finds <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_Rosling">Rosling</a> realizing that facts are not enough,
because thinking is polluted by "dramatic instincts," so his
presentation of little-known optimistic trends is organized to address
not just ignorance, but systematic biases in how people think.</p>
<ol>
<li><em>The Gap Instinct</em>: Giving its name to his <a href="https://www.gapminder.org/">foundation</a>, this is
   the tendency to think groups are completely different. Usually even
   if group averages are different, the distributions significantly
   overlap.</li>
<li><em>The Negativity Instinct</em>: Bad news is reported and feels salient,
   even if trends are positive overall.</li>
<li><em>The Straight Line Instinct</em>: Trends are not always linear, but
   it's easiest to extrapolate as if they were&#8212;and be wrong.</li>
<li><em>The Fear Instinct</em>: Fear is often not calibrated to true risk.</li>
<li><em>The Size Instinct</em>: Understanding "big" requires appropriate
   comparison.</li>
<li><em>The Generalization Instinct</em>: Both categories and anecdotes can be
   misleading.</li>
<li><em>The Destiny Instinct</em>: Slow change is not the same as no change.</li>
<li><em>The Single Perspective Instinct</em>: Understanding requires more than
   one approach, view, or tool (even statistics).</li>
<li><em>The Blame Instinct</em>: Whether effects are good or bad, the reasons
   are probably more complex than just one individual or organization.</li>
<li><em>The Urgency Instinct</em>: It's better to think and act carefully
    than jump into drastic moves.</li>
</ol>
<p>Rosling wants us to realize our shared humanity, see that things have
mostly gotten better over long time scales, and work to keep improving
things. The philanthropy of <a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/books/factfulness">Bill Gates</a> is largely working to
continue the trends Rosling focuses on, for example.</p>
<p>Like his classic <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jbkSRLYSojo">presentation</a>, celebrated by data visualizers, the
book is a study in good communication. I particularly noticed that he
often found opportunities to present dialogue rather than just
narrative, and that he used cute attention-getting flourishes like
using hypothetical "chimps" to stand in for random performance on his
quizzes.</p>
<p>I agree there's risk in assuming positive trends inevitably continue.
But it isn't fair to say Rosling ignored future risks. He listed five
things that he thought we <em>should</em> worry about:</p>
<ol>
<li>Global pandemic</li>
<li>Financial collapse</li>
<li>World War III</li>
<li>Climate change</li>
<li>Extreme poverty</li>
</ol>
<p>Writing in 2017, he seems particularly prescient today.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... free access to data doesn't turn into knowledge without
effort." (page 79)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It will be helpful to you if you always assume your categories are
misleading." (page 158)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200805-factfulness_by_rosling/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200805-factfulness_by_rosling/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Man Who Solved the Market, by Zuckerman</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/557104/the-man-who-solved-the-market-by-gregory-zuckerman/">book</a> demystifies <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Simons_(mathematician)">Jim Simons</a> and makes his
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renaissance_Technologies#Monemetrics">Medallion Fund</a> seem more like grinding at a poker table than like
solving the market. I was interested to read about his connection to
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Mercer">Robert Mercer</a> and otherwise hiring "smart people" regardless of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_No_Asshole_Rule">other characteristics</a>.</p>
<p>Technical detail is light, but Zuckerman emphasizes that Renaissance
used a monolithic trading model that could accept additional signals
over time, manage <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slippage_(finance)">slippage</a> sometimes to the extent that signals
Renaissance was using could be made to disappear to outside observers
while exploited, and that frequently was basically based on reversion
to the mean. And Renaissance was not at all shy about using any
available tax dodges.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Simons was struck by the unique way talented researchers were
recruited and managed in his unit [of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institute_for_Defense_Analyses" title="the Institute for Defense Analyses">IDA</a>]. Staff members, most
of whom had doctorates, were hired for their brainpower, creativity,
and ambition, rather than for any specific expertise or background.
The assumption was that researchers would find problems to work on
and be clever enough to solve them. Lenny Baum, among the most
accomplished code-breakers, developed a saying that became the
group's credo: "Bad ideas is good, good ideas terrific, no ideas is
terrible."" (pages 24-25)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Courting accomplished candidates, Simons developed a unique
perspective on talent. He told one Stony Brook professor, Hershel
Farkas, that he valued "killers," those with a single-minded focus
who wouldn't quit on a math problem until arriving at a solution.
Simons told another colleague that some academics were "super smart"
yet weren't original thinkers worthy of a position at the
university.</p>
<p>""There are guys and there are <em>real</em> guys," he said." (pages 34-35)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Truth ... is much too complicated to allow for anything but
approximations." (page 67, epigraph quoting John von Neuman)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"No one ever made a decision because of a number. They need a
story." (page 161, epigraph quoting Daniel Kahneman)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Early one evening, his eyes blurry from staring at his computer
screen for hours on end, Magerman spotted something odd: A line of
simulation code used for Brown and Mercer&#8217;s trading system showed
the Standard &amp; Poor&#8217;s 500 at an unusually low level. This test code
appeared to use a figure from back in 1991 that was roughly half the
current number. Mercer had written it as a static figure, rather
than as a variable that updated with each move in the market.</p>
<p>"When Magerman fixed the bug and updated the number, a second
problem&#8212;an algebraic error&#8212;appeared elsewhere in the code. Magerman
spent most of the night on it but he thought he solved that one,
too. Now the simulator&#8217;s algorithms could finally recommend an ideal
portfolio for the Nova system to execute, including how much
borrowed money should be employed to expand its stock holdings. The
resulting portfolio seemed to generate big profits, at least
according to Magerman&#8217;s calculations.</p>
<p>"Overcome with excitement, he raced to tell Brown what he had
discovered. Brown flashed his breathless colleague a look of deep
skepticism but agreed to hear Magerman out. Afterward, Brown still
showed little enthusiasm. Mercer had done the coding for the system,
after all. Everyone knew Mercer rarely made errors, especially
mathematical ones. Crestfallen, Magerman slunk away. His screwup had
branded him a nuisance, not any kind of potential savior.</p>
<p>"Without much to lose, Magerman brought his work to Mercer, who also
agreed to take a look. Sitting at his desk, hunched over his
computer, Mercer patiently examined the old code, line by line,
comparing it to Magerman&#8217;s new code. Slowly, a smile formed on his
face. Mercer reached for some paper and a pencil from his desk and
began working on a formula. He was checking Magerman&#8217;s work. After
about fifteen minutes of scribbling, Mercer put his pencil down and
looked up.</p>
<p>"&#8220;You&#8217;re right,&#8221; Mercer told Magerman.</p>
<p>"Later, Mercer convinced Brown that Magerman was on to something.
But when Brown and Mercer told other staffers about the problem that
had been uncovered, as well as the fix, they were met with
incredulity, even laughter. A junior programmer fixed the problem?
The same guy who had crashed the system a few weeks after being
hired?</p>
<p>"Brown and Mercer ignored the doubts and restarted the system, with
Simons&#8217;s backing, incorporating the improvements and corrections.
Instant gains resulted, defying the skeptics. The long losing streak
was over. Magerman finally received the appreciation he longed for,
receiving a cherished pat on the back from Brown.</p>
<p>"&#8220;This is great,&#8221; Simons boomed at a weekly meeting. &#8220;Let&#8217;s keep it
going.&#8221;</p>
<p>"A new era for both Magerman and the firm seemed within reach."
(pages 194-195)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When asked to comment, Bannon said there are "errors of fact" in
this description of events surrounding the election and his
interactions with the Mercers, though he wouldn't specify the
inaccuracies. "Dude, it's not my fucking book," he said in an
email." (footnote page 280)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>&#8220;We can teach you about money,&#8221; Patterson explains. &#8220;We can&#8217;t teach
you about smart.&#8221; (page 284)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200804-man_who_solved_the_market/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200804-man_who_solved_the_market/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Technological Revolutions and Financial Capital, by Perez</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlota_Perez">Perez</a> offers a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Other_Canon_Foundation" title="The Other Canon">heterodox</a> abduction from economic history, in
the tradition of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Schumpeter">Schumpeter</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kondratiev_wave">Kondratiev</a>, suggesting
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_Revolutions_and_Financial_Capital">Technological Revolutions and Financial Capital</a> dance through
"great surges" of 40 to 60 years, like giant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hype_cycle">hype cycles</a> driving
development.</p>
<p><img alt="hype cycle overlaid with great surge pattern" src="cycle.jpg"></p>
<p>(The hype cycle analogy isn't perfect; see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_Revolutions_and_Financial_Capital">elsewhere</a> for
summarization of Perez's formulation and five surges.)</p>
<p>Taking Dosi's extension of Kuhn's scientific paradigms to
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_paradigm#Giovanni_Dosi">technological paradigms</a> and further involving economics and
societal institutions (especially as capitalism vs. regulation), the
ideas are <a href="https://www.oxfordscholarship.com/view/10.1093/0199251053.001.0001/acprof-9780199251056" title="As Time Goes By, Freeman and Lou&#231;&#227;">not wholly original</a>, but neither are they very common.</p>
<p><img alt="diagram of technological, economic, and institutional change" src="diagram.jpg"></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The justification for an exercise that claims to give order to the
historical record at the expense of its infinite complexity and
richness is its heuristic value." (page 161)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Perez doesn't seem happy that the historical approach
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methodenstreit" title="Methodenstreit">fell out of favor</a> in economics, and it's neat to see her analysis
cover hundreds of years. This is economic history that doesn't just
refer to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bretton_Woods_system">Bretton Woods</a>, but also the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peterloo_Massacre">Peterloo Massacre</a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corn_Laws">Corn Laws</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nabob">nabobs</a>, to sample a few references. You know
about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May_68">May 1968 in Europe</a>, right?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The role of the economic historian, as Gay perceived it, was to
study and comprehend these cycles and to suggest ways of restraining
their excesses." (page 158, quoting Cruikshank, extended quote
below)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This book is the closest thing I've seen to Asimov's
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychohistory_(fictional)">psychohistory</a>, as in the <a href="/20200714-foundation_trilogy/">Foundation</a> books. The time-scale
(around 50 years vs. thousands) and claimed predictive power (little
vs. godlike) are very different, but the ideas of anticipating
long-term shifts and being ready for them are analogous, and Perez
does discuss some psychosocial aspects, as in "ethical softening"
during parts of her surges.</p>
<p>The book was published in 2002. It was a theory that fit the dot-com
crash. How has the theory fit since then? The financial industry was
not much reined in, for one.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"However, this change in the rules of the game may not be easy,
because the financial collapse has not been spectacular enough to
wipe out the excess self-confidence." (page 168, on the dot-com
crash)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Maybe the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Recession">Great Recession</a> was just a late example of financial
adventurism. The theory suggests that shouldn't be happening so much
during the deployment phase of the age of information. It's easy to
feel like markets were <em>never</em> really brought back in line with the
real economy. Have we been in a "gilded age"?</p>
<p>It should be about time for the start of a new surge. What will the
next big technology be?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"It has often been suggested that biotechnology, bioelectrics and
nanotechnology might conform the next technological revolution."
(page 13)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>From where I sit, AI/ML seems like a good candidate. Should we throw
in VR/AR? Blockchain? Private space? Does the social web constitute a
separate technology?</p>
<p>The book's theory treats technologies as available resources just
waiting for capital to fund them into prominence. I think this may be
too much of a simplification. In particular, it's <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/8-lessons-from-20-years-hype-cycles-michael-mullany/">pretty hard</a> to
guess in advance which technologies will take off and which will
fizzle, and I don't think there's any guarantee that there will always
be a technology at hand substantial enough to power another surge.</p>
<p>Alternatively, what if an even longer phase is coming to an end? What
if <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Productivity_paradox">declines in productivity growth</a> are a real indication of the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigmoid_function">sigmoid</a> peak of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Great_Transformation_(book)" title="The Great Transformation">Market Society</a> overall, and extended
financial weirdness a sign of an impending larger transformation of
societal system?</p>
<p>It certainly feels, in 2020, as if the world sits on a knife-edge,
with forces pulling in multiple directions. Hopefully history will
help us to create a worthy future.</p>
<p><img alt="book cover" src="book_cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... Schumpeter's own view that aggregate figures conceal more than
they reveal." (page 61, refs Schumpeter (1939) Vol. 1, pp. 43-4, I
checked the ref and it's correct, but unfortunately Schumpeter's
language is not very quotable)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"People living through the period of paradigm transition experience
great uncertainty as to the 'right' price of things (including that
of stocks, of course)." (page 62)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"So again, and not surprisingly, nothing in the capitalist system is
clear and simple." (page 67)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Schumpeter defined capitalism as 'that form of private property
economy in which innovations are carried out by means of borrowed
money'." (page 72, refs Schumpeter (1939) p. 223)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There is a certain amount of circularity in all these observations,
because the phases have been dated taking the occurrence of crises
into account." (page 79)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Interesting reference: <a href="https://www.amazon.com/End-Finance-Inflation-Derivatives-Capitalism/dp/0415208815">The End of Finance: Capital Market Inflation, Financial Derivatives and Pension Fund Capitalism</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The full history of the readjustment of relative paper and real
values at the beginning of the twenty-first century will only be
appropriately judged with hindsight." (page 112)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As with many processes in capitalism, it is by taking a successful
behavior to its extreme that it turns into failure." (page 115)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"To begin with, knowledge, experience and information have become
capital goods." (page 144)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Without recognizable labor unions, salaries would not have been
enough to serve as solvent demand much beyond food and basics."
(page 145)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Page 146 has an interesting meta-analysis of the field of economics
viewed through the lens of the book's theory.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Technology is the fuel of the capitalist engine." (page 155)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"[E.F. Gay] developed a dynamic vision of economic history [as] a
record of swings of the pendulum between periods when social
controls dominated and periods dominated by the actions of
aggressive individuals. The former periods were static,
characterized by security and stability. The latter periods ushered
in by the introduction of new tools, weapons or other forces, were
controlled by the powerful individuals who introduced these forces.
These dynamic periods ... were crucial to economic development ...
The role of the economic historian, as Gay perceived it, was to
study and comprehend these cycles and to suggest ways of restraining
their excesses." (page 158, quoting Cruikshank, 1987, on the
founding Dean of Harvard Business School)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The <em>Methodenstreit</em> between the historical school and the
neo-classicals, which in practice expelled the state, Society and
the historical context from economic theory, occurred in the period
of installation of the third surge, which in the periodization
proposed here is parallel to the installation period of the fifth,
when the monetarists defeated the Keynesians." (page 162)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The ultimate test of usefulness of a model such as the one
presented here is in relation to policy making, be it in business,
in social organizations or in government." (page 163)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Yet if this model is a reasonable approximation to the way the
system works then it is wise to try to engage in the design of
regulations and institutions so they will be ready and in the arena
of debate when the moment comes for them to be accepted." (page 165)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"A golden age of worldwide expansion is possible." (page 171)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200728-technological_revolutions_and_financial_capital/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200728-technological_revolutions_and_financial_capital/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Art of Doing Science and Engineering, by Hamming</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>You should definitely read <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Hamming">Hamming</a>'s "You and Your Research"
<a href="https://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/YouAndYourResearch.html">talk</a>, and probably also his 1996 <a href="http://worrydream.com/refs/Hamming-TheArtOfDoingScienceAndEngineering.pdf">book</a> (both freely available).
I read the beautiful new printing from <a href="https://press.stripe.com/">Stripe Press</a>, with a
forward by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bret_Victor">Victor</a>. Hamming may not be perfect, but he has a lot of
ideas.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"We live in an age of exponential growth in knowledge, and it is
increasingly futile to teach only polished theorems and proofs. We
must abandon the guided tour through the art gallery of mathematics,
and instead teach how to create the mathematics we need. In my
opinion, there is no long-term practical alternative." (page v,
epigraph quoting Hamming)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The book is roughly Hamming's lectures from a graduate course he
taught after he could teach whatever he felt like. It is "Hamming on
Hamming" in that it's largely him expounding on whatever he liked.
It's a bit like a (very technical) grandparent telling stories and
giving advice to their grandkids.</p>
<p><img alt="book cover" src="book_cover.jpg"></p>
<p>The cover image is a visual form of the book's inspirational message:
A random walk won't take you anywhere, but if you have a vision, a
direction that you keep trying to pursue, then even if not every step
is correct, you will make progress in that direction.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"What is wanted in the long run, of course, is that the man with the
problem does the actual writing of the code with no human interface,
as we all too often have these days, between the person who knows
the problem and the person who knows the programming language. This
date is unfortunately too far off to do much good immediately, but I
would think by the year 2020 it would be fairly universal practice
for the expert in the field of application to do the actual program
preparation rather than have experts in computers (and ignorant of
the field of application) do the program preparation." (page 55;
writing around 1995)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"You read constantly about "engineering the production of software,"
both for the efficiency of production and for the reliability of the
product. But you do not expect novelists to "engineer the production
of novels." The question arises: "Is programming closer to novel
writing than it is to classical engineering?" I suggest yes! Given
the problem of getting a man into outer space, both the Russians and
the Americans did it pretty much the same way, all things
considered, and allowing for some espionage. They were both limited
by the same firm laws of physics. But give two novelists the problem
of writing on "the greatness and misery of man," and you will
probably get two very different novels (without saying just how to
measure this). Give the same complex problem to two modern
programmers and you will, I claim, get two rather different
programs. Hence my belief that current programming practice is
closer to novel writing than it is to engineering. The novelists are
bound only by their imaginations, which is somewhat as the
programmers are when they are writing software. Both activities have
a large creative component, and while you would like to make
programming resemble engineering, it will take a lot of time to get
there&#8212;and maybe you really, in the long run, do not want to do it!
Maybe it just sounds good. You will have to think about it many
times in the coming years; you might as well start now and discount
propaganda you hear, as well as all the wishful thinking which goes
on in the area! The software of the utility programs of computers
has been done often enough, and is so limited in scope, so it might
reasonably be expected to become "engineered," but the general
software preparation is not likely to be under "engineering control"
for many, many years.</p>
<p>"There are many proposals on how to improve the productivity of the
individual programmer, as well as groups of programmers. I have
already mentioned top-down and bottom-up; there are others, such as
head programmer, lead programmer, proving the program is correct in
a mathematical sense, and the waterfall model of programming, to
name but a few. While each has some merit I have faith in only one,
which is almost never mentioned&#8212;<em>think before you write the
program,</em> it might be called. Before you start, think carefully
about the whole thing, <em>including</em> what will be your acceptance test
that it is right, as well as how later field maintenance will be
done. Getting it right the first time is much better than fixing it
up later!</p>
<p>"One trouble with much of programming is simply that often there is
not a well-defined job to be done; rather, the programming process
itself will gradually discover what the problem is! The desire that
you will be given a well-defined problem before you start
programming often does not match reality, and hence a lot of the
current proposals to "solve the programming problem" will fall to
the ground if adopted rigorously." (pages 57-58)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Many studies have shown programmers differ in productivity, from
worst to best, by much more than a factor of ten. From this I long
ago concluded the best policy is to pay your good programmers very
well but regularly fire the poorer ones&#8212;if you can get away with it!
One way is, of course, to hire them on contract rather than as
regularly employed people, but that is increasingly against the law,
which seems to want to guarantee even the worst have some
employment. In practice you may actually be better off to pay the
worst to stay home and not get in the way of the more capable (and I
am serious)!" (page 59)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I made the comparison of writing software with the act of literary
writing; both seem to depend fundamentally on clear thinking. Can
good programming be taught? If we look at the corresponding teaching
of "creative writing" courses we find most students of such courses
do not become great writers, and most great writers in the past did
not take creative writing courses! Hence it is dubious that great
programmers can be trained easily.</p>
<p>"Does experience help? Do bureaucrats after years of writing reports
and instructions get better? I have no real data, but I suspect with
time they get worse! The habitual use of "governmentese" over the
years probably seeps into their writing style and makes them worse.
I suspect the same for programmers! Neither years of experience nor
the number of languages used is any reason for thinking the
programmer is getting better from these experiences. An examination
of books on programming suggests most of the authors are not good
programmers!</p>
<p>"The results I picture are not nice, but all you have to oppose it
is wishful thinking&#8212;I have evidence of years and years of
programming on my side!" (pages 60-61)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"People often make the mistake of saying, "Thinking is what Newton
and Einstein did." But by that definition most of us cannot
think&#8212;and usually we do not like that conclusion!" (page 79)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... Of course robots will displace many humans doing routine jobs.
In a very real sense, machines can best do routine jobs, thus
freeing humans for more humane jobs. Unfortunately, many humans at
present are not equipped to compete with machines&#8212;they are unable to
do much more than routine jobs. There is a widespread belief (hope?)
that humans can compete, once they are given proper training.
However, I have long publicly doubted you could take many coal
miners and make them into useful programmers. I have my reservations
on the fraction of the human population that can be made into
programmers in the classical sense; if you call getting money from
the bank dispensing "machine programming," or the dialing of a
telephone number (both of which apply the human input to an
elaborate program which is then executed, much like an interpreter
acts on your program input), then of course most people can be made
into programmers. But if you mean the more classical activity of
careful analysis of a situation and then the detailed specification
as to what is to be done, then I say there are doubts as to what
fraction of the population can <em>compete</em> with computers, even with
nice interactive prompting menus.</p>
<p>"Computers have both displaced so many people from jobs, and also
made so many new jobs, it is hopeless to try to answer which is the
larger number. But it is clear that on average it is the lower-level
jobs which are disappearing and the higher-level jobs which are
appearing. Again, one would like to believe <em>most</em> people can be
trained in the future to do the higher-level jobs&#8212;but that is a hope
without any real evidence." (pag 94)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We started to play games on computers to study the human thought
processes and not to win the game; the goal has been perverted to
win, and never mind the insight into the human mind and how it
works." (page 100)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Thus AI requires your careful thought and should not be dismissed
lightly just because many experts make obviously false claims."
(page 103)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"<em>Information theory</em> was created by C.E. Shannon in the late 1940s.
The management of Bell Telephone Labs wanted him to call it
"communication theory," as that is a far more accurate name, but for
obvious publicity reasons "information theory" has a much greater
impact&#8212;this Shannon chose and so it is known to this day." (page
163)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is always wise to adopt a standard notation and framework of
thinking of diverse things&#8212;one field of application may suggest
things to do in the other. I have found it of great value to do so
whenever possible&#8212;remove the extraneous scale factors and get to the
basic expressions. (But then I was originally trained as a
mathematician.)" (page 184)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is another example of why you need to know the fundamentals very
well; the fancy parts then follow easily and you can do things that
they never told you about." (page 186)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Many people had the opportunity to discover (really rediscover) the
Gibbs phenomenon, and it was Gibbs who made the effort. It is
another example of what I maintain, that there are opportunities all
around and few people reach for them. As Pasteur said, "Luck favors
the prepared mind."" (page 201)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It must be your friends, in some sense, who make you famous by
quoting and citing you, and it pays, so I claim, to be helpful to
others as they try to do their work. They may in time give you
credit for the work, which is better than trying to claim it
yourself. Cooperation is essential in these days of complex
projects; the day of the individual worker is dying fast. Teamwork
is more and more essential, and hence learning to work on a team,
indeed possibly seeking out places where you can help others, is a
good idea. In any case the fun of working with good people on
important problems is more pleasure than the resulting fame." (page
210)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Moral: when you know something cannot be done, also remember the
essential reason why, so later, when the circumstances have changed,
you will not say, "It can't be done."" (page 218, on how he missed
the opportunity to help develop FFT)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Let us analyze carefully what we do and its implications, because
<em>what we do to a great extent controls what we can see.</em>" (page 219)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"If you will only ask yourself, "Is what I am being told really
true?," it is amazing how much you can find is, or borders on, being
false, even in a well-developed field!" (page 227)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When I went to Bell Telephone Laboratories in 1946 I soon found
myself in the early stages of the design of the earliest Nike system
of guided missiles." (page 238)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I have emphasized the necessity of having the underlying laws of
whatever field you are simulating well under control. But there are
no such laws of economics! The only law of economics that I believe
in is Hamming's law: "You cannot consume what is not produced."
There is not another single reliable law in all of economics I know
of which is not either a tautology in mathematics or else sometimes
false. Hence when you do simulations in economics you have not the
reliability you have in the hard sciences." (page 250)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Now this fact, once understood, impacts design! Good design
protects you from the need for too many highly accurate components
in the system. But such design principles are still, to this date,
ill understood and need to be researched extensively. Not that good
designers do not understand this intuitively, merely it is not
easily incorporated into the design methods you were taught in
school. Good minds are still needed in spite of all the computing
tools we have developed. But the best mind will be the one who gets
the principle into the design methods taught so it will be
automatically available for lesser minds!" (page 269)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"You also realize any dictionary must be circular; the first word
you look up must be defined in terms of other words&#8212;there can be no
first definition which does not use words." (page 307)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When stuck I often ask myself, "If I had a solution, what would it
look like?" This tends to sharpen up the approach, and may reveal
new ways of looking at the problem you had subconsciously ignored
but now see should not be excluded. What must the solution involve?
Are there conservation laws which must apply? Is there some
symmetry? How does each assumption enter into the solution, and is
each one really necessary? Have you recognized all the relevant
factors?" (page 327)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"...saturate the subconscious with the problem, try to not think
seriously about anything else for hours days, or even weeks, and
thus the subconscious ... is left with only the problem to mull
over. We simply deprive it of all else as best we can! ... In a way,
I am repeating Pasteur, "Luck favors the prepared mind." You prepare
your mind for success "by thinking on it constantly" (Newton), and
occasionally you are lucky." (page 328)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Probably the most important tool in creativity is the use of an
<em>analogy.</em> Something seems like something else which we knew in the
past. Wide acquaintance with various fields of knowledge is thus a
help&#8212;<em>provided</em> you have the knowledge filed away so it is available
when needed, rather than to be found only when led directly to it.
This flexible access to pieces of knowledge seems to come from
looking at knowledge <em>while you are acquiring it</em> from many
different angles, turning over any new idea to see its many sides
before filing it away. This implies effort on your part not to take
the easy, immediately useful "memorizing the material" path, but to
prepare your mind for the future. It is for this reason I have urged
you in many of the chapters to get down to the fundamentals of a
field, since it implies you must examine things in many ways before
you can decide what is fundamental and what is frills. In fact, for
one person they may be in one order, and for another in the opposite
order. What is fundamental partly depends on the individual and
their mental makeup. It is obvious you need many "hooks" on the
knowledge if you are to use it in new situations.</p>
<p>"... I can only advise you to do what I do&#8212;when you learn something
new, think of other applications of it, ones which have not arisen
in your past but which might in your future. How easy to say, but
how hard to do! Yet what else can I say about how to organize your
mind so useful things will be recalled readily at the right time?"
(pages 328-329)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The person who thinks they understand the problem and does not is
usually more of a curse (blockage) than the person who knows they do
not understand the problem." (page 333)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It has been my experience, as well as the experience of many others
who have looked, that data is generally much less accurate than it
is advertised to be." (page 345)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"From that experience I learned never to process any data until I
had first examined it carefully for errors. There have been
complaints that I would take too long, but almost always I found
errors, and when I showed the errors to them they had to admit I was
wise in taking the precautions I did. No matter how sacred the data
and urgent the answer, I have learned to pretest it for consistency
and outliers at a minimum." (page 348)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Second, you cannot gather a really large amount of data accurately.
It is a known fact which is constantly ignored. It is always a
matter of limited resources and limited time. The management will
usually want a 100% survey when a small one consisting of a good
deal less, say 1% or even 0.1%, will yield more accurate results! It
is known, I say, but ignored. The telephone companies, in order to
distribute the income to the various companies involved in a single
long-distance phone call, used to take a very small, carefully
selected sample, and on the basis of this sample they distributed
the money among the partners. The same is now done by the airlines.
It took them a long while before they listened, but they finally
came to realize the truth that <em>small samples carefully taken are
better than large samples poorly done</em>&#8212;better both in lower cost and
in greater accuracy." (page 355)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Of the things you can choose to measure some are hard, firm
measurements, such as height and weight, while some are soft, such
as social attitudes. There is always a tendency to grab the hard,
firm measurement, though it may be quite irrelevant as compared to
the soft one, which in the long run may be much more relevant to
your goals. <em>Accuracy</em> of measurement tends to get confused with
<em>relevance</em> of measurement, much more than most people believe. That
a measurement is accurate, reproducible, and easy to make does not
mean it should be done; instead, a much poorer one which is more
closely related to your goals may be much preferable. For example,
in school it is easy to measure training and hard to measure
education, and hence you tend to see on final exams an emphasis on
the training part and a great neglect of the education part.</p>
<p>"Let me turn to another effect of a measurement system, and
illustrate it by the definition and use of IQs. What is done is a
plausible list of questions&#8212;plausible from past experience&#8212;is made
and then tried out on a small number of people. Those questions
which show an internal correlation with others are kept and those
which do not correlate well are dropped. Next, the revised test is
calibrated by using it on a much larger sample. How? Simply by
taking the accumulated scores (the number of people's score which
are below the given amount) and plotting these revised numbers on
probability paper&#8212;meaning the cumulative probabilities of a normal
distribution are the horizontal lines. Next, the points where the
cumulative actual scores fall at a given percentage points are
related, via a calibration table, to the corresponding points on the
cumulative normal probability curve. As a result it is observed
intelligence has a normal distribution in the population! Of course
it has, it was made to be that way! Furthermore, they have defined
intelligence to be what is measured by the calibrated exam, and if
that is the definition of intelligence, then of course intelligence
is normally distributed. But if you think maybe intelligence is not
exactly what the calibrated exam measures, then you are entitled to
doubt intelligence is normally distributed in the population. Again,
you get what was measured, and the normal distribution announced is
an artifact of the method of measurement and hardly relates to
reality." (pages 374-375)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200725-art_of_doing_science_and_engineering/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200725-art_of_doing_science_and_engineering/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Lateral Thinking: Creativity Step by Step</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>After a reference in <a href="/20200523-peopleware_productive_projects_and_teams/">Peopleware</a>, I found Edward de Bono's <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Lateral-Thinking-Creativity-Step/dp/0060903252">book</a>
on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lateral_thinking">Lateral Thinking</a>. I'd mostly heard about lateral thinking in
the context of brain-teasers, and was pleased to find much more depth.
This book could be a companion to <a href="/2013/09/28/polyas-how-to-solve-it-quotes-and-comments/">How to Solve It</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"creativity is usually treated as something desirable which is to be
brought about by vague exhortation." (page 7)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Lateral Thinking is almost a textbook for a class in creativity,
complete with very concrete activities and teachers' guides. The topic
is orthogonal to deductive reasoning; it's about finding more starting
points rather than following one path.</p>
<p>This can be applied to problems with "correct" answers, but it also
applies to many other things: writing, design, planning, deciding what
other problems to work on. Nearly anything can benefit from "insight
restructuring."</p>
<p>One technique for finding new ideas is to use random input: take a
<a href="https://randomword.com/">random word</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Random">random WikiPedia article</a>, juxtapose it with
your topic or problem, and see where you go. Using random input
reminds me of <a href="http://proceedings.mlr.press/v97/zhou19d/zhou19d.pdf">noise in training neural networks</a>.</p>
<p>Throughout, de Bono emphasizes suspending judgment, which is useful
not just in brainstorming. One related practice is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yes,_and...">yes, and</a>: build
from ideas rather than shutting them down. A possible tactic is
"extracting the functional principle of the idea" (page 163): even if
the particulars seem unworkable, the underlying concept could be
affirmed and expanded.</p>
<hr>
<p>A few quotes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"<em>It is historical continuity that maintains most assumptions&#8212;not a
repeated assessment of their validity.</em>" (page 91, italics in
original)</p>
<p>"The purpose of thinking is not to be right but to be effective."
(page 107)</p>
<p>"Unless one can pick out the dominant idea one is going to be
dominated by it." (page 123)</p>
<p>"There is no harm in reinventing things that have already been
invented. It is very good practice." (page 282)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><img alt="Lateral Thinking cover" src="lateral_thinking_cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200716-lateral_thinking_creativity_step_by_step/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200716-lateral_thinking_creativity_step_by_step/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Communicate Immediately</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Discover what's important and present it early and concisely to refine
your ideas and engage with your audience. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverted_pyramid_(journalism)">Don't bury the lede</a>. Put
the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BLUF_(communication)">Bottom Line Up Front</a>. Communicate as if you may be
interrupted.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#message">Identify your message</a></li>
<li><a href="#line">Give a one-line version</a></li>
<li><a href="#paragraph">Give a one-paragraph version</a></li>
<li><a href="#detail">Add detail until complete</a></li>
<li><a href="#media">Use the best of text and other media</a></li>
</ul>
<h3><a name="message"></a>Identify your message</h3>
<p>What your audience needs most is your unique contribution: a result or
recommendation, a summary or synthesis. Help them to understand.
Prepare them to take action.</p>
<p>If you don't know what your message is, you have little chance of
communicating it. Think beyond listing what you've done, what you've
read, what you've seen. Find a deeper conclusion. Even without an
audience, you should be doing this for yourself.</p>
<p>According to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Mathematical_Theory_of_Communication">Shannon</a>, information is related to surprise. One
heuristic is to identify the most central "surprise" you have to
communicate. What does your audience not know? Can you anticipate
questions they would ask, and answer them?</p>
<p>Don't force your audience to come to their own conclusions. Your
message won't prevent them from doing that anyway, if you are honest
and <a href="#detail">complete</a>. Your message isn't the final word. It should
be a generous starting point.</p>
<p>Regardless of audience, the practice of articulating a message into
short concrete forms can help you to clarify and improve your ideas,
possibly through several iterations.</p>
<h3><a name="line"></a>Give a one-line version</h3>
<p>Start with a title, or subject line, or initial answer to a question.
A one-line version should be complete enough that the audience can
choose whether to continue.</p>
<p>Good newspaper headlines, like "Truman wins presidency," are tiny
versions of their articles. Clickbait titles illustrate what not to
do, as in "You won't believe what Truman did." Emulate good headlines.</p>
<!-- https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dewey_Defeats_Truman -->

<p>Good one-line versions are usually complete sentences, not just noun
phrases. Don't convey just the subject you're talking about, include
what you're saying about it.</p>
<p>Feel free to use the specialized language of your field.
<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.10029v1">Big Self-Supervised Models are Strong Semi-Supervised Learners</a> is
a great title for a Machine Learning paper, though it may seem opaque
to botanists.</p>
<p>Though the need for summarizing is real, there's value in retaining
important detail. For example, "Technique X Improves Results" is
likely not a better one-line version than "Technique X Improves Metric
Y by 3%." Include specifics as much as you can.</p>
<p>It may be challenging to distill your message into a faithful one-line
representation, but it can be done. In some cases, a one-line version
is all you need.</p>
<h3><a name="paragraph"></a>Give a one-paragraph version</h3>
<p>Whether it's labeled as an abstract or a summary or not, a first
paragraph should always be a complete version of your message, not an
introduction.</p>
<p>The one-line version of your message may be just a sketch, but a
well-crafted paragraph lets you convey, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle">Pareto</a>-style, a complete
core message, missing only detail.</p>
<p>The practice of skipping quickly to an article's conclusion is not a
natural part of reading, it is a defensive work-around for bad
writing. Present the conclusion at the beginning.</p>
<p>You shouldn't require your audience go all the way to the end. For
example, if the purpose of an email is to make a request, make the
request clear at the beginning.</p>
<p>The focus here is effective, purposeful, reality-oriented
communication. This is distinct from small talk, poetry, or fiction,
where it may make sense to approach a topic obliquely over time, to
carefully build an effect.</p>
<p>With a useful one-paragraph version at the beginning, the audience can
determine what information is being communicated and what further
detail they're interested in. This is kind to your audience&#8212;and your
audience may be you.</p>
<h3><a name="detail"></a>Add detail until complete</h3>
<p>Including condensed versions at the beginning doesn't mean omitting
supporting detail, clarification, data, and other supplementary
material. Be very inclusive. The expectation is not that the audience
must review everything, but that they may.</p>
<p>Organize for the benefit of the audience. Make it easy to find things.
This should follow from the nature of what you're communicating, and
could also be responsive to the expectations of your audience.</p>
<p>The overall structure should often be fractal, in that further
sections are organized following the overall guidelines, starting with
short versions.</p>
<p>Generally, information density and polish should decrease gradually.
Content at the beginning is likely still elaborating the core message.
More related detail is added gradually, until toward the end one might
include a list of references, notes, logs of activities over time,
source data, audio or transcriptions from interviews, and the like.</p>
<p>Enough should be provided that the audience can replicate your
conclusions or form their own. Nothing should be hidden.</p>
<h3><a name="media"></a>Use the best of text and other media</h3>
<p>Text is a mighty tool, but it is not the only tool. Always use the
best available tool for communicating. Outside of conversation, text
and its variants together with two-dimensional graphics (especially
data visualizations) are most useful, with time-distributed media and
interactive artifacts only sometimes worthwhile.</p>
<p>Text can be used in many ways. Headings add structure. Numbered and
bulleted lists and tables can help organize and summarize. Fonts,
weights, sizes, and styles can assist in communication when used well.
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext">Hypertext</a> allows linking easily to related resources.</p>
<p>Numbers are data visualizations, as are quantitative tables. Carefully
presented numbers can be very communicative.</p>
<p>Graphics can help communicate ideas diagrammatically. Graphical data
visualizations (plots, graphs, charts) can convey quantitative
information exceptionally well; their effective use is an extended
topic. Images can also sometimes be useful.</p>
<p>Time-distributed media refers principally to audio and video. To date,
these are difficult to search or skim. They tend to require the
audience to sit through them. Similarly, interactive artifacts are
relatively oblique rather than communicating directly. There are
places for all of these, but they are not often the best choice for
direct communication.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200715-communicate_immediately/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200715-communicate_immediately/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Asimov's Foundation trilogy</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3Gdm40MPYnw">inspired</a> to read the core trilogy of Asimov's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foundation_series">Foundation</a>
series. Started in 1942, it's in many ways a relic, but it's
interesting for its <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foundation_series#Cultural_impact">influence</a> and explorations of how history
develops, what matters, what can be predicted, and what can be
controlled.</p>
<p>Hari Seldon comes up with a mathematical <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychohistory_(fictional)">psychohistory</a> for
predicting the future of society, obtaining predictions we are to take
as correct for up to 30,000 years in the future. As a kind of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statistical_mechanics">statistical mechanics</a> for humanity, it seems like
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/People%27s_history">history from below</a>. This conflicts with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_man_theory">Great Man Theory</a>&#8212;and
the author's desire to have characters drive developments (though the
main characters do once turn out to be totally irrelevant).</p>
<p>I usually think of the future as hard to <a href="/20200112-predicting_the_future_from_2020/">predict</a>, so just
imagining there could be such good predictions is kind of fun. Is it
just that we don't know how, or (as the book suggests) that it's only
possible on scales greater than one planet?</p>
<p>I've recently been <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_Revolutions_and_Financial_Capital">learning</a> about supposed economic cycles as long
as 50 to 60 years, but it isn't clear how truly predictive these are.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The current view of mainstream economics is that business cycles
are essentially the summation of purely random shocks to the economy
and thus are not, in fact, cycles, despite appearing to be so."
[<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_cycle">wiki</a>]</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also, if a prediction is widely known then it may no longer be valid,
which is then a possible incentive to secrecy. Regardless, it's fun to
think about how much can be predicted, how it might be done, and what
might invalidate predictions.</p>
<p><img alt="Foundation trilogy cover" src="foundation_cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200714-foundation_trilogy/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200714-foundation_trilogy/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Peopleware: Productive Projects and Teams</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
<p>"... the major issues of software development are human, not
technical."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peopleware:_Productive_Projects_and_Teams">1987 book</a> has wisdom still in rare supply. Humans are
non-modular. Solving problems relies on people more than technology.
The best management is something like an evolution of Montessori
teaching. The book is organized into six parts:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>"Managing the Human Resource" (introduction)</li>
<li>"The Office Environment" (literally, setting up a nice physical
   space)</li>
<li>"The Right People" (people are important, hire well, avoid
   turnover)</li>
<li>"Growing Productive Teams" (encourage teams to jell)</li>
<li>"Fertile Soil" (good practices for meetings, email, etc.)</li>
<li>"It's Supposed to Be Fun to Work Here" (conclusion)</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<h2>The book's recommendations</h2>
<p>Make it possible for people to work without interruption.</p>
<p>Everyone can be self-coordinating:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Each time you're inclined to send a coordinating e-mail to a
colleague or to anyone who works for you, think about what steps you
have to make to coach that person to self-coordinate. Don't expect
this to be easy. Telling someone what to do <em>is</em> easy, while
instilling self-coordinating abilities in that same person is much
more complicated. But it pays off in the long run." (page 202)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Process rules and strict methodologies are bad. Let people have good
<em>training</em>, <em>tools</em>, and <em>peer review</em> (page 180).</p>
<p>Every project should be trying exactly one really new thing. Apart
from escaping local maxima, this is based on an interesting
interpretation of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawthorne_effect">the Hawthorne Effect</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"... the <em>Hawthorne Effect</em>. Loosely stated, it says that people
perform better when they're trying something new." (page 181)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Consider "Open-Space meetings" which are informal "mingling" meetings
that allow small group conversations (pages 190-191).</p>
<p>They recommend brainstorming techniques &#224; la <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_de_Bono">de Bono</a> on page 228:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>"Analogy thinking (How does nature solve this or some similar
  problem?)"</li>
<li>"Inversion (How might we achieve the opposite of our goal?)"</li>
<li>"Immersion (How might you project yourself into the problem?)"</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>They encourage considering fallback plans, especially regarding
deadlines:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The risk we tend not to manage is the risk of our own failure."
(page 184)</p>
</blockquote>
<h2>Flipping attitudes</h2>
<p>The Netflix "<a href="https://igormroz.com/documents/netflix_culture.pdf">freedom and responsibility</a>" approach provides an
interesting contrast. Netflix wants to be "a pro sports team" with
coaches who "cut smartly, so we have stars".</p>
<p>The Peopleware authors note explicitly (page 158) that they dislike
the sports team comparison, because sports teams have internal
competition and individuals can succeed or fail independent of the
group.</p>
<p>The Netflix approach can sound exciting, but it's also why Netflix is
known for a <a href="https://qz.com/work/1439451/the-seven-ways-netflix-culture-sounds-like-your-worst-work-nightmare/">culture of fear</a>. Peopleware is much more like
<a href="/20151118-debugging_teams/">Debugging Teams</a>, with its focus on humility, respect, and trust.
"Above all, resist the urge to manage."</p>
<p>I hadn't known anything about TQM (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Total_quality_management">Total Quality Management</a>) but I
was interested to see that it's a real flip from what I'd expect from
such a bureaucratic-sounding name.</p>
<p><a href="https://asq.org/quality-resources/total-quality-management/deming-points">Deming&#8217;s 14 Points on Quality Management</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>"Create constancy of purpose for improving products and
   services."</li>
<li>"Adopt the new philosophy."</li>
<li>"Cease dependence on inspection to achieve quality."</li>
<li>"End the practice of awarding business on price alone; instead,
   minimize total cost by working with a single supplier."</li>
<li>"Improve constantly and forever every process for planning,
   production and service."</li>
<li>"Institute training on the job."</li>
<li>"Adopt and institute leadership."</li>
<li>"Drive out fear."</li>
<li>"Break down barriers between staff areas."</li>
<li>"Eliminate slogans, exhortations and targets for the workforce."</li>
<li>"Eliminate numerical quotas for the workforce and numerical
    goals for management."</li>
<li>"Remove barriers that rob people of pride of workmanship, and
    eliminate the annual rating or merit system."</li>
<li>"Institute a vigorous program of education and self-improvement
    for everyone."</li>
<li>"Put everybody in the company to work accomplishing the
    transformation."</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Some of those points seem opposed to <a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/">metrics</a>, which isn't always
the stance of the Peopleware authors:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Gilb's Law: <em>Anything you need to quantify can be measured in some
way that is superior to not measuring it at all.</em>" (page 58)</p>
</blockquote>
<h2>Hiring and development</h2>
<p>The authors seem generally capable of holding
<a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2020/01/05/intelligence/">two opposed ideas at the same time</a>, and this is especially true in
their takes on hiring and development of employees.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"... managers are unlikely to change their people in any meaningful
way. ... If they're not right for the job from the start, they never
will be." (page 94)</p>
<p>"At Southern California Edison some years ago, the person in charge
of all data processing began as a meter reader. At EG&amp;G, there was a
program of retraining administrative staff to become systems
analysts. At the Bureau of Labor Statistics, philosophy Ph.D.s are
hired to become software developers and the retraining starts with
their first day on the job. At Hitachi Software, the chief scientist
has as his principal function the training of new hires. At Pacific
Bell, a main source of new systems people is the retrained lineman
or operator." (page 123)</p>
<p>"If your staff isn't up to the job at hand, you will fail. Of
course, if the people are badly suited to the job, you should get
new people. But once you've decided to go with a given group, your
best tactic is to trust them. Any defensive measure taken to
guarantee success in spite of them will only make things worse."
(page 144)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is an interesting apparent tension.</p>
<h2>Signs of age, signs of prescience</h2>
<p>Peopleware was updated in 2013, but it isn't completely modern.
Innocuously, it refers to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_General#32-bit_Project_Eagle_-_the_Eagle_project">Eagle project</a> as if everyone knows
it. More unfortunately, it uses "<a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/o/open-kimono.asp">open kimono</a>" as if there's no
reason not to.</p>
<p>The authors rail against the interruptions of the telephone. At least
for me, this is dated. They're right, phones are awful, but everybody
knows this now and I can't remember the last time somebody called me
for work.</p>
<p>They emphasize the importance of uninterrupted work time and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)">flow</a>
in a way that is pretty well known now, I think. Paul Graham's 2009
<a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html">Maker's Schedule, Manager's Schedule</a> is one related
popularization.</p>
<p>The authors don't comment at all on remote work, which I think is
unfortunate.</p>
<h2>Two more quotes</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>"There is very little true teamwork required in most of our work."
(page 136)</p>
<p>"Managers are often not true members of their teams" (page 137)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img alt="cover" src="peopleware.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200523-peopleware_productive_projects_and_teams/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200523-peopleware_productive_projects_and_teams/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Looks like people don't die on weekends</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Like a lot of people, my hobby recently has been checking COVID-19
stats more often than is helpful. It can be hard to tell if a new
day's numbers are relatively good or bad, in part because of a
distinct weekly pattern.</p>
<p><img alt="Daily new COVID-19 deaths (USA)" src="data_and_trend.png"></p>
<p>If you take out the trend, it's clear that there are consistently
relatively fewer deaths reported on Sundays and Mondays. There's a
compensatory tendency for Tuesdays and Wednesdays to have higher
numbers of deaths reported.</p>
<p><img alt="Week day average COVID-19 deaths (USA) relative to trend" src="week_day_residuals.png"></p>
<p>This clearly shows that the way to fight COVID-19 is by instituting an
all-weekend policy.</p>
<p>But it really is an interesting phenomenon. What's causing this effect
in the data?</p>
<ul>
<li>Do people really avoid death on weekends? I could imagine a small
   effect in that direction, but I wouldn't think it would be anything
   like this big.</li>
<li>Is it purely a reporting effect? Lots of health professionals are
   working weekends these days, I suspect, but maybe clerical staff or
   others in the reporting chain take consistent weekends? I suspect
   this is the main explanation.</li>
<li>Why is it primarily Sunday and Monday rather than Saturday and
   Sunday? Do the daily numbers correspond more accurately to the
   prior day?</li>
</ul>
<p>In any event, it's a good idea to, for example, use a 7-day rolling
average (as <a href="https://www.ft.com/coronavirus-latest">in the Financial Times</a>) to avoid being mislead by this
weekly pattern.</p>
<hr>
<p>Update 2020-05-04: The plot above uses an average of numbers of
deaths, which feels raw and real, but isn't super meaningful against
the changing scale of the pandemic in the US over time. The version
below is by percent difference (weighted by the trend, to avoid undue
influence when the numbers were all small and the fit of the trend
isn't as good.)</p>
<p><img alt="Week day average COVID-19 deaths (USA) relative to trend (percentage)" src="week_day_residuals_percent.png"></p>
<p>The plot looks very similar, but these percentages can be used (with a
little math) to try to "seasonally adjust" daily US COVID-19 death
numbers. I'm not saying this has any particular statistical validity,
but it's one way to try to guess what a Sunday or Monday number really
means, for example.</p>
<hr>
<p>I used the New York Times' <a href="https://github.com/nytimes/covid-19-data">covid-19-data</a>. My code is all up
<a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/covid_weekend">on GitHub</a>.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200502-looks_like_people_dont_die_on_weekends/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200502-looks_like_people_dont_die_on_weekends/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Tyranny of Metrics, by Muller</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/hardcover/9780691174952/the-tyranny-of-metrics" title="The Tyranny of Metrics (Princeton University Press)">The Tyranny of Metrics</a> is the book version of the author's
<a href="https://www.the-american-interest.com/2015/08/03/the-costs-of-accountability/" title="The Costs of Accountability (The American Interest)">earlier article</a>. It's a pretty good <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2013/05/31/178263/the-dictatorship-of-data/" title="The Dictatorship of Data (MIT Technology Review)">collection</a> of <a href="https://www.amstat.org/asa/files/pdfs/POL-ASAVAM-Statement.pdf" title="ASA Statement on Using Value-Added Models for Educational Assessment">concerns</a>
around measurement, focused on <a href="https://fs.blog/2018/02/unintended-consequences/" title="The Law of Unintended Consequences: Shakespeare, Cobra Breeding, and a Tower in Pisa (Farnam Street)">unintended consequences</a>.</p>
<p>One thing that <a href="https://history.catholic.edu/faculty-and-research/faculty-profiles/muller-jerry/index.html">Muller</a>'s historical perspective brought out was the
development of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientific_management">scientific management</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Management_consulting">management consulting</a>
as practices distinct from particular fields or businesses. I think
there are parallels to the development of data science.</p>
<p>He also maintains that the main value of a metric can come from
looking at outliers rather than tracking averages or otherwise using
the metric over all cases. I think this is an often neglected focus.</p>
<p>There's a lot of interesting stuff. Here are some quotes that I
thought were particularly interesting:</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Accountability ought to mean being held responsible for one's
actions. But by a sort of linguistic sleight of hand, accountability
has come to mean demonstrating success through standardized
measurement, as if only that which can be counted really counts."
(page 4)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When proponents of metrics advocate "accountability," they tacitly
combine two meanings of the word. On the one hand, to be accountable
means to be responsible. But it can also mean "capable of being
counted."" (page 17)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This book is not about the evils of measuring. It is about the
unintended consequences of trying to substitute standardized
measures of performance for personal judgment based on experience.
The problem is not measurement, but excessive measurement and
inappropriate measurement&#8212;not metrics, but metric fixation." (page
4)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The key components of metric fixation are</p>
<ul>
<li>"the belief that it is possible and desirable to replace judgment,
  acquired by personal experience and talent, with numerical
  indicators of comparative performance based upon standardized data
  (metrics);</li>
<li>"the belief that making such metrics public (transparent) assures
  that institutions are actually carrying out their purposes
  (accountability);</li>
<li>"the belief that the best way to motivate people within these
  organizations is by attaching rewards and penalties to their
  measured performance, rewards that are either monetary
  (pay-for-performance) or reputational (rankings)." (page 18)</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>"Recurring Flaws" from Chapter 2:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>"Measuring the most easily measurable"</li>
<li>"measuring the simple when the desired outcome is complex"</li>
<li>"Measuring inputs rather than outcomes"</li>
<li>"Degrading information quality through standardization"</li>
<li>"Gaming through creaming"</li>
<li>"Improving numbers by lowering standards"</li>
<li>"Improving numbers through omission or distortion of data"</li>
<li>"Cheating"</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Under scientific management the managers assume ... the burden of
gathering together all of the traditional knowledge which in the
past has been possessed by the workmen and then of classifying,
tabulating, and reducing this knowledge to rules, laws, formulae...
Thus all of the planning which under the old system was done by the
workmen, must of necessity under the new system be done by
management in accordance with the law of science." (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_Winslow_Taylor">Taylor</a>
quoted pages 32-33)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is only through <em>enforced</em> standardization of methods,
<em>enforced</em> adoption of the best implements and working conditions,
and <em>enforced</em> cooperation that this faster work can be assured. And
the duty of enforcing the adoption of standards and enforcing this
cooperation rests with <em>management</em> alone." (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_Winslow_Taylor">Taylor</a> quoted page
33)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The calculative is the enemy of the imaginative." (page 61)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This lends a certain air of unreality to the explorations of what
one might call the unworldly economists, who combine hard measures
of statistical validity with weak interest in the validity of the
units of measurement." (page 72)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>The effect of valuing quantity over quality in academic publishing
leads to:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"a great stream of publications that are both uninteresting and
unread." (page 79)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This is an instance of <em>diagnostic</em> metrics. It provides data that
can be used by a practitioner (physician), or internally within an
institution (hospital), or shared among practitioners and
institutions to discover what is working and what is not, and to use
that information to improve performance." (page 110)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... the metrics matter because of the way they are embedded into a
larger institutional culture." (page 110)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Extrinsic rewards become an important determinant of job
satisfaction only among workers for whom intrinsic rewards are
relatively unavailable." (<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2778664" title="The Happy Worker: An Analysis of Educational and Occupational Differences in Determinants of Job Satisfaction">Gruenberg</a> quoted page 137)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The fact that allies spy on one another to a certain degree to
determine intentions, capacities, and vulnerabilities is well known
to practitioners of government. But it cannot be publicly
acknowledged, since it represents a threat to the amour propre of
other nations." (page 164)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Chapter 15 "Unintended but predictable negative consequences":</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>"Goal displacement through diversion of effort to what gets
  measured"</li>
<li>"Promoting short-termism"</li>
<li>"Costs in employee time"</li>
<li>"Diminishing utility"</li>
<li>"Rule cascades" (to prevent gaming the metrics, etc.)</li>
<li>"Rewarding luck"</li>
<li>"Discouraging risk-taking"</li>
<li>"Discouraging innovation"</li>
<li>"Discouraging cooperation and common purpose"</li>
<li>"Degradation of work" (the experience of working people)</li>
<li>"Costs to productivity"</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Chapter 16 "When and how to use metrics":</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>"What <em>kind</em> of information are you thinking of measuring?"</li>
<li>"How <em>useful</em> is the information?"</li>
<li>"How useful are <em>more</em> metrics?"</li>
<li>"What are the costs of <em>not</em> relying upon standardized
   measurement?"</li>
<li>"To what <em>purposes</em> will the measurement be put, or to put it
   another way, to <em>whom</em> will the information be made transparent?"</li>
<li>"What are the <em>costs</em> of acquiring the metrics?"</li>
<li>"Ask why the people at the top of the organization are demanding
   performance metrics."</li>
<li>"<em>How</em> and <em>by whom</em> are the measures of performance developed?"</li>
<li>"Remember that <em>even the best measures are subject to corruption
   or goal diversion.</em>"</li>
<li>"Remember that sometimes, recognizing the limits of the possible
    is the beginning of wisdom."</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Here Muller lists a factor outside the control of the American medical
system, citing page 84 of <em>In Excellent Health</em> by Atlas and a paper
on <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w14333" title="Socioeconomic Status and Health: Dimensions and Mechanisms">Socioeconomic Status and Health</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Moreover, the United States is an ethnically heterogeneous country,
and some ethnic groups (such as African Americans) have
disproportionately high rates of infant mortality, reflecting
social, cultural, and possibly genetic factors." (p. 106)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This strikes me as, at the very least, unfortunate phrasing. Here's
<a href="https://www.americanprogress.org/issues/early-childhood/reports/2018/02/01/445576/exploring-african-americans-high-maternal-infant-death-rates/" title="Exploring African Americans&#8217; High Maternal and Infant Death Rates">how some others talk</a> about African American infant mortality rates:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is racism, not race itself, that threatens the lives of African
American women and infants."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="tyranny.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Ultimate Question 2.0, by Reichheld</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I was interested in Net Promoter&#174; score, so I read <a href="https://www.netpromotersystem.com/books/the-ultimate-question-2.0/" title="The Ultimate Question 2.0">the book</a>, which
is a longer version of <a href="https://hbr.org/2003/12/the-one-number-you-need-to-grow" title="The One Number You Need to Grow">the original article</a>. NPS is an interesting
case study in simplicity, interpretability, paths to action,
unintended consequences, and data collection.</p>
<h3>Simplicity</h3>
<p>Net Promoter is built around one question, now common in many
variants, about whether you'd make a recommendation.</p>
<p><img alt="NPS summary" src="nps_summary.png"></p>
<p>The single-question approach may help with response rate, but that
isn't the only rationale.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Traditional satisfaction surveys ... ask too many questions and
inspire analysis instead of action." (pages ix-x)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Reichheld describes research supporting the use of a single question
as a correlate of growth, and clustering analysis supporting the three
response categories. Whether these are perfect is beside the point of
<em>focusing</em> on <em>some</em> data about customer experience.</p>
<h3>Interpretability</h3>
<p>The Net Promoter score is explained as the percentage of promoters
minus the percentage of detractors. This is equivalent to averaging a
remapping of the 0 to 10 scale, but better at maintaining a meaningful
interpretation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"[This] made sense to frontline managers, who could relate to the
goal of increasing the number of promoters and reducing the number
of detractors more readily than increasing the mean of their
satisfaction index by one standard deviation." (<a href="https://hbr.org/2003/12/the-one-number-you-need-to-grow" title="The One Number You Need to Grow">HBR</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This scoring method amounts to a kind of data visualization, focused
on communicating and understanding. Whether or not it generates the
best correlation coefficients with other quantities of interest,
there's little doubt that it's instantly understandable.</p>
<h3>Paths to Action</h3>
<p>The Net Promoter <em>score</em> is quantitative, but the <em>system</em> is always
supposed to include a second question: "What is the primary reason for
your score?" This is one of the ways that NPS becomes actionable.</p>
<p>The open-ended follow-up avoids "the preconceived response categories
of traditional customer-satisfaction questionnaires" (page 5) and
invites the power of anecdote.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Reading a comment from a customer promoter or detractor has far
more impact than looking at a statistic on a monthly report from
headquarters." (page 186)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The bottom-up application of NPS is intended to be non-anonymous and
closed-loop: An employee might call detractors shortly after their
responses come in to apologize and try to address issues immediately.</p>
<p>This kind of feedback helps to "Make NPS a tool to help people succeed
(not just an evaluation metric)" (page 254) independent of statistics.
The scores themselves can also be used more directly, but not without
risk.</p>
<h3>Unintended Consequences</h3>
<p>NPS generates scores can be compared, incentivized, and then gamed:
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodhart%27s_law">Goodhart's law</a>.</p>
<p>NPS can also be used to evaluate employee satisfaction: "employee Net
Promoter scores (eNPS)" (page 165). Like any data, it can be used for
questionable purposes.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"When JetBlue first began its eNPS surveys, it discovered pockets of
detractors. Upon deeper investigation, management learned that some
of these unhappy employees were preparing a union-organizing
campaign. Rapid intervention helped resolve the key issues before
things reached that point." (page 168)</p>
</blockquote>
<h3>Data Collection</h3>
<p>It's hard to get people to fill out surveys in the age of survey
fatigue.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Customers already receive too many survey requests, and as NPS
spreads, their tolerance will diminish." (page 238 of 2011 version
of 2006 book)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Reichheld recommends using phone surveys over register receipt surveys
or email surveys.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Phone surveys may not be the right long-term solution for your
firm, but beware of defaulting to the cheapest alternative." (page
237)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Even with the shortest possible surveys, people are just
<a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2016-05-04/tasty-taco-helpful-hygienist-are-all-those-surveys-of-any-use" title="The Inventor of Customer Satisfaction Surveys Is Sick of Them, Too">sick of them</a>, which is a challenge for getting good data.</p>
<hr>
<p>Reichheld is a consultant who focuses on customer loyalty. Cynically,
he wants to be known for "a full-fledged management system with an
ethos that rivals <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Six_Sigma">Six Sigma</a> in power" (front flap) and get his
metric on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balanced_scorecard">balanced scorecards</a>. Less cynically, he really wants
companies to treat everyone well and avoid "bad profits" created by
taking advantage of customers.</p>
<p><img alt="book cover" src="ultimate_cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>Otherwise unrelated quote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"A bounced check cost [Charles Schwab Corporation] 82 cents, but the
firm charged the client $40." (page 128)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200413-ultimate_question_by_reichheld/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200413-ultimate_question_by_reichheld/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Montessori Toddler, by Simone Davies</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>We saw <a href="https://www.workman.com/products/the-montessori-toddler">this book</a> at <a href="https://toddlersonthehill.org/">TOTH</a> and subsequently picked up a copy.
It's a very nice book with lots of good advice for living with
toddlers, and plenty of universally good advice.</p>
<p>I like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Montessori">Montessori</a> in general. I read <em>The Absorbent Mind</em> a long
time ago and recall it fondly. There's room for debate around exactly
how to operationalize it, but the underlying idea is that people are
good and will do well, on the basis of internal motivation, if they're
supported appropriately.</p>
<p>This comparison resonates with me:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"...the children in the [other] school always put up their
hands to ask the teacher if something was on the test. The
Montessori children were used to learning because they loved to do
so, not because they were being tested." (page 231)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The author also draws from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nonviolent_Communication">non-violent communication</a> and there's
an "Instead of This, Say That" section at the back, with
recommendations (like "Instead of blaming others, take
responsibility") that are good regardless of the age of the person
you're speaking with.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="montessori_toddler_cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200322-montessori_toddler/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200322-montessori_toddler/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Zombie Ideas</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<ul><a id="zombie"></a>
</ul>

<h3>What is this?</h3>
<p>Sometimes I put ideas in <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/issues">my blog's GitHub Issues</a> "for later"&#8212;but
then I don't look at them any more. It's an idea graveyard. So this
hits the GitHub API and randomly shows eight old ideas on every page
load. (View source to see code.) Maybe I'll be inspired?</p>
<p>New ideas seem exciting, and urgent things get done urgently. But I do
find myself sometimes looking for something to do (like finding a show
to watch) rather than realizing I could work on one of these old
ideas.</p>
<p>Some ideas got so little attention that I've even forgotten what my
note for the idea means. See also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spaced_repetition">spaced repetition</a>. There's also
some connection here to prioritization, to-do lists, deciding to say
no to an idea, etc...</p>
<p>Amusingly, I'd forgotten that this very idea was <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/issues/164">#164</a> "random idea
refresher" until it came up while I was testing this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"some way of showing you a sample of your own ideas, things to think
about, quotes, etc."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I still think this is a neat idea. For the time being, this page will
replace my usual new browser tab image.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20200209-zombie_ideas/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20200209-zombie_ideas/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
