<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>(Audio) Bullshit Jobs, by Graeber</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
<p>“There is only one success – to be able to spend your life in your
own way.” (Christopher Morley)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Graeber">Graeber</a> had a <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180807024932/http://strikemag.org/bullshit-jobs/">popular article</a> and this is the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullshit_Jobs">book version</a>. As with <a href="/20240519-survival_of_the_richest_by_rushkoff/">Rushkoff's</a>, the titular concept is
mostly a hook. I'm more interested in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Critique_of_work">critique of work</a>
generally.</p>
<p>The first part of the book, most directly on "bullshit jobs" and
related surveys and interviews, isn't very good, compared to Graeber's
<a href="/20240906-debt_by_graeber/" title="(Audio) Debt: The first 5,000 years, by Graeber">Debt</a>. He wants to have it both ways, for one thing: We must trust
the people who say their jobs are bullshit, and at the same time not
trust people who say their jobs aren't.</p>
<p>Then there's the definition of a bullshit job, which is never done
quite consistently. I think it's supposed to be jobs that don't make
any difference (if they aren't done, nothing changes). But this bleeds
in at least two directions: Jobs where we may not <em>like</em> the
difference they make, and jobs that <em>wouldn't</em> be necessary if things
were set up differently.</p>
<p>So Graeber repeatedly criticizes Obama for using job preservation as a
reason to not completely upend the health care system. If the current
employees were all sent home, it would be bad: people wouldn't get
insurance reimbursement, etc. The current jobs are only (or primarily)
"bullshit" to Graeber because he thinks a single payer (or similar)
system could take care of people with fewer employees.</p>
<p>And while I know part of Graeber's point is to critique the Puritan
work ethic and "middle class thinking" in general, many of his
malcontent subjects just aren't very sympathetic.</p>
<p>Graeber did an academic thesis on "life cycle service," the historical
practice in northern Europe in which a young person would spend seven
or so years as an apprentice or servant, with some other family,
collecting some pay until they could set off on their own. I thought
this was interesting in relation to the modern idea of FIRE (Financial
Independence, Retire Early) in which a person similarly works for
others until they have enough money to be independent and then does
whatever they want.</p>
<p>Graeber talks a lot about "spiritual violence," and while this may be
worse when a job feels pointless (see also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sayre%27s_law">Sayre's Law</a>) I don't
think it's unique to "bullshit jobs" but common to any job that has
you doing what you really don't want to do. Hence the Morley quote
about success as being "able to spend your life in your own way."
People really like self-determination.</p>
<p>Graeber does connect at least a little bit with Black's
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Abolition_of_Work">Abolition of Work</a> and the idea given book form in
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fully_Automated_Luxury_Communism">Fully Automated Luxury Communism</a>. He spends some time on work as
caring work rather than factory production. And he also comes out in
support of UBI.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240907-bullshit_jobs_by_graeber/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240907-bullshit_jobs_by_graeber/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Debt: The first 5,000 years, by Graeber</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Graeber">Graeber</a> doesn't like debt, in the modern quantified, financial
sense. Also he thinks people are wrong about the history of money, and
that we should listen to anthropologists more. Graeber's equation is
something like "obligation + measurement + violence = debt."</p>
<p>A smattering of his ideas as I remember them:</p>
<ul>
<li>The standard economics story of money (as arising because barter is
   too hard) is silly because people hardly ever barter in the first
   place, except sometimes with strangers.</li>
<li>The standard economics story of money starting with coinage, then
   later developing debt instruments (see also <a href="/20240825-principles_changing_world_order_dalio/" title="(Audio) Principles for dealing with the changing world order, by Dalio">Dalio</a>, "money as
   starting from metal, then notes exchangeable for metal, then fiat
   money") is silly because ideas and methods of debt come <em>first</em>.</li>
<li>The moralism of "always paying your debts" in culture and language.</li>
<li>No single theory of money (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chartalism">Chartalism</a>, etc.) is right on its
   own because "money has no essence" and money is just one piece of a
   big evolving world. (Similarly, Graeber has no single thesis on
   debt.)</li>
<li>"Baseline communism" refers to the natural "from each according to
   his ability, to each according to his needs" that we have in real
   human relations, like feeding a child or asking for someone to hand
   you something.</li>
<li>Debt as two equals agreeing to no longer be equal: Now <em>you</em> owe
   <em>me</em>. (In the extreme: debt peonage.)</li>
<li>The difference of kind that comes from quantification: Not just
   owing me a favor, but owing me $47.39. The relation to
   dehumanization, as when slavery puts a price on a person, which is
   only possible by removing or denying their complex real
   (unquantifiable) value. (Reminds me of <a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/" title="The Tyranny of Metrics, by Muller">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>.)</li>
<li>The necessity of violence to make people pay back debts, as when
   military power stands behind the IMF.</li>
<li>Occasional hints of primitivism or anarcho-primitivism.</li>
<li>And really, shouldn't we get rid of capitalism?</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240906-debt_by_graeber/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240906-debt_by_graeber/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Principles for dealing with the changing world order, by Dalio</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray_Dalio">Ray Dalio</a> likes gold, doesn't like when <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/money-printer-go-brrr">money printer go brrr</a>,
and does like China. He also likes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Kissinger">Kissinger</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genghis_Khan">Genghis Khan</a>.
Dalio says some reasonable and some interesting things, but it isn't
clear he <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/11/01/business/how-does-the-worlds-largest-hedge-fund-really-make-its-money.html" title="How Does the World’s Largest Hedge Fund Really Make Its Money?">practices</a> what he preaches, or that he's right.</p>
<p><img alt="bump" src="bump.png"></p>
<p>Dalio has a bunch of signals and a framework of big cycles organizing
history. It's a little bit <a href="/20200714-foundation_trilogy/" title="Asimov's Foundation trilogy">psychohistory</a> and a little bit
<a href="/20200728-technological_revolutions_and_financial_capital/" title="Technological Revolutions and Financial Capital, by Perez">cycle-finding</a>. For Dalio, the biggest cycle is the debt cycle,
followed by cycles of internal disorder and external disorder. He
describes money as starting from metal, then notes exchangeable for
metal, then fiat money.</p>
<p><img alt="empires" src="empires.png"></p>
<p>For Dalio, the step after fiat money is collapse. He cares a lot about
whether a currency is The Reserve Currency. Combining his signals, he
gets charts that show the rise and fall of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_guilder">Dutch guilder</a>, the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pound_sterling">British pound</a>, and (soon) the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US dollar</a>. China is ascendant,
never mind that their currency has been fiat longer than the dollar.</p>
<p>Dalio says he's identifying timeless principles of cause and effect.
Is he right? Historical causality is hard to test, but there are at
least a few problems with Dalio's claims.</p>
<p>For most of history, the idea of a reserve currency hasn't really made
sense. The modern monetary system is in this light novel, not
timeless. Dalio has a narrow understanding of money compared to the
anthroplogical view in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debt:_The_First_5,000_Years">Debt: The First 5,000 Years</a>, for example.</p>
<p>It's hard to find falsifiable predictions in Dalio's science. He
admits to not having good tools for predicting <em>when</em> any given thing
might happen. In this sense, his whole system is basically noticing
that things have fallen apart in the past and concluding that things
could fall apart in the future. It isn't even wrong.</p>
<p>Looking at the charts, I'm reminded of a common tension in data work:
Is data leading to theory, or is theory leading to data? Data can be
found to support most theories; what was the process here? It's rather
easy to imagine that Dalio's employees are skilled in finding what he
thinks is there.</p>
<p>Not that Dalio hasn't looked at history and so on. The
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriottentijd">Patriot movement</a> in the Netherlands does kind of feel like it
rhymes with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Make_America_Great_Again">MAGA</a> energy. He knows about
<a href="https://deloitte.wsj.com/riskandcompliance/china-spotlight-triangular-debt-considerations-1413864154">triangular debt in China</a>. He's even concerned about inequality,
though mostly because it can lead to wealth-destroying crises.</p>
<p>Does Dalio have the courage of his convictions? Perhaps not. He
frequently comes off as defensive, and digresses substantially into
his concerns about public scrutiny of the prominent. The historical
theory he seems to hold most instinctively is a great man theory in
which he and the people he talks to are great; he sounds like Trump
talking about how he knows the best people.</p>
<p>If you think your ideas are timeless, you may be right about what
happens next, but you probably won't predict things that have never
happened before. So Dalio is limited to predicting rearrangements of
the world order, not substantially new things. If Marx thought much
change was inevitable, Dalio thinks real change is fundamentally
impossible, that recurrence is the nature of society.</p>
<p>So Dalio picks China as the new king of the hill.</p>
<p>I'm curious about many of the things Dalio talks about. What causes
what in the world? How do we operate in reality? What lessons can we
learn from history? I have to think Dalio believes he's sincere about
his program. At the same time, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/11/01/business/how-does-the-worlds-largest-hedge-fund-really-make-its-money.html" title="How Does the World’s Largest Hedge Fund Really Make Its Money?">reporting</a> suggests his ability to
follow his own advice is as constrained as his ability to imagine a
better world. For all the lip service to evolution, Dalio doesn't seem
to be its exemplar.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240825-principles_changing_world_order_dalio/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240825-principles_changing_world_order_dalio/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Explanations enhance equity</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>In achieving understanding, a poor explanation can still be sufficient
for people who are relatively advantaged. Better explanations make it
possible for more people to achieve understanding more easily.</p>
<p>For a new idea, there was by definition no prior explanation. It is
generally quite difficult to come up with new useful ideas, and often
takes many years. Only very few people have any understanding of the
new idea at first.</p>
<p>Someone, maybe the discoverer, tries to communicate the new idea. This
may not be a great explanation. It may be cloaked in specialist
language, heavy with background preconceptions, hidden from broader
communities.</p>
<p>The trap of a poor explanation is that it can still be good enough for
the most active, prepared, diligent seekers. Some will realize it
isn't a good explanation, but understand anyway and move on. Others
will fight through the poor explanation and conclude, with a kind of
Stockholm syndrome, that the explanation is canonical. The poor
explanation starts to be repeated to students.</p>
<p>This cycle can get harder to break as it becomes common knowledge that
a subject is difficult, even if the difficulty is not innate but due
to the poor explanation. It becomes hard to differentiate between
removing unneeded complication and "dumbing down" the subject because
people have become attached to the way they learned it. Maybe the
subject is now a "filter class" that people take pride in having
overcome.</p>
<p>An explanation should not be a filter but a fortifier, lifting up the
listener from ignorance to understanding. Things should not be
oversimplified, but should be made as simple as possible, so that as
many people as possible can profit, as quickly as possible, from
sharing in mastery—and contribute to the next ideas.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240723-explanations_enhance_equity/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240723-explanations_enhance_equity/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Loonshots, by Bahcall</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>It's a fun book, especially at the beginning, where Bahcall has a lot
of underdog success stories. I think some of the ideas are decent, but
it's also more like an unfinished brainstorming session than a settled
science, and it's hard to distinguish useful theory from just-so
history. I'm fundamentally on board for more discoveries though!</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<p>A major metaphor in the book is "phase transitions," like solid to
liquid. Bahcall offers "The Innovation Equation" (details in
<a href="https://hbr.org/2019/03/the-innovation-equation" title="The Innovation Equation">HBR article</a>) for \( M \), "a certain size at which human groups
shift from embracing radical ideas to quashing them."</p>
<p>\[ M = \frac{E S^{2} F}{G} \]</p>
<p>The only right hand term that isn't unitless is \( S \), "management
span," which is the average number of direct reports that managers
have. Since \( S \) is squared, the result is in units of people
squared, which I don't think makes sense. With his training as a
physicist, it's a little surprising that Bahcall would do this. (Am I
missing something?)</p>
<p>Also surprising is that there's no constant term. (For example,
gravity isn't mass times mass divided by distance squared; there's a
constant that we have to get from data.) Bahcall plugs in \( E = 50\%
\), meaning compensation is 50% equity, which seems rare, then
management span of 6, and \( F = 1 \) meaning equal returns to
project work and politics, finishing with \( G = 12\% \) meaning 12%
compensation increase at promotion. Ignoring the units, this gives
150, and he claims a connection with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunbar%27s_number" title="Wikipedia: Dunbar's number">Dunbar's number</a>, saying
"That's interesting."</p>
<p>I have to think Bahcall doesn't really take this equation seriously;
he must intend it as an illustration for his narrative. Still, it
offends my sensibilities because it seems like math-washing:
presenting something that looks "fancy" to make it seem more
legitimate. In this case, the evidence isn't really anything more than
suggestive.</p>
<p>One issue is boundaries: Where does an organization begin and end?
DARPA is considered an example of an innovative organization. Do we
consider just the DARPA PMs? Also their contractors? The whole
Department of Defense?</p>
<p>I think a much more promising attempt might be made by switching from
the organization to the individual view: At what point does an
individual change their behavior, based on the local structure of
their organization and incentives? This would also be more coherent
with Bahcall's ideas about having different parts of an organization
working on different goals (loonshots vs. "franchise" work). How do
you get loonshots? Support people who work on them.</p>
<p>A deeper critique is that Bahcall's "loonshot" forces here seem more
about <em>doing your job</em> than about working on crazy innovative ideas
specifically. "Project work" is not necessarily loonshot work.</p>
<hr>
<p>This "Goals Gone Wild" <a href="https://www.hbs.edu/ris/Publication%20Files/09-083.pdf">paper</a> is pretty fun, and reminds me of
<a href="/20200425-tyranny_of_metrics_by_muller/" title="The Tyranny of Metrics, by Muller">The Tyranny of Metrics</a>. The paper includes this warning label:</p>
<p><img alt="warning" src="warning.png"></p>
<hr>
<p>Also referenced (a lot) is Vannevar Bush's 1945
<a href="https://www.nsf.gov/about/history/vbush1945.htm">Science: The Endless Frontier</a>, which reminds me of
<a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/" title="The Beginning of Infinity, by Deutsch">The Beginning of Infinity</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“The graveyard of unexplained experiments, as Land would soon show,
is a great place to find a False Fail.” (page 76)</p>
<p>“Some companies are the equivalent of an innovation landfill,” wrote
one senior Apple executive, who helped lure some of PARC’s best
engineers to Apple. “They are garbage dumps where great ideas go to
die. At PARC, the key development people kept leaving because they
never saw their products get into the market.” (page 115)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is an interesting idea: What's out there that's known but
ignored, currently, when it shouldn't be ignored? Bahcall uses the
example of radar's foundations being known but ignored by the Navy for
nearly 20 years. What fun things are out there, already discovered but
not yet exposed to sunlight?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>“While the individual man is an insoluble puzzle, in the aggregate
he becomes a mathematical certainty.” (Sherlock Holmes, in The Sign
of the Four, quoted page 117)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Seems like everybody wants to do <a href="/20200714-foundation_trilogy/" title="Asimov's Foundation trilogy">psychohistory</a>!</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240722-loonshots_by_bahcall/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240722-loonshots_by_bahcall/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Brave New Words, by Khan</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
<p>“... a teacher has to be adjusted to fit the mind of each boy and
girl it teaches ... each kid has to be taught differently.” (Asimov,
<a href="https://www.bartlettschools.org/pdf/TheFunTheyHad.pdf">The Fun They Had</a>, 1951)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The title of this book refers to LLM text generation and Khan's call
for “educated bravery” in meeting new technologies, but it also refers
to Brave New World, a distopia. In his introduction, Khan mentions
<a href="https://planspace.org/20210422-the_diamond_age_by_stephenson/" title="The Diamond Age, by Stephenson">Diamond Age</a>, Ender's Game, and <a href="https://www.bartlettschools.org/pdf/TheFunTheyHad.pdf">The Fun They Had</a> as fiction
that “has gone on to inspire very real innovation.” In
<a href="https://planspace.org/20210422-the_diamond_age_by_stephenson/" title="The Diamond Age, by Stephenson">Diamond Age</a>, three “AI” books are really humans behind the scenes,
and the actual AI books train a child army. In Ender's Game, the
educational technology serves the goal of genocide. And in Asimov's
<a href="https://www.bartlettschools.org/pdf/TheFunTheyHad.pdf">The Fun They Had</a>, the joke is that AI education would make
children long for the current world of schooling. I'm fascinated by
the same fiction as Khan. I also think of the Star Trek post-scarcity
world (<a href="/20201109-economics_of_star_trek_by_webb/" title="The Economics of Star Trek, by Webb">1</a>, <a href="/20210401-trekonomics_by_saadia/" title="Trekonomics, by Saadia">2</a>) as an inspiration. I think Khan is right that
LLMs present opportunities, but they also face persistent challenges
of education.</p>
<p>There is a kind of “AI exceptionalism” that imagines generative AI as
immune to problems faced elsewhere. For example, Khan criticizes
Google for having ads. But will commercial LLMs remain disinterested?
Khan Academy doesn't offer its Khanmigo AI tutor for free to students
because of the cost of AI inference, and it's hard to imagine that
LLMs are permanently immune to the attentions of advertisers. And
while Khan speaks glowingly of Khanmigo, there is already at least one
<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/01/us/ai-chatbot-los-angeles-schools.html" title="A.I. ‘Friend’ for Public School Students Falls Flat">example</a> of a failed AI ed-bot effort.</p>
<p>More generally, Khan would have education and LLMs as somehow beyond
having a point of view, absolutely impartial. Researchers have worked
hard on “alignment” that creates this illusion, and certainly a
Socratic approach can have value in education. But fundamentally there
<em>is no</em> impartial view of the world, and the effect in aiming for one
is to allow the inane while preventing progress.</p>
<p>Khan wants to engage students by “incorporating their interests” in
ways that are superficial and misleading. One way to fail in this is
to imagine content as irredeemably rigid, and try to apply a false
veneer. Another way is to imagine there is no content in particular
worth focusing on.</p>
<p>Khan gives one example of imagining a soccer coach modeling goals
scored with a polynomial, and then asking for the degree of this
polynomial and the leading coefficient. This is a weak trick at best,
and doesn't at all get to <em>why</em> anyone would care about the question.
Applications can be motivating, but this one is so artificial that it
seems more likely to damage credibility.</p>
<p>Later Khan imagines restructuring a class's study of World War 2
through a focus on baseball, in a way that seems to suggest that
baseball was just as important an aspect of World War 2 as anything
else. I could see a research project on this narrow subject for an
interested student, but I also think that the bigger features of WW2
should not be deprioritized in order to pander to interests.</p>
<p>One theme here is that part of education is learning what's
interesting about things you weren't previously interested in. You
shouldn't come out of a class with only the same interests that you
went in with.</p>
<p>On history specifically, there's probably a lot more to discuss. Khan
offers that “it is impossible to engage in calculus if you don’t know
Algebra 2 well, but one can imagine engaging in college-level history
even without a strong foundation in history from high school.” I don't
know whether all history teachers would agree. To me, to the extent
that this is true, it suggests a problem with history as a discipline
at least as it is taught. I think we should ask more of history, make
more connections, draw more conclusions, have more of a sense of both
the theory and application of history. I think Khan is imagining
history as if, were it math, in high school students would learn one
table of equations and then in college learn a second table of
equations, never learning what they mean or how to use them. Perhaps
because lessons learned from history can have a political
interpretation, history is kept in schools with its hands tied? And so
we repeat the errors of the past.</p>
<p>In attempting to be impartial, existing curricula can become dogma.
Khan is so focused on how to teach everyone Pre-Algebra, Algebra 1,
and Algebra 2, that there doesn't seem to be room for re-thinking our
choices in what we teach. The “how” of education is important, but I
think the “what” and “why” are keystones, and at least as in need of
attention in light of technological advancement.</p>
<p>One pet peeve of mine is titles that are not conceptually coherent.
This is the case for Pre-Algebra, Algebra 1, and Algebra 2. These are
not good titles for courses. They reflect a bulk-frozen structure that
we should be embarrassed to offer students. Imagine if a student
submitted an outline so lousy, where the top-level bullets were "first
stuff," "second chunk," and "last bits." We should expect more clarity
of thought. No student should be given a grab bag of things to learn
without better organizing concepts and rationale, and that starts at
the level of course titles.</p>
<p>I suspect much of what is taught in schools could be improved
(dropped, modified, added to). This is not necessarily easy to do
(<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Math" title="Wikipedia: New Math">New Math</a>?) but there have been improvements over time and I
expect they can be extended. It has become rare for students to
memorize and recite <a href="https://allpoetry.com/Against-Idleness-and-Mischief">Against Idleness and Mischief</a>, for example,
while calculus, which used to be exclusively a university topic, is
now encountered by many in high school. Improving <em>what</em> is taught
should get more attention.</p>
<p>It seems like AI may move some classroom setups in directions that
feel old-fashioned: More in-person writing and tests, more focus on
spoken communication. Perhaps it will seem more obvious that teachers
are a specific type of manager, which has always been the case though
not always widely acknowledged. The toolkit expands.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240718-brave_new_words_by_khan/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240718-brave_new_words_by_khan/</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Titan, by Chernow</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I wouldn't have chosen this, but it was a book club pick. It did turn
out to be interesting enough for me to make it through over 35 hours
of audio. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron_Chernow" title="Ron Chernow">Chernow</a> does well, and there's lots to say about
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_D._Rockefeller" title="John D. Rockefeller">Rockefeller</a>. His dad was quite a character, and his son funded
Colonial Williamsburg, turns out. Topics of business, wealth, and the
good life remain relevant.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240625-titan_by_chernow/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240625-titan_by_chernow/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>A brief development of matrix multiplication</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Linear Algebra is math for multiple dimensions. Linearity is a
constraint that makes handling multi-dimensional complexity more
tractable. The structure of linear transformations quickly gives rise
to the dot product and matrix multiplication.</p>
<p>In Linear Algebra, a function is linear if \( f(u+v) = f(u) + f(v)
\) and \( f(cu) = cf(u) \). This is a powerful constraint. The
common equation of a line, \( y = f(x) = mx + b \), is not linear by
this definition when \( b \neq 0 \). In the situation of one numeric
input and output, linear functions are multiplication by a constant
coefficient, \( y = f(x) = mx \).</p>
<p>If there are two inputs and one output, linear functions are
multiplications followed by addition, \( y = f(x_1, x_2) = m_1 x_1 +
m_2 x_2 \). This is the dot product of the vector \( \vec{x} = (x_1,
x_2) \) and the coefficient vector \( \vec{m} = (m_1, m_2) \). The
result is a linear combination of the inputs.</p>
<p>If there are two inputs and two outputs, each output is a linear
combination of the inputs, \( (y_1, y_2) = f(x_1, x_2) = (m_1 x_1 +
m_2 x_2, m_3 x_1 + m_4 x_2) \), also written \( \vec{y} = M \vec{x}
\).</p>
<p>Applying a second linear transform \( N \) to the output of \( M
\), the new outputs \( y_1 \) and \( y_2 \) are:</p>
<p>\[ n_1 (m_1 x_1 + m_2 x_2) + n_2 (m_3 x_1 + m_4 x_2), \\
    n_3 (m_1 x_1 + m_2 x_2) + n_4 (m_3 x_1 + m_4 x_2)  \]</p>
<p>Re-grouping shows that applying these two linear transforms one after
the other is the same as applying just one linear transform with
different coefficients:</p>
<!--
n_1 m_1 x_1 + n_1 m_2 x_2 + n_2 m_3 x_1 + n_2 m_4 x_2,
n_3 m_1 x_1 + n_3 m_2 x_2 + n_4 m_3 x_1 + n_4 m_4 x_2

n_1 m_1 x_1 + n_2 m_3 x_1 + n_1 m_2 x_2 + n_2 m_4 x_2,
n_3 m_1 x_1 + n_4 m_3 x_1 + n_3 m_2 x_2 + n_4 m_4 x_2
-->

<p>\[ (n_1 m_1 + n_2 m_3) x_1 + (n_1 m_2 + n_2 m_4) x_2, \\
    (n_3 m_1 + n_4 m_3) x_1 + (n_3 m_2 + n_4 m_4) x_2  \]</p>
<p>If \( N M = T \), then \( t_1 \) is the dot product of \( (n_1,
n_2) \) and \( (m_1, m_3) \), and so on. The coefficients can be
arranged so that each pair that appears is adjacent horizontally or
vertically.</p>
<p>\[
\begin{bmatrix}
n_1 &amp; n_2 \\
n_3 &amp; n_4
\end{bmatrix}
\begin{bmatrix}
m_1 &amp; m_2 \\
m_3 &amp; m_4
\end{bmatrix} =
\begin{bmatrix}
n_1 m_1 + n_2 m_3 &amp; n_1 m_2 + n_2 m_4 \\
n_3 m_1 + n_4 m_3 &amp; n_3 m_2 + n_4 m_4
\end{bmatrix}
\]</p>
<p>There is a choice here: The coefficients are written in English
reading order, left to right and top to bottom. They could just as
well be placed top to bottom and right to left, for example. This
choice is arbitrary, but the nature of matrix multiplication is not.</p>
<hr>
<p>This is a terse version of what I think could be a good way to
introduce Linear Algebra and matrix multiplication. It is a more
traditionally symbolic version of
<a href="/20210915-flow_metaphor_for_matrix_multiplication/">the flow metaphor for matrix multiplication</a>, with more focus on
linearity as a driving part of the meaning of Linear Algebra.</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240624-brief_development_matrix_multiplication/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240624-brief_development_matrix_multiplication/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Linear Algebra Done Right, by Axler</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Axler's beautiful <a href="https://linear.axler.net/">textbook</a>, now in Open Access for the fourth
edition, is sort of an expansion of his 1995
<a href="https://www.axler.net/DwD.html" title="Down with Determinants!">Down with Determinants!</a> and is full of his characteristic
humanity, humor, joy, and good sense. I love the book's title most for
the implication that there <em>are</em> different ways that linear algebra
can be done—and Axler's book is convincing evidence that developing
the subject without prioritizing determinants can be done well.</p>
<p>The equation on the cover is the closed form solution for the \( n
\)th Fibonacci number, derived using linear algebra in an exercise on
page 174, just one of the book's treasures.</p>
<p><img src="cover.png" height="640"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Do not memorize the formula for the product of two complex
numbers—you can always rederive it by recalling that \( i^2 = -1
\) and then using the usual rules of arithmetic (as given by 1.3).
(page 2)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I love seeing advice like this in textbooks; sort of a didactic
principle of emphasizing what's fundamental and what's a
consequence... On the other hand you don't want to re-derive
everything every time, but there's some optimization of what gets a
spot in memory...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>When we think of an element of \( \mathbb{R}^2 \) as an arrow, we
refer to it as a vector.</p>
<p>Whenever we use pictures in \( \mathbb{R}^2 \) or use the somewhat
vague language of points and vectors, remember that these are just
aids to our understanding, not substitutes for the actual
mathematics that we will develop. (page 8)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Also good pedagogy here, I think: making a distinction between the
thing itself and a mental model or metaphor for it.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Mathematical models of the economy can have thousands of variables,
say \( x_1, ..., x_{5000} \), which means that we must work in \(
\mathbb{R}^{5000} \). Such a space cannot be dealt with
geometrically. However, the algebraic approach works well. Thus our
subject is called <strong>linear algebra</strong>. (page 8)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I appreciate the attempt to justify the name, but I feel like this one
isn't completely satisfying... Good aspect: Gets at the centrality of
multi-dimensionality. Less good aspect: Doesn't really justify the
"linear" part.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>We could define a multiplication in \( \mathbb{F}^n \) in a
similar fashion, starting with two elements of \( \mathbb{F}^n \)
and getting another element of \( \mathbb{F}^n \) by multiplying
corresponding coordinates. Experience shows that this definition is
not useful for our purposes. Another type of multiplication, called
scalar multiplication, will be central to our subject. (page 9)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I feel like the appeal to experience is not a satisfying justification
for matrix multiplication. I like the <a href="/20210915-flow_metaphor_for_matrix_multiplication/" title="The flow metaphor for matrix multiplication">flow metaphor</a>, and I think
even better can be done than my exposition there...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In general, a vector space is an abstract entity whose elements
might be lists, functions, or weird objects. (page 14)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Fun example of being both mathematically rigorous and friendly in
communication.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>I at once gave up my former occupations, set down natural history
and all its progeny as a deformed and abortive creation, and
entertained the greatest disdain for a would-be science which could
never even step within the threshold of real knowledge. In this mood
I betook myself to the mathematics and the branches of study
appertaining to that science as being built upon secure foundations,
and so worthy of my consideration.</p>
<p>—Frankenstein, Mary Wollstonecraft Shelley (page 50)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Axler has inserted some fun quotes at the ends of sections here and
there; this is one I liked.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>We will frequently use the powerful fundamental theorem of linear
maps, which states that the dimension of the domain of a linear map
equals the dimension of the subspace that gets sent to 0 plus the
dimension of the range. (page 51)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Thus the linear functions of high school algebra are not the same as
linear maps in the context of linear algebra. (page 56)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He's using zero-to-zero to show this here. I think this is a really
helpful thing to emphasize immediately.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Consider linear maps \( T: U \to V \) and \(S: V \to W \). The
composition \( ST \) is a linear map from \( U \) to \( W \).
Does \( M(ST) \) equal \( M(S)M(T) \)? This question does not
yet make sense because we have not defined the product of two
matrices. We will choose a definition of matrix multiplication that
forces this question to have a positive answer. (page 72)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here is at least some justification of matrix multiplication. I think
it comes a little late, since matrices were introduced already, and
really they sort of co-design...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Note that we define the product of two matrices only when the number
of columns of the first matrix equals the number of rows of the
second matrix. (73)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Couldn't this be made to feel less arbitrary?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The fundamental theorem of algebra is an existence theorem. Its
proof does not lead to a method for finding zeros. The quadratic
formula gives the zeros explicitly for polynomials of degree 2.
Similar but more complicated formulas exist for polynomials of
degree 3 and 4. No such formulas exist for polynomials of degree 5
and above. (page 124)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Axler does a lot to connect these algebra ideas and linear algebra,
which is pretty cool.</p>
<p>It's the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abel%E2%80%93Ruffini_theorem" title="Abel–Ruffini theorem">Abel–Ruffini theorem</a> that shows there aren't formulas for
degree five and up. Is this mentioned when teaching the quadratic
formula? Would be cool to at least show the crazy equations for degree
three and four...</p>
<p>A later example:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This exercise shows that every monic polynomial is the minimal
polynomial of some operator. Hence a formula or an algorithm that
could produce exact eigenvalues for each operator on each \(
\mathbb{F}^n \) could then produce exact zeros for each polynomial
[by 5.27(a)]. Thus there is no such formula or algorithm. However,
efficient numeric methods exist for obtaining very good
approximations for the eigenvalues of an operator. (page 152)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Now we begin our investigation of operators, which are linear maps
from a vector space to itself. Their study constitutes the most
important part of linear algebra. (page 132)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The word eigenvalue is half-German, half-English. The German prefix
eigen means “own” in the sense of characterizing an intrinsic
property. (page 134)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I like this kind of explanation.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The main reason that a richer theory exists for operators (which map
a vector space into itself) than for more general linear maps is
that operators can be raised to powers. (page 137)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>A central goal of linear algebra is to show that given an operator
\( T \) on a finite-dimensional vector space \( V \), there
exists a basis of \( V \) with respect to which \( T \) has a
reasonably simple matrix. (page 154)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>You may recall from a previous course that every matrix of numbers
can be changed to a matrix in what is called row echelon form. If
one begins with a square matrix, the matrix in row echelon form will
be an upper-triangular matrix. Do not confuse this upper-triangular
matrix with the upper-triangular matrix of an operator with respect
to some basis whose existence is proclaimed by 5.47 (if \(
\mathbb{F} = \mathbb{C} \))—there is no connection between these
upper-triangular matrices. (page 160)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The Euclidean algorithm for polynomials (look it up) can quickly
determine the greatest common divisor of two polynomials, without
requiring any information about the zeros of the polynomials. (page
173)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I'm just amused by the "look it up".</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Thus the pseudoinverse provides what is called a best fit to the
equation above. (page 222)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I thought a bit about how linear regression is solved. The thing
that's usually written down, \( (X^T X)^{-1} X^T y \), is really
crummy computationally if \( X \) isn't well-behaved, because of the
inverse...</p>
<p>It seems like nobody actually implements regression this way. In R,
<code>lm</code> is done via QR decomposition, anyway.</p>
<p>The pseudoinverse seems to work too, but doesn't always give the same
solution, when multiple solutions are possible. I suspect it isn't
used in practice because SVD is more work than QR. There may be more
reasons.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Recall that an operator on \( V \) is called diagonalizable if the
operator has a diagonal matrix with respect to some basis of \( V
\). Recall also that this happens if and only if there is a basis
of \( V \) consisting of eigenvectors of the operator (see 5.55).
(page 243)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>7.54 eigenvalues of unitary operators have absolute value 1 (page 262)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Makes me want to see some quantum examples...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>8.50 trace of matrix of operator does not depend on basis (page 327)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>How cool is this? Could it come earlier?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Our definition of the determinant leads to the following magical
proof that the determinant is multiplicative. (page 357)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We're having fun!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Vandermonde matrices have important applications in polynomial
interpolation, the discrete Fourier transform, and other areas of
mathematics. (page 366)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Makes me want to read an applied book.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>I find that in my own elementary lectures, I have, for pedagogical
reasons, pushed determinants more and more into the background. Too
often I have had the experience that, while the students acquired
facility with the formulas, which are so useful in abbreviating long
expressions, they often failed to gain familiarity with their
meaning, and skill in manipulation prevented the student from going
into all the details of the subject and so gaining a mastery.</p>
<p>—Elementary Mathematics from an Advanced Standpoint: Geometry, Felix
Klein (page 369)</p>
</blockquote>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240616-linear_algebra_done_right/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240616-linear_algebra_done_right/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Survival of the Richest, by Rushkoff</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Billionaire bunkers are just Rushkoff's hook. His gripe is with
capitalist growth as both cause and effect of the rich, and (he
argues) cause of social and environmental calamities past and future.
Rushkoff's <a href="https://wwnorton.com/books/survival-of-the-richest" title="Survival of the Richest: Escape Fantasies of the Tech Billionaires">book</a> argues for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Degrowth" title="Wikipedia: Degrowth">degrowth</a>.</p>
<p>I really like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_Rushkoff" title="Wikipedia: Douglas Rushkoff">Rushkoff</a> in some respects. I wish his <a href="https://www.teamhuman.fm/" title="Team Human">Team Human</a>
podcast would make really nice basketball jerseys and sweatshirts. (I
consider myself on Team Human quite independent of whatever Rushkoff
says; I think it's a nice idea.)</p>
<p>I don't think escapism is unique to the ultra-rich. Every time I put
on headphones, in some ways I'm trying to find safety in isolation.
Not only the wealthy are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Survivalism" title="Wikipedia: Survivalism">preppers</a>. Everyone could do well to
reflect on how interdependent we all really are.</p>
<p>There's a bit of a failure of imagination in not exploring in the
direction of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlas_Shrugged" title="Wikipedia: Atlas Shrugged">Atlas Shrugged</a>. Perhaps a Marxist can't imagine the
proletariat being replaced by technology. I <a href="https://planspace.org/20220101-predicting_the_future_from_2022/" title="Predicting the future from 2022">still</a> think that in
the near term "There will continue to be more real problems with not
having enough people to work than there are with having too many
people put out of work by technology," but there are big questions
about what's going to happen with all the people not working
conventional jobs (of which there are many already today).</p>
<p>I don't think Rushkoff has a good argument here. But he says so <em>many</em>
things that the book is quite thought-provoking regardless. He
characterizes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/QAnon" title="Wikipedia: QAnon">QAnon</a> as a kind of internet addiction. And you get
to hear about the many parties he's been invited to. Lucky you.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>He [<a href="https://nds-nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Dawkins" title="Wikipedia: Richard Dawkins">Richard Dawkins</a>] couldn’t acknowledge that his own
commitment to scientism is based on something passional—something
more like <em>faith</em> in an empiricist universe. In other words, his
insistence on living in an evidence-only universe isn’t based on
evidence at all. It’s an assumption. It’s part of a system of
meaning, developed by a community of people over time. It just
happens to be a meaning system that ignores meaning itself. Worse,
by rejecting the validity of any other meaning system, it is prone
to instilling in its adherents a sense of superiority over others.
Those who strive for meaning are mere “moralists.” (page 34)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I agree with parts of this critique; science should recognize its
foundation and scope.</p>
<hr>
<h3>A rather long tangent on a strange claim</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Initially the market economy, introduced just after the Crusades in
the late Middle Ages, benefited the former peasants of feudalism.
This was a lateral, peer-to-peer economy, not a hierarchical one.
Local farmers and bakers didn’t generally aspire to be “rich” so
much as to sustain themselves. Their currencies were optimized for
trade; they were less a way of saving or hoarding money than
facilitating the exchange of goods between people. It worked so well
that Europe saw its greatest period of economic growth to this
day—measured in the prosperity of the common folk. Towns got so
wealthy that they invested in building cathedrals to spur future
pilgrimages and tourism. People worked less, ate more, and grew
taller than ever before—and in some cases, ever since. (page 40)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't think this is the dominant historical view, but this time does
seem to be Rushkoff's "make economics great again" period. It's a
rather bold claim, saying that everybody used to be better off, and
even taller than now!</p>
<p>The citation here is the unpublished (but available online)
<a href="https://bernard-lietaer.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2004-Of-Human-Wealth-Beyond-Greed-Scarcity-Lieater-Belgin-annotated.pdf" title="Of Human Wealth">Of Human Wealth</a>. The authors (Lietar and Belgin) call the period
1050-1290 "the first European renaissance." On page 92 they have this
graph in classic Excel style:</p>
<p><img alt="graph from Of Human Wealth" src="of_human_wealth.png"></p>
<p>On page 91, the "ever since" is explained:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In a study of the skeletons of bodies in the same geographical area
(the City of London), informative findings emerged. The women of the
10-12th century were on average taller than in any other period in
recorded history, at least in London. During that period, the
average female Londoner was a whopping 7 centimeters taller than her
counterpart in Victorian times and 1 centimeter taller than the
average woman of London today! (Of Human Wealth, page 91)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The source for all this is <a href="https://www.amazon.com/London-Bodies-Changing-Londoners-Prehistoric/dp/090481890X" title="London Bodies: The Changing Shape of Londoners from Prehistoric Times to the Present Day">London Bodies</a>, the book companion to a
1998 exhibit at the Museum of London. The graph in Of Human Wealth
seems to be based on a table on the last page:</p>
<p><img alt="page from London Bodies" src="london_bodies.jpg"></p>
<p>It isn't clear that this is an authoritative source for drawing
conclusions about trends in height over time. It also isn't clear that
the table is even consistent with the rest of its own book, and
further it seems that Of Human Wealth is rather abusing what there is
in London Bodies anyway.</p>
<p>The "Saxon" numbers seem to correspond to page 56, in the "Saxon
Bodies" chapter:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>From this period, the eleventh and twelfth centuries, comes our best
group of medieval skeletons from a parish churchyard in London.
Excavations between 1975 and 1979 at the cemetery of St Nicholas
Shambles on Newgate Street produced over 200 burials. The average
heights of the people buried in the cemetery were 173cm (5ft 8in.)
for men and 157cm (5ft 2in.) for women. (London Bodies, page 56)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here the value for men matches the table, but the number for women is
quite different. Indeed nowhere in the "Saxon Bodies" chapter does the
163cm number appear.</p>
<p>Regardless of whether the number in the table is a typo or not, there
are many reasons to be skeptical. People buried at a particular church
are not at all guaranteed to be a random sample of the population.
Then there's the different methods for the heights: the first six
periods use long bone lengths, while the last two use height records.
The Victorian period is particularly suspect because it's based
exclusively on heights of "habitual criminals," not known to be the
most well-nourished of a given population. The mapping that the
authors of Of Human Wealth do from London Body's period labels to
centuries is also not quite right but hardly even worth mentioning
compared to everything else.</p>
<p>I'm sure I don't know enough about history to provide a complete
evaluation of this whole "first European renaissance" theory, but from
what I can see it doesn't seem very convincing. I'm surprised Rushkoff
would even mention it, and the fact he does makes me more skeptical of
everything else he says.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240519-survival_of_the_richest_by_rushkoff/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240519-survival_of_the_richest_by_rushkoff/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Build, by Fadell</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The "advice encyclopedia" from the father of the iPod is <a href="https://www.buildc.com/the-book" title="Build, the Book">billed</a> as
"an unorthodox guide" and maybe it is, depending on your orthodoxy.
Here are some of its recommendations as I recall them:</p>
<ul>
<li>Work really hard.</li>
<li>Be a perfectionist.</li>
<li>Micro-manage. (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Fadell" title="Tony Fadell">Tony</a> tries to clarify that what he recommends
   isn't micro-managing; the distinction is something like managing
   outputs as good vs. process as bad.)</li>
<li>Push people hard.</li>
<li>Have interviews done by a small group of people who will work with
   the new person, not a bunch of people from all over the company.</li>
<li>Don't have a lot of perks at the office.</li>
<li>Blame Google for Nest not going how you wanted.</li>
</ul>
<p>I think the most interesting thing, to me, is the tension between
intrinsic motivation vs. external pushing for generating results. Tony
seems like a pusher, and he's gotten results. But do bosses have to be
so hard-driving?</p>
<p>Fadell comments on how much time he spent on "people problems" (HR or
personnel issues) as a leader. This might always be the case, but I
also wonder whether particular leadership styles (and related hiring
choices) lead to more of this. Fadell says he followed a "no assholes
rule" in hiring. Might anosognosia be at play?</p>
<p>I'm not sure I'd like to work with Fadell, but I tend to like his
goals and his <a href="https://www.buildc.com/" title="Build Collective">Build Collective</a> seems to be supporting cool things.
(Ends vs. means?) The book is almost a promotional tie-in for this
venture operation.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240517-build_by_fadell/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240517-build_by_fadell/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Understanding bipolar disorder, by Daramus</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This 2020 <a href="https://www.audeotherapy.com/new-workbook-for-families-ofpeople-with-bipolar-disorder" title="Understanding Bipolar Disorder: The Essential Family Guide">book</a> is short (149 pages) and kind. With a therapist's
tact, it advises stoic behavior (see also: <a href="/20210107-enchiridion_in_52_sentences/" title="The Enchiridion in 52 sentences">The Enchiridion</a>) and
introduces helpful concepts and terminology (like on page 107,
"euthymic" means "not having a mood episode right now"). It seems like
pretty good guidance for a difficult condition.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There are times when having someone with bipolar live at home with
family is no longer realistic, and the person is not ready to live
on their own. In that case, a group home might be an option. (page
78)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It Won’t Work Right Away, and Not Everything Will Work (page 91)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes someone will go off medication without medical
supervision. This is dangerous but understandable. (page 94)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes You Need to Be a Caregiver (page 122)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>No matter how stable someone becomes, there will probably be another
mood episode eventually. (page 123)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Know the difference between your need to control things and what
will actually work. (page 135)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Repeated mood episodes are part of bipolar disorder: expect
setbacks. It’s not a disorder that anyone truly gets over, at least
not yet. (page 145)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240517-understanding_bipolar_disorder_by_daramus/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240517-understanding_bipolar_disorder_by_daramus/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Material World, by Conway</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ed_Conway">Conway</a> offers glimpses into a material world of sand, salt, iron,
copper, oil, and lithium for inhabitants of the aetherial world of
knowledge, software, and office blocks. It's often fascinating, and
delivers a thesis of global interconnection: we all depend on
everyone.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chloralkali_process">Chloralkali process</a> is electrolysis of very salty water. It
produces chlroine gas, which will kill you, and sodium hydroxide aka
lye, which isn't healthy either and which you can use to pulp wood and
make paper. This is very cool, and something you could probably do at
home. It's a little dangerous. I wonder if this is part of how we lose
education about the material world, by avoiding parts that are both
interesting and risky.</p>
<p>Maybe it's just my perspective as a computer guy, but I feel like the
work of the physical world is too often ignored and undervalued.
Something like Hammerbacher has said, it feels like everyone wants to
get rich at a keyboard while the lab benches are empty.</p>
<p>The book in a couple places recommends going to YouTube to see a
video, with search terms to use. I feel like I've heard this kind of
thing in a few books recently. Is this what books do now? They can't
embed video, so they tell you to go find the video yourself on
YouTube? I'm not 100% opposed, but this feels a little gross to me.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240413-material_world_by_conway/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240413-material_world_by_conway/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mortality rates have improved</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>A misleading graph from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rise_and_Fall_of_American_Growth" title="The Rise and Fall of American Growth, by Robert J. Gordon">The Rise and Fall of American Growth</a> was
reproduced and again misinterpreted in <a href="/20240128-outlive_by_attia/" title="Outlive, by Peter Attia">Outlive</a>. The graph
correctly shows that US deaths from infectious disease have decreased
a lot over the last hundred years. The graph incorrectly makes it seem
like death rates from other causes have been stable over this period.
The age-adjusted death rate has decreased by around 50% since 1950.
Death rates at every age band have been meaningfully decreasing, apart
from the impact of COVID-19.</p>
<p>Here's the graph in <a href="/20240128-outlive_by_attia/" title="Outlive, by Peter Attia">Outlive</a>:</p>
<p><img alt="in Outlive" src="outlive.png"></p>
<p>What a remarkably horizontal white line! It supports Attia's position,
in that he's arguing that we need to invest more in fighting other
causes of death (heart disease, cancer, dementia, diabetes) so he's
trying to make them seem like big unsolved problems. And certainly,
they are big unsolved problems. But the claim that mortality rates
haven't been improving is misleading.</p>
<p>Let's first go to the graph in
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rise_and_Fall_of_American_Growth" title="The Rise and Fall of American Growth, by Robert J. Gordon">The Rise and Fall of American Growth</a>:</p>
<p><img alt="in The Rise and Fall of American Growth" src="growth.png"></p>
<p>Attia copied this graph fairly exactly, except for adding "top" before
and removing the asterisk after "diseases," which is just as well
since the asterisk doesn't seem to have an explanation in <em>Growth</em>
anyway.</p>
<p>Such a horizontal white line! Here, it supports Gordon's position, in
that he's arguing that things were getting better in the US from
1870-1970, but things aren't getting better so much any more. So
here's a decrease that stops decreasing by 1970.</p>
<p>The biggest problem with this presentation is that the data is not
age-adjusted, and as such it's sensitive to the distribution of ages
in the population. For example, with low death rates for people in
their early years, one way to lower the raw death rate is to arrange
for the birth of a lot of babies. The raw death rate doesn't tell us
much about anything in particular, and certainly isn't the "real"
death rate in any meaningful way. Let's compare with a <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data-visualization/mortality-trends/index.htm" title="Mortality Trends in the United States, 1900–2018">CDC graph</a>
that is age-adjusted:</p>
<p><img alt="CDC graph" src="cdc.png"></p>
<p>The green line is the age-adjusted death rate. It was 1,446 in 1950,
1,222.6 in 1970, and 723.6 in 2018. That's a 50% improvement from
1950, and a 41% improvement from 1970.</p>
<p>Adjusting for age is important, because for example, when people don't
die young, you get more old people. Baby booms and so on also matter.
The population pyramid looks different now than it did in 1900.
Compare the 1900 and 2000 shapes as presented in a
<a href="http://vis.stanford.edu/jheer/d3/pyramid/shift.html" title="U.S. Census Population Pyramid, 1850-2000">Stanford visualization</a>:</p>
<p><img alt="population pyramids" src="stanford.png"></p>
<p>Both the raw and age-adjusted overall death rates don't tell us
everything about what's happening at every age, so let's look at that.
Here are death rates for the oldest nine age buckets in
<a href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/annual-death-rate-by-age-group" title="Annual death rate by age group, United States, 2021">data from the Human Mortality Database</a> from 1933 to 2021, shown
with a <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1VjBsxGqajqBThla0JDQGSAnS2fXUeUTVBG95PD6pbE4/edit" title="age-band death rates over time">quick graph</a> I made.</p>
<p><img alt="death rates by age group" src="by_age_group.png"></p>
<p>Every age group is seeing decreasing death rates up until COVID-19
impacts 2020 numbers. I left out younger age bands to avoid crowding,
but those also show improvement, especially for the youngest.</p>
<p>For people 85-89, the death rate per 1,000 was 179.87 in 1950, and
154.77 in 1970. It was 103.14 in 2018. That's a 43% improvement since
1950, and 33% improvement from 1970. Even the COVID-19 spike takes us
back only to around the same levels as we saw in 2000.</p>
<p>Things have been improving. Improving since 1950, improving since
1970, improving since 2000 apart from COVID-19. It just isn't accurate
to suggest that death rates haven't been going down over these
periods. There's still room for improvement, but the real gains should
be celebrated, not ignored.</p>
<p>The question of whether life expectancies have leveled off or even
decreased over shorter, more recent periods is quite distinct from the
trend over these longer periods.</p>
<p>I attempted to <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/19kuO6mIAi-f3etXZtVNndLEqoGOHACjLvzokBCrYGqQ/edit" title="death rates from HSUS">replicate</a> Gordon's graph using the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historical_Statistics_of_the_United_States" title="Historical Statistics of the United States">HSUS</a> data.
He cites Ab929-943, which includes ten columns of infectious disease
death, by my count. He uses Ab952 for the total death rate, I believe.</p>
<p>It adds only confusion that Gordon's figure is titled "Mortality Rate
<em>as Percentage of GNP</em>" (emphasis added). He also cites HSUS series
Bd46 (percentage of GNP spent on health care from 1929 to 1997) and
2012 SAUS table 134 (health care spending). This seems to be a
leftover of an idea from an earlier paper. Gordon's footnote 22 says
that his figure "is an update of McKinlay and McKinlay (1977, figure
3, p. 416)" so let's track that down.</p>
<p>The paper is
<a href="https://www.milbank.org/wp-content/uploads/mq/volume-55/issue-03/55-3-The-Questionable-Contribution-of-Medical-Measures-to-the-Decline-of-Mortality-in-the-United-States-in-the-Twentieth-Century.pdf">The Questionable Contribution of Medical Measures to the Decline of Mortality in the United States in the Twentieth Century</a>.
It has this Figure 3:</p>
<p><img alt="Figure 3" src="figure3.png"></p>
<p>There is no horizontal white line here. The presentation is quite
different, arguably better for showing the decrease in death from
infectious disease. McKinlay and McKinlay seem to have known to use
age-adjusted statistics as well. More relevant to the discussion of
GNP, however, their paper has this Figure 2:</p>
<p><img alt="Figure 2" src="figure2.png"></p>
<p>The point it's making is that increased spending on health care
doesn't seem to be driving a lot of increased reduction in death rate.
There's something to this argument, but 50 years later we can also see
(in the CDC graph above) that the period roughly 1955-1965 was a
fairly flat spot on the death rate graph, with improvement continuing
after it.</p>
<p>Gordon mentions the concern that spending on health care isn't
delivering matching results in death rate improvement, but it doesn't
make it into his figure apart from the title and data citations.</p>
<p>The horizontal white line is basically a coincidence as death has been
shifting from younger to older people over time and the population
pyramid has been changing shape. This graph is misleading.</p>
<p><img alt="warning" src="warning.png"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240407-mortality_rates_have_improved/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240407-mortality_rates_have_improved/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Homo Deus, by Harari</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>It feels like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yuval_Noah_Harari" title="Yuval Noah Harari">Harari</a> got the advance for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homo_Deus:_A_Brief_History_of_Tomorrow" title="Homo Deus: A Brief History of Tomorrow">Homo Deus</a> before
really thinking it through. It's rambling, over-long, without cohesive
thesis, and like a time capsule of science and tech news from 2014:
Big Data! Watson! Quantified Self! Mild <a href="/20191108-accelerando_by_stross/" title="Accelerando, by Stross">Accelerando</a> flavor. I wish
I'd read the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yuval_Noah_Harari#Critical_reception">Critical Reception</a> section from Harari's Wikipedia
entry and skipped this book.</p>
<p>My biggest gripe is probably that Harari argues (at length) that
animals have consciousness, and that animals are algorithms, and then
also claims without a second thought that algorithms implemented via
computer have no consciousness.</p>
<p>Harari also makes the fairly common error of scientific
exceptionalism: the belief that scientific ways of knowing are
fundamentally distinct from all others. For the number of words he
releases on related topics, this is frustrating.</p>
<p>Harari does say some reasonable things. I think he's correct in
pointing out limitations in our understanding of consciousness. (I
think this is such an interesting topic I wrote a <a href="/20230325-conversion_of_guelph_energy_to_mass/" title="Conversion of Guelph energy to mass (p=0.049)">short story</a>
about it.)</p>
<p>I also like Harari's phrasing around learning history in order to be
liberated from it. But throughout the book, the moments of lucidity
make the languid and ludicrous majority that much more unbearable.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240331-homo_deus_by_harari/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240331-homo_deus_by_harari/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Lifespan, by Sinclair</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I heard about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lifespan:_Why_We_Age_%E2%80%93_and_Why_We_Don%27t_Have_To" title="Lifespan: Why We Age – and Why We Don't Have To">this book</a> from a neighbor after I was talking about
<a href="/20240128-outlive_by_attia/" title="(Audio) Outlive, by Attia">Outlive</a>. Compared to Attia, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_A._Sinclair" title="David A. Sinclair">Sinclair</a> is more academic, not as
into protein (especially animal protein), and more extreme in his
claims that aging is a curable disease explained by his "Information
Theory" of epigenetic aging. Sinclair takes metformin, resveratrol,
and NMN. (After the book he started taking rapamycin as well, based on
a YouTube interview.) The book is longer than it needs to be to cover
the topics of Sinclair's expertise. The audio book has little
interludes between Sinclair and his writer, which is sort of a fun
idea but I'm not sure it added much.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.png"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240319-lifespan_by_sinclair/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240319-lifespan_by_sinclair/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) The Body, by Bryson</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Bryson's intonation is a little like Werner Herzog's. His book on the
body is charmingly, gently amusing. It's a selection of fun facts and
good advice: exercise more, eat less, maybe get some more vitamin D
and choline. One reference is Haldane's 1926
<a href="https://www.phys.ufl.edu/courses/phy3221/spring10/HaldaneRightSize.pdf">On Being the Right Size</a>, which has a similar sense of humor.
Bryson has a good time, and so does the reader (or listener).</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240303-the_body_by_bryson/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240303-the_body_by_bryson/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) The Comfort Crisis, by Easter</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Built from Men's Health articles, Easter's book gathers tales of his
hunting trips with the bros. Sometimes there are scientific and
philosophical digressions. I liked how the chapter about death came at
the moment between shooting and killing the wild reindeer.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<p>Easter talks about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B._J._Fogg" title="B. J. Fogg">Fogg</a> Behavior Model (action requires
Motivation, Ability, and a Prompt) and suggests that scrolling on your
phone all the time is a bad idea. Okay. He also suggests that audible
white noise is caused by EM radiation in air. I struggle to find a
reasonable interpretation that makes this true. There's also a good
deal of "people used to do this long ago, therefore it's a good idea,"
which isn't necessarily wrong, but it's too easy to ignore whether
there's a good argument beyond the appeal to nature.</p>
<p>The thesis is basically that we should get off the couch, eat
healthier, and challenge ourselves. I agree, basically. I'm now
listening to Rushkoff's Survival of the Richest, which has some advice
which is similar in effect: Focus on the real world rather than
disappearing into a technologically mediated isolation pod. Rushkoff
gets there by a different path, and from his mouth it sounds like a
call to a pro-social future. From Easter, it sounds like rugged
individualism for reclaiming masculinity.</p>
<p>We're very lucky to be able to choose our level of difficulty, when we
can.</p>
<p><a href="https://webcomicname.com/"><img alt="comic" src="comic.png"></a></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240211-comfort_crisis_by_easter/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240211-comfort_crisis_by_easter/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Outlive, by Attia</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I was already thinking about improving my health, then my last
grandparent died, and this book was recommended in Spotify and by a
friend. It was gratifying to listen to while running because <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/">Attia</a>
kept saying how good exercise is.</p>
<p>He's a little bit of a tech bro. He talks about how he mellowed and
started taking one (1) day off per week. And is he responsible for the
popularity of <a href="https://www.goruck.com/pages/what-is-rucking">rucking</a>? He used to be very into <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ketogenic_diet">keto</a> and
fasting. He still seems to be a little quick to assume causation. But
still: Who doesn't want more healthspan?</p>
<ul>
<li>Recommendations<ul>
<li>Exercise<ul>
<li>"Zone 2" sustained cardio</li>
<li>Intense cardio for improving VO2-max</li>
<li>Strength (with weights)</li>
<li>Stability (core, <a href="https://www.posturalrestoration.com/">posture</a>, flexitility...)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Diet<ul>
<li>A lot of protein and fiber</li>
<li>Avoid too much other stuff</li>
<li>Keep bad cholesterol (LDL, but he prefers measuring
   <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apolipoprotein_B">ApoB</a>) <em>very</em> low (usual guideline is under 100; he says
   under 20)<ul>
<li>Maybe use statins and/or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metformin">metformin</a> etc.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Minimal to no alcohol</li>
<li><em>Don't get diabetes</em></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Get lots of tests done, screen early for cancer, etc.</li>
<li>Sleep (lots of good)</li>
<li>Emotional health (good)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sirolimus">Rapamycin</a> taken once a week<ul>
<li>You can get this from <a href="https://agelessrx.com/">AgeLessRx</a> or <a href="https://gethealthspan.com/">HealthSpan</a>, for
   example.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Anchor phrases<ul>
<li>Medicine 3.0: Where 1.0 was witchcraft/superstition, 2.0 is
   scientific "treat the disease" modern medicine, and 3.0 is his
   style of life-long health improvement to avoid diseases of
   aging etc. (Attia's practice is called "Early.")</li>
<li>The Four Horsemen<ul>
<li>Heart disease, stroke, etc.</li>
<li>Cancer</li>
<li>Dementia etc.</li>
<li>Diabetes and friends ("metabolic disfunction") which he
   says is related to the other three</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The Centenarian Decathlon: Work toward being able to do things
   when you're really old; overprepare because you will age.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Oh also he talks a little bit about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mendelian_randomization">Mendelian randomization</a>, which
it turns out is just using genetics as an <a href="/20210430-a_simple_instrumental_variable/">instrumental variable</a>.
Also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bradford_Hill_criteria">Bradford Hill criteria</a> for causation. Neat!</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240128-outlive_by_attia/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240128-outlive_by_attia/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fundamentals: Ten Keys to Reality, by Wilczek</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I liked <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank_Wilczek" title="Wikipedia: Frank Wilczek">Wilczek</a> on <a href="/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/" title="The Strangest Man, by Farmelo">Dirac</a> in <a href="/20231119-it_must_be_beautiful/" title="It must be beautiful, edited by Farmelo">It must be beautiful</a>, and I
like him a lot <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fundamentals:_Ten_Keys_to_Reality" title="Wikipedia: Fundamentals: Ten Keys to Reality">here</a>! This is Nobel-prize-winning <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_chromodynamics" title="Wikipedia: Quantum chromodynamics">QCD</a> and also
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_crystal" title="Wikipedia: Time crystal">time crystal</a> guy. Just a beautiful intro to modern particle
physics, scientific perspective, an an optimism for open-ended future
development across all scientific disciplines that reminds me of
<a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/" title="The Beginning of Infinity, by Deutsch">The Beginning of Infinity</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Fundamentals</em> is meant, as well, to offer an alternative to
traditional religious fundamentalism. It takes up some of the same
basic questions, but addresses them by consulting physical reality,
rather than texts or traditions. (page xiii)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Of course, consulting physical reality is its own tradition...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The method of Kepler, Galileo, and Newton combines the humble
discipline of respecting the facts and learning from Nature with the
systematic chutzpah of using what you think you've learned
aggressively, applying it everywhere you can, even in situations
that go beyond your original evidence. If it works, then you've
discovered something useful; if it doesn't, then you've learned
something important. I've called that attitude Radical Conservatism,
and to me it's the essential innovation of the Scientific
Revolution. (pages 4-5)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't know if he has priority, but I'm pretty sure Wilczek's sense
of Radical Conservatism isn't the most common...</p>
<p>See also <a href="/20170825-characteristics_of_good_theories/">Characteristics of good theories</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Ptolemy's [geocentric] synthesis was a magnificent achievement, but
it had two shortcomings. One was its complexity and, related to
this, its ugliness. In particular, the recipes it used to calculate
planetary motions brought in many numbers that were determined
purely by fitting the calculations to observations, without deeper
guiding principles connecting them. Copernicus (1473-1543) noticed
that the values of some of those numbers were related to one another
in surprisingly simple ways. These otherwise mysterious,
"coincidental" relationships could be explained geometrically, if
one assumed that Earth together with Venus, Mars, Jupiter, and
Saturn all revolve around the Sun as center (and the Moon further
revolves around Earth). (page 6)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't think I'd heard quite this explanation before... In light of
"end of science" arguments that big data pushes us more toward
"numbers ... determined purely by fitting the calculations to
observations" this Ptolemaic narrative could almost fit into a kind of
"we were once less wise in our theory, and now we become less wise
again" story.</p>
<p>Wilczek goes on to briefly cover how Kepler's work made the system
still simpler and better-working. Have we simplified everything as
much as it can be? Could we do better?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But Galileo aspired to a different kind of understanding. He wanted
to understand <em>something</em> precisely, rather than <em>everything</em>
vaguely. (page 7)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Finding the right questions, etc. etc.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>A more recent quotation from John R. Pierce, a pioneer of modern
information science, beautifully captures the contrast between the
modern concept of scientific understanding and all other approaches:
"We require that our theories harmonize in detail with the very wide
range of phenomena they seek to explain. And we insist that they
provide us with useful guidance rather than with rationalizations."
(page 9)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This reminds me of <a href="/20170825-characteristics_of_good_theories/">Characteristics of good theories</a>.</p>
<p>Also, this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_R._Pierce" title="Wikipedia: John R. Pierce">Pierce</a> character came up a bunch in <a href="/20231231-myth_of_ai_by_larson/" title="The myth of artificial intelligence, by Larson">Larson's book</a>
as well. (But this book is much, much better.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Unlike the situation for stars or planets, which almost invariably
are separated from their neighbors by distances many times their own
size, the typical separation between galaxies is not vastly larger
than the galaxies themselves. (page 27)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Huh! Neat.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The Roman philosopher Seneca expressed the opposite of this thought
[that human life is short] in "On the Shortness of Life." "Why do we
complain about nature?" he writes. "It has acted generously; life,
if you know how to use it, is long." (pages 43-44)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Oh interesting! It seems like <a href="/20201107-how_to_live_on_24_hours_a_day/" title="How to Live on 24 Hours a Day, by Bennett">Bennett</a> didn't know (or at least
didn't reference) Seneca's <a href="https://archive.org/stream/SenecaOnTheShortnessOfLife/Seneca+on+the+Shortness+of+Life_djvu.txt" title="Full text of 'Seneca On The Shortness Of Life'">work</a> in his How to Live on 24 Hours a
Day.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li><em>The basic laws describe change.</em> It is useful to separate the
   description of the world into two parts: states and laws. States
   describe "what there is," while laws describe "how things
   change."</li>
<li><em>The basic laws are universal.</em> That is, the basic laws hold
   everywhere, and for all times.</li>
<li><em>The basic laws are local.</em> That is, the behavior of an object in
   the immediate future depends only on current conditions in its
   immediate vicinity. The standard scientific jargon for this
   principle is <em>locality.</em></li>
<li><em>The basic laws are precise.</em> The laws are precise, and they
   admit no exceptions. Thus, they can be formulated as mathematical
   equations. (pages 64-65)</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Locality over reality.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Fields, rather than particles, are the fundamental building blocks
of matter in modern physics. (page 67)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Wilczek identifies "Mass" and "Charge" and "Spin" as the only three
basic, primary properties of matter. (page 73)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>(There's an interesting mathematical reason why physicists call the
basic unit of angular momentum spin 1/2, rather than spin 1, but it
is beyond the scope of this book.) (page 75)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It seems like this is related to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spin%E2%80%93statistics_theorem">spin–statistics theorem</a> or
something? But come on, Wilczek, you big tease...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Contrary to Democritus, though, our modern basic ingredients don't
have hooks. They aren't even solid bodies. Indeed, thought it's
convenient to call them "elementary particles," they aren't really
particles. (That is, they have little in common with what the word
"particle" suggests.) Our modern fundamental ingredients have no
intrinsic size or shape. If we insist on visualizing them, we should
think of structureless points where concentrations of mass, charge,
and spin reside. We have, in places of "atoms and the void,"
space-time and properties. (page 77)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Democritus was the early atomic theory guy.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>By being first, Franklin got to choose which kind of charge to call
positive and which negative. He chose to call the charge that
accumulates on glass, after it is rubbed with silk, positive. This
was long before people knew about electrons. Unfortunately, it turns
out that according to Franklin's choice the electron's charge is
negative. It's much too late to undo that choice, since it has
seeped into thousands of books, papers, and circuit diagrams.
Therefore, we list the electron's charge as -1. (pages 81-82)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Benjamin Franklin.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Once you get to thinking about materials as homes to quasiparticles,
a profound question is not far off: Can we consider "empty space"
itself to be a material, whose quasiparticles are our "elementary
particles"? We can, and we should. It is a very fruitful line of
thought, as you'll see in later chapters. (page 90)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I'm not sure that last promise was ever paid off very well...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>John Wheeler, the poet of relativity, summed it up this way:
"Space-time tells matter how to move; matter tells space-time how to
bend." (page 117)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is that really a good way to sum up? It reminds me of the
stretched-sheet-of-rubber image, which I think is not so good...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The Future of Comprehension (page 119)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I just thought this was a cool section heading.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>You should not fail to notice that 500 trillion is a great deal
larger than 25, or even 95. (page 127)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Cute!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>H. G. Wells caught the spirit of thermal equilibrium memorably: "If
anything is possible, then nothing is interesting." (page 151)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>How the Universe got Interesting (page 161)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another fun heading.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There are several kinds of anomalous color perception, misnamed
"color blindness," that are not terribly rare. Around 95 percent of
humans have similar color vision, based on three types of cone cells
that vary little between individuals. There are theoretical reasons,
based on genetics, to believe that a significant fraction of humans,
specifically mothers and full sisters of males with the most common
color anomaly, have four kinds of cone cells. These "tetrachromats"
might have super-normal color vision. But as far as I know, direct
evidence for this is surprisingly rare. (page 170)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetrachromacy">Huh!</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Let's recall that John Wheeler, the poet of general relativity,
summed it up this way: "Space-time tells matter how to move; matter
tells space-time how to bend." Wheeler's summary is catchy, but it
is misleading, or at least incomplete, whithout this important
addition: <em>Space-time is a form of matter, too.</em> (page 178)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Although we understand <em>a lot</em> about how the world works, there are
still big mysteries. These three great questions came up earlier:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>What triggered the big bang? Could it happen again?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Are there meaningful patterns hidden in the apparent sprawl of
  fundamental particles and forces?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>How, concretely, does mind emerge from matter? (Or does it?) (page
  187)</p>
</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>On page 190, he uses "rock bottom" to refer to that final point in
explanation beyond which there is no further "why?" I think it's a
good thing to remember, that we can't avoid having such a rock bottom.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Dark energy" is another theoretically motivated modification to the
law of gravity, also considered by Einstein. He called it by a
different name: the cosmological constant. (page 195)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There is immense satisfaction in describing the world in terms of
its most elementary building blocks. It is tempting to say that this
is the ideal description, while other, high-level descriptions are
mere approximations—compromises, which reflect weakness in
understanding. That attitude, which makes the perfect the enemy of
the good, is superficially deep, but deeply superficial.</p>
<p>In order to answer questions of interest, we often need to change
focus. To discover—or invent—new concepts, and new ways of working
with them, is an open-ended, creative activity. Computer scientists
and software engineers are well aware that in designing useful
algorithms, it is important to pay attention to how knowledge is
represented. A good representation can make the difference between
usable knowledge and knowledge that is there "in principle" but not
really available, because it takes too long and too much trouble to
locate and process. It's like the difference between owning bars of
gold and knowing that in principle there are vast stores of gold
atoms floating dissolved in the ocean.</p>
<p>For that reason, complete understanding of the fundamental laws, if
we ever achieved it, would be neither "the Theory of Everything" nor
"the End of Science." (Those are two phrases, endemic in popular
science journalism, that I find extremely irritating.) We would
still need complementary descriptions of reality. There would still
be plenty of great questions left unanswered, and plenty of great
scientific work left to do.</p>
<p>There always will be. (pages 215-216)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is just the conclusion of a longer section on this topic, which I
like quite a lot. It reminds me of Deutsch's
<a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/">Beginning of Infinity</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Do people have choice in what they do, or are they puppets who dance
to the tune of mathematical physics? That is a bad question, not
unlike asking whether music is harmony or melody. (page 218)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>...what the great biologist Francis Crick has called "the
astonishing hypothesis": that mind, in all its aspects, is "no more
than the behavior of a vast assembly of nerve cells and their
associated molecules." (pages 225-226)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... there are three different kinds [sic] color charge, and eight
different kinds of gluons that respond to them. (page 234)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What? This seems cool and fun.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Now we come to a group of elementary particles nobody really knows
what to make of. The bonus particles are all unstable. They were
discovered among the debris of high-energy collisions, either in
cosmic rays (early in the twentieth century) or at parcle
accelerators (more recently). When the first of them, the muon, was
discovered in 1936, the renowned physicist I. I. Rabi captured the
community's bewilderment in a quip that's become legendary: "Who
ordered that?" (page 236)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>These are the charm, top, strange, and bottom quark, together with the
muon and tauon.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The website of the Particle Data Group is http://pdg.lbl.gov. (page 238)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Nice!</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240114-fundamentals_by_wilczek/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240114-fundamentals_by_wilczek/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
