<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>The Ride of a Lifetime, by Iger</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob_Iger" title="Bob Iger">Bob</a> starts chapter one with “This book is not a memoir,” so you
know from the start you're dealing with an unreliable narrator.
Compared to Catmull in <a href="/20220213-creativity_inc_by_catmull/" title="Creativity, Inc., by Catmull">Creativity, Inc.</a>, Iger does seem more
direct, and his experiences are interesting, but I like Iger less, I
think.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>Here are Iger's ten principles from the prologue:</p>
<ol>
<li>Optimism</li>
<li>Courage</li>
<li>Focus</li>
<li>Decisiveness</li>
<li>Curiosity</li>
<li>Fairness</li>
<li>Thoughtfulness</li>
<li>Authenticity</li>
<li>The Relentless Pursuit of Perfection</li>
<li>Integrity</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>On page 9, you get a story of how some coworker exposed himself to
Iger.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As for all the glamour, there is (and eventually there was) a
convincing argument to be made that living that high off the hog was
irresponsible." (page 14)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I wonder if the old TV business is analogous to the current tech
scene...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I’ve found that often people will focus on little details as a way
of masking a lack of any clear, coherent, big thoughts." (page 43)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is legit.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I wouldn’t as a rule recommend promoting someone as rapidly as they
promoted me," (page 49)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>haha~</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I wanted the merger to go well, and I wanted to make sure the
Capital Cities team was treated well by Disney. Without me there, I
was fairly certain they would get subsumed by Disney in potentially
dispiriting ways." (page 53)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This guy, huh?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Managing your own time and respecting others’ time is one of the
most vital things to do as a manager," (page 63)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Concur.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"these are the people to nurture—not the ones who are clamoring for
promotions and complaining about not being utilized enough but the
ones who are proving themselves to be indispensable day in and day
out." (page 66)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Concur.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"He wanted the “albino Mickeys,” as he called them, taken from the
shelves, which we didn’t do, but it was a huge distraction." (page
87)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Crazy micro-managing board member...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I’ve always prided myself on my ability and willingness to put in a
greater effort than anyone else." (page 104)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This guy, huh? He elsewhere makes a point of how he didn't take a
two-week vacation until late in his career.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I could control what I did and how I comported myself. Everything
else was beyond my control." (page 109)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See also: <a href="/20210107-enchiridion_in_52_sentences/" title="The Enchiridion in 52 sentences">The Enchiridion</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"pushing strategic responsibility back to the businesses sooner
rather than later. I hoped that if we could reduce the grip that
Strat Planning had over all of our divisions, we would slowly begin
to restore the company’s morale." (page 116)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is one of the more interesting things he actually did, moving
toward more decentralization. Seems good.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We landed on Twitter." (page 190)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I didn't realize Disney had been close to acquiring Twitter!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Twitter was a potentially powerful platform for us, but I couldn’t
get past the challenges that would come with it. The challenges and
controversies were almost too much to list, but they included how to
manage hate speech, and making fraught decisions regarding freedom
of speech, what to do about fake accounts algorithmically spewing
out political “messaging” to influence elections, and the general
rage and lack of civility that was sometimes evident on the
platform. Those would become our problems. They were so unlike any
we’d encountered, and I felt they would be corrosive to the Disney
brand. On the Sunday after the board had just given me the go-ahead
to pursue the acquisition of Twitter, I sent a note to all of the
members telling them I had “cold feet,” and explaining my reasoning
for withdrawing. Then I called Jack Dorsey, Twitter’s CEO, who was
also a member of the Disney board. Jack was stunned, but very
polite. I wished Jack luck, and I hung up feeling relieved." (page
190)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I would decide at the end of each year how much stock would vest,
and that it was going to be based not on revenue but on how well
they were able to work together. “I don’t want any politics,” I
said. “This is too important. It’s for the good of the company, and
it’s good for you. I need you to step up.”" (page 196)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is interesting too; kind of the reverse of decentralization, but
I like how it gets away from purely quantified compensation.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"My new retirement date is December 2021," (page 221)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob_Iger" title="Bob Iger">Bob</a>'s Wikipedia page makes it seem like this was not the initial
plan, but here it seems like it was?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Esther Newberg, for your guidance and for talking me into writing
this book. You said it was going to be easy and you sure were
wrong!" (page 236)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220620-ride_of_a_lifetime_by_iger/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220620-ride_of_a_lifetime_by_iger/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mastering Python, by van Hattem</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/priyadarshini-sharma-95a35215b/" title="Priyadarshini Sharma">Sharma</a> from <a href="https://www.packtpub.com/">Packt</a> sent me a review copy of the
<a href="https://www.packtpub.com/product/mastering-python-second-edition/9781800207721" title="Mastering Python - Second Edition">second edition</a>. I skimmed it, and I like it a lot. It seems like
<a href="https://w.wol.ph/about/" title="Rick van Hattem (Wolph)">van Hattem</a> knows his stuff. The book is hugely inclusive and
erudite; you'll almost certainly learn new things. It includes the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fixed-point_combinator#Fixed-point_combinators_in_lambda_calculus" title="Fixed-point combinators in lambda calculus">Y combinator</a> as an example. It isn't perfect, but it's better than
<a href="/20190707-expert_python_programming_by_jaworski_and_ziade/" title="Expert Python Programming by Jaworski and Ziadé">Jaworski and Ziadé's book</a>, I think, and I'll recommend it.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220611-mastering_python_by_van_hattem/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220611-mastering_python_by_van_hattem/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Before the Coffee Gets Cold, by Kawaguchi</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>It's a cute short <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Before_the_Coffee_Gets_Cold">book</a>. It reads very clearly as a novelization of
a one-set play. It's about interpersonal relationships and making
tough choices even when you have incorrect information. In the end,
the real time travel was inside us all along.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220604-before_the_coffee_gets_cold_by_kawaguchi/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220604-before_the_coffee_gets_cold_by_kawaguchi/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Beginning of Infinity, by Deutsch</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I read <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Beginning_of_Infinity" title="The Beginning of Infinity">this book</a> years ago (2017 or earlier) and didn't write it
up at the time, but some of the themes keep coming up.
<a href="/20170825-characteristics_of_good_theories/" title="Characteristics of good theories">Characteristics of good theories</a>, for one thing. But more so the
fundamental optimism that we can keep going indefinitely. Deutsch is
focused on knowledge, understanding, and explanations—but perhaps also
for prosperity, as in a post-scarcity "Star Trek" future (<a href="/20210401-trekonomics_by_saadia/" title="Trekonomics, by Saadia">Saadia</a>,
<a href="/20201109-economics_of_star_trek_by_webb/" title="The Economics of Star Trek, by Webb">Webb</a>). Deutsch's thoughts on quantum theory are fun, but the
optimistic worldview may be more valuable.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Myth of the Rational Voter, by Caplan</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Did anyone ever seriously believe voters were rational? Well,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryan_Caplan">Caplan</a> has a 2007 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Myth_of_the_Rational_Voter">book</a>, and of course the conclusion is that
we should be more libertarian. "Rational" means in agreement with
economists (meaning Caplan), and by page 197 he advocates "a test of
voter competence." As usual, it's not all wrong, but I'm not sure it's
all right.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"[T]he superstitions to be feared in the present day are much less
religious than political; and of all the forms of idolotry I know
none more irrational and ignoble than this blind worship of mere
numbers." (epigraph)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"You should not blame the prescription simply because the patient
refuses to take his medicine. <em>The Myth of the Rational Voter</em>
contains many workable reforms, but due to voter irrationality they
are unlikely to be tried." (ix)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At some point, it is part of the task of solving problems to create
solutions that work in practice, not only in a hypothetical world
imagined by the solver.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Once economists admit to themselves that voters are just like their
students, only worse, they will be poised to unravel the mysteries
of politics and policy." (xi)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The paradox of democracy ... In theory, democracy is a bulwark
against socially harmful policies, but in practice it gives them a
safe harbor." (page 1)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Economists and cognitive psychologists usually presume that
everyone "processes information" to the best of his ability." (page
2)</p>
<p>"The main difference between the two disciplines is that cognitive
psychologists are much more likely than economists to conclude that
people's best information processing is not very good." (page 211,
note to preceeding)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a href="http://www.tomstafford.staff.shef.ac.uk/docs/tetlock03.pdf">Thinking the unthinkable: sacred values and taboo cognitions, by Tetlock</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This book has three conjoined themes. The first: Doubts about the
rationality of voters are empirically justified. The second: Voter
irrationality is precisely what economic theory implies once we
adopt introspectively plausible assumptions about human motivation.
The third: Voter irrationality is the key to a realistic picture of
democracy." (page 3)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Biases: antimarket, antiforeign, make-work, pessimistic (page 10)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We also note that <em>no</em> replicated study has made rationality
violations disappear purely by raising incentives." (page 135,
quoting Camerer and Hogarth)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"To get ahead in politics, leaders need a blend of naive populism
and realistic cynicism. No wonder the modal politician has a law
degree." (page 169)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Yet a standard debating tactic of creation scientists is to insist
that "evolutionary theory, along with its bedfellow, secular
humanism, is really a religion."" (page 186; quote is
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/People-Believe-Weird-Things-Pseudoscience/dp/0805070893" title="Why People Believe Weird Things: Pseudoscience, Superstition, and Other Confusions of Our Time">Shermer 2002</a> page 143)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Private Choice as an Alternative to Democracy and Dictatorship"
(page 192)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... the Laffer Curve of learning: They retain less if you try to
teach them more." (page 200)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is this as bad an idea as the original Laffer Curve?</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bertrand_competition">Bertrand competition</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"A proverb tells us that "a wise man learns more from a fool than a
fool learns from a wise man."" (page 209)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220405-myth_of_the_rational_voter_by_caplan/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220405-myth_of_the_rational_voter_by_caplan/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Red Roulette, by Shum</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The success of this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_Roulette">book</a> is that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Desmond_Shum">Shum</a> straddles sympathetic
and repulsive. He is deeply flawed and yet less flawed than the China
he describes. He is an unreliable narrator but perhaps among the most
reliable available. His viewpoint is part of the view.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220404-red_roulette_by_shum/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220404-red_roulette_by_shum/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Seven Games, by Roeder</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://oroeder.github.io/">Roeder</a> writes about checkers, chess, go, backgammon, poker,
scrabble, and bridge. He gets philosophical, on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homo_Ludens">Homo ludens</a> and
what AI is and so on. It's interesting and I learned about some game
variations that are fun to try. Quality pandemic book.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"I’m a machine and you’re a machine and we both think, don’t we?"
(epigraph, quoting Claude Shannon, when asked whether machines could
think)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"games offer a space to enjoy agency." (page 9)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Games also offer simplified models of a dauntingly complicated
world," (page 82)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"a game is “the voluntary attempt to overcome unnecessary
obstacles.”" (page 11)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"adding structure to play—that is, inventing and playing games—is
central to our developmental intelligence." (page 12)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Ken Thompson, the designer of the Unix operating system and a chess
machine called Belle, once spent an hour a day for three years
keying in lines from the Encyclopedia of Chess Openings." (page 35)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Shannon’s paper described two strategies for programming a computer
to play chess. Type A programs employed brute-force search and
evaluation, analyzing every possible move, and all possible
subsequent moves, no matter how unpromising they might look to a
human observer. In other words, they exploited the computer’s chief
strength: sheer calculation. Shannon, however, thought such a player
would be “both slow and weak.” Type B programs were more selective,
examining only certain small yet promising branches on chess’s
enormous tree. In other words, they exploited something like human
intuition. Early computer scientists thought the successful players
would be Type B, but with the rapid expansion of computing power,
computer scientists were lured into pursuing Type A." (page 69)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The key to elite chess is preparation, which Stockfish
facilitates." (page 84)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"“My own works have been described as works of emptiness, but it is
not to be taken for the nihilism of the West,”" (page 100, quoting
<a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/1968/kawabata/lecture/" title="Japan, the Beautiful and Myself">Kawabata</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"“I feel something very strange,” Fan said afterward. “I lose with
the program and I don’t understand myself anymore.”" (page 102)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The rules of Go—called weiqi in Chinese, igo in Japanese, and baduk
in Korean—are stark and elegant, as if they were discovered rather
than invented." (page 102)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Compare to ideas of math being discovered vs. invented...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Even Confucius begrudgingly agreed that playing Go was better than
sitting idle." (page 105)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Backgammon is one of only two things in life, I heard many times
during my research, that one never tires of." (page 153)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In the end, of course, it was futile. Tesauro, whose research
inspired XG, expressed a similar sentiment about human players in
light of essentially perfect AI. “They play tournaments and they
study very hard,” he said. “I just don’t see the point.”" (page 160)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Chance, in other words, is a fertile garden in which human ego and
delusion flourish." (page 162)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Before bots, everybody believed that they were the best player. The
type of people we have now are people who like to study, who enjoy
the process of improving their own game." (pages 163-164)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I came to understand that the appeal of this game, like the method
used to train its AI players, is not winning but learning." (page
165)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The actual lived experience of the World Series of Poker, however,
comprises five elemental modes: loneliness, boredom, waiting,
folding, and, ultimately, devastation." (page 172)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As the great player Marlon Hill once said about learning the
Scrabble words’ definitions, “If you are sane at all, it will drive
you slowly insane.”" (page 213)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"First, Scrabble, like life, is a trade-off between today and
tomorrow—between spending and saving." (page 221)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Next to him on the table was a plastic box containing bottles of
something called D-cycloserine, a molecule that, online, is
purported to enhance brain activity and learning; something called
F-phenibut, another brain booster and the subject of many personal
drug-experience website accounts that is said to aid memory;" (page
228)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Moreover, these languages must be common knowledge. You and your
partner must reveal your dialect’s structure and intricacies to your
opponents, and players are allowed to ask questions of their
opponents like “What did that bid mean?” Bridge is a game of
communication but not of subterfuge. As such, the “gravest possible
offense” in bridge, according to its official rules, is exchanging
information with one’s partner outside of what the rules allow—that
is, outside of the formal and public bidding process. Illicit
language is the cardinal sin of the game." (page 247)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"A sociological principle called Sayre’s law holds that disputes in
academia are so bitter because the stakes are so low." (page 264)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"“I believe that when I say ‘mathematics’ and when Pam or Tim says
‘God,’ we are talking about the same thing. And I mean the very same
thing. In both cases we are talking about the stunningly beautiful
order that underlies the universe.”" (page 267, quoting Matt
Ginsberg)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Marx and Nietzsche, Hurka points out, believed that “a central
human good was activity that on the one side is necessarily directed
to a goal but on the other derives its value entirely from aspects
of the process of achieving it.”" (page 274)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"“You have this AI built to do this thing really well,” he added,
“but it doesn’t have any particular experience of it. ... I’m a rock
climber, and AI being able to beat me at Go matters as much as a
helicopter being able to beat me at a rock climb.”" (page 277,
quoting C. Thi Nguyen)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Modern AI systems require gobs of data to train, which makes easily
collectible and cheap data attractive. These easy, quantified
metrics can stand in for success in fields whose aims are in reality
complicated and subtle: clicks for journalism, steps for exercise,
box office for cinema, auction prices for paintings. Nguyen calls
this “value collapse”—when rich, subtle values are replaced by
simplified, quantified versions of those values." (page 278)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Games became solace. We players did not arrive in droves seeking
difficulty or complexity, or a sense of achievement, or a frivolous
distraction. We arrived, I believe, in search of agency that had
been temporarily denied by sensible public health measures." (page
280)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220403-seven_games_by_roeder/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220403-seven_games_by_roeder/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Elder Race, by Tchaikovsky</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>As mentioned in its dedication, Tchaikovsky's 2021 short novel
<a href="https://publishing.tor.com/elderrace-adriantchaikovsky/9781250768711/">Elder Race</a> is heavily inspired by Wolfe's 1967 story
<a href="https://www.wolfewiki.com/pmwiki/pmwiki.php?n=Stories.TripTrap">Trip, Trap</a>. What's new?</p>
<ul>
<li>Some female characters instead of all-male cast</li>
<li>Lots of exploration of using technology to fight depression</li>
<li>Last of high-tech civilization is protagonist rather than villain</li>
<li>Villain is less familiar than "just" a telepathic alien</li>
</ul>
<p>Both explore the idea of advanced technology being indistinguishable
from magic (Arthur C. Clarke's quote) with fantasy and sci-fi POV
characters. Perhaps the most interesting thing about both stories, and
perhaps more so Elder Race, is the idea that there is a level of
understanding well beyond that of the high-tech human "wizard."</p>
<p>Mostly it's straightforward fun though. In the end they destroy what
they don't understand and live happily ever after.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220402-elder_race_by_tchaikovsky/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220402-elder_race_by_tchaikovsky/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Smarter, Faster, Better, by Duhigg</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This is a very readable book that talks about motivation, teams
(psychological safety), appropriate focus, goal-setting (big and
SMART), management, decision-making, innovation, and absorbing data,
all through interesting stories. There's some good stuff.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>Duhigg connects his book about productivity to the idea of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Power_of_Habit" title="The Power of Habit">his first book</a> on habits.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Productive people have habits—what psychologists might call
'contemplative routines'—that push them to <em>think more deeply</em> about
the choices they make." (page 6)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>The book spends substantial time exploring possible biological
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Striatum" title="Striatum">determinants</a> of motivation, and then becomes less fatalistic.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Motivation is more like a skill, akin to reading or writing, that
can be learned and honed. Scientists have found that people can get
better at self-motivation if they practice the right way. The trick,
researchers say, is realizing that a prerequisite to motivation is
believing we have authority over our actions and surroundings. To
motivate ourselves, we must feel like we are in control." (page 19)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The division [Google's People Analytics] had successfully pushed to
increase paid maternity leave from twelve to eighteen weeks because
computer models indicated that would reduce the frequency of new
mothers quitting by 50 percent." (page 42)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In the age of automation, knowing how to manage your focus is more
critical than ever." (page 76)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Most pharaohs were considered elderly if they made it to
thirty-five." (page 194)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think this is not correct; see
<a href="/20200806-life_expectancy_is_historically_misleading/" title="Life expectancy is historically misleading">Life expectancy is historically misleading</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intermediate_disturbance_hypothesis" title="Intermediate disturbance hypothesis">Intermediate disturbance hypothesis</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Productivity is about recognizing choices that other people often
overlook." (page 284)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220327-smarter_faster_better_by_duhigg/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220327-smarter_faster_better_by_duhigg/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>A Visit from the Goon Squad, by Egan</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>“Time's a goon, right?” This book is very much as described
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Visit_from_the_Goon_Squad" title="Wikipedia: A Visit from the Goon Squad">on Wikipedia</a>. I enjoyed it. It shows things from different
people's perspectives and gives you a lot of things to react to.
There's largely no singular narrative, the good aren't rewarded, the
bad aren't punished. It's most disappointing when hints of arc or
closure appear toward the end.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220320-visit_from_the_goon_squad_by_egan/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220320-visit_from_the_goon_squad_by_egan/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Creativity, Inc., by Catmull</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edwin_Catmull" title="Edwin 'Ed' Catmull">Catmull</a> says it's not a memoir, but of course it is, too, and
that's a good thing. I like his focus on getting fear out of
organizations and making it possible to do things, to try things,
without having rigid plans in advance. Pretty good advice throughout,
I think.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>Catmull reminds me of the Montessori idea of a prepared environment,
when for example he discusses the effect of a particular table on his
team (page 5).</p>
<hr>
<p>He discusses fear about hiring someone smarter than him, which seems
sort of weird to me (page 23). Am I scared to hire someone smarter
than me? It's always hard to tell relative smartness, of course, but I
think in general I've been very happy, the smarter the person.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Why "Pixar"? The name emerged from a back-and-forth between Alvy
and another of our colleagues, Loren Carpenter. Alvy, who spent much
of his childhood in Texas and New Mexico, had a fondness for the
Spanish language, and was intrigued by how certain nouns in English
looked like Spanish verbs—words like "laser," for example. So Alvy
lobbied for "Pixer," which he imagined to be a (fake) Spanish verb
meaning "to make pictures." Loren countered with "Radar," which he
thought sounded more high-tech. That's when it hit them: Pixer +
radar = Pixar! It stuck." (page 30)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"["Focus, focus, focus!"] was a particular favorite piece of
nonadvice. When people hear it, they nod their heads in agreement as
if a great truth has been presented, not realizing that they've been
diverted from addressing the far harder problem: deciding what it is
that they should be focusing on. There is nothing in this advice
that gives you any idea how to figure out where the focus should be,
or how to apply your energy to it. It ends up being advice that
doesn't mean anything." (page 46)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Getting the team right is the necessary precursor to getting the
ideas right. ... Getting the right people and the right chemistry is
more important than getting the right idea." (page 74)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Reminds me of "gelling" (as in <a href="/20200523-peopleware_productive_projects_and_teams/" title="Peopleware: Productive Projects and Teams">Peopleware</a>).</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>""Trust the process" had morphed into "Assume that the Process Will
Fix Things for Us."" (page 79)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Imagine an old, heavy suitcase whose well-worn handles are hanging
by a few threads. The handle is "Trust the Process" or "Story is
King"—a pithy statement that seems, on the face of it, to stand for
so much more. The suitcase represents all that has gone into the
formation of the phrase: the experience, the deep wisdom, the truths
that emerge from struggle. Too often, we grab the handle and—without
realizing it—walk off without the suitcase. What's more, we don't
even think about what we've left behind. After all, the handle is so
much easier to carry around than the suitcase." (pages 79-80)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I like this image a lot. I think it connects to a lot of
learning/education.</p>
<p>The book closes with a section called "Starting points," which is five
pages of short statements, almost aphorisms, that highlight major
ideas from the book. Handles, maybe.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>""The process of developing a story is one of discovery," Pete
says." (page 113)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is interesting to me in relation to the question of whether math
is discovered or created. Surely a story is created, but this connects
to the process as being about externalizing and evaluating, connects
to <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/ajschumacher.github.io/issues/206">no ideas but in things</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As leaders, we should think of ourselves as teachers and try to
create companies in which teaching is seen as a valued way to
contribute to the success of the whole." (page 123)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The problem is that our brains aren't wired to think about it
[randomness]. Instead, we are built to look for patterns in sights,
sounds, interactions, and events in the world. This mechanism is so
ingrained that we see patterns even when they aren't there. There is
a subtle reason for this: We can store patterns and conclusions in
our heads, but we cannot store randomness itself. Randomness is a
concept that defies categorization; by definition, it comes out of
nowhere and can't be anticipated. While we intellectually accept
that it exists, our brains can't completely grasp it, so it has less
impact on our consciousness than things we can see, measure, and
categorize." (page 155)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Everyone says they want to hire excellent people, but in truth we
don't <em>really</em> know, at first, who will rise up to make a
difference." (page 165)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Let's pause for a moment and look at it from the position of a
manager who is having someone manage up <em>to</em> them. I'm not talking
about brownnosing per se but more subtle forms of flattery." (page
172)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is this what managing up means? I've always thought of it as a more
positive thing, where an IC is helping guide their manager and the
organization as much as the manager guides the IC, reciprocally. But
it seems some people think of "managing up" as a negative thing?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Craft is what we are expected to know; art is the unexpected use of
our craft." (page 196)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"And those cuts [to art programs in schools] stem from a fundamental
misconception that art classes are about learning to draw. In fact,
they are about learning to see." (page 213)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Companies, like individuals, do not become exceptional by believing
they are exceptional but by understanding the ways in which they
<em>aren't</em> exceptional." (page 215)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>""You can't manage what you can't measure" is a maxim that is taught
and believed by many in both the business and education sectors. But
in fact, the phrase is ridiculous—something said by people who are
unaware of how much is hidden. A large portion of what we manage
<em>can't</em> be measured, and not realizing this has unintended
consequences. The problem comes when people think that data paints a
full picture, leading them to ignore what they can't see." (page
219)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a href="http://www.calgran.net/upf/recursos/ima_dig/_2_/estampes/d3_1.html"><img alt="Road to Point Reyes" src="pointreyes.jpg"></a></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220213-creativity_inc_by_catmull/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220213-creativity_inc_by_catmull/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Still Life, by Louise Penny</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Put on your Sony ‘Discman’ and grab your palm pilot, because it's
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louise_Penny" title="Wikpedia: Louise Penny">Louise Penny</a>'s first book featuring
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief_Inspector_Armand_Gamache" title="Chief Inspector Armand Gamache">Chief Inspector Armand Gamache</a> (read "Galonche") from 2006!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>‘Life is change. If you aren’t growing and evolving you’re standing
still, and the rest of the world is surging ahead. Most of these
people are very immature. They lead “still” lives, waiting.’ (Myrna,
page 140)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I would be very pleased if I wrote a book as good as this. It's
charming fun with a bit of morality play blended in.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>‘We choose our thoughts. We choose our perceptions. We choose our
attitudes. We may not think so. We may not believe it, but we do. I
absolutely know we do. I’ve seen enough evidence, time after time,
tragedy after tragedy. Triumph after triumph. It’s about choice.’
(Gamache, page 80)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Stoic? Positive psychology? Right wing?</p>
<p>There's little sympathy for men's-rights-style whining:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"We’re not respected just by virtue of being English. It’s not the
same thing. Do you have any idea how much our lives have changed in
the last twenty years? All the rights we’ve lost?" (Ben Hadley, page
50)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I enjoyed the art world dalliance, which reminded me somewhat of the
end of Vonnegut's Bluebeard. And Nichol! Who's never been Nichol? So
awful! So fun to hate, and/or pity.</p>
<p>I collected things of varying degrees of Canadianness that I looked
up. (Do compound bows have built-in triggers in Montreal?)</p>
<ul>
<li>as hard as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canadian_Shield">Canadian Shield</a>: a large area of exposed
   Precambrian rock</li>
<li><a href="https://carnegiemnh.org/b-is-for-beaver-sticks/">beaver stick</a>: just what it sounds like</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montreal_Canadiens">Canadiens</a>: the Montreal hockey team</li>
<li>cured Canadian bacon: but they mean regular bacon</li>
<li><em>dépanneur</em>: A convenience store, especially one that sells
   alcohol (in Quebec)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eaton%27s_catalogue">Eaton's catalogue</a>: one of the first mail-order catalogs
   distributed by a Canadian retail store</li>
<li>He’s a Golden Mile boy: refers to a rich <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Square_Mile" title="Golden Square Mile">area</a> of Montreal</li>
<li>Inspector Clouseau: The Chief Inspector from The Pink Panther</li>
<li>Inuk island: apparently Inuk is interchangeable with Inuit? Is this
   a specific place?</li>
<li>"Lee Valley catalogue": "Lee Valley Tools Ltd. is a Canadian
   business specializing in tools and gifts for woodworking and
   gardening."</li>
<li>Lune Moon: a funny Canadian <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hazboy/30114619898" title="Lune Moons">snack cake</a></li>
<li>‘May I have his co-ordinates, please?’ (page 61) was asking for a
   person's location. Is this a common phrasing?</li>
<li>Méteo Media: "a Canadian French-language weather information
   specialty channel and web site"</li>
<li>tabarouette, tabarnouche: "Mild version of french-canadian curse
   word tabarnak."</li>
<li>Tabernacle: This is a curse, somehow?</li>
<li>tête carrée: "square head" / blockhead</li>
<li>three extra large ‘All Dressed’ from Pizza Pizza: "Montreal
   <a href="https://good-pizza-great-pizza.fandom.com/wiki/List_of_orders#All-Dressed">slang</a> for the works"</li>
<li>tins of soft drinks: Is this what they say in Quebec?</li>
<li>toques: normal winter hats, but in Canada (read "tooks")</li>
<li>to twig: To realise something; to catch on; to recognize someone or
   something (British?)</li>
<li>village cozy: A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cozy_mystery" title="Wikipedia: Cozy mystery">mystery genre</a> referenced by a character. Still
   Life is pretty close to a village cozy.</li>
<li>‘yes yes’ cookies: Apparently these are like the Girl Scouts'
   "Samoas"</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220212-still_life_by_louise_penny/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220212-still_life_by_louise_penny/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>7 Habits weekly cards</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://smile.amazon.com/Habits-Highly-Effective-People-Anniversary/dp/1642500267" title="The 7 Habits of Highly Effective People: 30th Anniversary Card Deck">It</a>'s a card a week for a year, classic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_7_Habits_of_Highly_Effective_People" title="The 7 Habits of Highly Effective People">7 Habits</a> material, with
reflections and tasks for the week. I did it mostly in 2021, and I
enjoyed it. It inspired me to write a <a href="/20210226-vision_and_mission/" title="Vision and Mission">vision and mission</a>, for
example. More than the content, I like the practice of having a weekly
reflection.</p>
<p>The calendar is somewhat arbitrary, but it can be used for multiple
scales of reflection and planning. I have a <a href="/20211030-my_daily_routine/" title="My daily routine">daily practice</a>, and a
weekly practice is a nice additional layer. Maybe I should think about
a monthly equivalent as well. It's pretty common to use the
<a href="/20211228-habits_for_2022_ratio/" title="Habits for 2022: “ratio”">new year</a> for a yearly reflection and focusing too. I haven't done
five year plans, but could...</p>
<p><img alt="box" src="box.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220206-7_habits_weekly_cards/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220206-7_habits_weekly_cards/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>System Design Interview, by Xu</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I hadn't done system design interviews before last summer when I
interviewed at Google, Uber, Facebook, Robinhood, and a few others.
Alex Xu's <a href="https://www.amazon.com/System-Design-Interview-Insiders-Guide-ebook/dp/B08B3FWYBX" title="System Design Interview – An Insider's Guide">insider's guide</a> became one of my main prep materials for
this interview type. I think it helped.</p>
<p>I was preparing for system design interviews for machine learning
engineering positions, and sort of related design questions on ML for
data science positions. Xu's book is on more general software
engineering, but I thought it was still interesting and valuable. MLE
interviews can have "regular" SWE system design components too. For
system design content more specific to machine learning, I thought
<a href="https://www.educative.io/">Educative</a> had some decent materials.</p>
<p>I think system design interviews are often trying to evaluate not just
abstract or academic knowledge, but experience, thinking, and
communication skills. Reading a book like this helps jumpstart and
review your knowledge, and is definitely valuable, but is probably not
sufficient for a truly outstanding performance. So you could start
here, but don't stop!</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220109-system_design_interview_by_xu/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220109-system_design_interview_by_xu/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Resume dos and don'ts</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I've thought about my resume, I've read <a href="/20220107-tech_resume_inside_out_by_orosz/" title="The Tech Resume Inside Out, by Orosz">a book about resumes</a>, and
I've reviewed hundreds of candidate resumes. Your resume is the first
work product you share with an employer. Make sure it's good. Here's a
collection of resume advice, together with some appalling errors you
wouldn't think people would make—until you see them happen.</p>
<h3>Do this</h3>
<ul>
<li>Consider your audience and what you want them to think about you.</li>
<li>Focus on what you've achieved. Provide <em>evidence</em>, not just claims.<ul>
<li>Use this pattern:
   <a href="https://www.inc.com/bill-murphy-jr/google-recruiters-say-these-5-resume-tips-including-x-y-z-formula-will-improve-your-odds-of-getting-hired-at-google.html" title="Google Recruiters Say Using the 'X-Y-Z Formula' on Your Resume Will Improve Your Odds of Getting Hired at Google">Accomplished X, as measured by Y, by doing Z.</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="/20200715-communicate_immediately/" title="Communicate Immediately">Communicate immediately.</a> Be direct. Be clear.</li>
<li>Use bullet-points, short sentences, rarely anything longer than one
   line.</li>
<li>Make the document look perfect. Format must be PDF.<ul>
<li>Page layout matters. 1.5 pages is worse than 1 or 2.</li>
<li>If at all possible, use LaTeX.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Don't do this</h3>
<ul>
<li>Do not include these elements (as listed by <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/07/20/remove-these-things-from-your-resume-asap-says-ceo-who-has-read-thousands-of-resumes.html" title="Remove these 7 things from your resume ‘ASAP,’ says CEO who has read more than 1,000 resumes this year">Peter Yang</a>):<ul>
<li>Irrelevant hobbies and interests</li>
<li>Too many soft skills</li>
<li>Your professional headshot</li>
<li>Personal pronouns (As in: “Managed a team,” not “I managed a
   team”)</li>
<li>The wrong kind of email (As in: AOL or Hotmail, etc.)</li>
<li>Your mailing address (if you’re applying out-of-state)</li>
<li>Job positions older than 10 to 15 years</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://algodaily.com/lessons/the-perfect-software-engineering-resume-is-like-a-google-search-result/step-eight-8" title="from: Writing The Perfect Software Engineering Resume Is Like a Google Search Result">No Need For a Global Summary (Don't Have a Summary/Objective Section)</a></li>
<li>Include no errors in content and formatting. (See next section for
   examples.)</li>
</ul>
<h3>Resume horror</h3>
<p>Your expertise should be clear from what you've done, not from some
rating scale that you use on yourself. Please no star ratings or “An
asterisk denotes *Expert level” etc.</p>
<p>Don't say “40 Hours/Week” for every job you've worked. Full time
employment is assumed. I'm thinking about resumes for salaried
positions, but even if it were hourly, I don't think I'd want to see
“40 Hours/Week” repeated over and over.</p>
<p>Links and email addresses should not have old-school underlined blue
styling. Control the formatting to make it simple and beautiful.</p>
<p>If you have links in your resume, <em>make sure you know where they go</em>.
I've seen resumes where, presumably because they used somebody else's
resume as a starting point, the link text was updated but the link
still took me to <em>somebody else's</em> LinkedIn and Twitter.</p>
<p>Pay special attention with things you're claiming expertise in: It's
hard to believe you if you say you know “CentOs”—because it's CentOS.</p>
<p>Please get the names of your prior employers correct. There is no “Red
American Cross”—it's “American Red Cross.”</p>
<p>If you are “quick to learn new tools and technics” why have you not
learned how to spell “techniques?”</p>
<p>It's easier to not use color at all than to use it well. Particularly
bad: “Wor” in blue, regular weight, with “k Experience” in bold black.
Why do that?</p>
<p>Almost nobody should include GPA(s) in their resume. Possible
exception: It's perfect, and you've never had a job. Particularly bad:
Including a mediocre GPA for one degree, with GPA then conspicuously
absent for one or more other degrees.</p>
<p>Notice how this actual section from a real resume is
self-contradictory:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Communication – Persuasive communicator, comfortable challenging the
status quo when appropriate, whether to long-standing processes or
to conventional thinking to drive greater efficiencies and outcomes.
Able to adjust communications to a diverse audience to ensure
understanding and clarity. Recognizes the importance of providing
concise, complete visualizations of complex data.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Show,_don't_tell" title="Wikipedia: Show, don't tell">Show, don't tell.</a> Words without evidence are only demonstrating
that you can waste time.</p>
<p>Don't use two spaces between sentences. We're using computers.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220108-resume_dos_and_donts/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220108-resume_dos_and_donts/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Tech Resume Inside Out, by Orosz</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I read <a href="https://thetechresume.com/" title="The Tech Resume Inside Out: What a Good Developer Resume Looks Like">this</a> when I was re-doing my resume last spring, and I think
it helped. Here are some changes to my resume that I made based on its
advice:</p>
<ul>
<li>With double the experience, I cut the length in half to get to one
   page.</li>
<li>I dropped my full address, keeping just city and state.</li>
<li>I put job titles before and more prominently than employer names.</li>
<li>Instead of paragraphs describing jobs, 16 bullet-points, all single
   lines.</li>
<li>Lots of active voice, immediate quantitative detail, and specifics.</li>
<li>Instead of a separate section, programming languages etc. mentioned
   in context.</li>
<li>I dropped months, so dates of employment only include years.</li>
</ul>
<p>I didn't make a separate resume for <em>every</em> position I applied for,
but I did distribute at least six different versions for different
kinds of roles.</p>
<p>Do resumes matter? I'm not sure. You probably still need to have one
though. And it may be that the <em>less</em> they matter, the better the
signal you provide by <em>still</em> having a good one. People who are great
do the little things well.</p>
<p>If nothing else, thinking about your resume can focus your work: How
would what I'm doing today look on my resume? If you're doing
something that would seem pointless on a resume, maybe you should do
something else.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.png"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220107-tech_resume_inside_out_by_orosz/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220107-tech_resume_inside_out_by_orosz/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 07 Jan 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Radium Girls, by Moore</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I like that <a href="https://www.kate-moore.com/" title="Kate Moore">Moore</a> writes with purpose; all her books expose
injustice against and give voice to women (with the possible exception
of the Felix the Railway Cat series; I'm not sure about those).
<a href="https://www.theradiumgirls.com/" title="The Radium Girls">The Radium Girls</a> stays readable over nearly 500 pages, conveying
history that feels relevant to current issues of business, law,
rights, and risks.</p>
<p><strong>Capitalism can be stupid and mean</strong>: Several businesspeople seem
Trump-like in their disregard for ethics in the pursuit of profit.
It's hard to take a libertarian point of view with externalities like
these. And radium dials at least look cool, but many radium businesses
sold absolute snake oil. I noticed today that a company will sell you
<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/01/style/gummies-edibles-marijuana-diet.html" title="Counterculture to Counterintuitive: Cannabis to Help You Diet? An edibles company says one of its products will lead not to the “the munchies” but to weight loss. There’s just one problem: the science.">marijuana gummies for weight loss</a>. Maybe not much has changed.</p>
<p><strong>Ignorance and geography</strong>: It was much harder, it seemed, to find a
competent doctor or lawyer in small-town Illinois, compared to the New
York metropolitan area. It seems there was more religiosity in the
middle west as well. It also struck me as strange that terminal
patients were generally not told that they were terminal. Is that
still the case? Is ignorance really better in such cases?</p>
<p><strong>Weaponizing “experts”</strong>: As with radium, so with cigarettes and
opioids and climate change and on and on... The pursuit of knowledge
pushed behind debate-club he-said/she-said and outright lies.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"But if you looked a little closer at all those positive
publications, there was a common denominator: the researchers, on
the whole, worked for radium firms. As radium was such a rare and
mysterious element, its commercial exploiters in fact controlled, to
an almost monopolizing extent, its image and most of the knowledge
about it. Many firms had their own radium-themed journals, which
were distributed free to doctors, all full of optimistic research.
The firms that profited from radium medicine were the primary
producers and publishers of the positive literature." (page 49)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Dangers with delayed effects</strong>: Radium took years, usually, to have
negative effects on the radium dial painters. What risks do we
currently not know or underestimate?</p>
<ul>
<li>Climate change? Microplastics?</li>
<li>Social media? Entertainment?</li>
<li>Unemployment? Overemployment?</li>
<li>Migration? Lack of migration?</li>
<li>Trends in education?</li>
<li>Kombucha?</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Gender and class</strong>: Moore highlights inequities in societal
attention and care. For example, "It seemed wealthy consumers were
much more worthy of protection than working-class girls..." (page 273)
It reminds me of the 21st-century popularization of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_Neel" title="Wikipedia: Alice Neel">Alice Neel</a>,
who similarly focused on working people and "the female gaze." How far
is there still to go?</p>
<p><strong>The legal system</strong>: The tales of slow and capricious legal
processes, out-of-court settlements, rhetoric over reality, the
influence of wealth, and general nonsense... The 1920s and 30s sound
very much like the present.</p>
<hr>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220102-radium_girls_by_moore/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220102-radium_girls_by_moore/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Try the GSS WORDSUM questions!</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Social_Survey" title="Wikipedia: General Social Survey">General Social Survey</a> includes a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wordsum" title="Wikipedia: Wordsum">WORDSUM</a> vocabulary test
component that is often used as a proxy measure for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intelligence_quotient" title="Wikipedia: Intelligence quotient">IQ</a>. Want to see
how well you can do? Try these 20 questions!</p>
<hr>
<style>
input[type="radio"], label { cursor: pointer; }
input[type="radio"]:checked+label { font-weight: bold; }
.marked_correct { font-style: italic }
</style>

<table width="100%"><tr><td width="60%">

<p>For each initial word, find the other word which means the same or
most nearly the same.</p>

<p>In the example at right, “animal” is selected because it has the
closest meaning to “beast.”</p>

</td><td style="padding-left: 10%;">

<b>beast</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="ex" id="ex_1" disabled>
<label for="ex_1">afraid</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="ex" id="ex_2" disabled>
<label for="ex_2">words</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="ex" id="ex_3" disabled>
<label for="ex_3">large</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="ex" id="ex_4" checked>
<label for="ex_4">animal</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="ex" id="ex_5" disabled>
<label for="ex_5">separate</label>

</td></tr></table>

<hr>
<p><b>space</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="01" id="01_1">
<label for="01_1">school</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="01" id="01_2">
<label for="01_2">noon</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="01" id="01_3">
<label for="01_3">captain</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="01" id="01_4" class="correct">
<label for="01_4" class="correct_label">room</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="01" id="01_5">
<label for="01_5">board</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>lift</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="02" id="02_1">
<label for="02_1">sort out</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="02" id="02_2" class="correct">
<label for="02_2" class="correct_label">raise</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="02" id="02_3">
<label for="02_3">value</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="02" id="02_4">
<label for="02_4">enjoy</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="02" id="02_5">
<label for="02_5">fancy</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>concern</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="03" id="03_1">
<label for="03_1">see clearly</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="03" id="03_2">
<label for="03_2">engage</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="03" id="03_3">
<label for="03_3">furnish</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="03" id="03_4">
<label for="03_4">disturb</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="03" id="03_5" class="correct">
<label for="03_5" class="correct_label">have to do with</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>broaden</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="04" id="04_1">
<label for="04_1">efface</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="04" id="04_2">
<label for="04_2">make level</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="04" id="04_3">
<label for="04_3">elapse</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="04" id="04_4">
<label for="04_4">embroider</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="04" id="04_5" class="correct">
<label for="04_5" class="correct_label">widen</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>blunt</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="05" id="05_1" class="correct">
<label for="05_1" class="correct_label">dull</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="05" id="05_2">
<label for="05_2">drowsy</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="05" id="05_3">
<label for="05_3">deaf</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="05" id="05_4">
<label for="05_4">doubtful</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="05" id="05_5">
<label for="05_5">ugly</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>accustom</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="06" id="06_1">
<label for="06_1">disappoint</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="06" id="06_2">
<label for="06_2">customary</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="06" id="06_3">
<label for="06_3">encounter</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="06" id="06_4" class="correct">
<label for="06_4" class="correct_label">get used</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="06" id="06_5">
<label for="06_5">business</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>chirrup</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="07" id="07_1">
<label for="07_1">aspen</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="07" id="07_2">
<label for="07_2">joyful</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="07" id="07_3">
<label for="07_3">capsize</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="07" id="07_4" class="correct">
<label for="07_4" class="correct_label">chirp</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="07" id="07_5">
<label for="07_5">incite</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>edible</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="08" id="08_1">
<label for="08_1">auspicious</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="08" id="08_2">
<label for="08_2">eligible</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="08" id="08_3" class="correct">
<label for="08_3" class="correct_label">fit to eat</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="08" id="08_4">
<label for="08_4">sagacious</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="08" id="08_5">
<label for="08_5">able to speak</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>pact</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="09" id="09_1">
<label for="09_1">puissance</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="09" id="09_2">
<label for="09_2">remonstrance</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="09" id="09_3" class="correct">
<label for="09_3" class="correct_label">agreement</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="09" id="09_4">
<label for="09_4">skillet</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="09" id="09_5">
<label for="09_5">pressure</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>solicitor</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="10" id="10_1" class="correct">
<label for="10_1" class="correct_label">lawyer</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="10" id="10_2">
<label for="10_2">chieftain</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="10" id="10_3">
<label for="10_3">watchman</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="10" id="10_4">
<label for="10_4">maggot</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="10" id="10_5">
<label for="10_5">constable</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>allusion</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="11" id="11_1">
<label for="11_1">aria</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="11" id="11_2">
<label for="11_2">illusion</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="11" id="11_3">
<label for="11_3">eulogy</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="11" id="11_4">
<label for="11_4">dream</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="11" id="11_5" class="correct">
<label for="11_5" class="correct_label">reference</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>caprice</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="12" id="12_1">
<label for="12_1">value</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="12" id="12_2">
<label for="12_2">a star</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="12" id="12_3">
<label for="12_3">grimace</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="12" id="12_4" class="correct">
<label for="12_4" class="correct_label">whim</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="12" id="12_5">
<label for="12_5">inducement</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>animosity</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="13" id="13_1" class="correct">
<label for="13_1" class="correct_label">hatred</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="13" id="13_2">
<label for="13_2">animation</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="13" id="13_3">
<label for="13_3">disobedience</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="13" id="13_4">
<label for="13_4">diversity</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="13" id="13_5">
<label for="13_5">friendship</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>emanate</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="14" id="14_1">
<label for="14_1">populate</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="14" id="14_2">
<label for="14_2">free</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="14" id="14_3">
<label for="14_3">prominent</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="14" id="14_4">
<label for="14_4">rival</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="14" id="14_5" class="correct">
<label for="14_5" class="correct_label">come</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>madrigal</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="15" id="15_1" class="correct">
<label for="15_1" class="correct_label">song</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="15" id="15_2">
<label for="15_2">mountebank</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="15" id="15_3">
<label for="15_3">lunatic</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="15" id="15_4">
<label for="15_4">ribald</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="15" id="15_5">
<label for="15_5">sycophant</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>cloistered</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="16" id="16_1">
<label for="16_1">miniature</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="16" id="16_2">
<label for="16_2">bunched</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="16" id="16_3">
<label for="16_3">arched</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="16" id="16_4">
<label for="16_4">malady</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="16" id="16_5" class="correct">
<label for="16_5" class="correct_label">secluded</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>encomium</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="17" id="17_1">
<label for="17_1">repetition</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="17" id="17_2">
<label for="17_2">friend</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="17" id="17_3" class="correct">
<label for="17_3" class="correct_label">panegyric</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="17" id="17_4">
<label for="17_4">abrasion</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="17" id="17_5">
<label for="17_5">expulsion</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>pristine</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="18" id="18_1">
<label for="18_1">flashing</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="18" id="18_2">
<label for="18_2">earlier</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="18" id="18_3" class="correct">
<label for="18_3" class="correct_label">primeval</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="18" id="18_4">
<label for="18_4">bound</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="18" id="18_5">
<label for="18_5">green</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>tactility</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="19" id="19_1" class="correct">
<label for="19_1" class="correct_label">tangibility</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="19" id="19_2">
<label for="19_2">grace</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="19" id="19_3">
<label for="19_3">subtlety</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="19" id="19_4">
<label for="19_4">extensibility</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="19" id="19_5">
<label for="19_5">manageableness</label></p>
<hr>
<p><b>sedulous</b>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="20" id="20_1">
<label for="20_1">muddied</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="20" id="20_2">
<label for="20_2">sluggish</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="20" id="20_3">
<label for="20_3">stupid</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="20" id="20_4" class="correct">
<label for="20_4" class="correct_label">assiduous</label>
<br>
<input type="radio" name="20" id="20_5">
<label for="20_5">corrupting</label></p>
<hr>
<div id="show_scoring">

<input type="submit" value="Show scoring and italicize correct answers" onclick="
    document.getElementById('scoring').style.visibility = 'visible';
    document.getElementById('show_scoring').style.visibility = 'hidden';
    document.querySelectorAll('.correct_label').forEach(
      element =&gt; element.classList.add('marked_correct'))">

</div>

<div id="scoring" style="visibility: hidden;">

<h3><span id="wordsum">0</span> of 10 points (<span id="count">0</span> correct of 20 questions)</h3>

<input type="submit" value="Hide scoring and un-italicize correct answers" onclick="
    document.getElementById('scoring').style.visibility = 'hidden';
    document.getElementById('show_scoring').style.visibility = 'visible';
    document.querySelectorAll('.correct_label').forEach(
      element =&gt; element.classList.remove('marked_correct'))">

</div>

<hr>
<p>Caveats:</p>
<ul>
<li>I'm pretty sure I've identified the right answers, but I haven't
   seen an answer key (just the relevant test booklets).</li>
<li>The actual <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wordsum" title="Wikipedia: Wordsum">WORDSUM</a> has 10 questions, not 20. I know that those
   ten questions are among these 20, but I don't know <em>which</em>. For
   more detail, read on.</li>
</ul>
<p>Here's an <a href="https://gss.norc.org/Documents/reports/methodological-reports/MR111%20The%20Psychometric%20Properties%20of%20the%20GSS%20Wordsum%20Vocabulary%20Test.pdf" title="The Psychometric Properties of the GSS Wordsum Vocabulary Test">excerpt</a> on the history of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wordsum" title="Wikipedia: Wordsum">WORDSUM</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In the early 1920s, Edward L. Thorndike developed a lengthy
vocabulary test as part of the I.E.R. Intelligence Scale CAVD to
measure, in his words, “verbal intelligence.” As in the modern-day
Wordsum test, each question asked respondents to identify the word
or phrase in a set of five whose meaning was closest to a target
word. Robert L. Thorndike (1942) later extracted two subsets of the
original test, each containing twenty items of varying difficulty.
For each subset, two target words were selected at each of ten
difficulty levels. The ten items in Wordsum (labeled with letters
A though J) were selected from the first of these two subsets.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's not perfectly accurate to say Thorndike developed a lengthy
vocabulary test. The I.E.R Intelligence Scale CAVD, <a href="https://copyright.cornell.edu/publicdomain" title="Copyright at Cornell Libraries: Copyright Term and the Public Domain">copyright</a> 1925
and 1926, is 17 levels (A through Q) and each level has ten vocabulary
questions in multiple choice format, among other question types.</p>
<p>Thorndike 1942 is <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/1942-04205-001" title="Thorndike, R. L. (1942). Two screening tests of verbal intelligence. Journal of Applied Psychology, 26(2), 128–135.">Two screening tests of verbal intelligence</a>,
which describes how two 20-word tests “containing two words from each
of the levels of CAVD from H through Q” (the more difficult end of the
spectrum; levels A through E use pictures) were constructed.</p>
<p><img alt="two forms" src="two_forms.png"></p>
<p>The first subset then is <em>Form A</em>, and those are the questions
included above. I don't know <em>which</em> ten words from Form A's twenty
are in WORDSUM, however. As <a href="https://gssdataexplorer.norc.org/documents/444/display" title="GSS Codebook Appendix D">GSS Codebook Appendix D</a> explains:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To minimize the admittedly small possibility that some form of
publicity would affect the public's knowledge of the words included
in the test, they are not reported here.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think it's fascinating that a vocab test from the 1920s is part of
the GSS, which continues to be administered in the 2020s. I think it's
fascinating that WORDSUM has been used for evidence that
<a href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Intelligence-makes-people-think-like-economists%3A-Caplan-Miller/ef579356c5c461914e3c0ff896c7949554be1774" title="Intelligence makes people think like economists: Evidence from the General Social Survey">Intelligence makes people think like economists</a>, among many other
things.</p>
<p>I think the benefit of knowing what the WORDSUM questions are far
outweighs any risk “that some form of publicity would affect the
public's knowledge of the words included in the test.” Frankly, I'm
not sure WORDSUM deserves an encomium.</p>

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220101-try_the_gss_wordsum_questions/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220101-try_the_gss_wordsum_questions/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Predicting the future from 2022</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>For the third year in a row (<a href="/20200112-predicting_the_future_from_2020/" title="Predicting the Future from 2020">2020</a>, <a href="/20210102-predicting_the_future_from_2021/" title="Predicting the future from 2021">2021</a>) I consider what might
happen. I continue to mostly imagine current trends continue, and
throw in some extra stuff for fun.</p>
<h3>By 2023 (1 year from now)</h3>
<ul>
<li>Omicron is the last major Covid variant, but supply chain and
   workforce issues continue to be hard all year.</li>
<li>Democrats become minorities in the House and Senate in 2022 US elections.</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_II" title="Wikipedia: Elizabeth II">Queen Elizabeth</a> is dead. (Recommended by Tonia.)</li>
<li>Inflation carries on around 5%.</li>
<li>S&amp;P 500 closes above 5,000.</li>
</ul>
<h3>By 2027 (5 years from now)</h3>
<ul>
<li>Democratic candidate wins presidency in 2024 US election.</li>
<li>Inflation around 2%.</li>
<li>Global population exceeds 8 billion for the first time in 2023
   (<a href="https://population.un.org/wpp/Download/Standard/Population/" title="Total Population - Both Sexes (XLSX, 2.4 MB)">predicted</a> by the UN).</li>
<li>Total population between 8,221,264 and 8,333,078 (low/med
   <a href="https://population.un.org/wpp/Download/Standard/Population/" title="Total Population - Both Sexes (XLSX, 2.4 MB)">predicted</a> by the UN).</li>
<li>S&amp;P 500 closes above 7,000.</li>
</ul>
<h3>By 2032 (10 years from now)</h3>
<ul>
<li>Texas has non-zero state income tax and plenty of climate and
   infrastructure things to spend on.</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zendaya" title="Wikipedia: Zendaya">Zendaya</a> wins an Oscar.</li>
<li>At least one European nation has something identifiable as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_basic_income" title="Wikipedia: Universal Basic Income">UBI</a>.</li>
<li>Total population between 8,445,932 and 8,687,228 (low/med
   <a href="https://population.un.org/wpp/Download/Standard/Population/" title="Total Population - Both Sexes (XLSX, 2.4 MB)">predicted</a> by the UN).</li>
<li>S&amp;P 500 closes above 9,000.</li>
</ul>
<h3>By 2042 (20 years from now)</h3>
<ul>
<li>The US effectively has <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_basic_income" title="Wikipedia: Universal Basic Income">UBI</a>, but it isn't called that. Maybe a
   patchwork of policies.</li>
<li>At least one international advertising campaign intended to
   encourage immigration to the US by ameliorating the reputation of
   unemployed Americans.</li>
<li>Total population between 8,769,695 and 9,315,508 (low/med
   <a href="https://population.un.org/wpp/Download/Standard/Population/" title="Total Population - Both Sexes (XLSX, 2.4 MB)">predicted</a> by the UN).</li>
<li>S&amp;P 500 closes above 15,000.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3>Trends</h3>
<ul>
<li>I think global population growth will be <em>slightly</em> slower than the
   medium variant <a href="https://population.un.org/wpp/Download/Standard/Population/" title="Total Population - Both Sexes (XLSX, 2.4 MB)">predicted</a> by the UN. Covid might contribute a
   little, but I think this is mostly from efforts like Bill Gates's,
   possibly Belt and Road, and general technology and modernization.</li>
<li>Climate change continues. More fires, more floods, more droughts,
   more storms. Climate action continues to be nominal.</li>
<li>It keeps being easy/easier to fake things.<ul>
<li>Lots of cheap/low-quality stuff.</li>
<li>The value of direct human relationships/trust stays very
   high/grows. Elite college education keeps getting more
   valuable.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Inequality continues to grow.<ul>
<li>Extreme poverty continues to decline; the bottom of the range
   is higher than previously. In some places, there may be <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_basic_income" title="Wikipedia: Universal Basic Income">UBI</a>
   eventually.</li>
<li>But the gap between the bottom of the range and the top grows.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>More legalization of drugs.</li>
<li>There will continue to be more real problems with not having enough
   people to work than there are with having too many people put out
   of work by technology.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3>Wilder speculations</h3>
<ul>
<li>“The middle class is precarious.” To what extent is <em>downward</em>
   mobility present? acceptable? desirable? To what extent is/should
   mobility be like a ratchet: only upward? The idle rich are not
   generally admired as virtuous, I think, but people also really
   dislike it when their children are worse off than they are/were (or
   if they're those children). What will be the long-term trend? What
   level of wealth should anyone have to “earn”? (Inspired by Emilie.)</li>
<li>Infant (and child) mortality is dramatically <a href="/20200806-life_expectancy_is_historically_misleading/" title="Life expectancy is historically misleading">down</a> and will
   likely continue to get lower. The first-order effect is obviously
   good. What are the second-order effects? Does the decrease in
   infant mortality contribute to any population health effects?</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3>Reviewing past predictions</h3>
<p>I was a little crazy in <a href="/20210102-predicting_the_future_from_2021/" title="Predicting the future from 2021">2021</a>. Depending on the level of generosity
in interpretation, I was somewhere from 1/4 to 4/4 on one-year
predictions. None of my longer-term predictions have materialized.
Still no aliens.</p>
<p>From <a href="/20200112-predicting_the_future_from_2020/" title="Predicting the Future from 2020">2020</a>: Hong Kong <a href="https://www.ksl.com/article/50319384/how-democracy-was-dismantled-in-hong-kong-in-2021" title="How democracy was dismantled in Hong Kong in 2021">seems to be</a> pretty well controlled by the
mainland now.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220101-predicting_the_future_from_2022/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220101-predicting_the_future_from_2022/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>A Calendar of Wisdom, by Tolstoy</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>In 2021, I followed <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leo_Tolstoy" title="Wikipedia: Leo Tolstoy">Tolstoy</a>'s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Calendar_of_Wisdom" title="A Calendar of Wisdom">Calendar of Wisdom</a>. It's a
page-a-day calendar, circa 1910, with a little more gravitas. I like
the concept but I don't always agree with Tolstoy.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Guiding your thoughts is one of the keys to self-perfection."
(August 9)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Tolstoy is quite religious, pacifist, vegetarian, and
back-to-the-earth. He mixes quotes and paraphrases with his own
commentary and aphorisms. I can't quite recommend it all because I
find some things objectionable, but I like the idea of having
something to reflect on daily. Some of my most and least favorite
selections are below.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<h3>Not bad, Tolstoy</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>"To accept the dignity of another person is an axiom." (April 16)</p>
<p>"<em>Effort is the necessary condition of moral perfection.</em>" (July 23)</p>
<p>"When a person tries to apply his intellect to the question “Why do
I exist in this world?” he becomes dizzy. The human intellect cannot
find the answers to such questions." (July 29)</p>
<p>"Think good thoughts, and your thoughts will be turned into good
actions. Everything begins in thought. Guiding your thoughts is one
of the keys to self-perfection." (August 9)</p>
<p>"<em>Real goodness is not something that can be acquired in an instant,
but only through constant effort, because real goodness lies in
constantly striving for perfection.</em>" (September 4)</p>
<p>"You should abstain from arguments. They are very illogical ways to
convince people. Opinions are like nails: the stronger you hit them,
the deeper inside they go." (November 4, quoting Decimus Junius
Juvenalis)</p>
<p>"The more urgently you want to speak, the more likely it is that you
will say something foolish." (November 4)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h3>No thanks, Tolstoy</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>"<em>A marriage is a special obligation between two people, of opposite
sexes, to have children only with each other. To break this pact is
a lie, a deception, and a crime.</em>" (March 11)</p>
<p>"We can improve this world only by distributing the true faith among
the world's people." (March 17)</p>
<p>"You should never feel depressed.</p>
<p>A man should always feel happy; if he is unhappy, it means he is
guilty." (June 29)</p>
<p>"People know little, because they try to understand those things
which are not open to them for understanding: God, eternity, spirit;
or those which are not worth thinking about: how water becomes
frozen, or a new theory of numbers, or how viruses can transmit
illnesses." (July 27)</p>
<p>"Only religion destroys egoism and selfishness, so that one starts
to live life not only for himself. Only religion destroys the fear
of death, only religion gives us the meaning of life, only religion
creates equality among people, only religion sets a person free from
outer pressures." (August 18)</p>
<p>"It is dangerous to disseminate the idea that our life is purely the
product of material forces and that it depends entirely on these
forces." (August 22)</p>
<p>"<em>Faith is the foundation on which all else rests; it is the root of
all knowledge.</em>" (August 28)</p>
<p>"Though the mission of a woman's life is the same as that of a man's
life and the service to God is fulfilled by the same means, namely
love, for the majority of women the method of this service is more
specific than for men. This is the birth and upbringing of new
workers for the Lord throughout life." (December 1)</p>
<p>"There is nothing more natural for a woman than self-sacrifice."
(December 1)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20211231-calendar_of_wisdom_by_tolstoy/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20211231-calendar_of_wisdom_by_tolstoy/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
