<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>(Audio) Survival of the Richest, by Rushkoff</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Billionaire bunkers are just Rushkoff's hook. His gripe is with
capitalist growth as both cause and effect of the rich, and (he
argues) cause of social and environmental calamities past and future.
Rushkoff's <a href="https://wwnorton.com/books/survival-of-the-richest" title="Survival of the Richest: Escape Fantasies of the Tech Billionaires">book</a> argues for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Degrowth" title="Wikipedia: Degrowth">degrowth</a>.</p>
<p>I really like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_Rushkoff" title="Wikipedia: Douglas Rushkoff">Rushkoff</a> in some respects. I wish his <a href="https://www.teamhuman.fm/" title="Team Human">Team Human</a>
podcast would make really nice basketball jerseys and sweatshirts. (I
consider myself on Team Human quite independent of whatever Rushkoff
says; I think it's a nice idea.)</p>
<p>I don't think escapism is unique to the ultra-rich. Every time I put
on headphones, in some ways I'm trying to find safety in isolation.
Not only the wealthy are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Survivalism" title="Wikipedia: Survivalism">preppers</a>. Everyone could do well to
reflect on how interdependent we all really are.</p>
<p>There's a bit of a failure of imagination in not exploring in the
direction of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlas_Shrugged" title="Wikipedia: Atlas Shrugged">Atlas Shrugged</a>. Perhaps a Marxist can't imagine the
proletariat being replaced by technology. I <a href="https://planspace.org/20220101-predicting_the_future_from_2022/" title="Predicting the future from 2022">still</a> think that in
the near term "There will continue to be more real problems with not
having enough people to work than there are with having too many
people put out of work by technology," but there are big questions
about what's going to happen with all the people not working
conventional jobs (of which there are many already today).</p>
<p>I don't think Rushkoff has a good argument here. But he says so <em>many</em>
things that the book is quite though-provoking regardless. He
characterizes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/QAnon" title="Wikipedia: QAnon">QAnon</a> as a kind of internet addiction. And you get
to hear about the many parties he's been invited to. Lucky you.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>He [<a href="https://nds-nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Dawkins" title="Wikipedia: Richard Dawkins">Richard Dawkins</a>] couldn’t acknowledge that his own
commitment to scientism is based on something passional—something
more like <em>faith</em> in an empiricist universe. In other words, his
insistence on living in an evidence-only universe isn’t based on
evidence at all. It’s an assumption. It’s part of a system of
meaning, developed by a community of people over time. It just
happens to be a meaning system that ignores meaning itself. Worse,
by rejecting the validity of any other meaning system, it is prone
to instilling in its adherents a sense of superiority over others.
Those who strive for meaning are mere “moralists.” (page 34)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I agree with parts of this critique; science should recognize its
foundation and scope.</p>
<hr>
<h3>A rather long tangent on a strange claim</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Initially the market economy, introduced just after the Crusades in
the late Middle Ages, benefited the former peasants of feudalism.
This was a lateral, peer-to-peer economy, not a hierarchical one.
Local farmers and bakers didn’t generally aspire to be “rich” so
much as to sustain themselves. Their currencies were optimized for
trade; they were less a way of saving or hoarding money than
facilitating the exchange of goods between people. It worked so well
that Europe saw its greatest period of economic growth to this
day—measured in the prosperity of the common folk. Towns got so
wealthy that they invested in building cathedrals to spur future
pilgrimages and tourism. People worked less, ate more, and grew
taller than ever before—and in some cases, ever since. (page 40)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't think this is the dominant historical view, but this time does
seem to be Rushkoff's "make economics great again" period. It's a
rather bold claim, saying that everybody used to be better off, and
even taller than now!</p>
<p>The citation here is the unpublished (but available online)
<a href="https://bernard-lietaer.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2004-Of-Human-Wealth-Beyond-Greed-Scarcity-Lieater-Belgin-annotated.pdf" title="Of Human Wealth">Of Human Wealth</a>. The authors (Lietar and Belgin) call the period
1050-1290 "the first European renaissance." On page 92 they have this
graph in classic Excel style:</p>
<p><img alt="graph from Of Human Wealth" src="of_human_wealth.png"></p>
<p>On page 91, the "ever since" is explained:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In a study of the skeletons of bodies in the same geographical area
(the City of London), informative findings emerged. The women of the
10-12th century were on average taller than in any other period in
recorded history, at least in London. During that period, the
average female Londoner was a whopping 7 centimeters taller than her
counterpart in Victorian times and 1 centimeter taller than the
average woman of London today! (Of Human Wealth, page 91)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The source for all this is <a href="https://www.amazon.com/London-Bodies-Changing-Londoners-Prehistoric/dp/090481890X" title="London Bodies: The Changing Shape of Londoners from Prehistoric Times to the Present Day">London Bodies</a>, the book companion to a
1998 exhibit at the Museum of London. The graph in Of Human Wealth
seems to be based on a table on the last page:</p>
<p><img alt="page from London Bodies" src="london_bodies.jpg"></p>
<p>It isn't clear that this is an authoritative source for drawing
conclusions about trends in height over time. It also isn't clear that
the table is even consistent with the rest of its own book, and
further it seems that Of Human Wealth is rather abusing what there is
in London Bodies anyway.</p>
<p>The "Saxon" numbers seem to correspond to page 56, in the "Saxon
Bodies" chapter:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>From this period, the eleventh and twelfth centuries, comes our best
group of medieval skeletons from a parish churchyard in London.
Excavations between 1975 and 1979 at the cemetery of St Nicholas
Shambles on Newgate Street produced over 200 burials. The average
heights of the people buried in the cemetery were 173cm (5ft 8in.)
for men and 157cm (5ft 2in.) for women. (London Bodies, page 56)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here the value for men matches the table, but the number for women is
quite different. Indeed nowhere in the "Saxon Bodies" chapter does the
163cm number appear.</p>
<p>Regardless of whether the number in the table is a typo or not, there
are many reasons to be skeptical. People buried at a particular church
are not at all guaranteed to be a random sample of the population.
Then there's the different methods for the heights: the first six
periods use long bone lengths, while the last two use height records.
The Victorian period is particularly suspect because it's based
exclusively on heights of "habitual criminals," not known to be the
most well-nourished of a given population. The mapping that the
authors of Of Human Wealth do from London Body's period labels to
centuries is also not quite right but hardly even worth mentioning
compared to everything else.</p>
<p>I'm sure I don't know enough about history to provide a complete
evaluation of this whole "first European renaissance" theory, but from
what I can see it doesn't seem very convincing. I'm surprised Rushkoff
would even mention it, and the fact he does makes me more skeptical of
everything else he says.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240519-survival_of_the_richest_by_rushkoff/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240519-survival_of_the_richest_by_rushkoff/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Build, by Fadell</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The "advice encyclopedia" from the father of the iPod is <a href="https://www.buildc.com/the-book" title="Build, the Book">billed</a> as
"an unorthodox guide" and maybe it is, depending on your orthodoxy.
Here are some of its recommendations as I recall them:</p>
<ul>
<li>Work really hard.</li>
<li>Be a perfectionist.</li>
<li>Micro-manage. (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Fadell" title="Tony Fadell">Tony</a> tries to clarify that what he recommends
   isn't micro-managing; the distinction is something like managing
   outputs as good vs. process as bad.)</li>
<li>Push people hard.</li>
<li>Have interviews done by a small group of people who will work with
   the new person, not a bunch of people from all over the company.</li>
<li>Don't have a lot of perks at the office.</li>
<li>Blame Google for Nest not going how you wanted.</li>
</ul>
<p>I think the most interesting thing, to me, is the tension between
intrinsic motivation vs. external pushing for generating results. Tony
seems like a pusher, and he's gotten results. But do bosses have to be
so hard-driving?</p>
<p>Fadell comments on how much time he spent on "people problems" (HR or
personnel issues) as a leader. This might always be the case, but I
also wonder whether particular leadership styles (and related hiring
choices) lead to more of this. Fadell says he followed a "no assholes
rule" in hiring. Might anosognosia be at play?</p>
<p>I'm not sure I'd like to work with Fadell, but I tend to like his
goals and his <a href="https://www.buildc.com/" title="Build Collective">Build Collective</a> seems to be supporting cool things.
(Ends vs. means?) The book is almost a promotional tie-in for this
venture operation.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240517-build_by_fadell/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240517-build_by_fadell/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Understanding bipolar disorder, by Daramus</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This 2020 <a href="https://www.audeotherapy.com/new-workbook-for-families-ofpeople-with-bipolar-disorder" title="Understanding Bipolar Disorder: The Essential Family Guide">book</a> is short (149 pages) and kind. With a therapist's
tact, it advises stoic behavior (see also: <a href="/20210107-enchiridion_in_52_sentences/" title="The Enchiridion in 52 sentences">The Enchiridion</a>) and
introduces helpful concepts and terminology (like on page 107,
"euthymic" means "not having a mood episode right now"). It seems like
pretty good guidance for a difficult condition.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There are times when having someone with bipolar live at home with
family is no longer realistic, and the person is not ready to live
on their own. In that case, a group home might be an option. (page
78)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It Won’t Work Right Away, and Not Everything Will Work (page 91)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes someone will go off medication without medical
supervision. This is dangerous but understandable. (page 94)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes You Need to Be a Caregiver (page 122)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>No matter how stable someone becomes, there will probably be another
mood episode eventually. (page 123)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Know the difference between your need to control things and what
will actually work. (page 135)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Repeated mood episodes are part of bipolar disorder: expect
setbacks. It’s not a disorder that anyone truly gets over, at least
not yet. (page 145)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240517-understanding_bipolar_disorder_by_daramus/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240517-understanding_bipolar_disorder_by_daramus/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Material World, by Conway</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ed_Conway">Conway</a> offers glimpses into a material world of sand, salt, iron,
copper, oil, and lithium for inhabitants of the aetherial world of
knowledge, software, and office blocks. It's often fascinating, and
delivers a thesis of global interconnection: we all depend on
everyone.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chloralkali_process">Chloralkali process</a> is electrolysis of very salty water. It
produces chlroine gas, which will kill you, and sodium hydroxide aka
lye, which isn't healthy either and which you can use to pulp wood and
make paper. This is very cool, and something you could probably do at
home. It's a little dangerous. I wonder if this is part of how we lose
education about the material world, by avoiding parts that are both
interesting and risky.</p>
<p>Maybe it's just my perspective as a computer guy, but I feel like the
work of the physical world is too often ignored and undervalued.
Something like Hammerbacher has said, it feels like everyone wants to
get rich at a keyboard while the lab benches are empty.</p>
<p>The book in a couple places recommends going to YouTube to see a
video, with search terms to use. I feel like I've heard this kind of
thing in a few books recently. Is this what books do now? They can't
embed video, so they tell you to go find the video yourself on
YouTube? I'm not 100% opposed, but this feels a little gross to me.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240413-material_world_by_conway/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240413-material_world_by_conway/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mortality rates have improved</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>A misleading graph from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rise_and_Fall_of_American_Growth" title="The Rise and Fall of American Growth, by Robert J. Gordon">The Rise and Fall of American Growth</a> was
reproduced and again misinterpreted in <a href="/20240128-outlive_by_attia/" title="Outlive, by Peter Attia">Outlive</a>. The graph
correctly shows that US deaths from infectious disease have decreased
a lot over the last hundred years. The graph incorrectly makes it seem
like death rates from other causes have been stable over this period.
The age-adjusted death rate has decreased by around 50% since 1950.
Death rates at every age band have been meaningfully decreasing, apart
from the impact of COVID-19.</p>
<p>Here's the graph in <a href="/20240128-outlive_by_attia/" title="Outlive, by Peter Attia">Outlive</a>:</p>
<p><img alt="in Outlive" src="outlive.png"></p>
<p>What a remarkably horizontal white line! It supports Attia's position,
in that he's arguing that we need to invest more in fighting other
causes of death (heart disease, cancer, dementia, diabetes) so he's
trying to make them seem like big unsolved problems. And certainly,
they are big unsolved problems. But the claim that mortality rates
haven't been improving is misleading.</p>
<p>Let's first go to the graph in
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rise_and_Fall_of_American_Growth" title="The Rise and Fall of American Growth, by Robert J. Gordon">The Rise and Fall of American Growth</a>:</p>
<p><img alt="in The Rise and Fall of American Growth" src="growth.png"></p>
<p>Attia copied this graph fairly exactly, except for adding "top" before
and removing the asterisk after "diseases," which is just as well
since the asterisk doesn't seem to have an explanation in <em>Growth</em>
anyway.</p>
<p>Such a horizontal white line! Here, it supports Gordon's position, in
that he's arguing that things were getting better in the US from
1870-1970, but things aren't getting better so much any more. So
here's a decrease that stops decreasing by 1970.</p>
<p>The biggest problem with this presentation is that the data is not
age-adjusted, and as such it's sensitive to the distribution of ages
in the population. For example, with low death rates for people in
their early years, one way to lower the raw death rate is to arrange
for the birth of a lot of babies. The raw death rate doesn't tell us
much about anything in particular, and certainly isn't the "real"
death rate in any meaningful way. Let's compare with a <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data-visualization/mortality-trends/index.htm" title="Mortality Trends in the United States, 1900–2018">CDC graph</a>
that is age-adjusted:</p>
<p><img alt="CDC graph" src="cdc.png"></p>
<p>The green line is the age-adjusted death rate. It was 1,446 in 1950,
1,222.6 in 1970, and 723.6 in 2018. That's a 50% improvement from
1950, and a 41% improvement from 1970.</p>
<p>Adjusting for age is important, because for example, when people don't
die young, you get more old people. Baby booms and so on also matter.
The population pyramid looks different now than it did in 1900.
Compare the 1900 and 2000 shapes as presented in a
<a href="http://vis.stanford.edu/jheer/d3/pyramid/shift.html" title="U.S. Census Population Pyramid, 1850-2000">Stanford visualization</a>:</p>
<p><img alt="population pyramids" src="stanford.png"></p>
<p>Both the raw and age-adjusted overall death rates don't tell us
everything about what's happening at every age, so let's look at that.
Here are death rates for the oldest nine age buckets in
<a href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/annual-death-rate-by-age-group" title="Annual death rate by age group, United States, 2021">data from the Human Mortality Database</a> from 1933 to 2021, shown
with a <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1VjBsxGqajqBThla0JDQGSAnS2fXUeUTVBG95PD6pbE4/edit" title="age-band death rates over time">quick graph</a> I made.</p>
<p><img alt="death rates by age group" src="by_age_group.png"></p>
<p>Every age group is seeing decreasing death rates up until COVID-19
impacts 2020 numbers. I left out younger age bands to avoid crowding,
but those also show improvement, especially for the youngest.</p>
<p>For people 85-89, the death rate per 1,000 was 179.87 in 1950, and
154.77 in 1970. It was 103.14 in 2018. That's a 43% improvement since
1950, and 33% improvement from 1970. Even the COVID-19 spike takes us
back only to around the same levels as we saw in 2000.</p>
<p>Things have been improving. Improving since 1950, improving since
1970, improving since 2000 apart from COVID-19. It just isn't accurate
to suggest that death rates haven't been going down over these
periods. There's still room for improvement, but the real gains should
be celebrated, not ignored.</p>
<p>The question of whether life expectancies have leveled off or even
decreased over shorter, more recent periods is quite distinct from the
trend over these longer periods.</p>
<p>I attempted to <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/19kuO6mIAi-f3etXZtVNndLEqoGOHACjLvzokBCrYGqQ/edit" title="death rates from HSUS">replicate</a> Gordon's graph using the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historical_Statistics_of_the_United_States" title="Historical Statistics of the United States">HSUS</a> data.
He cites Ab929-943, which includes ten columns of infectious disease
death, by my count. He uses Ab952 for the total death rate, I believe.</p>
<p>It adds only confusion that Gordon's figure is titled "Mortality Rate
<em>as Percentage of GNP</em>" (emphasis added). He also cites HSUS series
Bd46 (percentage of GNP spent on health care from 1929 to 1997) and
2012 SAUS table 134 (health care spending). This seems to be a
leftover of an idea from an earlier paper. Gordon's footnote 22 says
that his figure "is an update of McKinlay and McKinlay (1977, figure
3, p. 416)" so let's track that down.</p>
<p>The paper is
<a href="https://www.milbank.org/wp-content/uploads/mq/volume-55/issue-03/55-3-The-Questionable-Contribution-of-Medical-Measures-to-the-Decline-of-Mortality-in-the-United-States-in-the-Twentieth-Century.pdf">The Questionable Contribution of Medical Measures to the Decline of Mortality in the United States in the Twentieth Century</a>.
It has this Figure 3:</p>
<p><img alt="Figure 3" src="figure3.png"></p>
<p>There is no horizontal white line here. The presentation is quite
different, arguably better for showing the decrease in death from
infectious disease. McKinlay and McKinlay seem to have known to use
age-adjusted statistics as well. More relevant to the discussion of
GNP, however, their paper has this Figure 2:</p>
<p><img alt="Figure 2" src="figure2.png"></p>
<p>The point it's making is that increased spending on health care
doesn't seem to be driving a lot of increased reduction in death rate.
There's something to this argument, but 50 years later we can also see
(in the CDC graph above) that the period roughly 1955-1965 was a
fairly flat spot on the death rate graph, with improvement continuing
after it.</p>
<p>Gordon mentions the concern that spending on health care isn't
delivering matching results in death rate improvement, but it doesn't
make it into his figure apart from the title and data citations.</p>
<p>The horizontal white line is basically a coincidence as death has been
shifting from younger to older people over time and the population
pyramid has been changing shape. This graph is misleading.</p>
<p><img alt="warning" src="warning.png"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240407-mortality_rates_have_improved/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240407-mortality_rates_have_improved/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Homo Deus, by Harari</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>It feels like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yuval_Noah_Harari" title="Yuval Noah Harari">Harari</a> got the advance for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homo_Deus:_A_Brief_History_of_Tomorrow" title="Homo Deus: A Brief History of Tomorrow">Homo Deus</a> before
really thinking it through. It's rambling, over-long, without cohesive
thesis, and like a time capsule of science and tech news from 2014:
Big Data! Watson! Quantified Self! Mild <a href="/20191108-accelerando_by_stross/" title="Accelerando, by Stross">Accelerando</a> flavor. I wish
I'd read the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yuval_Noah_Harari#Critical_reception">Critical Reception</a> section from Harari's Wikipedia
entry and skipped this book.</p>
<p>My biggest gripe is probably that Harari argues (at length) that
animals have consciousness, and that animals are algorithms, and then
also claims without a second thought that algorithms implemented via
computer have no consciousness.</p>
<p>Harari also makes the fairly common error of scientific
exceptionalism: the belief that scientific ways of knowing are
fundamentally distinct from all others. For the number of words he
releases on related topics, this is frustrating.</p>
<p>Harari does say some reasonable things. I think he's correct in
pointing out limitations in our understanding of consciousness. (I
think this is such an interesting topic I wrote a <a href="/20230325-conversion_of_guelph_energy_to_mass/" title="Conversion of Guelph energy to mass (p=0.049)">short story</a>
about it.)</p>
<p>I also like Harari's phrasing around learning history in order to be
liberated from it. But throughout the book, the moments of lucidity
make the languid and ludicrous majority that much more unbearable.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240331-homo_deus_by_harari/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240331-homo_deus_by_harari/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Lifespan, by Sinclair</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I heard about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lifespan:_Why_We_Age_%E2%80%93_and_Why_We_Don%27t_Have_To" title="Lifespan: Why We Age – and Why We Don't Have To">this book</a> from a neighbor after I was talking about
<a href="/20240128-outlive_by_attia/" title="(Audio) Outlive, by Attia">Outlive</a>. Compared to Attia, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_A._Sinclair" title="David A. Sinclair">Sinclair</a> is more academic, not as
into protein (especially animal protein), and more extreme in his
claims that aging is a curable disease explained by his "Information
Theory" of epigenetic aging. Sinclair takes metformin, resveratrol,
and NMN. (After the book he started taking rapamycin as well, based on
a YouTube interview.) The book is longer than it needs to be to cover
the topics of Sinclair's expertise. The audio book has little
interludes between Sinclair and his writer, which is sort of a fun
idea but I'm not sure it added much.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.png"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240319-lifespan_by_sinclair/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240319-lifespan_by_sinclair/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) The Body, by Bryson</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Bryson's intonation is a little like Werner Herzog's. His book on the
body is charmingly, gently amusing. It's a selection of fun facts and
good advice: exercise more, eat less, maybe get some more vitamin D
and choline. One reference is Haldane's 1926
<a href="https://www.phys.ufl.edu/courses/phy3221/spring10/HaldaneRightSize.pdf">On Being the Right Size</a>, which has a similar sense of humor.
Bryson has a good time, and so does the reader (or listener).</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240303-the_body_by_bryson/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240303-the_body_by_bryson/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) The Comfort Crisis, by Easter</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Built from Men's Health articles, Easter's book gathers tales of his
hunting trips with the bros. Sometimes there are scientific and
philosophical digressions. I liked how the chapter about death came at
the moment between shooting and killing the wild reindeer.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<p>Easter talks about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B._J._Fogg" title="B. J. Fogg">Fogg</a> Behavior Model (action requires
Motivation, Ability, and a Prompt) and suggests that scrolling on your
phone all the time is a bad idea. Okay. He also suggests that audible
white noise is caused by EM radiation in air. I struggle to find a
reasonable interpretation that makes this true. There's also a good
deal of "people used to do this long ago, therefore it's a good idea,"
which isn't necessarily wrong, but it's too easy to ignore whether
there's a good argument beyond the appeal to nature.</p>
<p>The thesis is basically that we should get off the couch, eat
healthier, and challenge ourselves. I agree, basically. I'm now
listening to Rushkoff's Survival of the Richest, which has some advice
which is similar in effect: Focus on the real world rather than
disappearing into a technologically mediated isolation pod. Rushkoff
gets there by a different path, and from his mouth it sounds like a
call to a pro-social future. From Easter, it sounds like rugged
individualism for reclaiming masculinity.</p>
<p>We're very lucky to be able to choose our level of difficulty, when we
can.</p>
<p><a href="https://webcomicname.com/"><img alt="comic" src="comic.png"></a></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240211-comfort_crisis_by_easter/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240211-comfort_crisis_by_easter/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Outlive, by Attia</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I was already thinking about improving my health, then my last
grandparent died, and this book was recommended in Spotify and by a
friend. It was gratifying to listen to while running because <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/">Attia</a>
kept saying how good exercise is.</p>
<p>He's a little bit of a tech bro. He talks about how he mellowed and
started taking one (1) day off per week. And is he responsible for the
popularity of <a href="https://www.goruck.com/pages/what-is-rucking">rucking</a>? He used to be very into <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ketogenic_diet">keto</a> and
fasting. He still seems to be a little quick to assume causation. But
still: Who doesn't want more healthspan?</p>
<ul>
<li>Recommendations<ul>
<li>Exercise<ul>
<li>"Zone 2" sustained cardio</li>
<li>Intense cardio for improving VO2-max</li>
<li>Strength (with weights)</li>
<li>Stability (core, <a href="https://www.posturalrestoration.com/">posture</a>, flexitility...)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Diet<ul>
<li>A lot of protein and fiber</li>
<li>Avoid too much other stuff</li>
<li>Keep bad cholesterol (LDL, but he prefers measuring
   <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apolipoprotein_B">ApoB</a>) <em>very</em> low (usual guideline is under 100; he says
   under 20)<ul>
<li>Maybe use statins and/or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metformin">metformin</a> etc.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Minimal to no alcohol</li>
<li><em>Don't get diabetes</em></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Get lots of tests done, screen early for cancer, etc.</li>
<li>Sleep (lots of good)</li>
<li>Emotional health (good)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sirolimus">Rapamycin</a> taken once a week<ul>
<li>You can get this from <a href="https://agelessrx.com/">AgeLessRx</a> or <a href="https://gethealthspan.com/">HealthSpan</a>, for
   example.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Anchor phrases<ul>
<li>Medicine 3.0: Where 1.0 was witchcraft/superstition, 2.0 is
   scientific "treat the disease" modern medicine, and 3.0 is his
   style of life-long health improvement to avoid diseases of
   aging etc. (Attia's practice is called "Early.")</li>
<li>The Four Horsemen<ul>
<li>Heart disease, stroke, etc.</li>
<li>Cancer</li>
<li>Dementia etc.</li>
<li>Diabetes and friends ("metabolic disfunction") which he
   says is related to the other three</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The Centenarian Decathlon: Work toward being able to do things
   when you're really old; overprepare because you will age.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Oh also he talks a little bit about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mendelian_randomization">Mendelian randomization</a>, which
it turns out is just using genetics as an <a href="/20210430-a_simple_instrumental_variable/">instrumental variable</a>.
Also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bradford_Hill_criteria">Bradford Hill criteria</a> for causation. Neat!</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240128-outlive_by_attia/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240128-outlive_by_attia/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fundamentals: Ten Keys to Reality, by Wilczek</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I liked <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank_Wilczek" title="Wikipedia: Frank Wilczek">Wilczek</a> on <a href="/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/" title="The Strangest Man, by Farmelo">Dirac</a> in <a href="/20231119-it_must_be_beautiful/" title="It must be beautiful, edited by Farmelo">It must be beautiful</a>, and I
like him a lot <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fundamentals:_Ten_Keys_to_Reality" title="Wikipedia: Fundamentals: Ten Keys to Reality">here</a>! This is Nobel-prize-winning <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_chromodynamics" title="Wikipedia: Quantum chromodynamics">QCD</a> and also
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_crystal" title="Wikipedia: Time crystal">time crystal</a> guy. Just a beautiful intro to modern particle
physics, scientific perspective, an an optimism for open-ended future
development across all scientific disciplines that reminds me of
<a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/" title="The Beginning of Infinity, by Deutsch">The Beginning of Infinity</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Fundamentals</em> is meant, as well, to offer an alternative to
traditional religious fundamentalism. It takes up some of the same
basic questions, but addresses them by consulting physical reality,
rather than texts or traditions. (page xiii)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Of course, consulting physical reality is its own tradition...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The method of Kepler, Galileo, and Newton combines the humble
discipline of respecting the facts and learning from Nature with the
systematic chutzpah of using what you think you've learned
aggressively, applying it everywhere you can, even in situations
that go beyond your original evidence. If it works, then you've
discovered something useful; if it doesn't, then you've learned
something important. I've called that attitude Radical Conservatism,
and to me it's the essential innovation of the Scientific
Revolution. (pages 4-5)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't know if he has priority, but I'm pretty sure Wilczek's sense
of Radical Conservatism isn't the most common...</p>
<p>See also <a href="/20170825-characteristics_of_good_theories/">Characteristics of good theories</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Ptolemy's [geocentric] synthesis was a magnificent achievement, but
it had two shortcomings. One was its complexity and, related to
this, its ugliness. In particular, the recipes it used to calculate
planetary motions brought in many numbers that were determined
purely by fitting the calculations to observations, without deeper
guiding principles connecting them. Copernicus (1473-1543) noticed
that the values of some of those numbers were related to one another
in surprisingly simple ways. These otherwise mysterious,
"coincidental" relationships could be explained geometrically, if
one assumed that Earth together with Venus, Mars, Jupiter, and
Saturn all revolve around the Sun as center (and the Moon further
revolves around Earth). (page 6)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't think I'd heard quite this explanation before... In light of
"end of science" arguments that big data pushes us more toward
"numbers ... determined purely by fitting the calculations to
observations" this Ptolemaic narrative could almost fit into a kind of
"we were once less wise in our theory, and now we become less wise
again" story.</p>
<p>Wilczek goes on to briefly cover how Kepler's work made the system
still simpler and better-working. Have we simplified everything as
much as it can be? Could we do better?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But Galileo aspired to a different kind of understanding. He wanted
to understand <em>something</em> precisely, rather than <em>everything</em>
vaguely. (page 7)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Finding the right questions, etc. etc.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>A more recent quotation from John R. Pierce, a pioneer of modern
information science, beautifully captures the contrast between the
modern concept of scientific understanding and all other approaches:
"We require that our theories harmonize in detail with the very wide
range of phenomena they seek to explain. And we insist that they
provide us with useful guidance rather than with rationalizations."
(page 9)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This reminds me of <a href="/20170825-characteristics_of_good_theories/">Characteristics of good theories</a>.</p>
<p>Also, this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_R._Pierce" title="Wikipedia: John R. Pierce">Pierce</a> character came up a bunch in <a href="/20231231-myth_of_ai_by_larson/" title="The myth of artificial intelligence, by Larson">Larson's book</a>
as well. (But this book is much, much better.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Unlike the situation for stars or planets, which almost invariably
are separated from their neighbors by distances many times their own
size, the typical separation between galaxies is not vastly larger
than the galaxies themselves. (page 27)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Huh! Neat.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The Roman philosopher Seneca expressed the opposite of this thought
[that human life is short] in "On the Shortness of Life." "Why do we
complain about nature?" he writes. "It has acted generously; life,
if you know how to use it, is long." (pages 43-44)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Oh interesting! It seems like <a href="/20201107-how_to_live_on_24_hours_a_day/" title="How to Live on 24 Hours a Day, by Bennett">Bennett</a> didn't know (or at least
didn't reference) Seneca's <a href="https://archive.org/stream/SenecaOnTheShortnessOfLife/Seneca+on+the+Shortness+of+Life_djvu.txt" title="Full text of 'Seneca On The Shortness Of Life'">work</a> in his How to Live on 24 Hours a
Day.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li><em>The basic laws describe change.</em> It is useful to separate the
   description of the world into two parts: states and laws. States
   describe "what there is," while laws describe "how things
   change."</li>
<li><em>The basic laws are universal.</em> That is, the basic laws hold
   everywhere, and for all times.</li>
<li><em>The basic laws are local.</em> That is, the behavior of an object in
   the immediate future depends only on current conditions in its
   immediate vicinity. The standard scientific jargon for this
   principle is <em>locality.</em></li>
<li><em>The basic laws are precise.</em> The laws are precise, and they
   admit no exceptions. Thus, they can be formulated as mathematical
   equations. (pages 64-65)</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Locality over reality.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Fields, rather than particles, are the fundamental building blocks
of matter in modern physics. (page 67)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Wilczek identifies "Mass" and "Charge" and "Spin" as the only three
basic, primary properties of matter. (page 73)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>(There's an interesting mathematical reason why physicists call the
basic unit of angular momentum spin 1/2, rather than spin 1, but it
is beyond the scope of this book.) (page 75)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It seems like this is related to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spin%E2%80%93statistics_theorem">spin–statistics theorem</a> or
something? But come on, Wilczek, you big tease...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Contrary to Democritus, though, our modern basic ingredients don't
have hooks. They aren't even solid bodies. Indeed, thought it's
convenient to call them "elementary particles," they aren't really
particles. (That is, they have little in common with what the word
"particle" suggests.) Our modern fundamental ingredients have no
intrinsic size or shape. If we insist on visualizing them, we should
think of structureless points where concentrations of mass, charge,
and spin reside. We have, in places of "atoms and the void,"
space-time and properties. (page 77)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Democritus was the early atomic theory guy.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>By being first, Franklin got to choose which kind of charge to call
positive and which negative. He chose to call the charge that
accumulates on glass, after it is rubbed with silk, positive. This
was long before people knew about electrons. Unfortunately, it turns
out that according to Franklin's choice the electron's charge is
negative. It's much too late to undo that choice, since it has
seeped into thousands of books, papers, and circuit diagrams.
Therefore, we list the electron's charge as -1. (pages 81-82)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Benjamin Franklin.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Once you get to thinking about materials as homes to quasiparticles,
a profound question is not far off: Can we consider "empty space"
itself to be a material, whose quasiparticles are our "elementary
particles"? We can, and we should. It is a very fruitful line of
thought, as you'll see in later chapters. (page 90)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I'm not sure that last promise was ever paid off very well...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>John Wheeler, the poet of relativity, summed it up this way:
"Space-time tells matter how to move; matter tells space-time how to
bend." (page 117)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is that really a good way to sum up? It reminds me of the
stretched-sheet-of-rubber image, which I think is not so good...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The Future of Comprehension (page 119)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I just thought this was a cool section heading.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>You should not fail to notice that 500 trillion is a great deal
larger than 25, or even 95. (page 127)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Cute!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>H. G. Wells caught the spirit of thermal equilibrium memorably: "If
anything is possible, then nothing is interesting." (page 151)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>How the Universe got Interesting (page 161)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another fun heading.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There are several kinds of anomalous color perception, misnamed
"color blindness," that are not terribly rare. Around 95 percent of
humans have similar color vision, based on three types of cone cells
that vary little between individuals. There are theoretical reasons,
based on genetics, to believe that a significant fraction of humans,
specifically mothers and full sisters of males with the most common
color anomaly, have four kinds of cone cells. These "tetrachromats"
might have super-normal color vision. But as far as I know, direct
evidence for this is surprisingly rare. (page 170)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetrachromacy">Huh!</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Let's recall that John Wheeler, the poet of general relativity,
summed it up this way: "Space-time tells matter how to move; matter
tells space-time how to bend." Wheeler's summary is catchy, but it
is misleading, or at least incomplete, whithout this important
addition: <em>Space-time is a form of matter, too.</em> (page 178)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Although we understand <em>a lot</em> about how the world works, there are
still big mysteries. These three great questions came up earlier:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>What triggered the big bang? Could it happen again?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Are there meaningful patterns hidden in the apparent sprawl of
  fundamental particles and forces?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>How, concretely, does mind emerge from matter? (Or does it?) (page
  187)</p>
</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>On page 190, he uses "rock bottom" to refer to that final point in
explanation beyond which there is no further "why?" I think it's a
good thing to remember, that we can't avoid having such a rock bottom.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Dark energy" is another theoretically motivated modification to the
law of gravity, also considered by Einstein. He called it by a
different name: the cosmological constant. (page 195)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>There is immense satisfaction in describing the world in terms of
its most elementary building blocks. It is tempting to say that this
is the ideal description, while other, high-level descriptions are
mere approximations—compromises, which reflect weakness in
understanding. That attitude, which makes the perfect the enemy of
the good, is superficially deep, but deeply superficial.</p>
<p>In order to answer questions of interest, we often need to change
focus. To discover—or invent—new concepts, and new ways of working
with them, is an open-ended, creative activity. Computer scientists
and software engineers are well aware that in designing useful
algorithms, it is important to pay attention to how knowledge is
represented. A good representation can make the difference between
usable knowledge and knowledge that is there "in principle" but not
really available, because it takes too long and too much trouble to
locate and process. It's like the difference between owning bars of
gold and knowing that in principle there are vast stores of gold
atoms floating dissolved in the ocean.</p>
<p>For that reason, complete understanding of the fundamental laws, if
we ever achieved it, would be neither "the Theory of Everything" nor
"the End of Science." (Those are two phrases, endemic in popular
science journalism, that I find extremely irritating.) We would
still need complementary descriptions of reality. There would still
be plenty of great questions left unanswered, and plenty of great
scientific work left to do.</p>
<p>There always will be. (pages 215-216)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is just the conclusion of a longer section on this topic, which I
like quite a lot. It reminds me of Deutsch's
<a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/">Beginning of Infinity</a>.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Do people have choice in what they do, or are they puppets who dance
to the tune of mathematical physics? That is a bad question, not
unlike asking whether music is harmony or melody. (page 218)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>...what the great biologist Francis Crick has called "the
astonishing hypothesis": that mind, in all its aspects, is "no more
than the behavior of a vast assembly of nerve cells and their
associated molecules." (pages 225-226)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>... there are three different kinds [sic] color charge, and eight
different kinds of gluons that respond to them. (page 234)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What? This seems cool and fun.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Now we come to a group of elementary particles nobody really knows
what to make of. The bonus particles are all unstable. They were
discovered among the debris of high-energy collisions, either in
cosmic rays (early in the twentieth century) or at parcle
accelerators (more recently). When the first of them, the muon, was
discovered in 1936, the renowned physicist I. I. Rabi captured the
community's bewilderment in a quip that's become legendary: "Who
ordered that?" (page 236)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>These are the charm, top, strange, and bottom quark, together with the
muon and tauon.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The website of the Particle Data Group is http://pdg.lbl.gov. (page 238)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Nice!</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240114-fundamentals_by_wilczek/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240114-fundamentals_by_wilczek/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>(Audio) Hidden Potential, by Grant</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Spotify has audiobooks now! Fifteen hours per month before charging
more. So I listened to <a href="https://adamgrant.net/book/hidden-potential/">Hidden Potential</a> while running. It was a
fun, inspiring listen. Everyone can be great!</p>
<p>I don't take many notes on audiobooks, but one study caught my ear:
<a href="https://www.sesp.northwestern.edu/docs/publications/142575725559b6ba6c4706e.pdf">Are tenure track professors better teachers?</a> Grant presented it as
saying that less experienced professors were better teachers, but that
isn't quite right; it's comparing tenure track professors to teaching
adjuncts. Also, it says the bad performance of tenure track folks is
because roughly a quarter of them were particularly bad, not that all
of them were bad. Neat study, anyway.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240113-audio_hidden_potential_grant/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240113-audio_hidden_potential_grant/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Seneca's De Brevitate Vitae</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I guess it's just an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_Brevitate_Vitae_(Seneca)" title="Wikipedia: De Brevitate Vitae (Seneca)">essay</a>, but I spent a dollar and highlighted a
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B084QKS7PG/" title="Amazon: On the Shortness of Life Kindle Edition">Kindle version</a> of On the Shortness of Life, so I'm probably making
the most of mine. It's a little bit like a much earlier version of
<a href="/20201107-how_to_live_on_24_hours_a_day/" title="How to Live on 24 Hours a Day, by Bennett">How to Live on 24 Hours a Day</a>, except that it's quite specific in
what you <em>should</em> be doing with your life: philosophy. Okay, senator.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Of all men they alone are at leisure who take time for philosophy,
they alone really live; for they are not content to be good
guardians of their own lifetime only.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>It is not that we have a short space of time, but that we waste much
of it.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>the life we receive is not short, but we make it so,</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Everyone hurries his life on and suffers from a yearning for the
future and a weariness of the present.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Men trifle with the most precious thing in the world; but they are
blind to it because it is an incorporeal thing, because it does not
come beneath the sight of the eyes, and for this reason it is
counted a very cheap thing—nay, of almost no value at all.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>busy men find life very short.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>so enfeebled are they by the excessive lassitude of a pampered mind
that they cannot find out by themselves whether they are hungry!</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>it seems the part of a man who is very lowly and despicable to know
what he is doing.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>They annex every age to their own; all the years that have gone
before them are an addition to their store.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Has some time passed by? This he embraces by recollection. Is time
present? This he uses. Is it still to come? This he anticipates. He
makes his life long by combining all times into one.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>They lose the day in expectation of the night, and the night in fear
of the dawn.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Reasons for anxiety will never be lacking, whether born of
prosperity or of wretchedness; life pushes on in a succession of
engrossments. We shall always pray for leisure, but never enjoy it.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>knowledge of their disease has caused the death of many.</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20240105-seneca_de_brevitate_vitae/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20240105-seneca_de_brevitate_vitae/</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The myth of artificial intelligence, by Larson</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The relevant point in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erik_J._Larson" title="Wikipedia: Erik J. Larson">Larson</a>'s <a href="https://www.hup.harvard.edu/books/9780674278660" title="The Myth of Artificial Intelligence: Why Computers Can’t Think the Way We Do">book</a> is that advances in AI
shouldn't undermine human intellectual flourishing. We shouldn't hand
over all our thinking to machines. He explores the example of the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_Brain_Project" title="Wikipedia: Human Brain Project">Human Brain Project</a>, arguing convincingly that its "big data"
computational focus was not effective. While I think it isn't quite so
black and white (AI can be a useful tool) I also support human
learning, not just machine learning.</p>
<p>The book doesn't deliver on its subtitle, "Why computers can't think
the way we do." It doesn't even really argue for "can't," but only for
"don't, so far." Like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary_Marcus" title="Wikipedia: Gary Marcus">Marcus</a>, Larson is arguing that we need
something more than deep learning and other extant approaches.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The myth of artificial intelligence is that its arrival is
inevitable, and only a matter of time—that we have already embarked
on the path that will lead to human-level AI, and then
superintelligence. (page 1)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Larson's main argument is that current machine learning doesn't do
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abductive_reasoning" title="Wikipedia: Abductive reasoning">abduction</a>, and it should. This is close to Marcus arguing for
algebraic reasoning. It is even close to me, <a href="/20170429-from_behaviorist_to_constructivist_ai/" title="From Behaviorist to Constructivist AI">arguing</a> for going
from Behaviorist to Constructivist AI.</p>
<p>This book came out before ChatGPT, which is relevant in at least two
ways.</p>
<p>First, it's more possible now to take seriously the idea that neural
generative models might really be, eventually, enough for AGI; this is
roughly what Sutskever seems to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YEUclZdj_Sc" title="Youtube: Why next-token prediction is enough for AGI - Ilya Sutskever (OpenAI Chief Scientist)">say</a>. The human brain is a big mess
that somehow does smart-seeming things. A generative transformer is a
big mess that somehow does smart-seeming things. Maybe they can
achieve equivalent results? This is not a proof, but it might be a
plausibility argument.</p>
<p>Second, Larson spends a good deal of time on examples to show that
models weren't solving some problems very well, when he published.
Many of these examples haven't aged well for his argument, as models
now do better.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For instance (and ironically), Google Translate as of October 2020
still gets Bar-Hillel's 1960s example wrong. Bar-Hillel asked how to
program a machine to translate <em>The box is in the pen</em> correctly.
Here, <em>pen</em> is ambiguous. (page 202)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In December 2023, Google Translate still fails.</p>
<p><img alt="Google Translate" src="google_translate.png"></p>
<p>But ChatGPT <a href="https://chat.openai.com/share/b4dfff5f-413b-466c-af57-c0c4d64e2e7e">succeeds</a>, as far as I can tell.</p>
<p><img alt="ChatGPT translating" src="gpt_translate.png"></p>
<p>ChatGPT similarly has no problem with challenges like "Can a crocodile
run a steeplechase?" (page 196) (It even titles the <a href="https://chat.openai.com/share/97595ce1-03c3-4c99-bc52-942752615dbb">chat</a>,
"Crocodile Steeplechase: Not Feasible.") And where Larson wrote "Their
[AI's] performance on Winograd schemas is not much better than random
guessing," (page 197) his 2016 reference score of <a href="https://cs.nyu.edu/~davise/papers/WinogradSchemas/WS.html">58%</a> has been
improved as of 2022 to <a href="https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/wsc">90%</a> (or higher).</p>
<p>Whether or not AGI will require explicit architectural support for
abduction (or symbolic reasoning, etc.) the performance limits of
current approaches are not entirely clear.</p>
<p>Really I wish Larson was a better spokesperson for ideas I agree with.
Supporting human learning is a good idea, I think (though Larson
unfortunately takes even this in strange hero-oriented directions).
Larson doesn't really address at all the point that LeCun sometimes
foregrounds, that current AI is hugely data-inefficient (it requires
tons of data) which could actually point to future directions for AI.
I can't endorse this book.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Data science (the application of AI to “big data”) is at best a
prosthetic for human ingenuity, which if used correctly can help us
deal with our modern “data deluge.” (page 4)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Somewhat routinely, Larson defines things strangely. Data science is
not the application of AI to “big data,” and foundational
misalignments like this make it hard for Larson to land arguments.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The Turing test is actually very difficult—no computer has ever
passed it. (page 10)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There are plenty of articles claiming that this or that passed the
Turing test, but it seems that
<a href="https://isturingtestpassed.github.io/">isturingtestpassed.github.io</a>
is correct: the answer is still no.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Turing's great genius, and his great error, was in thinking that
human intelligence reduces to problem-solving. (page 23)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There's a bunch of unclear language here. How is problem-solving
defined? What is excluded from that definition? What even is
intuition?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Turing and colleagues called it the “weight of evidence,” borrowing
a term coined by the American scientist and logician C. S. Peirce
(who is prominently featured in Part Two of this book). (page 24)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The "it" here has no clear referent, but as it happens I've been
interested in <a href="/20210917-weight_of_evidence_is_logistic_coefficients/" title="Weight of Evidence is logistic coefficients">weight of evidence</a> before, and it seems that this is
the same thing! How neat, to know it traces to Turing. One interesting
work of interpretation is Gillies' short <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/688010">paper</a>, "The Turing-Good
Weight of Evidence Function and Popper's Measure of the Severity of a
Test."</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Japan had invested millions in its high-profile
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fifth_Generation_Computer_Systems" title="Fifth Generation Computer Systems">Fifth Generation project</a> aimed at achieving success in robotics,
and Japan too had failed, rather spectacularly. (page 55)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At a quick search, Larson seems to be the only person saying the Fifth
Generation project was principally interested in robotics.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Here, it's best to be clear: equating a mind with a computer is not
scientific, it's philosophical. (page 69)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Dan Gardner's excellent book <em>Future Babble</em> documents the success
rate of predictions in realms from history and geopolitics to the
sciences. He found that theorists—experts with big visions of the
future based on a particular theory they endorse—tend to make worse
predictions than pragmatic people, who see the world as complicated
and lacking a clear fit with any single theory. (page 69)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Werner Heisenberg discovered his uncertainty principle by working
out the consequences of the new physics of quanta. The principle
states that it is impossible to isolate the position and the
momentum of a subatomic particle simultaneously. This places
fundamental limits on our ability to predict the individual
movements of particles at the subatomic realm (because “seeing” the
position of a particle requires impinging it with a photon, which
also has the effect of knocking it off course). (page 72)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But it isn't "because" of that; this is a common misconception. Even
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncertainty_principle" title="Uncertainty principle">wikipedia</a> does better:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Historically, the uncertainty principle has been confused with a
related effect in physics, called the observer effect, which notes
that measurements of certain systems cannot be made without
affecting the system, that is, without changing something in a
system. Heisenberg used such an observer effect at the quantum level
(see below) as a physical "explanation" of quantum uncertainty. It
has since become clearer, however, that the uncertainty principle is
inherent in the properties of all wave-like systems, and that it
arises in quantum mechanics simply due to the matter wave nature of
all quantum objects.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Statistical AI ends up with a long-tail problem, where common
patterns (in the fat head of a distribution curve) are easy, but
rare ones (in the long tail) are hard. (page 128)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is true, and something of a missed opportunity to better tie into
the overall argument.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Calling such systems <em>learners</em> is ironic, because the meaning of
the word <em>learn</em> for humans essentially involves escaping narrow
performances to gain more general understanding of things in the
world. (page 141)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There's a good point in here somewhere on function approximation vs.
model-building; on interpolation vs. extrapolation.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Big data is an inevitable consequence of Moore's law: as computers
become more powerful, statistical techniques like machine learning
become better, and new business models emerge—all from data and its
analysis. (page 144)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I pulled this out just as an example of the kind of muddy reasoning
and poor use of language found throughout the book. This is the kind
of sort-of-but-are-you-sure-you-want-to-say-it-that-way output that
I'd expect from a language model.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Much inference in the real world is defeasible, that is, proven
wrong or incomplete by subsequent observation or learning (say, by
reading a book). (page 163)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Work on so-called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-monotonic_logic" title="Non-monotonic logic">non-monotonic</a> reasoning peaked in the 1980s
and 1990s, but has since been largely abandoned, in large part
because the extensions of deduction to make it more flexible for
language understanding work only on “toy” examples that aren't
useful in the real world. (page 167)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Many of the same researchers who worked on extending deduction in AI
to make it defeasible also worked out deductive-based approaches to
abduction in the 1980s and 1990s, notably with
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abductive_logic_programming" title="Abductive logic programming">abductive logic programming</a> (ALP). (page 168)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Page 172 has a breakdown like this:</p>
<ul>
<li>Deduction: A→B; A ∴ B</li>
<li>Induction: A; B ∴ A→B</li>
<li>Abduction: A→B; B ∴ A</li>
</ul>
<p>Nice to see compactly this way, I think...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The strategy of exposing supervised learning systems to foreseeable
exceptions, as is done with ongoing work on driverless cars, is a
Sisyphean undertaking, because exceptions by their very nature
cannot be completely foreseen. (pages 173-174)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(See the selection above from page 128.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>a once-prominent field in AI known as
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knowledge_representation_and_reasoning" title="Knowledge representation and reasoning">knowledge representation and reasoning</a> (KR&amp;R) (page 175)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>technically, entailment is stronger than material implication (page
176)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Poking around online, there are lots of people making claims about the
difference here, but it doesn't seem like everyone agrees... It seems
roughly like entailment is more causal, while implication can be
correlative.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>To abduce we must solve the selection problem among competing causes
or factors, and to solve this problem, we must somehow grasp what is
relevant in some situation or other. The problem is that no one has
a clue how to do this. (page 183)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>noetic, or knowledge-based. (page 185)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This does not seem to be the sense in which the word is typically used.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>What people mean is almost never a literal function of what they
word-for-word say. (page 206)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes... Though the world-knowledge bits of the book are the ones that
most fail in the face of LLMs.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cooperative_principle#Grice's_maxims">Grice's Maxims</a> (page 215)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Quantity, Quality, Relation, Manner</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Text_Retrieval_Conference">Text REtrieval Conferences</a> (page 221)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Writing about the experience
[of working on early computing machines] in 1887 in an oddly
prescient paper titled "Logical Machines," in the <em>American Journal
of Psychology,</em> Peirce begins characteristically with cautionary
comment. "In the 'Voyage to Laputa' there is a description of a
machine for evolving science automatically," he writes. "The
intention is to ridicule the Organon of Aristotle and the Organon of
Bacon by showing the absurdity of supposing any 'instrument' can do
the work of the mind." Peirce, the skeptic, no doubt appreciated the
wisdom of Swift's imagination. (page 232)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is <a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/829/829-h/829-h.htm#part03">Gulliver's Travels</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Every one knew how laborious the usual method is of attaining to
arts and sciences; whereas, by his contrivance, the most ignorant
person, at a reasonable charge, and with a little bodily labour,
might write books in philosophy, poetry, politics, laws,
mathematics, and theology, without the least assistance from genius
or study.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is there a better description of ChatGPT than as a contrivance by
which "the most ignorant person, at a reasonable charge, and with a
little bodily labour, might write books in philosophy, poetry,
politics, laws, mathematics, and theology, without the least
assistance from genius or study"?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>He assured me “that this invention had employed all his thoughts
from his youth; that he had emptied the whole vocabulary into his
frame, and made the strictest computation of the general proportion
there is in books between the numbers of particles, nouns, and
verbs, and other parts of speech.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A very early statistical NLP! And with a charming illustration:</p>
<p><img alt="the frame" src="theframe.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>For scientists don't believe in vagaries like the "evolution of
science" except as frosting, as backdrop. They really believe in
scientific genius. They really are all possessed by Prometheus, by
what innovators can dream and achieve. (page 239)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is quite the generalization... Maybe you're not a real scientist
if you don't go in for a Great Man theory of science? Maybe the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ortega_hypothesis">Ortega hypothesis</a> is for the weak?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>principles linking neurons together into circuits and larger
functional units (mesa circuits) (page 250)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don't find a lot of support for "mesa circuits" as a term people
use...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>we are actively attempting to cover up a key deficiency—a lack of
flourishing human culture—with rhetoric about the inevitable rise of
machines. (page 277)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>The problem of inference, like the problem of consciousness, is
entrenched at the center of ongoing grand mysteries, and is really
presupposed in our understanding of everything else. We should not
be surprised that the undiscovered mind resists technological
answers. It's possible that, as Horgan worried, we're out of ideas.
If so, the myth represents our final, unrecoverable turn away from
human possibility—a darkly comforting fairy tale, a pretense that
out of our ashes something else, something great and alive, must
surely and inevitably arise.</p>
<p>If we're <em>not</em> out of ideas, then we must do the hard and deliberate
work of reinvesting in a culture of invention and human flourishing.
For we will need our own general intelligence to find paths to the
future, and a future better than the past. (pages 280-281)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is interesting material.</p>
<p>I think a lot of "AI isn't as good as people" reduces to how we feel
about consciousness. You can't prove consciousness by behaviors or any
other observable. So do we extend our belief in consciousness to
machines?</p>
<p>On whether we're out of ideas, I like the arguments of <a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/" title="The Beginning of Infinity, by Deutsch">Deutsch</a> and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank_Wilczek" title="Wikipedia: Frank Wilczek">Wilczek</a>, which suggest that we're not.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20231231-myth_of_ai_by_larson/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20231231-myth_of_ai_by_larson/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Social Security is a great deal</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Social Security in its current form pays out, with no volatility, a
perpetual inflation-adjusted annual yield of up to 51% on what
individuals pay in tax. 15% is common, and 5% is the worst you can
get.</p>
<p>I know it's not really an individual investment; younger Americans are
supposed to be supporting older ones and so on. But I had no idea how
good Social Security is for recipients, relative to how much they put
in.</p>
<p>Social Security pays out a percentage of your income. In monthly
terms, it's 90% of up to $1,115/month, then 32% up to $6,721/month,
then 15% up to $13,350/month. These are 2023 dollars and give the
maximum full retirement age monthly payment of $3,792.</p>
<p>Full retirement age for me is 67. If I start collecting Social
Security early, at 62, payments are locked in at 70% of the “full”
value. If instead I delay until 70, payments are 124%.</p>
<p>Social Security is based on inflation-adjusted income over your 35
highest-earning years. (If you're working your 36th year and earning
no more than any other year, this calculation won't apply.)</p>
<p>The last factor we need is the 6.2% tax you pay in to Social Security.
Your employer also separately pays as much, but most people don't
consider that part of their income.</p>
<p>So the best “return” you can get is if you have lifetime earnings so
far under $468,300 and you plan to start collecting Social Security as
late as possible:</p>
<pre><code>0.9 * 1.24 / 35 / 0.062  # 51.4%</code></pre>

<p>The worst non-zero return you can get is if your lifetime Social
Security earnings are already over $2.8M and you plan to collect
Social Security as soon as possible.</p>
<pre><code>0.15 * 0.7 / 35 / 0.062  # 4.8%</code></pre>

<p>A conservative mid-career value is likely about 15%.</p>
<pre><code>0.32 * 1.0 / 35 / 0.062  # 14.7%</code></pre>

<p>Social Security adjusts for inflation, so these are all returns <em>over</em>
inflation. I just can't think of anything that gets returns like this.</p>
<p>You get the same return on your last year's contribution before
collecting, so comparative investments can't really be allowed <em>any</em>
time for compounding. Still, most contributions will sit for some time
before the contributor starts collecting, so a full comparison could
be more complicated and depend on age at contribution etc.</p>
<p>Social Security is less flexible than an investing account. But is
there <em>anything</em> that comes close to delivering what Social Security
does, for someone contributing at 60 who lives to be 90, say?</p>
<hr>
<p>The calculations above may seem opaque. I simplified a little,
dropping things that cancel out. More explicitly:</p>
<pre><code class="language-r">($100 new income this year / 35 years considered)
 * 90% income replacement factor
 * 1.24 late start factor
 = annual Social Security benefit from income
-------------------------------------------------------
($100 new income this year * 6.2% tax = tax paid on income)</code></pre>

<p>I rearranged terms a little, and I'm still leaving out conversion
to/from monthly basis which is just a distraction.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20231202-social_security_is_a_great_deal/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20231202-social_security_is_a_great_deal/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>It must be beautiful, edited by Farmelo</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This is a nice collection of essays about some beautiful equations,
edited by the author of <a href="/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/" title="The Strangest Man, by Farmelo">a biography of Dirac</a>. Not every equation
is fully explained, but there's great history and big-picture
explanation. The authors are frequently major contributors to the
fields.</p>
<ol>
<li>The Planck-Einstein Equation for the Energy of a Quantum: \( E = hf\)</li>
<li>The Logistic Map: \( x_{next} = a x_{initial} (1 - x_{initial}) \)</li>
<li>The Drake Equation: \( N = R^* \cdot f_p \cdot n_e \cdot f_l \cdot f_i \cdot f_c \cdot L \)</li>
<li>\( E = m c^2 \)</li>
<li>The Molina-Rowland Chemical Equations<ul>
<li>\( CFCl_3 \rightarrow CFCl_2 + Cl \)</li>
<li>\( Cl + O_3 \rightarrow ClO + O_2 \)</li>
<li>\( ClO + O \rightarrow Cl + O_2\)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Schrödinger's Wave Equation: \( \hat{H} \psi = E \psi \)</li>
<li>The Dirac Equation: \( \left[ \gamma^\mu \left( i \frac{\partial}{\partial x^\mu} - e A_\mu (x) \right) + m \right] \psi (x) = 0 \)</li>
<li>Evolutionarily Stable Strategy: \( E(S, S) &gt; E(T, S) \)</li>
<li>The Einstein Equation of General Relativity: \( R_{ab} - \frac{1}{2}Rg_{ab} = -8\pi G T_{ab} \)</li>
<li>Shannon's Equations<ul>
<li>\( I = -p \log_2 p \)</li>
<li>\( C = W \log_2 (1 + S/N) \)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The Yang-Mills Equation: \( \partial \mathbf{f}_{μν} / \partial x_ν + 2 \varepsilon (\mathbf{b}_ν \cdot \mathbf{f}_{μν}) + \mathbf{J}_μ = 0 \)</li>
</ol>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It was in large part thanks to this [logistic map] equation, one so
simple that children can study it at school, that scientists in the
1970s came to see that some equations that appear to predict the
future in terms of the past are completely unable to make such
predictions, contrary to what most scientists had thought." (page
xvii)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Maybe children <em>should</em> study it at school, if they're not,
currently...</p>
<p>See also: <a href="/20200714-foundation_trilogy/" title="Asimov's Foundation trilogy">psychohistory</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The [wave-particle] problem's resolution came in the late 1920s,
when physicists developed quantum theory into what became known as
quantum field theory, which made possible a unified description of
radiation and matter." (page 24)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2021/04/09/period-three-implies-chaos/" title="explainer">Period three implies chaos</a> is one of the best paper names of all
time.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Avoiding detailed assumptions about this or that feature of the way
particular objects were built or interacted, Einstein's theory
hardly resembled the work of senior physicists of the time. Instead,
it had an outsider's style—or perhaps a return to an older form of
clarity." (page 75)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The sense of aesthetics that Shcrödinger alludes to here is his
preference for a mathematics that is more familiar and also not as
ugly as Heisenberg's 'transcendental algebra' (or matrices), but
which also permits visualizability of atomic processes." (page 117)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Transcendental algebra?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In the pantheon of twentieth-century physics, Heisenberg is second
only to Einstein." (page 129)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Feel like somebody told me that was <a href="/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/" title="The Strangest Man, by Farmelo">Dirac</a>...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As the physicist who did more to delve into the foundations of
quantum theory than anyone else since Bohr, Einstein and Heisenberg,
John Bell, once put it, 'for all practical purposes' quantum
mechanics works well. He forcefully reminded us, however, that we
still do not fully understand the Schrödinger equation." (page 131)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The citation here is <a href="https://www.informationphilosopher.com/solutions/scientists/bell/Against_Measurement.pdf">Against 'measurement'</a>, which is straight FIRE.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Is it really possible, by logical processing or calculation, to
arrive at essentially new insights—to get out more than you put in?</p>
<p>"This question is especially timely today, since it lies at the
heart of debates regarding the nature of machine
intelligence—whether it may develop into a species of mind on a par
with human intelligence, or even its eventual superior." (pages
155-156)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This was in <em>2002.</em></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"They [Dirac, Maxwell, Einstein] proceed by <em>experimental logic.</em>
That concept is an oxymoron only on the surface. In experimental
logic, one formulates hypotheses in equations, and experiments with
those equations. That is, one tries to improve the equations from
the point of view of beauty and consistency, and then checks whether
the 'improved' equations elucidate some feature of nature.
Mathematicians recognize the technique of 'proof by contradiction':
to prove <em>A,</em> you assume the opposite of <em>A,</em> and reach a
contradiction. Experimental logic is 'validation by fruitfulness':
to validate <em>A,</em> assume it, and show that it leads to fruitful
consequences. Relative to routine deductive logic, experimental
logic abides by the Jesuit credo: 'It is more blessed to ask
forgiveness than permission.'" (page 159)</p>
<p>"Creative mathematics and physics rely not on perfect logic, but
rather on an experimental logic. Experimental logic involves
noticing patterns, playing with them, making assumptions to explain
them, and—especially—recognizing beauty."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Abduction? With guess-and-check? And aesthetics?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As the anthropologists Robert Boyd and Peter Richerson once
remarked, ‘To replace a world you do not understand by a model of
the world you do not understand is no advance.’" (page 165)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There are questions that are too hard to think about without the
aid of mathematics." (page 179)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In fact, in the four dimensions of space-time, there are <em>twenty</em>
independent components to the curvature, and these can be collected
together to describe a mathematical entity referred to as the
'Rieman curvature tensor'. (page 191)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In 1918, the young German mathematician Emmy Noether discovered a
deeply fundamental relationship between symmetry and the
conservation of physical quantities, such as electric charge. She
found that for every conserved quantity there is a related
symmetry—and vice versa." (page 236)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In an essay on 'Beauty and theoretical physics,' Yang quotes
Heisenberg as saying in 1973, 'We will have to abandon the
philosophy of Democritus and the concept of elementary particles. We
should accept instead the concept of fundamental symmetries.'" (page
251)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Dirac has a paper called "Pretty mathematics."</p>
<hr>
<p>Something about the Einstein summation convention...</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20231119-it_must_be_beautiful/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20231119-it_must_be_beautiful/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fireside Chat / Pro Tips (with Codecademy)</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>My <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/minhzy/" title="Jonathan (Minhzy) Truong">friend</a> at Codecademy invited me to do a sort of AMA on my
career working with data, in an event that was variously promoted as a
“<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7108029659493138432/" title="We’re hosting a fireside chat with Meta Data Scientist Aaron Schumacher next Tuesday.">fireside chat</a>” and “<a href="https://community.codecademy.com/events/details/codecademy-official-community-events-presents-pro-tips-with-aaron-schumacher-meta/" title="Pro Tips with Aaron Schumacher, Meta">pro tips</a>.”</p>
<ul>
<li>I made some <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/19qy_rOaPYbEgF5ykJeA39a2XjgPVE4Tp2a_YvSc9hXQ/edit" title="Fireside Chat / Pro Tips">slides</a> to introduce myself and some recommendations.</li>
<li>It's <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8PCL5ogz7xM&amp;ab_channel=Codecademy" title="Pro Tips with Aaron Schumacher, Meta">on YouTube</a>!</li>
</ul>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230919-fireside_chat_pro_tips/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230919-fireside_chat_pro_tips/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Strangest Man, by Farmelo</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I think I like this Graham Farmelo, and I like his book about Dirac.
Farmelo is interested in connections between mathematics and physics,
and aesthetics in both. I think I'll read some of his other books too.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>[Charlie] Broad was a wonderfully idiosyncratic lecturer. He always
appeared with a carefully prepared script, and he read every
sentence twice, except for the jokes, which he delivered three
times. (page 39)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In the space-time of the special theory of relativity, things are
different: the square of the distance between two points in
space-time is equal to the sum of the squares of the spatial lengths
<em>minus</em> the square of the time. (page 42)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is it fair to say that a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spacetime#Spacetime_interval">spacetime interval</a> <em>is</em> “the square of
the distance between two points in space-time”? Maybe?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><em>A System of Logic,</em> published in 1843, is a plain-spoken if
laborious account of how empiricism can shape every aspect of human
life. The book features Mill's agenda for science, which assumes
that there is an underlying ‘uniformity of nature’. The aim of
scientists should be to explain more and more observations in terms
of fewer and fewer laws, every one of them grounded in experience
and induced from it. (page 43)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mill%27s_Methods">Mill's Methods</a>!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>All his life, Dirac had the same attitude to the written word as his
contemporary George Orwell: ‘Good prose is like a window pane.’
(page 75)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Dirac knew that it was impossible to deduce the equation from first
principles and that he would find it only through a happy guess.
(page 141)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See also Polya on guessing...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>‘Don't despise philosophers too much,’ she had counselled him after
one of his visits, ‘a great deal that they say may be useless, but
they are after something which matters.’ Mrs Whitehead had been on
the receiving end of one of Dirac's tirades against the only
academic discipline he openly disdained. One of his <em>bêtes noire</em>
was teh internationally admired Trinity College philosopher Ludwig
Wittgenstein, regarded by many as one of the cleverest academics in
Cambridge. Several decades later, Dirac remarked that he was an
‘Awful fellow. Never stopped talking.’ (page 220)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>When Dirac focuses on the transcience of life, he is driven to an
important moral conclusion: ‘A termination of one's life is
necessary in the scheme of things <u>to provide a logical reason for
unselfishness</u>. [...] The fact that there is an end to one's life
compels one to take an interest in things that will continue to live
after one is dead.’ (page 221)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think one could argue exactly the opposite...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>In my case this article of faith is that the human race will
continue to live for ever and will develop and progress <u>without
limit</u>. This is an assumption that I must make for my peace of
mind. Living is worthwhile if one can contribute in some small way
to the endless chain of progress. (quoting Dirac, page 221)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See also: <a href="/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/">The Beginning of Infinity</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Anderson later remarked that any experimenter who took the theory
[Dirac's hole theory] at face value and who was working in a
well-equipped laboratory ‘could have discovered the positron in a
single afternoon’ using radioactive soures. (page 225)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This kind of thing is fascinating... What's still out there, that
could be seen in an afternoon, if we knew what to look for?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>He [Dirac] rarely spoke about science but did once exchange a few
words with her about mathematics: she thought it was a human
invention, while Dirac maintained that it had ‘always existed’ and
had been ‘discovered’ by humans. (page 251)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>She [Manci] would probably not have welcomed Dirac's view that his
religion was simply that ‘the world has to improve’. (page 257)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>For the physicists who were interested, a treat was in store:
[at the 1945-12-06 lecture] they heard Dirac coin two of the
best-known technical terms that he introduced: ‘fermions’, quantum
particles that obey the laws that he and Fermi had set out in 1926,
and ‘bosons’, the other type of quantum particles, which obey laws
set out by Einstein and the Indian theoretician Stayendra Bose.
(page 331)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Dirac made the theme of his 1980 lecture ‘The Engineer and the
Physicist’: ‘The main problem of the engineer is to decide which
approximations to make.’ Good engineers make wise choices, often
based on physical intuition, about the mathematical terms they can
ignore in their equations: ‘The terms neglected must be small and
their neglect must not have a big influence on the result. He must
not neglect terms that are not small.’ (page 337)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>He brought the same attention to detail to Dostoevsky's <em>Crime and
Punishment,</em> which he thought was ‘nice’, though he pointed out that
‘In one of the chapters the author makes a mistake: he describes the
sun as rising twice on the same day.’ (page 339)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is there such a mistake???</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Bertrand Russell's fictional don, Professor Driuzdustades (page 347)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Russell has fiction!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>When you ask what are electrons and protons I ought to answer that
this question is not a profitable one to ask and does not really
have a meaning. The important thing about electrons and protons is
not what they are but how they behave — how they move. I can
describe the situation by comparing it to the game of chess. In
chess, we have various chessmen, kings, knights, pawns and so on. If
you ask what a chessman is, the answer would be [that] it is a piece
of wood, or a piece of ivory, or perhaps just a sign written on
paper, [or anything whatever]. It does not matter. Each chessman has
a characteristic way of moving and this is all that matters about
it. The whole game of chess follows from this way of moving the
various chessmen [...] (page 354, quoting Dirac)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>PHYSICAL LAWS SHOULD HAVE MATHEMATICAL BEAUTY. (page 359, quoting
Dirac's blackboard writing)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230816-strangest_man_by_farmelo/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Thought is not a monolith</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Any particular argument can in principle be formalized in a particular
system of assumptions and inference rules, but flexibility in level of
formality and use of different systems for different arguments is both
practical and inevitable.</p>
<p>The plurality of systems of thought is particularly transparent in
mathematics, where for example to know whether a statement of geometry
is correct one must first ask which system of geometry is determining
correctness. In one system the interior angles of a triangle always
add to two right angles, but in another this is not the case.
Conflicting results do not imply cognitive dissonance when each is
correct in its respective system. The ability to choose among systems
is a great power.</p>
<p>Mathematical formal systems are in a sense complete articulations, but
they are also generally quite verbose and not necessarily easily
understood. In another sense, by their very self-completeness formal
systems close themselves off from meaning beyond their symbols,
requiring something beyond themselves and in that sense being
incomplete.</p>
<p>In practice, it is rare to completely formalize an argument. Ideally,
the nearest acceptable assumptions and clearest steps of reasoning are
described clearly and expediently. Often, assumptions and reasoning
are just implied, or even elided. There may be more or less
uncertainty in excavating the underlying argument.</p>
<p>Natural language is an imperfect tool. Spoken, written, or purely in
thought, a statement of natural language is a phenomon not purely tied
to any particular semantics. As in the Shannon–Weaver model of
communication, language is a signal, and it is the only part of the
system that we have meaningfully direct access to. Everyone speaks
their own constantly-evolving language. Much of philosophy can be seen
as postcards from Sisyphus visiting the ruins of Babel.</p>
<p>Meaning is built based on language, but the meaning cannot be directly
inspected. Reading my own notes, I may find that now they mean nothing
to me, or I may otherwise understand them differently from what I was
understanding as I wrote them. It isn't clear that it is possible to
understand a statement twice in exactly the same way. In the case of
communication with others, the best we can hope for is roughly
compatible understandings.</p>
<p>In stimulating meanings, even if not always perfectly identical,
natural language is a powerful tool. By relying on shared
understandings, which can be built, natural language can be very
efficient and effective. Very often, it is the best option. Care
should be taken to avoid the extremes of its weaknesses.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230723-thought_is_not_a_monolith/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230723-thought_is_not_a_monolith/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Assume some proved things cannot be disproved</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Given a valid proof in a system of assumptions and inference rules,
there is no sure way to know that there isn't also a contradictory
proof, except by assumption outside the system.</p>
<p>Some systems allow a proof of every statement. For example, take a
system where <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principle_of_explosion" title="Principle of explosion, ex falso quodlibet">anything follows from a contradiction</a>, as is common,
and also assume a contradiction.</p>
<p>Systems that prove everything are not honest. In such systems, you can
prove that the system is consistent. You can prove the law of
non-contradiction, and that the system contains no contradictions.
Seeing such a proof does not establish that an opposite proof doesn't
exist. The situation is akin to the futile exercise of trying to
determine whether a person is a liar by asking them.</p>
<p>The situation is also bad even if attempting to show for just one
proved statement that there isn't a proof of its negation. Socrates
presents argument 1, demonstrating conclusion A. Socrates then
presents argument 2, demonstrating conclusion B, which is that there
is no argument for the negation of A. Socrates then presents argument
3, demonstrating conclusion C, which is that there is no argument for
the negation of B. And so on, forever, for every initial conclusion A.</p>
<p>A proof of consistency cannot be convincing, whether it be for a
system overall or even for a single statement in the system (that for
a specific proof, there isn't a proof for the opposite conclusion).</p>
<p>Stepping up a level, to a meta-system where the consistency of the
original system can be proved, does not solve the problem, because the
meta-system hasn't itself been shown to be consistent.</p>
<p>Gödel's second incompleteness theorem is a special case of this
phenomenon. It shows that for formal systems with certain properties,
they can't prove that they are consistent.</p>
<p>Introducing the law of non-contradiction as an axiom, or assuming that
the system contains no contradictions, does not solve the problem.
Such a claim made within the system can always coexist with its
negation, if it is present.</p>
<p>If a system proves both a statement and its negation, there is no
ambiguity. If a system proves a statement but its negation is not
proved, it is necessary to assume that there is no such proof.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20230716-assume_some_proved_things_cannot_be_disproved/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20230716-assume_some_proved_things_cannot_be_disproved/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
