<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>plan ➔ space</title>
    <link>http://planspace.org/</link>
    <description>plan space from outer nine</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://planspace.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item>
<title>Mindf*ck, by Wylie</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Cambridge Analytica was a US brand for the UK's SCL (Strategic
Communication Laboratories) Group. They <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facebook%E2%80%93Cambridge_Analytica_data_scandal" title="Facebook–Cambridge Analytica data scandal">got</a> Americans to fill out
personality surveys and install an app that sent them Facebook
information on likes, friends, etc. They used all this to advance the
agendas of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Bannon">Steve Bannon</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Mercer" title="Robert Mercer">Bob Mercer</a>, for example.</p>
<p>Facebook's crime in this seems to have been basically negligence. They
let a lot of information be accessible at the time, and people did
unsavory things with it. It's a little weird to call it a data breach,
since the system was working as intended.</p>
<p>I wonder how (or whether) Cambridge Analytica evaluated their
effectiveness... Trump became president, but was it <em>because of</em>
Cambridge Analytica? Or were they just pushing in a direction that
already had momentum? It is both horrifying and attractive to think
that manipulative actors are responsible for massive unpleasant
outcomes. But what share of the blame can be assigned?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Our system is broken, our laws don't work, our regulators are weak,
our governments don't understand what's happening, and our
technology is usurping our democracy." (page 248)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Bannon realized the power of cultivating the misogyny of of horny
virgins." (page 62)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It turns out that Republicans can accept a batshit insane
candidate, <em>so long as it's consistent insanity</em>." (page 71, italics
in original)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This [idea to simulate behavior with computers] brought to mind
experiments from the 1990s in a niche field of sociology called
"<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_society" title="Artificial society">artificial societies</a>," which involved attempts by crude
multi-agent systems to "grow" societies in silico. I could remember
as a teenager reading Isaac Asimov's <a href="https://planspace.org/20200714-foundation_trilogy/" title="Asimov's Foundation trilogy"><em>Foundation</em></a> series, where
scientists used large data sets about societies to create the field
of "psychohistory," which allowed them to not only predict the
future but also control it." (page 81)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In 2012, Facebook <a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/US8825764B2/en" title="Determining user personality characteristics from social networking system communications and characteristics">filed</a> for a U.S. patent for "<em>Determining
user personality characteristics from social networking system
communications and characteristics</em>." Facebook's patent application
explained that its interest in psychological profiling was because
"inferred personality characteristics are stored in connection with
the user's profile, and may be used for targeting, ranking,
selecting versions of products, and various other purposes."" (page
96)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In fact, a 2015 <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.1418680112" title="Computer-based personality judgments are more accurate than those made by humans">study</a> by Youyou, Kosinski, and Stillwell showed
that, using Facebook likes, a computer model reigned supreme in
predicting human behavior." (page 103)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It contained complete profiles of tens of thousands of users—name,
gender, age, location, status updates, likes, friends—<em>everything</em>.
Kogan said his Facebook app could even pull private messages."
(pages 104-105)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The private messages bit is quite the unsupported claim.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>""Think about it," I said to Bannon. "The message at a Tea Party
rally is the same as at a Gay Pride parade: <em>Don't tread on me! Let
me be who I am!</em>"" (page 117)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"A select minority of people exhibit traits of narcissism (extreme
self-centeredness), Machiavellianism (ruthless self-interest), and
psychopathy (emotional detachment). In contrast to the Big Five
traits found in everyone to some degree as part of normal
psychology—openness, conscientiousness, extroversion, agreeableness,
and neuroticism—these "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dark_triad" title="Dark triad">dark triad</a>" traits are maladaptive,
meaning that those who exhibit them are generally more prone to
antisocial behavior, including criminal acts. From the data CA
collected, the team was able to identify people who exhibited
neuroticism and dark-triad traits, and those who were more prone to
impulsive anger or conspiratorial thinking than average citizens.
Cambridge Analytica would target them, introducing narratives via
Facebook groups, ads, or articles that the firm knew from internal
testing were likely to inflame the very narrow segments of people
with these traits. CA wanted to provoke people, to get them to
engage." (pages 119-120)</p>
<p>"As it happens, the most engaging content on social media is often
horrible or enraging." (page 120)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Some of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Five_personality_traits">Big Five personality traits</a> stuff reminded me of what
I've heard about <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Righteous-Mind-Divided-Politics-Religion/dp/0307455777/">The Righteous Mind</a>: describing Republicans as low
on openness and high on conscientiousness, while Democrats are the
reverse.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Cambridge Analytica's research panels also identified that there
were relationships between target attitudes and a psychological
effect called the <em>just-world hypothesis</em> (JWH). This is a cognitive
bias where some people rely on a presumption of a fair world: The
world is a fair place where bad things "happen for a reason" or will
be offset by some sort of "moral balancing" in the universe. We
found that people who displayed the JWH bias were, for example, more
prone to victim-blaming in hypothetical scenarios of sexual assault.
If the world is fair, then random bad things should not happen to
innocent people, and therefore there must have been a fault in the
victim's behavior. Finding ways to blame victims is psychologically
prophylactic for some people because it helps them cope with anxiety
induced by uncontrollable environmental threats while maintaining a
comforting view that the world will still be fair <em>to them</em>.</p>
<p>"Cambridge Analytica found that JWH was related to many attitudes,
but that it had a special relationship with racial bias." (page 129)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This idea—the just-world hypothesis considered harmful—is very
interesting.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In 1988, George H. W. Bush's campaign ran the infamous
<a href="https://youtu.be/Io9KMSSEZ0Y" title="Willie Horton 1988 Attack Ad">Willie Horton ad</a>, terrifying white voters with visions of
wild-haired black criminals running amok." (page 131)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... Cambridge Analytica was merely a front-facing brand for
American clients that was entirely staffed by SCL personnel." (page
134)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In our invasion of America, we were purposefully activating the
worst in people, from paranoia to racism." (page 144)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"To Moscow, civil rights and the First Amendment are the American
political system's most glaring vulnerabilities." (page 153)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Cambridge Analytica identified that many people in non-urban
regions or in lower socioeconomic strata often externalized the
notion of "the economy" to something that only the wealthy and
metropolitan participated in. "The economy" was not their job in a
local store; it was something that bankers did." (page 172)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Page 192 includes a reference to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zelig" title="Zelig">Zelig</a>, which I hadn't known
about.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Later, it emerged that Facebook, in a panic about its PR crisis,
had hired the secret communications firm
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Definers_Public_Affairs">Definers Public Affairs</a>, which subsequently leaked out fake
narratives filled with anti-Semitic tropes about its critics being
part of a George Soros-funded conspiracy." (page 229)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Page 229 describes the 2013 "The Value of Science is in the Foresight"
by Valery Gerasimov (<a href="https://www.armyupress.army.mil/portals/7/military-review/archives/english/militaryreview_20160228_art008.pdf">PDF</a>).</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Peter Thiel, the venture capitalist behind Facebook, Palantir, and
Paypal, spoke at length about how he no longer believes "that
freedom and democracy are compatible." And in elaborating his views
on technology companies, he expounded on how CEOs are the new
monarchs in a techno-feudal system of governance. We just don't call
them monarchies in public, he said, because "anything that's not
democracy makes people uncomfortable."" (page 237)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The quote is included in Thiel's "<a href="https://www.cato-unbound.org/2009/04/13/peter-thiel/education-libertarian/">The Education of a Libertarian</a>."</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Information Commissioner's Office ... eventually issuing Facebook
the maximum fine allowable in law for data breaches." (page 247)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This appears to have been <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2018/oct/25/facebook-fined-uk-privacy-access-user-data-cambridge-analytica" title="UK fines Facebook £500,000 for failing to protect user data">£500,000</a>.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20221029-mindf*ck_by_wylie/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20221029-mindf*ck_by_wylie/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Consciousness Explained, by Dennett</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Dennett takes materialism as an axiom and uses it to prove there is no
dualist, soul-like consciousness, no audience in a “Cartesian
theater.” He thinks that if you imagine a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philosophical_zombie">philosophical zombie</a>,
then you're imagining too hard, and if you don't think the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_room">Chinese room</a> is conscious, then you aren't imagining hard enough.
His argument is that the brain must be where consciousness comes from,
and we know what kind of things are in the brain, so consciousness
must be from all that: lots of simple things together generate
consciousness and there's nothing more to the story. I don't feel like
it's explained.</p>
<p>Do I ask too much of an explanation of consciousness? Science is
fundamentally descriptive, after all. Maxwell's equations (etc.) don't
explain <em>why</em> electromagnetism (etc.) is the way it is. They don't
really explain <em>how</em> it works. Every theory is vulnerable to a child
repeatedly asking “why.” This is the kind of infinite regress Dennett
is trying to avoid. And yet, I am conscious. This <em>experience</em> is the
phenomenon of interest. Being able to <em>have</em> experiences. I don't
think there's anything being a magnet is like, but there is something
being me is like, and I'm not convinced Dennett explains the
difference.</p>
<p>It seems very much like a riff on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Society_of_Mind">Society of Mind</a>, which I should
probably read as well, though I don't know whether it will be more
persuasive. Do people consider this a settled issue? At least in the
popular press, folks are still <a href="https://www.popularmechanics.co.za/science/quantum-physics-could-finally-explain-consciousness-scientists-say/" title="Quantum Physics Could Finally Explain Consciousness, Scientists Say">pitching</a> weird ideas and describing
consciousness as a “deep and abiding philosophical problem.” Is
Dennett's explanation bad, or do I just not want to understand?</p>
<p>For the most part, I think Dennett is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Not_even_wrong">not even wrong</a>, because he
isn't explaining what he promises to. It is a challenge, though, to
imagine what explanation (between Dennett and dualism) I would prefer.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"One conclusion we can draw from this is that we are not brains in
vats—in case you were worried." (page 7)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He's arguing this is the case because it would be too computationally
expensive to simulate a world, based on the graphics of Donkey Kong
being crummy. Perhaps this seemed convincing in 1991?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"And, as with all the earlier mysteries, there are many who
insist—and hope—that there will never be a demystification of
consciousness." (page 22)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I do have some sympathy for this critique... What <em>would</em> a
satisfactory explanation look like?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The challenge is to construct a theory of mental events, using the
data that scientific method permits. Such a theory will have to be
constructed from the third-person point of view, since all science
is constructed from that perspective." (page 71)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Suppose you are confronted by a “speaking” computer, and suppose
you succeed in interpreting its output as speech acts expressing its
beliefs and opinions, presumably “about” its conscious states. The
fact that there is a single, coherent interpretation of a sequence
of behavior doesn’t establish that the interpretation is true; it
might be only as if the “subject” were conscious; we risk being
taken in by a zombie with no inner life at all. You could not
confirm that the computer was conscious of anything by this method
of interpretation. Fair enough. We can’t be sure that the speech
acts we observe express real beliefs about actual experiences;
perhaps they express only apparent beliefs about nonexistent
experiences. Still, the fact that we had found even one stable
interpretation of some entity’s behavior as speech acts would always
be a fact worthy of attention." (page 78)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you agree with Dennett, then do you agree that Google's
<a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/google-engineer-claims-ai-chatbot-is-sentient-why-that-matters/" title="Google Engineer Claims AI Chatbot Is Sentient: Why That Matters">LaMDA is conscious</a>? According to Dennett, it might as well be, and
he doesn't identify any method for distinguishing.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Other people, however, find the implication that there could be, in
principle, a conscious robot so incredible that it amounts in their
eyes to the reductio ad absurdum of my theory." (page 432)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"the famous four F’s (fight, flee, feed, or mate)" (page 188)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I hadn't heard this one before.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Here is the hypothesis I will defend: Human consciousness is itself
a huge complex of memes (or more exactly, meme-effects in brains)
that can best be understood as the operation of a “von Neumannesque”
virtual machine implemented in the parallel architecture of a brain
that was not designed for any such activities. The powers of this
virtual machine vastly enhance the underlying powers of the organic
hardware on which it runs, but at the same time many of its most
curious features, and especially its limitations, can be explained
as the byproducts of the kludges that make possible this curious but
effective reuse of an existing organ for novel purposes." (page 210)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"But still (I am sure you want to object): All this has little or
nothing to do with consciousness! After all, a von Neumann machine
is entirely unconscious; why should implementing it—or something
like it: a Joycean machine—be any more conscious? I do have an
answer: The von Neumann machine, by being wired up from the outset
that way, with maximally efficient informational links, didn’t have
to become the object of its own elaborate perceptual systems. The
workings of the Joycean machine, on the other hand, are just as
“visible” and “audible” to it as any of the things in the external
world that it is designed to perceive—for the simple reason that
they have much of the same perceptual machinery focused on them. Now
this appears to be a trick with mirrors, I know." (page 225)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"With so many idiots working on the problem, no wonder consciousness
is still a mystery." (page 255)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Out of context, yes.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"There seems to be phenomenology. That’s a fact that the
heterophenomenologist enthusiastically concedes. But it does not
follow from this undeniable, universally attested fact that there
really is phenomenology." (page 366)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is time to recognize the idea of the possibility of zombies for
what it is: not a serious philosophical idea but a preposterous and
ignoble relic of ancient prejudices. Maybe women aren’t really
conscious! Maybe Jews! What pernicious nonsense." (page 405)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This protest is a little weird, given that earlier Dennett defines
"people" as "adult human beings" (not children?) and argues that
consciousness is largely a cultural phenomenon (so one culture could
be more conscious than another?).</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"It is hard to imagine how “just more of the same” could add up to
understanding, but we have very good reason to believe that it does,
so in this case, we should try harder, not give up." (page 439)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Dennett implicitly rejects the possibility that there could be
something different, something not just more of the same, something
that is an explanation of consciousness rather than a rejection of a
dualist explanation.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"(What could a clam do with a secret? Just sit there in the mud,
chuckling to itself?)" (page 447)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is really funny to me somehow. What a happy clam!</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"the assumption that consciousness is a special all-or-nothing
property that sunders the universe into two vastly different
categories: the things that have it (the things that it is like
something to be, as Nagel would put it) and the things that lack
it." (page 447)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I agree that this is weird too.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"When a deaf-mute acquires language (in particular, Sign language,
the most natural language a deaf-mute can learn), a full-fledged
human mind is born, clearly different in discoverable ways from the
mind of a hearing person, but capable of all the reflective
intricacy and generative power—perhaps more."</p>
<p>"But without a natural language, a deaf-mute’s mind is terribly
stunted."</p>
<p>"Many people are afraid to see consciousness explained because they
fear that if we succeed in explaining it, we will lose our moral
bearings. Maybe we can imagine a conscious computer (or the
consciousness of a bat) but we shouldn’t try, they think. If we get
into that bad habit, we will start treating animals as if they were
wind-up toys, babies and deaf-mutes as if they were teddy bears,
and—just to add insult to injury—robots as if they were real
people."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(page 448)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Do we think, for instance, that vast resources should be set aside
to preserve the imaginary prospects of a renewed mental life for
deeply comatose people, while there are no resources to spare to
enhance the desperate, but far from imaginary, expectations of the
poor? Myths about the sanctity of life, or of consciousness, cut
both ways. They may be useful in erecting barriers (against
euthanasia, against capital punishment, against abortion, against
eating meat) to impress the unimaginative, but at the price of
offensive hypocrisy or ridiculous self-deception among the more
enlightened." (page 454)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Leaving something out is not a feature of failed explanations, but
of successful explanations."</p>
<p>"Only a theory that explained conscious events in terms of
unconscious events could explain consciousness at all."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(page 454)</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220918-consciousness_explained_by_dennett/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220918-consciousness_explained_by_dennett/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Heads, by Greg Bear</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I read this because I heard it was about consciousness. It was only a
little bit about consciousness. Some quantum computers had some kind
of consciousness, but they were not central to anything. At the end
there was some possible additional consciousness stuff, but mostly
not. In the end, not nearly enough about consciousness. Three stars.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220910-heads_by_greg_bear/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220910-heads_by_greg_bear/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Tuesdays with Morrie, by Albom</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuesdays_with_Morrie" title="Tuesdays with Morrie">It</a>'s a nice book.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Once you get your fingers on the important questions, you can't
turn away from them.” (page 175, quoting Morrie)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220910-tuesdays_with_morrie_by_albom/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220910-tuesdays_with_morrie_by_albom/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Sea of Tranquility, by Mandel</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea_of_Tranquility_(novel)" title="Sea of Tranquility (novel)">Sea of Tranquility</a> is a lot of fun. There's a good deal of amusing
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autofiction">autofiction</a>, and fun mystery and sci-fi aspects. I have a fondness
for time travel. It's not very long, and it reads really quickly.</p>
<p>I agree with the author's take on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simulation_hypothesis">simulation hypothesis</a>, which
is that it doesn't really matter. I think, therefore I am. I think
consciousness is a mysterious, special, and important part of this.</p>
<p>You can tell it's sci-fi because in the future there are airships.
There always have to be airships. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emily_St._John_Mandel" title="Emily St. John Mandel">Mandel</a>'s airships are not just
dirigibles though! They're fast enough for daily global commutes.
Exciting. More is not explained.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"I think, as a species, we have a desire to believe that we’re
living at the climax of the story. It’s a kind of narcissism. We
want to believe that we’re uniquely important, that we’re living at
the end of history, that now, after all these millennia of false
alarms, now is finally the worst that it’s ever been, that finally
we have reached the end of the world.”" (page 165)</p>
<p>"“My personal belief is that we turn to postapocalyptic fiction not
because we’re drawn to disaster, per se, but because we’re drawn to
what we imagine might come next. We long secretly for a world with
less technology in it.”" (page 167)</p>
<p>"A life lived in a simulation is still a life." (page 210)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220806-sea_of_tranquility_by_mandel/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220806-sea_of_tranquility_by_mandel/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>That little voice in your head, by Gawdat</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rob-archangel-50bb35176/" title="Rob Archangel">Rob Archangel</a> (of <a href="https://www.archangelink.com/" title="Your partner in leveraging your credibility and expertise into self-publishing success">Archangel Ink</a>) sent me <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mo_Gawdat" title="Mo Gawdat">Mo Gawdat</a>'s
latest <a href="https://www.mogawdat.com/littlevoice" title="That little voice in your head">book</a> to review, so I skimmed it. Gawdat's son died at 21.
The book is a collection of <a href="/20210107-enchiridion_in_52_sentences/" title="The Enchiridion in 52 sentences">stoic</a>, Buddhist, and TED Talk
philosophy. You could do worse, though I do think Gawdat is <a href="https://www.mogawdat.com/scarysmart" title="Scary Smart The Future of Artificial Intelligence and How You Can Save Our World">wrong</a>
about AI and consciousness. That Little Voice is uncomfortably like
watching him struggle to mourn.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>To its credit, the book includes summaries.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Summary of Part One</p>
<p>4-3-2-1, those are the reasons our brains make us unhappy.</p>
<p><strong>4</strong> (wrong) <strong>Inputs</strong> distort our perception of the truth. Three
come from within us. Those are conditioning, recycled thoughts and
trapped emotions. But the biggest one is all-pervasive around us. It
is the hidden triggers, from the news media to the entertainment
industry, all the way to the advice of a friend that does not apply
to your life context. Don’t let your thoughts be influenced by your
inner inputs. See them for what they are and weed them out. Then,
whatever you do, stop injecting your life with hidden triggers. You
are what you think. Stop letting the thoughts of others make you who
you are.</p>
<p><strong>3</strong> (exaggerated) <strong>Defences</strong> keep us safe but make us suffer.
Our brains have built within them every defence mechanism that’s
helped other species. A reptilian brain that lives for avoiding
danger, a mammalian brain that exists to seek rewards and avoid
pain, and a rational brain that is constantly planning and
analysing. Those defences keep us stuck in Aversion, Attachment and
an All-Pervasive Dissatisfaction. Learn to make your reptile feel
safe, make your mammal enjoy what is and remind your rational human
to see that all is OK.</p>
<p><strong>2</strong> (opposite) <strong>Polarities</strong> are part of every one of us. The
feminine and the masculine. Those polarities are not determined by
biology, gender or sexual preference. They are a way of life. One is
about being and the other about doing. Our modern world, and each of
us, are submerged in doing. We need more of our feminine qualities.
We need to learn to be.</p>
<p><strong>1</strong> (harmful) <strong>Thought</strong> – the incessant type of thinking – is
the result of letting our thoughts repeat, unchecked by our
deliberate attention. Many clinical conditions that are associated
with unhappiness are the result of scattered thoughts and
mind-wandering. Learning to pay deliberate attention has always been
my top advice for anyone who seeks to be happy. Be here. Repeat a
bad habit often enough, and you become really good at it because,
through neuroplasticity, Practice Makes Miserable. Stop practising
your own unhappiness. Turn the process the opposite way. Learn to go
to the happiness gym and work on the habits that reverse the 4-3-2-1
model.</p>
<p>Practise limiting your information diet only to what’s good for you.
Remember to practise your gratitude muscle. Live more in the
feminine and pay deliberate attention. One small step after another
and your brain will be rewired for happiness to be its default
state.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Summary of Part Two</p>
<p>The impact of a thought is surely not confined within our skull and
surely not to the instant that thought took place. What you think
changes you emotionally and physically, and then it changes your
pattern of thinking itself as it plays endlessly on repeat.</p>
<p>Our emotions, erratic as they sometimes may seem, are
hyperpredictable. They are triggered by thoughts that follow
repeatable patterns. The modern world teaches us to hide our
emotions and this disconnects us from them, even to deny them.
Leaving our emotions unexpressed turns us into zombies walking
through life uninterested or pressure cookers waiting to explode.</p>
<p>But we only feel alive when we feel, just like we only feel when we
are alive. We need to get in touch with our emotions, acknowledge
them – even celebrate them – sit with them, experience their storms
and harness their energy to move us forward.</p>
<p>Our autonomic nervous system responds to the world even before our
thoughts catch up with what happened. Our sympathetic nervous system
stresses us to protect us. It prepares us to face challenges and
threats with superhuman powers. This feature in our design saved our
species, but now, as our stress response lingers, it is leading us
to unhappiness.</p>
<p>We need to engage our parasympathetic nervous system to remind our
bodies that things are OK. Learn to relax, be around those who do,
and create a sense of safety by remembering our blessings and
removing what stresses us from our lives.</p>
<p>Finally, we need to stop the endless loops of incessant thinking.
They take us down a spiral of unhappiness and leave no positive
impact on the world whatsoever. To stop the thinking, treat your
brain like a third party. I call mine Becky and I have a clear
agreement with my brain. Bring me joyful thoughts or useful
thoughts. Every other thought is a waste of my life. Sign the
contract. Get your brain to comply.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>Summary of Part Three</p>
<p>Many happiness teachings may seem to come across as an invitation to
calm or control one’s brain. Because our stray incessant thoughts
can cause a lot of unhappiness, it is obvious that keeping our minds
in check is a sure path to a calmer, happier life. But it’s not the
only path.</p>
<p>If an active mind is engaged in useful thinking – generating
thoughts that improve your life and state of wellbeing – then, by
all means, think as much as you can.</p>
<p>There are four types of useful thoughts. I strongly urge you to make
those types of thoughts the norm of what your brain focuses on. That
way it will no longer have the capacity to think the negative
thoughts that waste your life and make you unhappy.</p>
<p>1) <strong>Experiential Thinking</strong> - Experiencing the world exactly as it
is requires your brain to engage just as much as it needs to when
processing any other kind of thought. As a matter of fact, because
your brain is only able to do one thing at a time, observing the
world with mindfulness is a bulletproof way to live in reality and
not inside your own head. Meditation is a valuable practice that
can, over time, reconfigure your brain to become more capable of
living in the present moment instead of lost in its own thoughts.</p>
<p>Meditation is just a practice, though. To truly transform those
skills into the reality of your everyday life, use newer versions of
it that are fit for the modern world to learn to be present every
minute of every day.</p>
<p>2) <strong>Problem-Solving</strong> – is the most highly praised type of thinking
in our analytical modern world. The capacity to overcome challenges
by finding solutions is mostly applied in our work and professional
life. Yet, it can equally be applied to lead to our happiness and
wellbeing.</p>
<p>The <strong>happiness flowchart</strong> is a good example of how you can use
your disciplined problem-solving brain to ensure you bounce back to
happiness swiftly when an event disturbs your mood. Once you’ve
learned to recognize, acknowledge, even embrace, an emotion, find
the thought that triggered it and then ask yourself three questions:</p>
<p>a. <strong>Is it true?</strong> Is there evidence to support the validity of the
thought triggering my happiness. If the thought is fiction created
by your brain, drop it. If it is true, then ask the next question...</p>
<p>b. <strong>Can I do something about it?</strong> Unhappiness, you see, is just a
survival mechanism. It’s your brain’s invitation for you to do
something about what it sees as a suboptimal condition for your
survival and success. If there is something you can do about what’s
making you unhappy, do it. The unhappiness will go away and your
world will become better. If there is nothing you can do, then ask
the last question ...</p>
<p>c. <strong>Can I accept and commit?</strong> Life, every now and again, is bound
to send a predicament your way. An event that doesn’t meet your
hopes of how life should be which is beyond your ability to fix or
improve. When there is nothing you can do about your situation,
learn to accept it for what it is, then commit to do whatever you
can do to make your life better despite, or even because of, the
challenge that you are facing.</p>
<p>3) <strong>Flow</strong> – When we flow, we merge our being with our doing. We
get absorbed into what we do fully, we do it better and we feel
lighter. To flow, make the task at hand a tiny bit harder than your
current skill, clear away the distractions and break it into smaller
tasks and focus on the small bits instead of the final results, do
each bit to the best of your abilities and forget about time. Give
every task all the time it needs.</p>
<p>4) <strong>Give</strong> – It is the smartest thing you can ever do. Nothing will
ever make you happier or make our world better.</p>
<p>Our brains are nothing but sophisticated computer systems. They are
highly predictable in their operations. You don’t necessarily need a
silent brain to be happy. All you need is a positive, useful brain.
Your brain will do what you tell it to do. It’s time to start your
training.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img alt="diagram" src="diagram.png"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220704-that_little_voice_in_your_head_by_gawdat/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220704-that_little_voice_in_your_head_by_gawdat/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Common jobs by income range</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This is a look at how people earn more or less money, <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/income" title="GitHub repository: ajschumacher/income">based on</a> the
2019 US Census 1% sample. It lists the occupations reported by 1% or
more of people in each income band. (Click to expand and collapse
lists.)</p>
<style>
  details {padding-left: 1em}
  summary {margin-left: -1em}
  ul {margin-top: 0em; margin-bottom: 0em; padding-left: 1em;}
</style>

<details><summary>60% of workers made up to $50,000</summary>
<ul>
<li> 3.3% Cashiers</li>
<li> 2.8% Retail Salespersons</li>
<li> 2.3% Driver/Sales Workers And Truck Drivers</li>
<li> 2.3% Janitors And Building Cleaners</li>
<li> 2.2% Secretaries And Administrative Assistants, Except Legal, Medical, And Executive</li>
<li> 2.2% Cooks</li>
<li> 2.2% Customer Service Representatives</li>
<li> 2.2% Laborers And Freight, Stock, And Material Movers, Hand</li>
<li> 2.0% Waiters And Waitresses</li>
<li> 1.8% First-Line Supervisors Of Retail Sales Workers</li>
<li> 1.7% Elementary And Middle School Teachers</li>
<li> 1.5% Teaching Assistants</li>
<li> 1.4% Stockers And Order Fillers</li>
<li> 1.4% Other Managers</li>
<li> 1.3% Construction Laborers</li>
<li> 1.3% Personal Care Aides</li>
<li> 1.3% Office Clerks, General</li>
<li> 1.3% Maids And Housekeeping Cleaners</li>
<li> 1.3% Receptionists And Information Clerks</li>
<li> 1.2% Nursing Assistants</li>
<li> 1.2% Registered Nurses</li>
<li> 1.2% Childcare Workers</li>
<li> 1.1% Landscaping And Groundskeeping Workers</li>
<li> 1.1% Bookkeeping, Accounting, And Auditing Clerks</li>
<li> 1.0% Food Preparation Workers</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary>26% made $50,000 to $100,000</summary>
<ul>
<li> 4.2% Registered Nurses</li>
<li> 3.4% Elementary And Middle School Teachers</li>
<li> 3.4% Other Managers</li>
<li> 2.9% Driver/Sales Workers And Truck Drivers</li>
<li> 1.8% Secondary School Teachers</li>
<li> 1.8% First-Line Supervisors Of Retail Sales Workers</li>
<li> 1.8% Accountants And Auditors</li>
<li> 1.4% Secretaries And Administrative Assistants, Except Legal, Medical, And Executive</li>
<li> 1.4% Postsecondary Teachers</li>
<li> 1.1% Financial Managers</li>
<li> 1.1% Sales Representatives, Wholesale And Manufacturing</li>
<li> 1.1% Software Developers</li>
<li> 1.1% General And Operations Managers</li>
<li> 1.1% Education And Childcare Administrators</li>
<li> 1.1% Retail Salespersons</li>
<li> 1.0% Customer Service Representatives</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary>10% made $100,000 to $200,000</summary>
<ul>
<li> 7.1% Other Managers</li>
<li> 4.3% Software Developers</li>
<li> 3.0% Chief Executives And Legislators</li>
<li> 2.6% Lawyers, And Judges, Magistrates, And Other Judicial Workers</li>
<li> 2.6% Registered Nurses</li>
<li> 2.1% Financial Managers</li>
<li> 2.0% Accountants And Auditors</li>
<li> 1.8% Computer And Information Systems Managers</li>
<li> 1.8% Postsecondary Teachers</li>
<li> 1.8% Sales Representatives, Wholesale And Manufacturing</li>
<li> 1.7% Management Analysts</li>
<li> 1.6% General And Operations Managers</li>
<li> 1.5% Other Engineers</li>
<li> 1.4% First-Line Supervisors Of Retail Sales Workers</li>
<li> 1.4% Education And Childcare Administrators</li>
<li> 1.3% Construction Managers</li>
<li> 1.3% Project Management Specialists</li>
<li> 1.3% First-Line Supervisors Of Non-Retail Sales Workers</li>
<li> 1.2% Pharmacists</li>
<li> 1.1% Physicians</li>
<li> 1.1% Elementary And Middle School Teachers</li>
<li> 1.0% Sales Managers</li>
<li> 1.0% Police Officers</li>
<li> 1.0% Computer Systems Analysts</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary>2% made $200,000 to $400,000</summary>
<ul>
<li> 8.6% Other Managers</li>
<li> 8.0% Chief Executives And Legislators</li>
<li> 7.2% Physicians</li>
<li> 5.9% Lawyers, And Judges, Magistrates, And Other Judicial Workers</li>
<li> 3.6% Software Developers</li>
<li> 2.4% Financial Managers</li>
<li> 2.1% Management Analysts</li>
<li> 2.0% Accountants And Auditors</li>
<li> 1.8% Sales Representatives, Wholesale And Manufacturing</li>
<li> 1.8% Real Estate Brokers And Sales Agents</li>
<li> 1.7% Postsecondary Teachers</li>
<li> 1.7% Personal Financial Advisors</li>
<li> 1.6% Computer And Information Systems Managers</li>
<li> 1.4% First-Line Supervisors Of Non-Retail Sales Workers</li>
<li> 1.4% Sales Managers</li>
<li> 1.4% General And Operations Managers</li>
<li> 1.3% First-Line Supervisors Of Retail Sales Workers</li>
<li> 1.2% Farmers, Ranchers, And Other Agricultural Managers</li>
<li> 1.2% Dentists</li>
<li> 1.1% Other Engineers</li>
<li> 1.1% Sales Representatives Of Services, Except Advertising, Insurance, Financial Services, And Travel</li>
<li> 1.0% Aircraft Pilots And Flight Engineers</li>
<li> 1.0% Construction Managers</li>
<li> 1.0% Marketing Managers</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary>1% made over $400,000</summary>
<ul>
<li>13.5% Chief Executives And Legislators</li>
<li>12.4% Physicians</li>
<li> 8.4% Other Managers</li>
<li> 7.8% Lawyers, And Judges, Magistrates, And Other Judicial Workers</li>
<li> 3.1% Financial Managers</li>
<li> 2.5% Personal Financial Advisors</li>
<li> 2.0% Management Analysts</li>
<li> 2.0% Accountants And Auditors</li>
<li> 1.9% Real Estate Brokers And Sales Agents</li>
<li> 1.8% Software Developers</li>
<li> 1.6% Securities, Commodities, And Financial Services Sales Agents</li>
<li> 1.5% Dentists</li>
<li> 1.5% Surgeons</li>
<li> 1.3% Sales Representatives, Wholesale And Manufacturing</li>
<li> 1.3% First-Line Supervisors Of Retail Sales Workers</li>
<li> 1.2% First-Line Supervisors Of Non-Retail Sales Workers</li>
<li> 1.2% General And Operations Managers</li>
<li> 1.2% Sales Managers</li>
<li> 1.0% Postsecondary Teachers</li>
<li> 1.0% Property, Real Estate, And Community Association Managers</li>
<li> 1.0% Sales Representatives Of Services, Except Advertising, Insurance, Financial Services, And Travel</li>
</ul>
</details>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220703-common_jobs_by_income_range/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220703-common_jobs_by_income_range/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>What are people doing?</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>What are the jobs Americans do? Here's a view <a href="https://github.com/ajschumacher/income" title="GitHub repository: ajschumacher/income">based on</a> the 2019 US
Census 1% sample. (Click to expand and collapse lists.)</p>
<style>
  details {padding-left: 1em}
  summary {margin-left: -1em}
  ul {margin-top: 0em; margin-bottom: 0em; padding-left: 1em;}
</style>

<details><summary>31.52% Management, Business, Science, and Arts Occupations</summary>
<details><summary>12.62% Management, Business, and Financial Occupations</summary>
<details><summary> 8.44% Management Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.78% Chief Executives And Legislators</li>
<li> 0.52% General And Operations Managers</li>
<li> 0.03% Advertising And Promotions Managers</li>
<li> 0.26% Marketing Managers</li>
<li> 0.25% Sales Managers</li>
<li> 0.05% Public Relations And Fundraising Managers</li>
<li> 0.03% Administrative Services Managers</li>
<li> 0.06% Facilities Managers</li>
<li> 0.32% Computer And Information Systems Managers</li>
<li> 0.64% Financial Managers</li>
<li> 0.01% Compensation And Benefits Managers</li>
<li> 0.14% Human Resources Managers</li>
<li> 0.03% Training And Development Managers</li>
<li> 0.14% Industrial Production Managers</li>
<li> 0.11% Purchasing Managers</li>
<li> 0.13% Transportation, Storage, And Distribution Managers</li>
<li> 0.45% Farmers, Ranchers, And Other Agricultural Managers</li>
<li> 0.44% Construction Managers</li>
<li> 0.50% Education And Childcare Administrators</li>
<li> 0.09% Architectural And Engineering Managers</li>
<li> 0.41% Food Service Managers</li>
<li> 0.02% Entertainment and Recreation Managers</li>
<li> 0.07% Lodging Managers</li>
<li> 0.32% Medical And Health Services Managers</li>
<li> 0.01% Natural Sciences Managers</li>
<li> 0.30% Property, Real Estate, And Community Association Managers</li>
<li> 0.21% Social And Community Service Managers</li>
<li> 0.01% Emergency Management Directors</li>
<li> 2.13% Other Managers</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 4.18% Business and Financial Operations Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.02% Agents And Business Managers Of Artists, Performers, And Athletes</li>
<li> 0.00% Buyers And Purchasing Agents, Farm Products</li>
<li> 0.10% Wholesale And Retail Buyers, Except Farm Products</li>
<li> 0.14% Purchasing Agents, Except Wholesale, Retail, And Farm Products</li>
<li> 0.16% Claims Adjusters, Appraisers, Examiners, And Investigators</li>
<li> 0.15% Compliance Officers</li>
<li> 0.08% Cost Estimators</li>
<li> 0.40% Human Resources Workers</li>
<li> 0.04% Compensation, Benefits, And Job Analysis Specialists</li>
<li> 0.08% Training And Development Specialists</li>
<li> 0.08% Logisticians</li>
<li> 0.31% Project Management Specialists</li>
<li> 0.49% Management Analysts</li>
<li> 0.08% Meeting, Convention, And Event Planners</li>
<li> 0.04% Fundraisers</li>
<li> 0.17% Market Research Analysts And Marketing Specialists</li>
<li> 0.18% Business Operations Specialists, All Other</li>
<li> 0.85% Accountants And Auditors</li>
<li> 0.05% Property Appraisers and Assessors</li>
<li> 0.03% Budget Analysts</li>
<li> 0.02% Credit Analysts</li>
<li> 0.13% Financial And Investment Analysts</li>
<li> 0.20% Personal Financial Advisors</li>
<li> 0.06% Insurance Underwriters</li>
<li> 0.01% Financial Examiners</li>
<li> 0.16% Credit Counselors And Loan Officers</li>
<li> 0.03% Tax Examiners And Collectors, And Revenue Agents</li>
<li> 0.07% Tax Preparers</li>
<li> 0.05% Other Financial Specialists</li>
</ul>
</details>
</details>
<details><summary> 4.91% Computer, Engineering, and Science Occupations</summary>
<details><summary> 2.40% Computer and Mathematical Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.02% Computer And Information Research Scientists</li>
<li> 0.29% Computer Systems Analysts</li>
<li> 0.06% Information Security Analysts</li>
<li> 0.17% Computer Programmers</li>
<li> 0.74% Software Developers</li>
<li> 0.03% Software Quality Assurance Analysts and Testers</li>
<li> 0.05% Web Developers</li>
<li> 0.03% Web And Digital Interface Designers</li>
<li> 0.30% Computer Support Specialists</li>
<li> 0.06% Database Administrators and Architects</li>
<li> 0.11% Network And Computer Systems Administrators</li>
<li> 0.05% Computer Network Architects</li>
<li> 0.31% Computer Occupations, All Other</li>
<li> 0.02% Actuaries</li>
<li> 0.08% Operations Research Analysts</li>
<li> 0.08% Other Mathematical Science Occupations</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 1.65% Architecture and Engineering Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.10% Architects, Except Landscape And Naval</li>
<li> 0.02% Landscape Architects</li>
<li> 0.02% Surveyors, Cartographers, And Photogrammetrists</li>
<li> 0.07% Aerospace Engineers</li>
<li> 0.01% Biomedical And Agricultural Engineers</li>
<li> 0.04% Chemical Engineers</li>
<li> 0.21% Civil Engineers</li>
<li> 0.03% Computer Hardware Engineers</li>
<li> 0.13% Electrical And Electronics Engineers</li>
<li> 0.02% Environmental Engineers</li>
<li> 0.13% Industrial Engineers, Including Health And Safety</li>
<li> 0.01% Marine Engineers And Naval Architects</li>
<li> 0.03% Materials Engineers</li>
<li> 0.16% Mechanical Engineers</li>
<li> 0.02% Petroleum, Mining And Geological Engineers, Including Mining Safety Engineers</li>
<li> 0.30% Other Engineers</li>
<li> 0.03% Architectural And Civil Drafters</li>
<li> 0.05% Other Drafters</li>
<li> 0.06% Electrical And Electronic Engineering Technologists And Technicians</li>
<li> 0.20% Other Engineering Technologists And Technicians, Except Drafters</li>
<li> 0.04% Surveying And Mapping Technicians</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 0.87% Life, Physical, and Social Science Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.02% Agricultural And Food Scientists</li>
<li> 0.05% Biological Scientists</li>
<li> 0.02% Conservation Scientists And Foresters</li>
<li> 0.07% Other Life Scientists</li>
<li> 0.01% Astronomers And Physicists</li>
<li> 0.01% Atmospheric And Space Scientists</li>
<li> 0.05% Chemists And Materials Scientists</li>
<li> 0.02% Environmental Scientists And Specialists, Including Health</li>
<li> 0.03% Geoscientists And Hydrologists, Except Geographers</li>
<li> 0.15% Physical Scientists, All Other</li>
<li> 0.02% Economists</li>
<li> 0.01% Clinical And Counseling Psychologists</li>
<li> 0.03% School Psychologists</li>
<li> 0.08% Other Psychologists</li>
<li> 0.02% Urban And Regional Planners</li>
<li> 0.03% Other Social Scientists</li>
<li> 0.02% Agricultural And Food Science Technicians</li>
<li> 0.01% Biological Technicians</li>
<li> 0.04% Chemical Technicians</li>
<li> 0.01% Environmental Science and Geoscience Technicians, And Nuclear Technicians</li>
<li> 0.12% Other Life, Physical, And Social Science Technicians</li>
<li> 0.04% Occupational Health And Safety Specialists and Technicians</li>
</ul>
</details>
</details>
<details><summary> 9.34% Education, Legal, Community Service, Arts, and Media Occupations</summary>
<details><summary> 1.43% Community and Social Service Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.06% Substance Abuse And Behavioral Disorder Counselors</li>
<li> 0.19% Educational, Guidance, And Career Counselors And Advisors</li>
<li> 0.02% Marriage And Family Therapists</li>
<li> 0.06% Mental Health Counselors</li>
<li> 0.01% Rehabilitation Counselors</li>
<li> 0.10% Counselors, All Other</li>
<li> 0.03% Child, Family, And School Social Workers</li>
<li> 0.04% Healthcare Social Workers</li>
<li> 0.01% Mental Health And Substance Abuse Social Workers</li>
<li> 0.33% Social Workers, All Other</li>
<li> 0.04% Probation Officers And Correctional Treatment Specialists</li>
<li> 0.11% Social And Human Service Assistants</li>
<li> 0.05% Other Community and Social Service Specialists</li>
<li> 0.28% Clergy</li>
<li> 0.04% Directors, Religious Activities And Education</li>
<li> 0.06% Religious Workers, All Other</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 0.92% Legal Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.62% Lawyers, And Judges, Magistrates, And Other Judicial Workers</li>
<li> 0.01% Judicial Law Clerks</li>
<li> 0.21% Paralegals And Legal Assistants</li>
<li> 0.05% Title Examiners, Abstractors, and Searchers</li>
<li> 0.03% Legal Support Workers, All Other</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 5.28% Educational Instruction, and Library Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.80% Postsecondary Teachers</li>
<li> 0.42% Preschool And Kindergarten Teachers</li>
<li> 1.57% Elementary And Middle School Teachers</li>
<li> 0.71% Secondary School Teachers</li>
<li> 0.22% Special Education Teachers</li>
<li> 0.14% Tutors</li>
<li> 0.41% Other Teachers and Instructors</li>
<li> 0.04% Archivists, Curators, And Museum Technicians</li>
<li> 0.12% Librarians And Media Collections Specialists</li>
<li> 0.03% Library Technicians</li>
<li> 0.75% Teaching Assistants</li>
<li> 0.08% Other Educational Instruction and Library Workers</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 1.71% Arts, Design, Entertainment, Sports, and Media Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.14% Artists And Related Workers</li>
<li> 0.01% Commercial And Industrial Designers</li>
<li> 0.02% Fashion Designers</li>
<li> 0.04% Floral Designers</li>
<li> 0.16% Graphic Designers</li>
<li> 0.05% Interior Designers</li>
<li> 0.01% Merchandise Displayer And Windows Trimmers</li>
<li> 0.17% Other Designers</li>
<li> 0.04% Actors</li>
<li> 0.09% Producers And Directors</li>
<li> 0.02% Athletes and Sports Competitors</li>
<li> 0.15% Coaches and Scouts</li>
<li> 0.03% Umpires, Referees, And Other Sports Officials</li>
<li> 0.01% Dancers And Choreographers</li>
<li> 0.03% Music Directors and Composers</li>
<li> 0.10% Musicians and Singers</li>
<li> 0.01% Disc Jockeys, Except Radio</li>
<li> 0.02% Entertainers And Performers, Sports and Related Workers, All Other</li>
<li> 0.01% Broadcast Announcers And Radio Disc Jockeys</li>
<li> 0.04% News Analysts, Reporters, And Journalists</li>
<li> 0.06% Public Relations Specialists</li>
<li> 0.07% Editors</li>
<li> 0.03% Technical Writers</li>
<li> 0.13% Writers And Authors</li>
<li> 0.05% Interpreters and Translators</li>
<li> 0.02% Court Reporters and Simultaneous Captioners</li>
<li> 0.01% Media And Communication Workers, All Other</li>
<li> 0.05% Other Media And Communication Equipment Workers</li>
<li> 0.10% Photographers</li>
<li> 0.05% Television, Video, And Film Camera Operators And Editors</li>
</ul>
</details>
</details>
<details><summary> 4.65% Healthcare Practitioners and Technical Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.03% Chiropractors</li>
<li> 0.09% Dentists</li>
<li> 0.05% Dietitians And Nutritionists</li>
<li> 0.02% Optometrists</li>
<li> 0.16% Pharmacists</li>
<li> 0.45% Physicians</li>
<li> 0.03% Surgeons</li>
<li> 0.07% Physician Assistants</li>
<li> 0.01% Podiatrists</li>
<li> 0.01% Audiologists</li>
<li> 0.07% Occupational Therapists</li>
<li> 0.13% Physical Therapists</li>
<li> 0.01% Radiation Therapists</li>
<li> 0.01% Recreational Therapists</li>
<li> 0.05% Respiratory Therapists</li>
<li> 0.09% Speech-Language Pathologists</li>
<li> 0.08% Other Therapists</li>
<li> 0.05% Veterinarians</li>
<li> 1.62% Registered Nurses</li>
<li> 0.02% Nurse Anesthetists</li>
<li> 0.11% Nurse Practitioners, And Nurse Midwives</li>
<li> 0.01% Acupuncturists</li>
<li> 0.01% Healthcare Diagnosing Or Treating Practitioners, All Other</li>
<li> 0.16% Clinical Laboratory Technologists And Technicians</li>
<li> 0.10% Dental Hygienists</li>
<li> 0.02% Cardiovascular Technologists and Technicians</li>
<li> 0.04% Diagnostic Medical Sonographers</li>
<li> 0.11% Radiologic Technologists And Technicians</li>
<li> 0.02% Magnetic Resonance Imaging Technologists</li>
<li> 0.01% Nuclear Medicine Technologists and Medical Dosimetrists</li>
<li> 0.06% Emergency Medical Technicians</li>
<li> 0.06% Paramedics</li>
<li> 0.16% Pharmacy Technicians</li>
<li> 0.03% Psychiatric Technicians</li>
<li> 0.05% Surgical Technologists</li>
<li> 0.07% Veterinary Technologists and Technicians</li>
<li> 0.03% Dietetic Technicians And Ophthalmic Medical Technicians</li>
<li> 0.32% Licensed Practical And Licensed Vocational Nurses</li>
<li> 0.09% Medical Records Specialists</li>
<li> 0.03% Opticians, Dispensing</li>
<li> 0.07% Miscellaneous Health Technologists and Technicians</li>
<li> 0.05% Other Healthcare Practitioners and Technical Occupations</li>
</ul>
</details>
</details>
<details><summary>12.86% Service Occupations</summary>
<details><summary> 2.29% Healthcare Support Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.24% Home Health Aides</li>
<li> 0.66% Personal Care Aides</li>
<li> 0.59% Nursing Assistants</li>
<li> 0.03% Orderlies and Psychiatric Aides</li>
<li> 0.03% Occupational Therapy Assistants And Aides</li>
<li> 0.06% Physical Therapist Assistants And Aides</li>
<li> 0.09% Massage Therapists</li>
<li> 0.14% Dental Assistants</li>
<li> 0.24% Medical Assistants</li>
<li> 0.03% Medical Transcriptionists</li>
<li> 0.02% Pharmacy Aides</li>
<li> 0.03% Veterinary Assistants And Laboratory Animal Caretakers</li>
<li> 0.05% Phlebotomists</li>
<li> 0.08% Other Healthcare Support Workers</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 1.69% Protective Service Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.02% First-Line Supervisors Of Correctional Officers</li>
<li> 0.06% First-Line Supervisors Of Police And Detectives</li>
<li> 0.03% First-Line Supervisors Of Firefighting And Prevention Workers</li>
<li> 0.04% Miscellaneous First-Line Supervisors, Protective Service Workers</li>
<li> 0.16% Firefighters</li>
<li> 0.01% Fire Inspectors</li>
<li> 0.01% Bailiffs</li>
<li> 0.18% Correctional Officers and Jailers</li>
<li> 0.07% Detectives And Criminal Investigators</li>
<li> 0.01% Fish And Game Wardens And Parking Enforcement Officers</li>
<li> 0.38% Police Officers</li>
<li> 0.01% Animal Control Workers</li>
<li> 0.05% Private Detectives And Investigators</li>
<li> 0.44% Security Guards And Gambling Surveillance Officers</li>
<li> 0.03% Crossing Guards And Flaggers</li>
<li> 0.02% Transportation Security Screeners</li>
<li> 0.02% School Bus Monitors</li>
<li> 0.15% Other Protective Service Workers</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 4.05% Food Preparation and Serving Related Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.21% Chefs And Head Cooks</li>
<li> 0.23% First-Line Supervisors Of Food Preparation And Serving Workers</li>
<li> 1.04% Cooks</li>
<li> 0.48% Food Preparation Workers</li>
<li> 0.19% Bartenders</li>
<li> 0.34% Fast Food And Counter Workers</li>
<li> 0.95% Waiters And Waitresses</li>
<li> 0.09% Food Servers, Nonrestaurant</li>
<li> 0.16% Dining Room And Cafeteria Attendants And Bartender Helpers</li>
<li> 0.18% Dishwashers</li>
<li> 0.17% Hosts And Hostesses, Restaurant, Lounge, And Coffee Shop</li>
<li> 0.01% Food Preparation and Serving Related Workers, All Other</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 2.68% Building and Grounds Cleaning and Maintenance Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.11% First-Line Supervisors Of Housekeeping And Janitorial Workers</li>
<li> 0.07% First-Line Supervisors Of Landscaping, Lawn Service, And Groundskeeping Workers</li>
<li> 1.21% Janitors And Building Cleaners</li>
<li> 0.62% Maids And Housekeeping Cleaners</li>
<li> 0.04% Pest Control Workers</li>
<li> 0.58% Landscaping And Groundskeeping Workers</li>
<li> 0.04% Tree Trimmers and Pruners</li>
<li> 0.01% Other Grounds Maintenance Workers</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 2.15% Personal Care and Service Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.05% Supervisors Of Personal Care And Service Workers</li>
<li> 0.03% Animal Trainers</li>
<li> 0.15% Animal Caretakers</li>
<li> 0.05% Gambling Services Workers</li>
<li> 0.03% Ushers, Lobby Attendants, And Ticket Takers</li>
<li> 0.15% Other Entertainment Attendants And Related Workers</li>
<li> 0.01% Embalmers, Crematory Operators And Funeral Attendants</li>
<li> 0.02% Morticians, Undertakers, And Funeral Arrangers</li>
<li> 0.05% Barbers</li>
<li> 0.37% Hairdressers, Hairstylists, And Cosmetologists</li>
<li> 0.10% Manicurists And Pedicurists</li>
<li> 0.03% Skincare Specialists</li>
<li> 0.01% Other Personal Appearance Workers</li>
<li> 0.04% Baggage Porters, Bellhops, And Concierges</li>
<li> 0.05% Tour And Travel Guides</li>
<li> 0.56% Childcare Workers</li>
<li> 0.13% Exercise Trainers And Group Fitness Instructors</li>
<li> 0.17% Recreation Workers</li>
<li> 0.06% Residential Advisors</li>
<li> 0.07% Personal Care and Service Workers, All Other</li>
</ul>
</details>
</details>
<details><summary>15.79% Sales and Office Occupations</summary>
<details><summary> 7.40% Sales and Related Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 1.36% First-Line Supervisors Of Retail Sales Workers</li>
<li> 0.52% First-Line Supervisors Of Non-Retail Sales Workers</li>
<li> 1.57% Cashiers</li>
<li> 0.04% Counter And Rental Clerks</li>
<li> 0.06% Parts Salespersons</li>
<li> 1.60% Retail Salespersons</li>
<li> 0.06% Advertising Sales Agents</li>
<li> 0.29% Insurance Sales Agents</li>
<li> 0.11% Securities, Commodities, And Financial Services Sales Agents</li>
<li> 0.04% Travel Agents</li>
<li> 0.30% Sales Representatives Of Services, Except Advertising, Insurance, Financial Services, And Travel</li>
<li> 0.65% Sales Representatives, Wholesale And Manufacturing</li>
<li> 0.03% Models, Demonstrators, And Product Promoters</li>
<li> 0.49% Real Estate Brokers And Sales Agents</li>
<li> 0.03% Sales Engineers</li>
<li> 0.02% Telemarketers</li>
<li> 0.06% Door-To-Door Sales Workers, News And Street Vendors, And Related Workers</li>
<li> 0.16% Sales And Related Workers, All Other</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 8.40% Office and Administrative Support Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.52% First-Line Supervisors Of Office And Administrative Support Workers</li>
<li> 0.01% Switchboard Operators, Including Answering Service</li>
<li> 0.02% Telephone Operators</li>
<li> 0.01% Communications Equipment Operators, All Other</li>
<li> 0.06% Bill And Account Collectors</li>
<li> 0.22% Billing And Posting Clerks</li>
<li> 0.66% Bookkeeping, Accounting, And Auditing Clerks</li>
<li> 0.08% Payroll And Timekeeping Clerks</li>
<li> 0.02% Procurement Clerks</li>
<li> 0.15% Tellers</li>
<li> 0.06% Other Financial Clerks</li>
<li> 0.04% Court, Municipal, And License Clerks</li>
<li> 0.02% Credit Authorizers, Checkers, And Clerks</li>
<li> 1.25% Customer Service Representatives</li>
<li> 0.04% Eligibility Interviewers, Government Programs</li>
<li> 0.09% File Clerks</li>
<li> 0.07% Hotel, Motel, And Resort Desk Clerks</li>
<li> 0.09% Interviewers, Except Eligibility And Loan</li>
<li> 0.07% Library Assistants, Clerical</li>
<li> 0.06% Loan Interviewers And Clerks</li>
<li> 0.01% New Accounts Clerks</li>
<li> 0.05% Correspondence Clerks And Order Clerks</li>
<li> 0.03% Human Resources Assistants, Except Payroll And Timekeeping</li>
<li> 0.63% Receptionists And Information Clerks</li>
<li> 0.06% Reservation And Transportation Ticket Agents And Travel Clerks</li>
<li> 0.07% Other Information And Records Clerks</li>
<li> 0.01% Cargo And Freight Agents</li>
<li> 0.15% Couriers And Messengers</li>
<li> 0.05% Public Safety Telecommunicators</li>
<li> 0.09% Dispatchers, Except Police, Fire, And Ambulance</li>
<li> 0.01% Meter Readers, Utilities</li>
<li> 0.07% Postal Service Clerks</li>
<li> 0.18% Postal Service Mail Carriers</li>
<li> 0.03% Postal Service Mail Sorters, Processors, And Processing Machine Operators</li>
<li> 0.15% Production, Planning, And Expediting Clerks</li>
<li> 0.28% Shipping, Receiving, And Inventory Clerks</li>
<li> 0.04% Weighers, Measurers, Checkers, And Samplers, Recordkeeping</li>
<li> 0.14% Executive Secretaries And Executive Administrative Assistants</li>
<li> 0.04% Legal Secretaries and Administrative Assistants</li>
<li> 0.04% Medical Secretaries and Administrative Assistants</li>
<li> 1.34% Secretaries And Administrative Assistants, Except Legal, Medical, And Executive</li>
<li> 0.16% Data Entry Keyers</li>
<li> 0.03% Word Processors And Typists</li>
<li> 0.09% Insurance Claims And Policy Processing Clerks</li>
<li> 0.04% Mail Clerks And Mail Machine Operators, Except Postal Service</li>
<li> 0.71% Office Clerks, General</li>
<li> 0.02% Office Machine Operators, Except Computer</li>
<li> 0.01% Proofreaders And Copy Markers</li>
<li> 0.01% Statistical Assistants</li>
<li> 0.32% Other Office And Administrative Support Workers</li>
</ul>
</details>
</details>
<details><summary> 6.56% Natural Resources, Construction, and Maintenance Occupations</summary>
<details><summary> 0.55% Farming, Fishing, and Forestry Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.02% First-Line Supervisors Of Farming, Fishing, And Forestry Workers</li>
<li> 0.01% Agricultural Inspectors</li>
<li> 0.03% Graders And Sorters, Agricultural Products</li>
<li> 0.42% Other Agricultural Workers</li>
<li> 0.03% Fishing And Hunting Workers</li>
<li> 0.01% Forest And Conservation Workers</li>
<li> 0.04% Logging Workers</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 3.64% Construction and Extraction Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.31% First-Line Supervisors Of Construction Trades And Extraction Workers</li>
<li> 0.01% Boilermakers</li>
<li> 0.07% Brickmasons, Blockmasons, Stonemasons, And Reinforcing Iron And Rebar Workers</li>
<li> 0.59% Carpenters</li>
<li> 0.06% Carpet, Floor, And Tile Installers And Finishers</li>
<li> 0.03% Cement Masons, Concrete Finishers, And Terrazzo Workers</li>
<li> 0.78% Construction Laborers</li>
<li> 0.22% Construction Equipment Operators</li>
<li> 0.05% Drywall Installers, Ceiling Tile Installers, And Tapers</li>
<li> 0.44% Electricians</li>
<li> 0.02% Glaziers</li>
<li> 0.02% Insulation Workers</li>
<li> 0.24% Painters and Paperhangers</li>
<li> 0.02% Pipelayers</li>
<li> 0.28% Plumbers, Pipefitters, And Steamfitters</li>
<li> 0.01% Plasterers And Stucco Masons</li>
<li> 0.09% Roofers</li>
<li> 0.07% Sheet Metal Workers</li>
<li> 0.03% Structural Iron And Steel Workers</li>
<li> 0.01% Solar Photovoltaic Installers</li>
<li> 0.02% Helpers, Construction Trades</li>
<li> 0.06% Construction And Building Inspectors</li>
<li> 0.01% Elevator And Escalator Installers And Repairers</li>
<li> 0.01% Fence Erectors</li>
<li> 0.01% Hazardous Materials Removal Workers</li>
<li> 0.05% Highway Maintenance Workers</li>
<li> 0.00% Rail-Track Laying And Maintenance Equipment Operators</li>
<li> 0.02% Other Construction And Related Workers</li>
<li> 0.02% Derrick, Rotary Drill, And Service Unit Operators, And Roustabouts, Oil, Gas, And Mining</li>
<li> 0.02% Surface Mining Machine Operators And Earth Drillers</li>
<li> 0.01% Explosives Workers, Ordnance Handling Experts, and Blasters</li>
<li> 0.03% Underground Mining Machine Operators</li>
<li> 0.03% Other Extraction Workers</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 2.37% Installation, Maintenance, and Repair Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.12% First-Line Supervisors Of Mechanics, Installers, And Repairers</li>
<li> 0.07% Computer, Automated Teller, And Office Machine Repairers</li>
<li> 0.08% Radio And Telecommunications Equipment Installers And Repairers</li>
<li> 0.01% Avionics Technicians</li>
<li> 0.01% Electric Motor, Power Tool, And Related Repairers</li>
<li> 0.02% Other Electrical And Electronic Equipment Mechanics, Installers, And Repairers</li>
<li> 0.01% Audiovisual Equipment Installers And Repairers</li>
<li> 0.02% Security And Fire Alarm Systems Installers</li>
<li> 0.09% Aircraft Mechanics And Service Technicians</li>
<li> 0.07% Automotive Body And Related Repairers</li>
<li> 0.01% Automotive Glass Installers And Repairers</li>
<li> 0.39% Automotive Service Technicians And Mechanics</li>
<li> 0.15% Bus And Truck Mechanics And Diesel Engine Specialists</li>
<li> 0.12% Heavy Vehicle And Mobile Equipment Service Technicians And Mechanics</li>
<li> 0.03% Small Engine Mechanics</li>
<li> 0.04% Miscellaneous Vehicle And Mobile Equipment Mechanics, Installers, And Repairers</li>
<li> 0.01% Control And Valve Installers And Repairers</li>
<li> 0.20% Heating, Air Conditioning, And Refrigeration Mechanics And Installers</li>
<li> 0.02% Home Appliance Repairers</li>
<li> 0.20% Industrial And Refractory Machinery Mechanics</li>
<li> 0.34% Maintenance And Repair Workers, General</li>
<li> 0.02% Maintenance Workers, Machinery</li>
<li> 0.03% Millwrights</li>
<li> 0.06% Electrical Power-Line Installers And Repairers</li>
<li> 0.06% Telecommunications Line Installers And Repairers</li>
<li> 0.03% Precision Instrument And Equipment Repairers</li>
<li> 0.02% Coin, Vending, And Amusement Machine Servicers And Repairers</li>
<li> 0.01% Locksmiths And Safe Repairers</li>
<li> 0.00% Riggers</li>
<li> 0.01% Helpers--Installation, Maintenance, And Repair Workers</li>
<li> 0.11% Other Installation, Maintenance, And Repair Workers</li>
</ul>
</details>
</details>
<details><summary> 9.81% Production, Transportation, and Material Moving Occupations</summary>
<details><summary> 4.19% Production Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.37% First-Line Supervisors Of Production And Operating Workers</li>
<li> 0.06% Electrical, Electronics, And Electromechanical Assemblers</li>
<li> 0.01% Engine And Other Machine Assemblers</li>
<li> 0.01% Structural Metal Fabricators And Fitters</li>
<li> 0.48% Other Assemblers And Fabricators</li>
<li> 0.10% Bakers</li>
<li> 0.10% Butchers And Other Meat, Poultry, And Fish Processing Workers</li>
<li> 0.01% Food And Tobacco Roasting, Baking, And Drying Machine Operators And Tenders</li>
<li> 0.04% Food Batchmakers</li>
<li> 0.01% Food Cooking Machine Operators And Tenders</li>
<li> 0.06% Food Processing Workers, All Other</li>
<li> 0.06% Computer Numerically Controlled Tool Operators And Programmers</li>
<li> 0.02% Forming Machine Setters, Operators, And Tenders, Metal And Plastic</li>
<li> 0.04% Cutting, Punching, And Press Machine Setters, Operators, And Tenders, Metal And Plastic</li>
<li> 0.02% Grinding, Lapping, Polishing, And Buffing Machine Tool Setters, Operators, And Tenders, Metal And Plastic</li>
<li> 0.01% Other Machine Tool Setters, Operators, And Tenders, Metal and Plastic</li>
<li> 0.19% Machinists</li>
<li> 0.01% Metal Furnace Operators, Tenders, Pourers, And Casters</li>
<li> 0.02% Model Makers, Patternmakers, And Molding Machine Setters, Metal And Plastic</li>
<li> 0.03% Tool And Die Makers</li>
<li> 0.30% Welding, Soldering, And Brazing Workers</li>
<li> 0.19% Other Metal Workers And Plastic Workers</li>
<li> 0.01% Prepress Technicians And Workers</li>
<li> 0.08% Printing Press Operators</li>
<li> 0.01% Print Binding And Finishing Workers</li>
<li> 0.07% Laundry And Dry-Cleaning Workers</li>
<li> 0.02% Pressers, Textile, Garment, And Related Materials</li>
<li> 0.08% Sewing Machine Operators</li>
<li> 0.01% Shoe And Leather Workers</li>
<li> 0.04% Tailors, Dressmakers, And Sewers</li>
<li> 0.01% Textile Machine Setters, Operators, And Tenders</li>
<li> 0.02% Upholsterers</li>
<li> 0.01% Other Textile, Apparel, And Furnishings Workers</li>
<li> 0.03% Cabinetmakers And Bench Carpenters</li>
<li> 0.01% Furniture Finishers</li>
<li> 0.02% Sawing Machine Setters, Operators, And Tenders, Wood</li>
<li> 0.01% Woodworking Machine Setters, Operators, And Tenders, Except Sawing</li>
<li> 0.02% Other Woodworkers</li>
<li> 0.03% Power Plant Operators, Distributors, And Dispatchers</li>
<li> 0.06% Stationary Engineers And Boiler Operators</li>
<li> 0.05% Water And Wastewater Treatment Plant And System Operators</li>
<li> 0.02% Miscellaneous Plant And System Operators</li>
<li> 0.03% Chemical Processing Machine Setters, Operators, And Tenders</li>
<li> 0.04% Crushing, Grinding, Polishing, Mixing, And Blending Workers</li>
<li> 0.04% Cutting Workers</li>
<li> 0.01% Extruding, Forming, Pressing, And Compacting Machine Setters, Operators, And Tenders</li>
<li> 0.01% Furnace, Kiln, Oven, Drier, And Kettle Operators And Tenders</li>
<li> 0.40% Inspectors, Testers, Sorters, Samplers, And Weighers</li>
<li> 0.02% Jewelers And Precious Stone And Metal Workers</li>
<li> 0.04% Dental And Ophthalmic Laboratory Technicians And Medical Appliance Technicians</li>
<li> 0.12% Packaging And Filling Machine Operators And Tenders</li>
<li> 0.07% Painting Workers</li>
<li> 0.01% Photographic Process Workers And Processing Machine Operators</li>
<li> 0.01% Adhesive Bonding Machine Operators And Tenders</li>
<li> 0.00% Etchers And Engravers</li>
<li> 0.01% Molders, Shapers, And Casters, Except Metal And Plastic</li>
<li> 0.01% Paper Goods Machine Setters, Operators, And Tenders</li>
<li> 0.01% Tire Builders</li>
<li> 0.04% Helpers--Production Workers</li>
<li> 0.59% Miscellaneous Production Workers, Including Equipment Operators And Tenders</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 5.61% Transportation and Material Moving Occupations</summary>
<details><summary> 2.93% Transportation Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.12% Supervisors Of Transportation And Material Moving Workers</li>
<li> 0.11% Aircraft Pilots And Flight Engineers</li>
<li> 0.02% Air Traffic Controllers And Airfield Operations Specialists</li>
<li> 0.05% Flight Attendants</li>
<li> 0.00% Ambulance Drivers And Attendants, Except Emergency Medical Technicians</li>
<li> 0.18% Bus Drivers, School</li>
<li> 0.12% Bus Drivers, Transit And Intercity</li>
<li> 1.74% Driver/Sales Workers And Truck Drivers</li>
<li> 0.05% Shuttle Drivers And Chauffeurs</li>
<li> 0.19% Taxi Drivers</li>
<li> 0.09% Motor Vehicle Operators, All Other</li>
<li> 0.02% Locomotive Engineers And Operators</li>
<li> 0.02% Railroad Conductors And Yardmasters</li>
<li> 0.01% Other Rail Transportation Workers</li>
<li> 0.02% Sailors And Marine Oilers, And Ship Engineers</li>
<li> 0.03% Ship And Boat Captains And Operators</li>
<li> 0.04% Parking Attendants</li>
<li> 0.05% Transportation Service Attendants</li>
<li> 0.02% Transportation Inspectors</li>
<li> 0.02% Passenger Attendants</li>
<li> 0.01% Other Transportation Workers</li>
</ul>
</details>
<details><summary> 2.69% Material Moving Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.03% Crane And Tower Operators</li>
<li> 0.01% Conveyor, Dredge, And Hoist and Winch Operators</li>
<li> 0.27% Industrial Truck And Tractor Operators</li>
<li> 0.17% Cleaners Of Vehicles And Equipment</li>
<li> 1.14% Laborers And Freight, Stock, And Material Movers, Hand</li>
<li> 0.02% Machine Feeders And Offbearers</li>
<li> 0.22% Packers And Packagers, Hand</li>
<li> 0.73% Stockers And Order Fillers</li>
<li> 0.01% Pumping Station Operators</li>
<li> 0.04% Refuse And Recyclable Material Collectors</li>
<li> 0.04% Other Material Moving Workers</li>
</ul>
</details>
</details>
</details>
<details><summary> 0.27% Military Specific Occupations</summary>
<ul>
<li> 0.03% Military Officer Special And Tactical Operations Leaders</li>
<li> 0.03% First-Line Enlisted Military Supervisors</li>
<li> 0.09% Military Enlisted Tactical Operations And Air/Weapons Specialists And Crew Members</li>
<li> 0.13% Military, Rank Not Specified</li>
</ul></details>
<ul>
<li> 0.12% Unemployed, With No Work Experience In The Last 5 Years Or Earlier Or Never Worked</li>
<li>23.07% Unspecified</li>
</ul>

<p>This is a breakdown of all people with positive personal income. 23%
of people with income don't have an occupation reported.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“It will be helpful to you if you always assume your categories are
misleading.” (Hans Rosling, Factfulness, page 158)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A while ago this kind of data was used to claim that “truck driver”
was the most common job in the US. That was <a href="https://www.marketwatch.com/story/no-truck-driver-isnt-the-most-common-job-in-your-state-2015-02-12" title="Opinion: No, ‘truck driver’ isn’t the most common job in your state">debunked</a>, but even the
debunking didn't do a great job of showing the impact of how we group
jobs together. The hierarchical view (using the census occupation code
<a href="https://www2.census.gov/programs-surveys/demo/guidance/industry-occupation/2018-occupation-code-list-and-crosswalk.xlsx" title="2018 Census Occupation Code List">list</a>) is somewhat helpful in this respect, I think.</p>
<p>While “Driver/Sales Workers And Truck Drivers” at 1.74% is the largest
non-“other”-titled category, you can see that there are significantly
more people working at K-12 schools, for example, across various
subcategories of teachers.</p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220702-what_are_people_doing/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220702-what_are_people_doing/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Ministry for the Future, by Robinson</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>576 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Ministry_for_the_Future" title="The Ministry for the Future">pages</a> in 106 chapters. One from POV of the market. Another: a
photon. Writing often in this style. One chapter a list of NGOs by
country. Repeated references to Zürich's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ganymed_%28Z%C3%BCrich%29" title="Ganymed (Zürich)">statue</a> of Ganymede.
Eco-fantasy from a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kim_Stanley_Robinson" title="Kim Stanley Robinson">lover</a> of Antarctica. Largely okay with
terrorism.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>Here are some of the core predictions and my thoughts on them:</p>
<ul>
<li>The rich will start caring about poor people affected by climate
   disasters.<ul>
<li>In the book a heatwave kills 20 million people in India,
   jump-starting a lot of action. Certainly people would take
   note, but I'm not sure even this kind of disaster would
   catalyze global empathy.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Eco-terrorism will lead to lots of good changes to behavior and
   policy.<ul>
<li>People deliberately give cows mad cow disease, so people stop
   eating meat. Lots of planes are crashed by swarms of drones, so
   people stop flying. I think it's unlikely the crimes would be
   committed, and I think if they were it's still unlikely the
   changes would result.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Agriculture will all switch to organic and it will go great.<ul>
<li>The author references <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sikkim" title="Sikkim">Sikkim</a> as an organic success story.
   More recently, it's hard not to think of the failure in
   <a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2022/03/05/sri-lanka-organic-farming-crisis/" title="In Sri Lanka, Organic Farming Went Catastrophically Wrong">Sri Lanka</a>. I don't think the world wants to have
   agriculture be more labor-intensive and less productive.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Everyone will switch to one privacy-first internet service.<ul>
<li>In the book it's called "YourLock" and it isn't clear how it
   works. Quantum encryption doesn't make this suddenly something
   people will want to use.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Blockchain-based "carbon coin" will encourage carbon sequestration.<ul>
<li>The book has all fiat currency becoming blockchain-based, and
   also central banks issue these "carbon coins" with guarantees
   on their value increasing over time. The author is really
   jazzed about this but I don't know why it's that much better
   than direct compensation in fiat currency, for example.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Modern Monetary Theory is right: You can print money without
   causing inflation.<ul>
<li>This probably seemed realistic in 2020. In 2022, it seems
   suspect.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>We're going post-capitalism.<ul>
<li>The author isn't super clear, in places favoring central
   planning that works (because of AI?) and elsewhere holding up
   <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mondragon_Corporation" title="Mondragon Corporation">Mondragón</a> and unions as exemplars.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Guaranteed jobs for all!<ul>
<li>Is a guaranteed job different from Universal Basic Income?
   (What prevents me from not turning up and just collecting the
   pay? If you can be fired is it a guaranteed job?)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>10x max ratio from lowest to highest income.<ul>
<li>Hmm! Would this be cool?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Global refugee passports<ul>
<li>This seems nice!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Airships<ul>
<li>At least this is sort of a plausible story for why we would use
   airships (to avoid burning carbon). Better story than
   steam-punk.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>As a novel, it's not great. As a collection of ideas to think about,
it does introduce a few, but it's not very convincing. It does prompt
some thought. What's really going to happen?</p>
<p>A few quotes follow.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"For a while, therefore, it looked like the great heat wave would be
like mass shootings in the United States—mourned by all, deplored by
all, and then immediately forgotten or superseded by the next one,
until they came in a daily drumbeat and became the new normal."
(page 25)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Ideology, n. An imaginary relationship to a real situation. In
common usage, what the other person has, especially when
systematically distorting the facts. But it seems to us that an
ideology is a necessary feature of cognition, and if anyone were to
lack one, which we doubt, they would be badly disabled. There is a
real situation, that can’t be denied, but it is too big for any
individual to know in full, and so we must create our understanding
by way of an act of the imagination. So we all have an ideology, and
this is a good thing. So much information pours into the mind,
ranging from sensory experience to discursive and mediated inputs of
all kinds, that some kind of personal organizing system is necessary
to make sense of things in ways that allow one to decide and to act.
Worldview, philosophy, religion, these are all synonyms for ideology
as defined above; and so is science, although it’s the different
one, the special one, by way of its perpetual cross-checking with
reality tests of all kinds, and its continuous sharpening of focus.
That surely makes science central to a most interesting project,
which is to invent, improve, and put to use an ideology that
explains in a coherent and useful way as much of the blooming
buzzing inrush of the world as possible. What one would hope for in
an ideology is clarity and explanatory breadth, and power. We leave
the proof of this as an exercise for the reader." (page 42)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"And yet even primitive math still takes mathematicians, the rest of
us being so clueless." (page 60)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"One-eight-billionth wasn’t a very big fraction, but then again
there were poisons that worked in the parts-per-billion range, so it
wasn’t entirely unprecedented for such a small agent to change
things." (page 65)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Indian agriculture moving into its post–green revolution is also a
giant step toward independent subtropical knowledge production,
achieved in collaboration with Indonesian and African and South
American permaculturists, and its importance going forward cannot be
over-emphasized." (page 126)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Volatile people, you can’t trust them, that’s the thing; and they
know it." (page 154)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Demonstrations are parties. People party and then go home. Nothing
changes." (page 156)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jevons_paradox" title="Jevons paradox">Jevons paradox</a> (page 165)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The capitalizing of state power now had its roots in private
wealth; thus the rich and the state became co-dependents, two
aspects of the same power structure." (page 211)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PIGS_(economics)" title="PIGS (economics)">PIIGS</a> (page 213)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The War for the Earth is often said to have begun on Crash Day."
(page 229)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(When a bunch of airplanes were taken down all at once by drones.)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I don’t own my kids’ teacher, I don’t own my doctor, I don’t need
to own my house." (page 248)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The Götterdämmerung Syndrome, as with most violent pathologies, is
more often seen in men than women. It is often interpreted as an
example of narcissistic rage. Those who feel it are usually
privileged and entitled, and they become extremely angry when their
privileges and sense of entitlement are being taken away. If then
their choice gets reduced to admitting they are in error or
destroying the world, a reduction they often feel to be the case,
the obvious choice for them is to destroy the world; for they cannot
admit they have ever erred." (page 298)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Make the next political economy. Invent post-capitalism!" (page
317)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"No conspiracy theories, please, so fucking tedious those people—as
if things secretly made sense!" (page 408)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"They had created and paid out trillions of carbon coins, and yet
had seen no signs of inflation, or deflation, for those who held
that theory; no noticeable price change." (page 420)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This made for a kind of double standard, or rather something
finally to replace the lost gold standard; they had now a carbon
standard, and also the dollar to use for exchanges." (page 454)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Setting a generous definition of a universal necessary income,
guaranteeing jobs to all, and capping personal annual income at ten
times that minimum amount, as they had done in many countries, had
immediately crushed Gini figures down. The EU had led the way, the
US and China had followed, and then everywhere else had begun to
leak their most educated young people to these flatter countries,
until the countries losing educated people also instituted it.
Guaranteed jobs, yes, but also universal basic services, and
supported social reproduction, along with infrastructure and housing
construction projects, had completed the rise out of poverty at the
low end of the world income scale." (page 478)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Looking at the central bankers listening attentively to her, Mary
saw it again; these people were as close to rulers of the world as
existed." (page 510)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><img alt="statue" src="statue.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220625-ministry_future_robinson/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220625-ministry_future_robinson/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nielsen's Quantum Country</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>You can understand the force of gravity as proportional to one over
distance squared without understanding why that should be, and this is
the manner in which Nielsen explains quantum mechanics in his
<a href="https://quantum.country/" title="Quantum Country">series of essays</a>—and with considerable clarity.</p>
<p><img alt="summary" src="summary.jpg"></p>
<p>I knew <a href="https://michaelnielsen.org/" title="Michael Nielsen">Nielsen</a> first from his book
<a href="http://neuralnetworksanddeeplearning.com/" title="Neural Networks and Deep Learning">Neural Networks and Deep Learning</a>. I hadn't realized he was a
quantum physicist first! His popular <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Quantum-Computation-Information-10th-Anniversary/dp/1107002176" title="Quantum Computation and Quantum Information">textbook</a> with Chuang was
published in 2001, and his YouTube series
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL1826E60FD05B44E4" title="Quantum computing for the determined">Quantum computing for the determined</a> came out in 2010. So the 2019
<a href="https://quantum.country/" title="Quantum Country">Quantum Country</a> was a return to the topic.</p>
<p><a href="https://andymatuschak.org/" title="Andy Matuschak">Matuschak</a> is a co-author on the project, and my guess is he built
the “mnemonic medium” it uses. There are flashcards. The
implementation relies on an account mechanism that doesn't work very
well. I love spaced repetition (<a href="/20201009-anki_is_easy/" title="Anki is easy">1</a>, <a href="/20210908-spaced_repetition_is_o_log_n_sustainable/" title="Spaced repetition is O(log n) sustainable">2</a>) but I think the strength
of the project is Nielsen's exposition.</p>
<p>A few takeaways in addition to the summary image above:</p>
<ul>
<li>Entanglement is key: Probabilities are not independent, which is
   how you get the exponential capability of quantum computing with
   more qubits. (See nutshell #4.)<ul>
<li>The usual entangled pair is just one where all the probability
   is on 00 and 11, with none on 01 or 10.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Quantum search gives \( O(\sqrt{n}) \) general performance.
   (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shor%27s_algorithm" title="Shor's algorithm">Shor's factoring</a> is faster but not much covered in the text.)</li>
<li>Quantum teleportation does <em>not</em> move information faster than the
   speed of light, because you have to send classical information as
   part of the procedure.</li>
</ul>
<p>A few explicitly unresolved issues:</p>
<ul>
<li>How do we feel, after <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bell%27s_theorem" title="Bell's theorem">Bell inequality</a> results, about not having
   <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principle_of_locality#Quantum_mechanics">local realism</a>? (I would rather give up locality, I guess, but
   Nielsen suggests giving up realism. Trippy.)</li>
<li>The interpretation problem: What does a quantum state even mean?</li>
<li>The measurement problem: What does it even mean to measure a
   system?</li>
</ul>
<p>The whole thing is great. Fun with linear algebra! Check it out!</p>
<!-- mathjax for formulas -->

    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220622-nielsen_quantum_country/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220622-nielsen_quantum_country/</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Ride of a Lifetime, by Iger</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob_Iger" title="Bob Iger">Bob</a> starts chapter one with “This book is not a memoir,” so you
know from the start you're dealing with an unreliable narrator.
Compared to Catmull in <a href="/20220213-creativity_inc_by_catmull/" title="Creativity, Inc., by Catmull">Creativity, Inc.</a>, Iger does seem more
direct, and his experiences are interesting, but I like Iger less, I
think.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>Here are Iger's ten principles from the prologue:</p>
<ol>
<li>Optimism</li>
<li>Courage</li>
<li>Focus</li>
<li>Decisiveness</li>
<li>Curiosity</li>
<li>Fairness</li>
<li>Thoughtfulness</li>
<li>Authenticity</li>
<li>The Relentless Pursuit of Perfection</li>
<li>Integrity</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>On page 9, you get a story of how some coworker exposed himself to
Iger.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As for all the glamour, there is (and eventually there was) a
convincing argument to be made that living that high off the hog was
irresponsible." (page 14)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I wonder if the old TV business is analogous to the current tech
scene...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I’ve found that often people will focus on little details as a way
of masking a lack of any clear, coherent, big thoughts." (page 43)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is legit.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I wouldn’t as a rule recommend promoting someone as rapidly as they
promoted me," (page 49)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>haha~</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I wanted the merger to go well, and I wanted to make sure the
Capital Cities team was treated well by Disney. Without me there, I
was fairly certain they would get subsumed by Disney in potentially
dispiriting ways." (page 53)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This guy, huh?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Managing your own time and respecting others’ time is one of the
most vital things to do as a manager," (page 63)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Concur.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"these are the people to nurture—not the ones who are clamoring for
promotions and complaining about not being utilized enough but the
ones who are proving themselves to be indispensable day in and day
out." (page 66)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Concur.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"He wanted the “albino Mickeys,” as he called them, taken from the
shelves, which we didn’t do, but it was a huge distraction." (page
87)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Crazy micro-managing board member...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I’ve always prided myself on my ability and willingness to put in a
greater effort than anyone else." (page 104)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This guy, huh? He elsewhere makes a point of how he didn't take a
two-week vacation until late in his career.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I could control what I did and how I comported myself. Everything
else was beyond my control." (page 109)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>See also: <a href="/20210107-enchiridion_in_52_sentences/" title="The Enchiridion in 52 sentences">The Enchiridion</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"pushing strategic responsibility back to the businesses sooner
rather than later. I hoped that if we could reduce the grip that
Strat Planning had over all of our divisions, we would slowly begin
to restore the company’s morale." (page 116)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is one of the more interesting things he actually did, moving
toward more decentralization. Seems good.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We landed on Twitter." (page 190)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I didn't realize Disney had been close to acquiring Twitter!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Twitter was a potentially powerful platform for us, but I couldn’t
get past the challenges that would come with it. The challenges and
controversies were almost too much to list, but they included how to
manage hate speech, and making fraught decisions regarding freedom
of speech, what to do about fake accounts algorithmically spewing
out political “messaging” to influence elections, and the general
rage and lack of civility that was sometimes evident on the
platform. Those would become our problems. They were so unlike any
we’d encountered, and I felt they would be corrosive to the Disney
brand. On the Sunday after the board had just given me the go-ahead
to pursue the acquisition of Twitter, I sent a note to all of the
members telling them I had “cold feet,” and explaining my reasoning
for withdrawing. Then I called Jack Dorsey, Twitter’s CEO, who was
also a member of the Disney board. Jack was stunned, but very
polite. I wished Jack luck, and I hung up feeling relieved." (page
190)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I would decide at the end of each year how much stock would vest,
and that it was going to be based not on revenue but on how well
they were able to work together. “I don’t want any politics,” I
said. “This is too important. It’s for the good of the company, and
it’s good for you. I need you to step up.”" (page 196)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is interesting too; kind of the reverse of decentralization, but
I like how it gets away from purely quantified compensation.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"My new retirement date is December 2021," (page 221)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob_Iger" title="Bob Iger">Bob</a>'s Wikipedia page makes it seem like this was not the initial
plan, but here it seems like it was?</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Esther Newberg, for your guidance and for talking me into writing
this book. You said it was going to be easy and you sure were
wrong!" (page 236)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220620-ride_of_a_lifetime_by_iger/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220620-ride_of_a_lifetime_by_iger/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mastering Python, by van Hattem</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/priyadarshini-sharma-95a35215b/" title="Priyadarshini Sharma">Sharma</a> from <a href="https://www.packtpub.com/">Packt</a> sent me a review copy of the
<a href="https://www.packtpub.com/product/mastering-python-second-edition/9781800207721" title="Mastering Python - Second Edition">second edition</a>. I skimmed it, and I like it a lot. It seems like
<a href="https://w.wol.ph/about/" title="Rick van Hattem (Wolph)">van Hattem</a> knows his stuff. The book is hugely inclusive and
erudite; you'll almost certainly learn new things. It includes the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fixed-point_combinator#Fixed-point_combinators_in_lambda_calculus" title="Fixed-point combinators in lambda calculus">Y combinator</a> as an example. It isn't perfect, but it's better than
<a href="/20190707-expert_python_programming_by_jaworski_and_ziade/" title="Expert Python Programming by Jaworski and Ziadé">Jaworski and Ziadé's book</a>, I think, and I'll recommend it.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220611-mastering_python_by_van_hattem/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220611-mastering_python_by_van_hattem/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Before the Coffee Gets Cold, by Kawaguchi</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>It's a cute short <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Before_the_Coffee_Gets_Cold">book</a>. It reads very clearly as a novelization of
a one-set play. It's about interpersonal relationships and making
tough choices even when you have incorrect information. In the end,
the real time travel was inside us all along.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220604-before_the_coffee_gets_cold_by_kawaguchi/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220604-before_the_coffee_gets_cold_by_kawaguchi/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Beginning of Infinity, by Deutsch</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>I read <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Beginning_of_Infinity" title="The Beginning of Infinity">this book</a> years ago (2017 or earlier) and didn't write it
up at the time, but some of the themes keep coming up.
<a href="/20170825-characteristics_of_good_theories/" title="Characteristics of good theories">Characteristics of good theories</a>, for one thing. But more so the
fundamental optimism that we can keep going indefinitely. Deutsch is
focused on knowledge, understanding, and explanations—but perhaps also
for prosperity, as in a post-scarcity "Star Trek" future (<a href="/20210401-trekonomics_by_saadia/" title="Trekonomics, by Saadia">Saadia</a>,
<a href="/20201109-economics_of_star_trek_by_webb/" title="The Economics of Star Trek, by Webb">Webb</a>). Deutsch's thoughts on quantum theory are fun, but the
optimistic worldview may be more valuable.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220410-beginning_of_infinity_by_deutsch/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Myth of the Rational Voter, by Caplan</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>Did anyone ever seriously believe voters were rational? Well,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryan_Caplan">Caplan</a> has a 2007 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Myth_of_the_Rational_Voter">book</a>, and of course the conclusion is that
we should be more libertarian. "Rational" means in agreement with
economists (meaning Caplan), and by page 197 he advocates "a test of
voter competence." As usual, it's not all wrong, but I'm not sure it's
all right.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"[T]he superstitions to be feared in the present day are much less
religious than political; and of all the forms of idolotry I know
none more irrational and ignoble than this blind worship of mere
numbers." (epigraph)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"You should not blame the prescription simply because the patient
refuses to take his medicine. <em>The Myth of the Rational Voter</em>
contains many workable reforms, but due to voter irrationality they
are unlikely to be tried." (ix)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At some point, it is part of the task of solving problems to create
solutions that work in practice, not only in a hypothetical world
imagined by the solver.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Once economists admit to themselves that voters are just like their
students, only worse, they will be poised to unravel the mysteries
of politics and policy." (xi)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The paradox of democracy ... In theory, democracy is a bulwark
against socially harmful policies, but in practice it gives them a
safe harbor." (page 1)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Economists and cognitive psychologists usually presume that
everyone "processes information" to the best of his ability." (page
2)</p>
<p>"The main difference between the two disciplines is that cognitive
psychologists are much more likely than economists to conclude that
people's best information processing is not very good." (page 211,
note to preceeding)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p><a href="http://www.tomstafford.staff.shef.ac.uk/docs/tetlock03.pdf">Thinking the unthinkable: sacred values and taboo cognitions, by Tetlock</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"This book has three conjoined themes. The first: Doubts about the
rationality of voters are empirically justified. The second: Voter
irrationality is precisely what economic theory implies once we
adopt introspectively plausible assumptions about human motivation.
The third: Voter irrationality is the key to a realistic picture of
democracy." (page 3)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Biases: antimarket, antiforeign, make-work, pessimistic (page 10)</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"We also note that <em>no</em> replicated study has made rationality
violations disappear purely by raising incentives." (page 135,
quoting Camerer and Hogarth)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"To get ahead in politics, leaders need a blend of naive populism
and realistic cynicism. No wonder the modal politician has a law
degree." (page 169)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Yet a standard debating tactic of creation scientists is to insist
that "evolutionary theory, along with its bedfellow, secular
humanism, is really a religion."" (page 186; quote is
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/People-Believe-Weird-Things-Pseudoscience/dp/0805070893" title="Why People Believe Weird Things: Pseudoscience, Superstition, and Other Confusions of Our Time">Shermer 2002</a> page 143)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Private Choice as an Alternative to Democracy and Dictatorship"
(page 192)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"... the Laffer Curve of learning: They retain less if you try to
teach them more." (page 200)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Is this as bad an idea as the original Laffer Curve?</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bertrand_competition">Bertrand competition</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"A proverb tells us that "a wise man learns more from a fool than a
fool learns from a wise man."" (page 209)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220405-myth_of_the_rational_voter_by_caplan/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220405-myth_of_the_rational_voter_by_caplan/</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Red Roulette, by Shum</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>The success of this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_Roulette">book</a> is that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Desmond_Shum">Shum</a> straddles sympathetic
and repulsive. He is deeply flawed and yet less flawed than the China
he describes. He is an unreliable narrator but perhaps among the most
reliable available. His viewpoint is part of the view.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220404-red_roulette_by_shum/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220404-red_roulette_by_shum/</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Seven Games, by Roeder</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p><a href="https://oroeder.github.io/">Roeder</a> writes about checkers, chess, go, backgammon, poker,
scrabble, and bridge. He gets philosophical, on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homo_Ludens">Homo ludens</a> and
what AI is and so on. It's interesting and I learned about some game
variations that are fun to try. Quality pandemic book.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"I’m a machine and you’re a machine and we both think, don’t we?"
(epigraph, quoting Claude Shannon, when asked whether machines could
think)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"games offer a space to enjoy agency." (page 9)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Games also offer simplified models of a dauntingly complicated
world," (page 82)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"a game is “the voluntary attempt to overcome unnecessary
obstacles.”" (page 11)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"adding structure to play—that is, inventing and playing games—is
central to our developmental intelligence." (page 12)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Ken Thompson, the designer of the Unix operating system and a chess
machine called Belle, once spent an hour a day for three years
keying in lines from the Encyclopedia of Chess Openings." (page 35)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Shannon’s paper described two strategies for programming a computer
to play chess. Type A programs employed brute-force search and
evaluation, analyzing every possible move, and all possible
subsequent moves, no matter how unpromising they might look to a
human observer. In other words, they exploited the computer’s chief
strength: sheer calculation. Shannon, however, thought such a player
would be “both slow and weak.” Type B programs were more selective,
examining only certain small yet promising branches on chess’s
enormous tree. In other words, they exploited something like human
intuition. Early computer scientists thought the successful players
would be Type B, but with the rapid expansion of computing power,
computer scientists were lured into pursuing Type A." (page 69)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The key to elite chess is preparation, which Stockfish
facilitates." (page 84)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"“My own works have been described as works of emptiness, but it is
not to be taken for the nihilism of the West,”" (page 100, quoting
<a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/1968/kawabata/lecture/" title="Japan, the Beautiful and Myself">Kawabata</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"“I feel something very strange,” Fan said afterward. “I lose with
the program and I don’t understand myself anymore.”" (page 102)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The rules of Go—called weiqi in Chinese, igo in Japanese, and baduk
in Korean—are stark and elegant, as if they were discovered rather
than invented." (page 102)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Compare to ideas of math being discovered vs. invented...</p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Even Confucius begrudgingly agreed that playing Go was better than
sitting idle." (page 105)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Backgammon is one of only two things in life, I heard many times
during my research, that one never tires of." (page 153)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In the end, of course, it was futile. Tesauro, whose research
inspired XG, expressed a similar sentiment about human players in
light of essentially perfect AI. “They play tournaments and they
study very hard,” he said. “I just don’t see the point.”" (page 160)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Chance, in other words, is a fertile garden in which human ego and
delusion flourish." (page 162)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Before bots, everybody believed that they were the best player. The
type of people we have now are people who like to study, who enjoy
the process of improving their own game." (pages 163-164)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"I came to understand that the appeal of this game, like the method
used to train its AI players, is not winning but learning." (page
165)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The actual lived experience of the World Series of Poker, however,
comprises five elemental modes: loneliness, boredom, waiting,
folding, and, ultimately, devastation." (page 172)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"As the great player Marlon Hill once said about learning the
Scrabble words’ definitions, “If you are sane at all, it will drive
you slowly insane.”" (page 213)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"First, Scrabble, like life, is a trade-off between today and
tomorrow—between spending and saving." (page 221)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Next to him on the table was a plastic box containing bottles of
something called D-cycloserine, a molecule that, online, is
purported to enhance brain activity and learning; something called
F-phenibut, another brain booster and the subject of many personal
drug-experience website accounts that is said to aid memory;" (page
228)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Moreover, these languages must be common knowledge. You and your
partner must reveal your dialect’s structure and intricacies to your
opponents, and players are allowed to ask questions of their
opponents like “What did that bid mean?” Bridge is a game of
communication but not of subterfuge. As such, the “gravest possible
offense” in bridge, according to its official rules, is exchanging
information with one’s partner outside of what the rules allow—that
is, outside of the formal and public bidding process. Illicit
language is the cardinal sin of the game." (page 247)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"A sociological principle called Sayre’s law holds that disputes in
academia are so bitter because the stakes are so low." (page 264)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"“I believe that when I say ‘mathematics’ and when Pam or Tim says
‘God,’ we are talking about the same thing. And I mean the very same
thing. In both cases we are talking about the stunningly beautiful
order that underlies the universe.”" (page 267, quoting Matt
Ginsberg)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Marx and Nietzsche, Hurka points out, believed that “a central
human good was activity that on the one side is necessarily directed
to a goal but on the other derives its value entirely from aspects
of the process of achieving it.”" (page 274)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"“You have this AI built to do this thing really well,” he added,
“but it doesn’t have any particular experience of it. ... I’m a rock
climber, and AI being able to beat me at Go matters as much as a
helicopter being able to beat me at a rock climb.”" (page 277,
quoting C. Thi Nguyen)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Modern AI systems require gobs of data to train, which makes easily
collectible and cheap data attractive. These easy, quantified
metrics can stand in for success in fields whose aims are in reality
complicated and subtle: clicks for journalism, steps for exercise,
box office for cinema, auction prices for paintings. Nguyen calls
this “value collapse”—when rich, subtle values are replaced by
simplified, quantified versions of those values." (page 278)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Games became solace. We players did not arrive in droves seeking
difficulty or complexity, or a sense of achievement, or a frivolous
distraction. We arrived, I believe, in search of agency that had
been temporarily denied by sensible public health measures." (page
280)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220403-seven_games_by_roeder/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220403-seven_games_by_roeder/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Elder Race, by Tchaikovsky</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>As mentioned in its dedication, Tchaikovsky's 2021 short novel
<a href="https://publishing.tor.com/elderrace-adriantchaikovsky/9781250768711/">Elder Race</a> is heavily inspired by Wolfe's 1967 story
<a href="https://www.wolfewiki.com/pmwiki/pmwiki.php?n=Stories.TripTrap">Trip, Trap</a>. What's new?</p>
<ul>
<li>Some female characters instead of all-male cast</li>
<li>Lots of exploration of using technology to fight depression</li>
<li>Last of high-tech civilization is protagonist rather than villain</li>
<li>Villain is less familiar than "just" a telepathic alien</li>
</ul>
<p>Both explore the idea of advanced technology being indistinguishable
from magic (Arthur C. Clarke's quote) with fantasy and sci-fi POV
characters. Perhaps the most interesting thing about both stories, and
perhaps more so Elder Race, is the idea that there is a level of
understanding well beyond that of the high-tech human "wizard."</p>
<p>Mostly it's straightforward fun though. In the end they destroy what
they don't understand and live happily ever after.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220402-elder_race_by_tchaikovsky/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220402-elder_race_by_tchaikovsky/</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Smarter, Faster, Better, by Duhigg</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>This is a very readable book that talks about motivation, teams
(psychological safety), appropriate focus, goal-setting (big and
SMART), management, decision-making, innovation, and absorbing data,
all through interesting stories. There's some good stuff.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>
<hr>
<p>Duhigg connects his book about productivity to the idea of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Power_of_Habit" title="The Power of Habit">his first book</a> on habits.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Productive people have habits—what psychologists might call
'contemplative routines'—that push them to <em>think more deeply</em> about
the choices they make." (page 6)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>The book spends substantial time exploring possible biological
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Striatum" title="Striatum">determinants</a> of motivation, and then becomes less fatalistic.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Motivation is more like a skill, akin to reading or writing, that
can be learned and honed. Scientists have found that people can get
better at self-motivation if they practice the right way. The trick,
researchers say, is realizing that a prerequisite to motivation is
believing we have authority over our actions and surroundings. To
motivate ourselves, we must feel like we are in control." (page 19)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"The division [Google's People Analytics] had successfully pushed to
increase paid maternity leave from twelve to eighteen weeks because
computer models indicated that would reduce the frequency of new
mothers quitting by 50 percent." (page 42)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"In the age of automation, knowing how to manage your focus is more
critical than ever." (page 76)</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Most pharaohs were considered elderly if they made it to
thirty-five." (page 194)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think this is not correct; see
<a href="/20200806-life_expectancy_is_historically_misleading/" title="Life expectancy is historically misleading">Life expectancy is historically misleading</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intermediate_disturbance_hypothesis" title="Intermediate disturbance hypothesis">Intermediate disturbance hypothesis</a></p>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p>"Productivity is about recognizing choices that other people often
overlook." (page 284)</p>
</blockquote>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220327-smarter_faster_better_by_duhigg/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220327-smarter_faster_better_by_duhigg/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>A Visit from the Goon Squad, by Egan</title>
<description><![CDATA[

<p>“Time's a goon, right?” This book is very much as described
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Visit_from_the_Goon_Squad" title="Wikipedia: A Visit from the Goon Squad">on Wikipedia</a>. I enjoyed it. It shows things from different
people's perspectives and gives you a lot of things to react to.
There's largely no singular narrative, the good aren't rewarded, the
bad aren't punished. It's most disappointing when hints of arc or
closure appear toward the end.</p>
<p><img alt="cover" src="cover.jpg"></p>    
    ]]></description>
<link>http://planspace.org/20220320-visit_from_the_goon_squad_by_egan/</link>
<guid>http://planspace.org/20220320-visit_from_the_goon_squad_by_egan/</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
